<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The iron age contayning the rape of Hellen: the siege of Troy: the combate between Hector and Aiax: Hector and Troilus slayne by Achilles: Achilles slaine by Paris: Aiax and Vlisses contend for the armour of Achilles: the death of Aiax, &amp;c. Written by Thomas Heyvvood.</title>
            <author>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>83 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006 June (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99839789</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 13340.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 467(AI), 468.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">4241</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03223</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">The iron age contayning the rape of Hellen: the siege of Troy: the combate between Hector and Aiax: Hector and Troilus slayne by Achilles: Achilles slaine by Paris: Aiax and Vlisses contend for the armour of Achilles: the death of Aiax, &amp;c. Written by Thomas Heyvvood.</title>
                  <title type="alt">Second part of the iron age.</title>
                  <author>Heywood, Thomas, d. 1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[168] p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>By Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>In verse.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Signatures: A-L4; 2A-K4.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>The first leaf is blank.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>"The second part of the iron age" has separate dated title page and register.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>In this issue the title page bears an oval printer's mark.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Title page from STC 13340.5 bound at beginning.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term>Trojan War -- Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="44"/>
                  <p>THE Second Part of the Iron Age VVhich contayneth the death of <hi>Pentheſilea, Paris Priam,</hi> and <hi>Hecuba:</hi> The burning of <hi>Troy:</hi> The deaths of <hi>Agamemnon, Menelaus, Clitemneſtra, Hellena, Orestes, Egiſtus, Pillades,</hi> King <hi>Diomed, Pyrhus, Cethus, Synon, Therſites,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Written</hi> by THOMAS HEYVVOOD.</p>
                  <quote>Aut prodeſſe ſolent aut Delectare.</quote>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Nicholas Okes.</hi> 1632.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <pb facs="45"/>
                  <head>Drammatis perſonae.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>New perſons not preſented in the former part of <hi>this History.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pyrhus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Achilles,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>ſurnamed <hi>Neoptolemus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Synon</hi> a perin●ed Greeke, by whoſe teares <hi>Troy</hi> was ſet on fire.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chorebus</hi> a Prince, who came to the warres for the loue of <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Laocoon,</hi> a prieſt of <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Polites,</hi> a young ſonne of King</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Priam,</hi> and Queene <hi>Hecuba.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A <hi>Troian</hi> Citizen. &amp; his wife.</item>
                     <item>A ſecond <hi>Troian.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Souldiers of <hi>Greece.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Souldiers of <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Ghoſt of <hi>Hector.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A Lord of <hi>Mycena.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A Guard.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pentheſilea</hi> Queene of the <hi>A|mazons,</hi> with her trayne of <hi>Ʋiragoes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cethus</hi> ſonne to King <hi>Naulus,</hi> and brother of <hi>Palamides.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pillades</hi> the friend of <hi>Orestes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſonne to King <hi>Aga|memnon,</hi> and his Queene <hi>Cli|temneſtra.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Electra,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Oreſtes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hermione</hi> daughter to King</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Menelaus</hi> and Q. <hi>Hellen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Clitemneſtra</hi> wife and Queene to <hi>Agamemnon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eg●ſtus</hi> a fauorite to Queene <hi>Clitemneſtra.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Prieſt of <hi>Apollo▪</hi> Attendants.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="45"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>_COurteous Reader:</hi> I commend vnto thee an intire Hiſtory, from <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturne,</hi> to the v●ter ſubuerſion of <hi>Troy▪</hi> with a faithfull account of the Deathes of all theſe Princes of <hi>Greece,</hi> who had hand in the Fate thereof, <hi>(Vliſſes</hi> only excepted, to whom belongeth a further <hi>Hiſtory.)</hi> Reade freely, and cenſure fauourably. Theſe Ages haue beene long ſince Writ, and ſuited with the Time then: I know not how they may beereceiued in this Age, where nothing but <hi>Satirica Dictaeria,</hi> and <hi>Comica Scommata</hi> are now inrequeſt: For mine owne part, I neuer affected either▪ when they ſtret|ched to the abuſe of any perſon publicke, or priuate. If the three former Ages (now out of Print,) bee ad|ded to theſe (as I am promiſed) to make vp an hand|ſome Volumne; I purpoſe <hi>(Deo Aſſiſtente,)</hi> to illu|ſtrate
<pb facs="46"/>
the whole Worke, with an Explanation of all he difficulties, and an Hiſtoricall Comment of euery hard name, which may appeare obſcure or intricate to ſuch as are not frequent in Poetry: Which (as the reſt) I ſhall freely deuote to thy fauorable peruſall, in this as all the reſt induſtrious to thy pleaſure and profit:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Heywood</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="46"/>
                  <head>Tomy VVorthy and much Reſpected Friend, Mr. <hi>Thomas Mannering</hi> Eſquire.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>_ANd my much reſpected Friend: The Impreſſion of your Loue, after ſo many yeares acknow|ledgment, inforceth me that I cannot chuſe, but in my beſt re|collection, to number you in the File and Liſt of my beſt and cho yceſt Well|wiſhers. True it is, that my vnable merit hath euer come much ſhort of your ample acknow|ledgement: Howſoe●er, though you bee now abſent in the Countrey, vppon a neceſſary retyre|ment; yet let this witneſſe in my behalfe, that you are not altogether vnremembred in the Citty: Nor take it vnkindly at my hands that I hauere|ſerued your name to the Cataſtrophe and conclu|ſion of this Worke: Since being <hi>Scoena nouiſſima,</hi>
                     <pb facs="47"/>
It muſt be conſequently the freſher in memory; as you haue had euer a charitable and indulgent cenſure of ſuch poore peeces of mine, as haue come accedentally vnto your view. So <hi>I</hi> intreate you now, (as one better able to iudge, then <hi>I</hi> to determine) to receiue into your fauourable patro|nage, this ſecond part of the <hi>Iron Age. I</hi> much deceiue my ſelfe, if <hi>J</hi> heard you not once com|mend it, when you ſaw it Acted; if you perſiſt in the ſame opinion, when you ſhall ſpare ſome ſorted houres to heare it read, in your paynes, <hi>I</hi> ſhal hold my ſelfe much pleaſed: ouer remaining</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, not to be chang'd: Thomas Heywood.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <head>
                  <pb facs="47"/>The ſecond Part of the IRON AGE: VVith the Deſtruction of <hi>TROY.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Agamemnon, Menelaus, Vliſſes, Diomed, Therſites. <hi>Drum, Colours, Souldiers,</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agamemnon.</speaker>
                     <l>_YOu Terrors of the <hi>Aſian</hi> Monarchy,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Europes</hi> glory: Warlike Lords of <hi>Greece:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Although the great Prince of the <hi>Mirmidons,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And arme-ſtrong <hi>Aiax,</hi> our beſt Champions,</l>
                     <l>Be by the gods bereft vs: yet now comes</l>
                     <l>A Phoenix out of their cold aſhes riſing:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Neoptolemus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>On whom for his deceaſed fathers ſake,</l>
                     <l>Wee muſt beſtow ſome honours. <hi>Menelaus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vliſſes, Diomed,</hi> giue the Prince meeting,</l>
                     <l>And be his conduct to the Generall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A flouriſh. Enter the Kings before named, bringing in <hi>Pyrhus, Synon,</hi> with attendants.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus</hi> kneele downe, we girt thee with this ſword,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="48"/>
It was thy fathers. In his warlike hand</l>
                     <l>It hath cleft Troians to the nauell downe,</l>
                     <l>Par'd heads off faſter then the harueſt Sithe</l>
                     <l>Doth the thin ſtalkes, or bending eares of graine:</l>
                     <l>Weare it, and draw it to reuenge his death.</l>
                     <l>Princes, performe your ſeuerall ceremonies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di●.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe golden ſpurs I faſten to thine heeles,</l>
                     <l>The ſame thy warlike father wonne in field,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Hector</hi> tide with thonges to his ſteeds fet-locks,</l>
                     <l>Was drag d about the high built wals of <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ʋliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>This Armour, and this plumed Burgonet,</l>
                     <l>In which thy father, like a rampier'd wall,</l>
                     <l>Oppoſde the fury of his enemies,</l>
                     <l>(By generall conſent of all theſe Princes</l>
                     <l>Attributed to me) loe I ſurrender</l>
                     <l>To youthful <hi>Neoptolemus,</hi> weare it Prince,</l>
                     <l>Not all the world yeeldes a more ſtrong defence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Achilles</hi> Tent, his Treaſure, and his iewels,</l>
                     <l>We haue reſeru'd, inioy them noble <hi>Pyrhus;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And laſtly his ſtrong guard of Mirmidons,</l>
                     <l>And with the honour hee with theſe haue wonne,</l>
                     <l>His Sword, Spurs, Armour, Guard, Pauileon,</l>
                     <l>Be by his valiant ſonne much dignified.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Before I touch the handle of his ſword,</l>
                     <l>Or to my Knightly ſpurres direct my eyes,</l>
                     <l>Lace this rich Armour to my youthfull ſides,</l>
                     <l>Or roofe mine head within this warlike Tent,</l>
                     <l>Make proofe of this his plumed Burgonet,</l>
                     <l>Or take on me the leading of his Guard:</l>
                     <l>Witneſſe you Grecian Princes, what I vow:</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Saturnes</hi> ſonne, the ſire of <hi>Aeacus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Begot on faire <hi>Europa;</hi> by their iſſue,</l>
                     <l>The ſecond Iudge, plac'd on the infernall bench</l>
                     <l>I will diſcend to <hi>Peleus,</hi> and from him,</l>
                     <l>Euen to my naturall father, with whoſe honours</l>
                     <l>I ioyne my mother <hi>Deidamiaes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in my venge●ull oath include them all,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="48"/>
Till <hi>Priam</hi> be compel'd to ſhut his Gates</l>
                     <l>For want of men: ●le be as merci●eſſe</l>
                     <l>As vntam'd Lyons, and the fleſh-fed Beares,</l>
                     <l>Blood ſhall looke brighter in young <hi>Pyrhus</hi> eyes</l>
                     <l>Then diſſo●u●d Chriſtall, till o●d <hi>Priams</hi> haires</l>
                     <l>Be dy'de in goare: till <hi>Hecub's</hi>●euerent lockes</l>
                     <l>Be gu●'d in ſlaughter; all their ſon●es and daughters,</l>
                     <l>Subiects, and Citty quite confuſ'd in ruine,</l>
                     <l>Bow to our mercileſ●e fury: Ile not leaue</l>
                     <l>This blacke and fatall ſiege; and this I ●weare</l>
                     <l>As I am Prince, and great <hi>Achille●</hi> heire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Euen in thy lookes I read the ſack of <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>●riams</hi> Tragedy: welcome ſweete <hi>Pyrhus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And welcome you his warlike followers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>where be theſe Troians? I would faine behold</l>
                     <l>Their wing'd battalions grapple? I would ſee</l>
                     <l>The batter'd center fiye about their eares</l>
                     <l>In cloudes of duſt: I would haue horſes hoofes</l>
                     <l>Beate thunder out of earth: the chariot Trees</l>
                     <l>I would ſee drown'd in blood, <hi>Scamander</hi> plaines</l>
                     <l>Ore-ſpread with intrailes bak'd in blood and duſt:</l>
                     <l>With terrour I would haue this day as blacke,</l>
                     <l>As when <hi>Hyperion</hi> leaping from his Spheare,</l>
                     <l>Caſt vgly darkneſſe from his Chariot wheeles,</l>
                     <l>And in this vail'd confuſion the faint Troians</l>
                     <l>Beate backe into the Yowne: I'de ſee their Gates</l>
                     <l>Entred, and fire by their high Battlements</l>
                     <l>Climing toward heauen: the pauement of th'ſtreets</l>
                     <l>I'de ſee pau'd ore with faces: infants toſt</l>
                     <l>On Lances poynts: big-bellied Ladies flung</l>
                     <l>From out their caſements: I'd haue all their ſoules</l>
                     <l>Set vpon wings, and <hi>Troy,</hi> no <hi>Troy,</hi> but fire,</l>
                     <l>As if ten thouſand Comets ioyn'd in one,</l>
                     <l>To cloſe the world in red confuſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Py.</speaker>
                     <l>Wel ſpake bold <hi>Synon;</hi> and my Lords of Greece,</l>
                     <l>This fellow boaſts no more then with his ſword,</l>
                     <l>Hee will aduenture for, and ſhould that ●ayle,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="49"/>
He'le ſet his braine to worke. I tell you Princes,</l>
                     <l>My Grandſire <hi>Lycomedes</hi> hath made proofe</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Synons</hi> pollicies, ſtate-quaking proiects</l>
                     <l>Are hand-maides to his braine; and he hath ſpirit</l>
                     <l>To driue his plots euen to the doore of Death,</l>
                     <l>With rare effects, and then not all the world</l>
                     <l>Affoords a villaine more incomparable,</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Synon</hi> my attendant. Warlike Princes,</l>
                     <l>I ſpeake this to his prayſe: and I profeſſe</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe as ſterne, bloody, and mercileſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>I haue not heard a brauer Character</l>
                     <l>Giuen to a Greeke: and had hee but my rayling▪</l>
                     <l>He were a man compleate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure there is ſomething</l>
                     <l>Aboue a common man in yon ſame fellow,</l>
                     <l>Whom nature hath ſo markt, and were his mind</l>
                     <l>As crooked as his body, hee were one</l>
                     <l>I could bee much in loue with.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee hath a feature</l>
                     <l>That I could court, nay will: I would not looſe</l>
                     <l>His friendſhip and acquaintance for the world.</l>
                     <l>Mee thinkes you are a comely Gentleman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I euer held my ſelfe ſo: and mine eye</l>
                     <l>Giues you no leſſe: of all the <hi>Grecians</hi> here</l>
                     <l>Thou haft a face like mine, that feares no weather▪</l>
                     <l>A ſhape that warre it ſelfe cannot deforme:</l>
                     <l>I beſt loue ſuch complexions.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>By the gods</l>
                     <l>Wee haue two meeting ſoules: be my ſweete Vrchin▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I will,</l>
                     <l>An thou ſhalt bee mine vgly Toade.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>A match: be wee hence forth brothers and friends.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Imbrace then friend and brother: my deare Toade▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>My amiable Vrchin.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>I long for worke, will not theſe Troians come,</l>
                     <l>To welcome <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> great <hi>Achilles</hi> ſonne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vlyſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Their drummes proclayme them ready for the field.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="49"/>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Priam, Paris, Pentheſilea, <hi>and her traine o●</hi> Viragoes, Aeneas, Chorebus, Laocoon, Anthenor, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps King <hi>Priam</hi> hath not yet related</l>
                     <l>The newes of <hi>Neoptolemus</hi> arriue,</l>
                     <l>That hee preſumes thus, weakned as he is,</l>
                     <l>To ope his Gates, and meete vs in the field.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis like hee hath, becauſe for want of men</l>
                     <l>Hee brings a troope of Women to the field:</l>
                     <l>Moſt ſure hee thinkes, wee (like our warlike father)</l>
                     <l>Will be inſnar'd with beauty: <hi>Priam</hi> no,</l>
                     <l>We for his death, are ſworne vaine beauties foe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penth.</speaker>
                     <l>Artthou <hi>Achilles</hi> ſonne, beneath whoſe hand</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſted by his bloody Mirmidons,</l>
                     <l>The valiant <hi>Hector</hi> fell?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Woman I am.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penth.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ſhouldſt be then a Coward.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>How?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penth.</speaker>
                     <l>Euen ſo:</l>
                     <l>Thy father was a foe diſhonourable▪</l>
                     <l>And ſo the world reputes him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>By all the gods—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>Sweare not, for ere the cloſure of the battaile,</l>
                     <l>If both the Generals pleaſe, with my good ſword,</l>
                     <l>In ſingle combate Ile make good my word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>O that thou wert a man! but womens tongues</l>
                     <l>Are priuiledg'd: come <hi>Priam,</hi> all his ſonnes,</l>
                     <l>The whole remayne of fifty, Ile make good</l>
                     <l>My fathers honour gainſt ſufficient oddes.</l>
                     <l>But for theſe ſcoulds, we leaue them to their ſexe▪</l>
                     <l>What make they amongſt ●ouldiers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penth.</speaker>
                     <l>Scorne not prou●<hi>Pyrhus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our preſence in the field; I tell thee Prince,</l>
                     <l>I am a Queene, the Queene of <hi>Amazons,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A warlike Nation diſciplin'd in Armes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Are you thoſe Harlots famous through the wo●ld,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="50"/>
That haue vſurpt a Kingdome to your ſelaes,</l>
                     <l>And pent your ſweete hearts in a barren iſle,</l>
                     <l>Where your adulterate ſportes are exerciſ'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>Curbe thy irregular tong: we are thoſe women</l>
                     <l>That practiſe armes, by which we purchaſe fame.</l>
                     <l>All the yeare long, onely three monethes excepted,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe wherein Phoebus driues his Chariot,</l>
                     <l>In height of ſplendor through the burning Cancer,</l>
                     <l>The fiery Lyon, and the Virgins ſigne:</l>
                     <l>Then we forſake our Sun-burnt Continent,</l>
                     <l>And in a cooler clime, ſport with our men,</l>
                     <l>And then returne▪ if we haue iſſue male,</l>
                     <l>Wee nurſe them vp, then ſend them to their Fathers.</l>
                     <l>If females, we then keepe them, and with irons</l>
                     <l>Their right paps we ſeare off, with better eaſe</l>
                     <l>To couch their ſpeares, and practiſe feates of armes.</l>
                     <l>We are thoſe women, who expel'd our Land</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Aegypts</hi> Tyrant: Conquered <hi>Aſia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Cappadocia:</hi> theſe two Ladies</l>
                     <l>Diſcend from <hi>Men●lippe</hi> and <hi>Hyppolita,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who in <hi>Antiopes</hi> raigne▪ fou●ht hand to hand</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Theſeus;</hi> we are thoſe</l>
                     <l>That came for loue of <hi>hector</hi> to the field,</l>
                     <l>And (being murdred) to reuenge his death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Py.</speaker>
                     <l>Then welcome <hi>Amazonians,</hi> as I liue</l>
                     <l>I loue you though I hate you: but beware,</l>
                     <l>Hate will out-way my loue, and ile not ſpare</l>
                     <l>Your ●usl ind ſquadrons: for my fathers fall,</l>
                     <l>Troians, and <hi>Amazonians</hi> periſh all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex●unt.</stage>
                  <stage>Alarum. <hi>Enter</hi> Pyrhus <hi>and</hi> Pentheſilea.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Py.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Queene of <hi>Amazons,</hi> by the ſtrong ſpirit</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Achilles</hi> left his ſonne, I let thee know</l>
                     <l>My father was an honourable Foe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>Defiance <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> ile to death proclaime,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hector</hi> was by <hi>Achilles</hi> baſely ſlayne:</l>
                     <l>And on his ſonnes head, with my keene edg'd ſword,</l>
                     <l>And th●●dring ſtroaks, I wll make good my word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="50"/>
                     <hi>Alarum.</hi> They are both wounded, and diuided by the two armies, who confuſedly come betwixt them: to <hi>Pyrhus</hi> enter <hi>Agamemnon, Vliſſes,</hi> and <hi>Menelaus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>What? wounded noble <hi>Pirhus?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Wounded? no,</l>
                     <l>I haue not met one that can raze the skinne</l>
                     <l>Of great <hi>Achilles</hi> ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet blood drops from your arme.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Not poſſible!</l>
                     <l>Tis ſure the blood of ſome ſlayne enemy.</l>
                     <l>Come lets vs breake into the battailes center,</l>
                     <l>And too't pel mel.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>But <hi>Neoptolemus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wee priſe thy ſafety more then all aduantage:</l>
                     <l>Retire thy ſel●e to haue thy wounds bound vp,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Cowards feare death,</l>
                     <l>Ile venge my blood, though with the loſſe of breath.</l>
                     <stage>Alarum. <hi>Enter</hi> Paris.</stage>
                     <l>Art thou a mad-man fellow, that aduentureſt</l>
                     <l>So neere the blood of <hi>Neoptolemus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſmalleſt drop muſt coſt a Troians life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou the bleeding ●ſ●ue of that <hi>Greeke?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I, in reuenge of noble <hi>Hectors</hi> death,</l>
                     <l>Slew in <hi>Apolloes</hi> Temple.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou then</l>
                     <l>That coward and effeminate Troian boy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                     <l>Arme wounded Greek, I ſlew the falſe <hi>Achilles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>An act which I am proud of.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Fall on the murderer,</l>
                     <l>And flake him ſmaller then the <hi>Lybean</hi> ſand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>If any but my ſelfe offer one blow,</l>
                     <l>Ile on the Troians party oppoſe him.</l>
                     <l>Come <hi>Paris,</hi> though againſt the oddes of breath,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Achilles</hi> wounded ſonne, will venge his death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> is ſlayne by <hi>Pyrhus. A</hi> retreate ſounded.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="51"/>
                     <hi>Enter then</hi> King Diomed, <hi>and</hi> Synon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſound the Troians this retreate?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Paris</hi> is ●●ayne, and <hi>Penthiſilea</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wounded by <hi>Pyrhus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Come then <hi>Synon</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Goe with me to my Tent, this night we'le reuell</l>
                     <l>With beauteous <hi>Creſſida.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Not I, I hate all women, painted beauty</l>
                     <l>And I am oppoſites: I loue thee leſſe</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thou doat'ſt on Troian <hi>Creſſida.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>She's worthy of our loue: I tell thee <hi>Synon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shee is both conſtant, wiſe, and beautifull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>She's neither conſtant, wiſe, nor beautifull,</l>
                     <l>Ile prooue it <hi>Diomed:</hi> foure Elements</l>
                     <l>Meete in the ſtructure of that <hi>Creſſida,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of which there's not one pure: ſhe's compact</l>
                     <l>Meerely of blood, of bones and rotten fleſh,</l>
                     <l>Which makes her Leaprous, where the Sun exhales</l>
                     <l>The moyſt complexion, it doth putrifie</l>
                     <l>The region of th'ayre: there's then another,</l>
                     <l>Sometimes the Sunne ſits muffled in his Caue,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt from the Clouds flye hideous ſhowers of raine,</l>
                     <l>Which ſweepes the earths corruption into Brookes,</l>
                     <l>Brookes into riuers, Riuers ſend their tribute,</l>
                     <l>As they receiue it to their Soueraigne</l>
                     <l>The ſeething Ocean: Thus Earth, Ayre, and Water,</l>
                     <l>Are all infected, ſhe then fram'd of theſe,</l>
                     <l>Can ſhe be beautefull? No <hi>Diomed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If they ſeeme faire, they haue the helpe of Arte,</l>
                     <l>By nature they are vgly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Leaue this detraction.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Now for this <hi>Creſſids</hi> wiſedome, is ſhe wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Who would forſake her birth-right, her b●aue friend,</l>
                     <l>The conſtant <hi>Troylus,</hi> for King <hi>Diomed;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To truſt the faith of Greekes, and to loue thee</l>
                     <l>That art to <hi>Troy</hi> a profeſt enemy?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Ca●●t thou diſproue her conſtancy?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="51"/>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I can.</l>
                     <l>Neuer was woman conſtant to one man:</l>
                     <l>For proofe, doe thou but put into one ſcale</l>
                     <l>A feather, in the other <hi>Creſſids</hi> truth,</l>
                     <l>The feather ſhall downe weigh it: <hi>Diomed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wilt thou beleeue me, if I win not <hi>Creſſid</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To be my ſweete heart: yet haue no ſuch face,</l>
                     <l>No ſuch proportion, to bewitch a Lady▪</l>
                     <l>I neuer practiſ'd court-ſhip, but am blunt;</l>
                     <l>Nor can I file my tongue: yet if I winne not</l>
                     <l>The moſt chaſt woman, I will cut it out.</l>
                     <l>Shall I make proofe with her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Creſſida.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>There ſhee comes,</l>
                     <l>Affront her <hi>Synon,</hi> Ile with-draw vnſeene▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>A gallant Lady, who but ſuch a villaine▪</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Synon</hi> would betray her: but my vowe</l>
                     <l>Is paſt, for ſhe's a Troian. <hi>Creſſida,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You are well incountred: whether away ſweet Lady?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>To meete with Kingly <hi>Diomed,</hi> and with kiſſes</l>
                     <l>Conduct him to his Tent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis kindly done:</l>
                     <l>You loue King <hi>Diomed</hi> then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>As mine owne life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſeeſt thou in him that is worth thy loue▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>He's of a faire and comely perſonage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Perſonage? ha, ha.</l>
                     <l>I prithee looke on me▪ and view me well,</l>
                     <l>And thou wilt find ſome difference.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>True, more oddes</l>
                     <l>Twixt him and thee, then betwixt <hi>Mercury</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And limping <hi>V●●can.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Yetas fayre a blowſe</l>
                     <l>As you, ſweete Lady, wedded with that Smith▪</l>
                     <l>And bedded too, a blacke complexion</l>
                     <l>Is alwayes precious in a womans eye:</l>
                     <l>Leaue <hi>Diomed,</hi> and loue me <hi>Creſſida.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="52"/>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Deformity forbeare, I will to <hi>Diomed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Make knowne thine inſolence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I care not, for I, not deſire to liue,</l>
                     <l>If not belou'd of <hi>Creſſid:</hi> tell the King</l>
                     <l>If hee ſtood by, I would not ſpare a word.</l>
                     <l>For thine owne part, rare goddeſſe, I adore thee,</l>
                     <l>And owe thee diuine reuerence: <hi>Diomed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Indeed's <hi>Aetolians</hi> King, and hath a Queene.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>A Queene?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>A Queene, that ſhal hereafter queſtion thee:</l>
                     <l>Or canſt thou thinke hee loues thee really</l>
                     <l>Beeing a Troian, but for preſent vſe:</l>
                     <l>Can Greekes loue Troians, are they not all ſworne</l>
                     <l>To do them outrage?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>How canſt thou then loue me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I am a pollitician, oathes with me</l>
                     <l>Are but the tooles I worke with, I may breake</l>
                     <l>An oath by my profeſſion. Heare me further,</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou King <hi>Diomed,</hi> forgets thy breach</l>
                     <l>Of loue with <hi>Troylus?</hi> Ey or that he hopes</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt be conſtant to a ſecond friend,</l>
                     <l>That waſt ſo falſe vnto thy firſt belou'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Syn●n</hi> thou art deceiu'd `thou knowſt I neuer</l>
                     <l>Had left Prince <hi>Troylus,</hi> but by the command</l>
                     <l>Of my old father <hi>Calchas.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Then loue <hi>Diomed;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yes, do ſo ſtill, but <hi>Creſſid</hi> marke the end▪</l>
                     <l>If euer hee tranſport thee to <hi>Ae●olia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His Queene wil bid thee welcome with a vengance:</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou more eyes then theſe? ſhe'le fal to work▪</l>
                     <l>For ſuch an other Vixen thou nere kneweſt▪</l>
                     <l>Come <hi>Creſſida</hi> bee wiſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſhall I doe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Loue me, loue <hi>Synon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon</hi> loues not mee▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="52"/>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile ſweare I do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I heard thee ſay, that thou wouldſt breake thine oath▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Then Ile not ſweare, becauſe I will not breake it:</l>
                     <l>But yet I loue thee <hi>Creſſida,</hi> loue mee,</l>
                     <l>Ile leaue the warres vnfiniſht, <hi>Troy</hi> vnſackt;</l>
                     <l>And to my natiue Country beare thee hence:</l>
                     <l>Nay wench Ile do't; come kiſſe me <hi>Creſſida.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, you may vſe your pleaſure;</l>
                     <l>But good <hi>Synon</hi> keep this from <hi>Diomed.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter King <hi>Diomed.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh periured ſtrumpet,</l>
                     <l>Is this thy faith? now <hi>Synon</hi> Ile beleeue</l>
                     <l>There is no truth in women.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Am ● betrayed? oh thou baſe vgly villaine,</l>
                     <l>Ile pull thine eyes out.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, ha, King <hi>Diomed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did I not tell thee what thy ſweet heart was.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou art a Traytor to all woman kinde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I am, and nought more grieues me then to</l>
                     <l>Thinke, a woman was my mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>A villaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Right.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>A Diuell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Little better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Go get you backe to <hi>Troy,</hi> away, begon,</l>
                     <l>You ſhall no more be my Companion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>And now faire ●roian Weather-hen adew▪</l>
                     <l>And when thou next loueſt, thinke to be more true▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh all you powers, aboue looke downe and ſee▪</l>
                     <l>How I am puniſht for my periury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Alarum.</hi> Enter <hi>Pentheſilea</hi> with her Amazonians.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Penth.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, what ſad Lady's this? whence are you woman?</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Troy</hi> or <hi>Greece?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I was of <hi>Troy</hi> till lone drew me from thence,</l>
                     <l>But ſince haue ſoiourn'd in the Tents of <hi>Greece,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="53"/>
With <hi>Diomed</hi> King of <hi>Etolin:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh had I neuer knowne him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>Would you truſt</l>
                     <l>You honour amongſt ſtrangers? but ſweete Lady</l>
                     <l>Diſcourſe your wrongs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I was betray'd:</l>
                     <l>It ſhames mee to relate the circumſtance,</l>
                     <l>By a falſe Greeke, one that doth hate our ſexe,</l>
                     <l>One <hi>Synon,</hi> if you meete him in the battaile,</l>
                     <l>I with my teares intreate you be reueng'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>How might wee know him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>His viſage ſwart, and earthy ore his ſhoulder</l>
                     <l>Hangs lockes of hayre, blacke as the Rauens phunes:</l>
                     <l>His eyes downe looking, you ſhall hardly ſee</l>
                     <l>One in whoſe ſhape appeares more treachery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>We looſe much time: Lady haft you to <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And if we meete a fellow in the battaile</l>
                     <l>Of your deſcription, by our honor'd names,</l>
                     <l>We'le haue his blood to recompence our ſhames.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Alarum. <hi>Enter</hi> Therſites.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amaz.</speaker>
                     <l>By her deſcription this ſhould be the man</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Compaſt with ſmockes and long coates:</l>
                     <l>Now you whoores.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>Is thy name <hi>Synon?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>No, but I know <hi>Synon.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hee is my friend and brother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
                     <l>For <hi>Synons</hi> ſake, prepare thy ſelfe for ●aughter▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Synon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>He▪ who names <hi>Synon?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Brother thou nere couldſt come in better time:</l>
                     <l>See, ſee, how I am rounded.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>Were euer ſuch a payre of Diuels feene?</l>
                     <l>They are ſo like, they needes muſt bee allied.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>What can their Dammes ſay to vs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pent.</speaker>
                     <l>You betray Ladies, enuy all our ſexe,</l>
                     <l>And that you now ſhall pay for girt him round.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I recan● nothing, 〈◊〉 me ſweete fac'd brother:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="53"/>
And now you witches▪ ●arlets, drabes, and queanes,</l>
                     <l>We'le cut you all to fragments.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Alarum. Synon</hi> and <hi>herſites</hi> beaten off by the <hi>Amazons. Pyrhus</hi> enters, fights with <hi>Pentheſilea,</hi> after this a retreate ſounded, then enters <hi>Menelaus, Aganieninon, Vliſſes, Diomed.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>The Troians ſound retreate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vliſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Who ſaw young <hi>Pyrhus?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>I feare his too much rage hath ſpur'd him on</l>
                     <l>Too farre amongſt the <hi>Amazonian</hi> troopes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Synon and Ther●ites.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſtand you idle here, and let the Troians</l>
                     <l>Lead warlike <hi>Pyrhus</hi> priſoner to the Towne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                     <l>How <hi>Pyrhus</hi> priſoner?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee ſaw him compaſt by the <hi>Amazous:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pentheſil●●</hi> with her buſtain troopes.</l>
                     <l>Layd load vpon his Helme.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ʋliſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Then this retreate</l>
                     <l>Vpon the ſuddaine argues that they lead him</l>
                     <l>Captiue to <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pyrhus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Courage braue Princes, I haue got a priſe</l>
                     <l>Worthy the purchaſe, on my Launces poynt</l>
                     <l>Sits pearcht the <hi>Amazonians</hi> lopt off head,</l>
                     <l>Vpon my warlike ſword her bleeding arme,</l>
                     <l>At ſight of which the Troians ſound retreate:</l>
                     <l>The honour of this day belongs to vs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>To none but <hi>Neoptolemus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon</hi> you play'd the coward: ſo <hi>Therſites.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>If not ſo.</l>
                     <l>I had not liu'd to ſee <hi>Troyes</hi> ouerthrow</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>When didſt thou euer ſee a villaine valiant?</l>
                     <l>What's paſt remember not, but what's to come:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Priam</hi> hath ſhut his Gates, and will no more</l>
                     <l>Meete him in armes: can you with all your valour</l>
                     <l>Glide through the wals, if not what are you neerer</l>
                     <l>For all your Ten yeares ſiege?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="54"/>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis true, ſome ſtratagem to enter <hi>Troy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Were admirable: for Princes till I ſee</l>
                     <l>The Temple burne wherein my father dyde,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Troy</hi> no <hi>Troy</hi> but aſhes; my reuenge</l>
                     <l>Will haue no ſterne aſpect, till I behold</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Troyes</hi> ground-ſils ſwim in pooles of crimſon goare</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ramnuſia's</hi> Alter fild with flowing helmes</l>
                     <l>Of blood and braines: <hi>Priam</hi> and <hi>Hecuba</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Drag'd by this hand to death, and this my ſword</l>
                     <l>Ra●iſh the breſt of faire <hi>Polixena,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I ſhall not thinke my fathers death reueng'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>To him that can contriue</l>
                     <l>A ſtratagem by which to enter <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ile giue the whole ſpoile of <hi>Apolloes</hi> Temple.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>I my rich Tent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ʋliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I the Palladium that I brought from <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>I all my birth-right in <hi>Aetoli●.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace, tis here: I ha't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile hugge thee <hi>Synon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Touch me not, away:</l>
                     <l>There're more hammers beating in my braine</l>
                     <l>Then euer toucht <hi>Vulcans</hi> Anuile, more Ideaes</l>
                     <l>Then Attomes, Embrions innumerable▪</l>
                     <l>Growing to perfect ſhape; and now 'tis good.</l>
                     <l>Call for <hi>Endimions</hi> baſtard, where's <hi>Epeus?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ile ſet him ſtraight a worke.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon ſome Engine <hi>Synon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>A horſe, a horſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Ten Kingdomes for a horſe to enter <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, let me ſee:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vliſſes</hi> you haue the Palladium.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I haue ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Call for <hi>Epeus</hi> then, the Generall</l>
                     <l>Hath no command in him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                     <l>Lets know the proiect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>And that Palladium ſtood in <hi>Pall●</hi> Temple,</l>
                     <l>And Conſecrate to her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="54"/>
                     <speaker>Vliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>It did ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Call for <hi>Epeus</hi> then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Lets heare what thou intendeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile haue an Horſe built with ſo huge a bulke,</l>
                     <l>As ſhall contayne a thouſand men in Armes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>And enter <hi>Troy</hi> with that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Doo't you, you trouble mine inuention,</l>
                     <l>I am growne muddy with your interruption:</l>
                     <l>Good young man lend more patience, heare me out:</l>
                     <l>This Engine fram'd, and ſtuft with armed Gre●kes.</l>
                     <l>(Will you take downe your Tents, march backe to <hi>Tenedos?)</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſhall the Horſe doe then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Not gallop as your tongue doth: good <hi>Vliſſes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lend me your apprehenſion; when the Troians</l>
                     <l>Finde you are gone aboord, theyle ſtraight ſuppoſe</l>
                     <l>You'l not weigh Anchor: till the gods informe you</l>
                     <l>Of your ſucceſſe at Sea: if then a villaine</l>
                     <l>Can driue into their eares, the goddeſſe <hi>Pallas</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Offended for her ſtolne Palladium:</l>
                     <l>(Will you erect this Machine to her honour?)</l>
                     <l>Withall that were it brought into her Temple,</l>
                     <l>It would retayne the gilt Palladiums vertue.</l>
                     <l>Might not the forged tale mooue aged <hi>Priam,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To hale this Engine preſently to <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pull downe his wals for entrance, leaue a breach</l>
                     <l>Where in the dead of night, all your whole Army</l>
                     <l>May enter, take them ſleeping in their beds,</l>
                     <l>And put them all to ſword.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis rare!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis admirable, I will aduenture</l>
                     <l>My perſon in the Horſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Do ſo, and get a thouſand ſpirits more.</l>
                     <l>King <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> if you like the proiect,</l>
                     <l>Downe with your Tent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon,</hi> wee will,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile ſet a lightvpon the wals of <hi>Troy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall giue the ſummous when you ſhall returne▪</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="55"/>
About it Princes: <hi>Pyrhus</hi> get you men</l>
                     <l>In readineſſe, I will expoſe my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>To bewitch <hi>Priam</hi> with a weeping tale,</l>
                     <l>I cannot to the life deſcribe in words,</l>
                     <l>What Ile expreſſe in action.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                     <l>Downe with our Tents.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile to picke out bold <hi>Greeks</hi> to fil the horſe:</l>
                     <l>Shine bright you lampes of Heaueu, for ere't be long</l>
                     <l>We'le dim your radiant beames with flaming lights</l>
                     <l>And bloody meteors, from <hi>Troyes</hi> burning ſtreetes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Such ſights are glorious ſparks in <hi>Synons</hi> eies,</l>
                     <l>Who longs to feaſt the Diuell with Tragedies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>Explicit Actus primus.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <head>Actus Secundus: Scoena prima.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Aeneas, <hi>and</hi> Chorebus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aenea●●</speaker>
                     <l>The <hi>Grecians</hi> gone?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>All their tents raiſ'd, their ten yeares ſiege remoon'd▪</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Troy</hi> may reſt ſecurely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>They may report at their returne to <hi>Greece</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The welcome they haue had: what haue they wonne?</l>
                     <l>But wounds, Times loſſe, ſhame, and confuſſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter K.</hi> Priam, Anthenor, <hi>young</hi> Polytes, Polixena, Hecuba, <hi>and</hi> Hellen, <hi>with attendance.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>We now are Lord of our owne Territories,</l>
                     <l>Ten yeares kept from vs by th'inuading <hi>Greekes▪</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now wee may freely take a full ſuruey</l>
                     <l>Of all <hi>Scamander</hi> plaine, drunke with the mixture</l>
                     <l>Of th'oppoſite bloods of Troians and of Greekes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hecu.</speaker>
                     <l>And royall Husband we haue cauſe to ioy,</l>
                     <l>That after ſo long ſiege the Greekes are f●ed,</l>
                     <l>And you in peace may reſt your aged head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="55"/>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon this Eaſt-ſide ſtood <hi>Vliſſes</hi> Tent,</l>
                     <l>The polliticke Greeke.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>There was old <hi>Neſtors</hi> quarter,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Agamemnons</hi> that; the Generall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon the north-ſide of the field, <hi>Achilles</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That bloody Greeke pitcht, and vpon this plaine,</l>
                     <l>I well remember, was my <hi>Hector</hi> ſlayne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>This empty place being South from all the reſt,</l>
                     <l>The valiant <hi>Diomed</hi> hath oft made good,</l>
                     <l>And here, euen here, his rich Pauillion ſtood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hecu.</speaker>
                     <l>But here, euen here, neere to Duke <hi>Aiax</hi> tent,</l>
                     <l>Round girt with Mirmidons, my <hi>Troilus</hi> fell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Then was this place a ſtanding Lake of blood,</l>
                     <l>Part of which moyſture the bright Sunne exhald;</l>
                     <l>And part the thirſty earth hath quaft to <hi>Mars:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But now the ſwords on eyther part are ſheath'd,</l>
                     <l>And after ten yeares tumults warres ſurceaſe,</l>
                     <l>They layding their ſhips home with ſhamefull peace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>For which we'le prayſe the gods, banquet and feaſt,</l>
                     <l>Since by their flight, our glorious fame's increaſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Horſe is diſcouered.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Soft, what huge Engine's that left on the ſtrond,</l>
                     <l>That beares the ſhape and figure of an Horſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>What, ſhal we hew it peace-meale with our ſwords?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh be not raſh, ſure tis ſome miſtery</l>
                     <l>That this great Architecture doth include.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>But mine opinion is, this Steedes huge bulke</l>
                     <l>Is ſtuft with Greekiſh guile.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>I rather thinke</l>
                     <l>It is ſome monumentall Edifice</l>
                     <l>Vnto the goddeſſe <hi>Pallas</hi> conſecrate:</l>
                     <l>Then ſpare your fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Laocoon</hi> with a Iauelin.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>La●.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſtand you gazing at this horrid craft,</l>
                     <l>Forg'd by the flye <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> is his braine</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="56"/>
Vnknowne in <hi>Troy?</hi> or can you looke for ſafety</l>
                     <l>From thoſe who ten yeares haue beſieg'd your wals?</l>
                     <l>Either this huge ſwolne bulke is big with ſouldiers,</l>
                     <l>Longing to be deliuer'd of arm'd Greekes,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe monſtrous fatall and abhorred birth,</l>
                     <l>Will be <hi>Troyes</hi> ruine: elſe this hill of timber</l>
                     <l>This horſe-like ſtructure ſtabled vp in <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wil ſpurne down theſe our wals, our towers demoliſh,</l>
                     <l>Which it ſhall neuer: come you Troian youth</l>
                     <l>That loue the publicke ſafety, no proud Greeke</l>
                     <l>Vpon this Steedes backe, o're <hi>'Troyes</hi> wall ſhall ride.</l>
                     <l>Firſt with this Iauelin Ile tranſpearce his ſide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>What meanes <hi>Laoooon?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Princes ſtay his fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lao.</speaker>
                     <l>Harke Troians, if a iarring noyſe of Armes,</l>
                     <l>Sighed not throw theſe deep Cauernes, I devine</l>
                     <l>This gluttenous wombe hath ſwallowed a whole band</l>
                     <l>Of men in ſteele, then with your ſwords and glaues</l>
                     <l>Rip vp his tough ſides, and imbowell him,</l>
                     <l>That we may prooue how they haue lin'd his intrailes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter two ſouldiers bringing in <hi>Synon</hi> bound.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, and proceed, no further in your rage,</l>
                     <l>Till we haue learnt ſome nouell from this Greeke,</l>
                     <l>Whom in a ditch we found faſt giu'd and bound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laocoon</hi> ceaſe thy violence till we know</l>
                     <l>From that poore Grecian, what that Machine meanes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh me, (of all on earth moſt miſerable,)</l>
                     <l>Whom neither Heauens will ſuccour, earth preſerue,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſeas keepe ſafe, I, whom the Heauens diſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>The Earth abandnos, and the Seas diſdaine:</l>
                     <l>Where ſhal I ſhroud me? whom, but now the Greekes</l>
                     <l>Threatned with vengeance; and eſcap'd from them,</l>
                     <l>Falne now into the hands of Troians, menacing death:</l>
                     <l>The world affoords no place, to wretched <hi>Synon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of comfort, for where ere I fixe my foote,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="56"/>
I tread vpon my graue: the foure vaſt corners</l>
                     <l>Of this large Vniuerſe, in all their roomes</l>
                     <l>And ſpacious emptineſſe, will not affoord me</l>
                     <l>My bodies length of reſt: where ere I flye,</l>
                     <l>Or ſtay, or turne, Death's th'obiect of mine eye!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>What art thou? or whence com'ſt thou? briefly ſpeake?</l>
                     <l>Thou wretched man, thou moou'ſt vs with thy teares:</l>
                     <l>Vnbind him ſouldiers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Shall I deny my ſelfe to be of Greece?</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I am brought Captiue into <hi>Troy?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No <hi>Synon</hi> cannot lye: Heauen, Earth, and Sea,</l>
                     <l>From all which I am out-caſt, witneſſe with me</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Synon</hi> cannot lye: thrice damn'd <hi>Vliſſes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The black-hair'd <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> and horned <hi>Menelaus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Grook-back'd <hi>Therſites,</hi> luxurious <hi>Di●med,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all the rable of deteſted Greekes,</l>
                     <l>I call to witneſſe, <hi>Synon</hi> cannot lye.</l>
                     <l>Could I haue oyl'd my tongue, and cring'd my ham,</l>
                     <l>Suppled mine humble knee to croutch and bend,</l>
                     <l>Heau'd at my bonnet, ſhrugg'd my ſhoulders thus,</l>
                     <l>Grin'd in their faces, <hi>Synon</hi> then had ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Whom now this houre muſt ſtue in his own blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>The perfect image of a wretched creature,</l>
                     <l>His ſpeeches begge remorſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas good man,</l>
                     <l>Shake off the timerous feare of ſeruile death,</l>
                     <l>Though 'mongſt vs Troians, and thy ſelfe a Greeke,</l>
                     <l>Thou art not now amongſt thine enemies,</l>
                     <l>Thy life Ile warrant, onely let vs know</l>
                     <l>What this Horſe meanes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Greece I renounce thee, thou haſt throwne me off,</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Troy</hi>● am thy creature. Now Ile vnrip</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vliſſes</hi> craft, my fatall enemy.</l>
                     <l>Who ſold to death the Duke <hi>Palamides,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Kinſman Troians (though in garments torne)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon</hi> ſtands here, yet is he nobly borne:</l>
                     <l>For that knowne murder did I haint his Tent</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="57"/>
With rayling menaces, horrible exclaimes,</l>
                     <l>Many a blacke-ſaint, of wiſhes, oathes, and curſes</l>
                     <l>Haue I ſung at his window, then demaunding</l>
                     <l>Iuſtice of <hi>Agamemnon, Diomed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Duke <hi>Nestor</hi> with the other Lords of <hi>Greece,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For murder of the Prince <hi>Palamides,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And being denide it in my moſt vexation,</l>
                     <l>My bitter tongue ſpar'd not to barke at them:</l>
                     <l>For this I was obſeru'd, lookt through and through</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ʋliſſes</hi> braine had markt me, for my tongue</l>
                     <l>And fatted me for death by <hi>Calchas</hi> meanes,</l>
                     <l>He wrought ſo farre that I ſhould haue bin offred</l>
                     <l>Vnto the gods for ſacrifice, the Prieſt</l>
                     <l>Lifting his hand aloft to ſtrike me dead,</l>
                     <l>I lept downe from the Altar, and ſo fled,</l>
                     <l>Purſuite and ſearch was made, but I lay ſafe</l>
                     <l>In a thicke tuft of ſedge, till I was found</l>
                     <l>By theſe your ſouldiers, who thus brought me bound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou now art free ſecur'd from all their tyrannys</l>
                     <l>Now tell vs what's the meaning of this Horſe?</l>
                     <l>Why haue they left him here, themſelues being gon?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>My new releaſ'd hands, thus I heaue on hye,</l>
                     <l>Witneſſe you gods, that <hi>Synon</hi> cannot lye,</l>
                     <l>But as a new adopted Troian now</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Priams</hi> grace; I here proteſt by <hi>Ioue,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By theſe eternall fires that ſpangle Heauen,</l>
                     <l>The Alter, and that ſacrificing ſword,</l>
                     <l>Beneath whoſe ſtroake I lay, ſince my baſe Country</l>
                     <l>Caſts me away to death, I am now borne</l>
                     <l>A ſonne of <hi>Troy:</hi> not <hi>Hector</hi> whilſt he liu'd</l>
                     <l>More dammag'd <hi>Greece</hi> by his all wounding arme,</l>
                     <l>Then I by my diſcouery: Well, you know</l>
                     <l>How the Greekes honour <hi>Pallas,</hi> who inceaſt</l>
                     <l>Becauſe <hi>Vl●ſſes</hi> the Palladium ſtole</l>
                     <l>Out of her Temple, and her Warders ſlew,</l>
                     <l>In rage ſhe threatned ruine to all <hi>Greece:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Therefore to her hath <hi>Calchas</hi> built this Horſe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="57"/>
(Greece pardon me, and all my Countrey gods</l>
                     <l>Be deafe to <hi>Synons</hi> tale, and let it bee</l>
                     <l>Henceforth forgot that I was borne in Greece,</l>
                     <l>Leaſt times to come record what I reueale,</l>
                     <l>The blacke confuſion of my Natiue weale.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priam.</speaker>
                     <l>And what's that <hi>Synon?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Where left I? at the Horſe, built of that ſize,</l>
                     <l>Lēaſt you ſhould giue it entrance at your Gates:</l>
                     <l>For know ſhould your ●ude hands da●e to prophan</l>
                     <l>This gift ſacred to <hi>Pallas;</hi> Rots and diſeaſes,</l>
                     <l>Peſts and infections ſhall depopulate you,</l>
                     <l>And in a ſmall ſhort ſeaſon, they returning,</l>
                     <l>Shal ſee thy ſubiects ſlain, faire <hi>Troy</hi> bright burning.</l>
                     <l>I'm euen with thee <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> and my breath</l>
                     <l>Strikes all Greece home for my intended death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>Thankes <hi>Synon,</hi> we ſhall bounteouſly reward thee,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>And ſee my Leige, to make good his report,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laocoon,</hi> he that with his Iauelin pierſt</l>
                     <l>This gift of <hi>Pallas,</hi> round embrac'd with Snakes,</l>
                     <l>That winde their traines about his wounded waſt,</l>
                     <l>And for his late preſumption ſting him dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>We haue not ſeene ſo ſtrange a prodigy,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laocoon</hi> hath offended all the gods,</l>
                     <l>In his prophane attempt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Then lend your helping hands,</l>
                     <l>To lift vp that Pallad an monument</l>
                     <l>Into <hi>Troyes</hi> Citty: Leauers, Cables, Cords.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>It cannot enter through the Citty Gates.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Downe with the wals then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe wals that ten yeares haue defended <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For all their ſeruice ſhall wee ruine them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>But this ſhall not defend you for ten yeares,</l>
                     <l>But make your Towne impregnable for euer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>Downe with the wals then, each man lend a hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>I heare a noyſe of Armour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, what's that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>I feare ſome treaſon in that Horſe incloſed:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="58"/>
Nor will I lend an hand to hale him in.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>Downe with the Wals.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>And Troians now after your ten years toile,</l>
                     <l>Dayes battailes, the fields trouble, and nights watch,</l>
                     <l>This is the firſt of all your reſt, feaſt, banquet, ioy and play,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pallas</hi> is ours, the Greekes ſay●'d hence away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pria.</speaker>
                     <l>Here we releaſe all Centries and commit</l>
                     <l>Our broken wals to her Celeſtiall guard:</l>
                     <l>We will rew●●d thee <hi>Synon,</hi> the Greekes gone,</l>
                     <l>Prian. may ● eſt his age, in his ſoft throne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>S●, ſo, ſo,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S●non</hi> I hope ſhall warme his hands annon,</l>
                     <l>A● a bright goodly bone-fire: Here's the Key</l>
                     <l>Vnto this Macnine by <hi>Ep●us</hi> built,</l>
                     <l>Which hath already with his brazen breſt,</l>
                     <l>Tilt ed <hi>Tro●es</hi> wall downe, and annon being drunke</l>
                     <l>With the beſt blood of Greece, in dead of night</l>
                     <l>Hauing ſurcharg'd his ſtomacke, will ſpew out</l>
                     <l>A thouſand men in Armes: ſweet mid-night come,</l>
                     <l>I long to maske me in thy ſable Wings,</l>
                     <l>That I may do ſome miſchiefe and blacke deedes:</l>
                     <l>We ſhall haue rare ſport, admirable ſpoyle,</l>
                     <l>Cutting of throats, with ſtabbing, wounding, killing</l>
                     <l>Some dead a ſleep, and ſome halfe ſleep, halfe wakes</l>
                     <l>Some dancing Antickes in their bloody ſhirts,</l>
                     <l>To which their wiues cries, &amp; their infants ſhreeks,</l>
                     <l>Play muſicke, braue mirth, pleaſing harmony:</l>
                     <l>Then hauing ſpitt young children on our ſpeares,</l>
                     <l>We'le roſt them at the ſcorching flames of <hi>Troy:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Flye ſwift you winged minutes till you catch</l>
                     <l>That long-wiſht houre of ſtilnes: in which <hi>Troy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sleeps her laſt ſleep, made drunk with wine and ioy.</l>
                     <l>In the receiuing of this fatall Steede,</l>
                     <l>Sicke <hi>Troy</hi> this day hath ſwallowed ſuch a pill,</l>
                     <l>Shall ſearch her intrayles, and her ●iues blood ſpill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Agamemnon, Menelaus, Vliſſes,</hi> with ſouldiers in a ſoft march, without noiſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="58"/>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Soft, ſoft, and let your ſtilneſſe ſuite with night,</l>
                     <l>Faire <hi>Phebe</hi> keepe thy ſiluer ſplendor in,</l>
                     <l>And be not ſeene to night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>Were <hi>Phebe</hi> in my caſe,</l>
                     <l>She ſoone would bluſh to ſhow her horned face.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vliſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>We would not haue a ſtarre caſt it's cleare eye</l>
                     <l>On our darke enterpriſe: too faſt: ſo, ſtill.</l>
                     <l>Here Ambuſh, till you ſee the flaming Torch,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon</hi> this night vpon the wals of <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Will toſſe about his eares, as a true ſignall,</l>
                     <l>The great <hi>Epean</hi> ſtructure is receiu'd,</l>
                     <l>And we may find ſafe entrance by the breach.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>A ſtand, the word through all the Regiment,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>A ſtand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Synon</hi> with a torch aboue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy euerlaſting ſleepe ſleepe careleſſe <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This horrid night buried in Wine and mirth,</l>
                     <l>This fatall Horſe ſpur'd by the braine of <hi>Synon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath lept ore <hi>Troys</hi> high bulwarks great with Greeks,</l>
                     <l>Foure times in rayſing vp the monument,</l>
                     <l>A ſhaking ſound of Armour harſhly iar'd</l>
                     <l>In all the Princes eares, and had they not</l>
                     <l>Beene drunk in <hi>Synons</hi> teares, they'd found our guile.</l>
                     <l>It is now mid-night. The blacke darkneſſe falne,</l>
                     <l>And rould o're all the world, as well the Poles,</l>
                     <l>As the great Ocean, and the earth: now's the time</l>
                     <l>For tragicke ſlaughter, clad in gules and ſables,</l>
                     <l>To ſpring out of Hels iawes, and play ſtrang reakes</l>
                     <l>In ſleepy <hi>Troy,</hi> this bright and flaming brand</l>
                     <l>Which I ſo often gire about mine eares,</l>
                     <l>Is ſignall for the Armies quicke returne,</l>
                     <l>And make proud <hi>Iſlium</hi> like my bright torch burne,</l>
                     <l>Winke all you eyes of Heauen, or you ſhall be</l>
                     <l>Blood-ſhot to view <hi>Troyes</hi> diſmall Tragedy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſignals on the wa●: forward braue ſouldiers,</l>
                     <l>The Horſe is entred, <hi>Synons</hi> Tale beleeu'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="59"/>
And wee this night ſhall ſee the ſacke of <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>March on then, the black darknes couers vs,</l>
                     <l>And we without ſuſpition eaſily may</l>
                     <l>Diſperſe our ſelues about theſe high built wals:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Now with a ſoft march enter at this breach</l>
                     <l>But giue no token of a loud Alarme,</l>
                     <l>Till we haue met with <hi>Pyrhus</hi> and the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Whom the Steedes bulke includes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They march ſoftly in at one doore, and preſent●● in at another. Enter <hi>Synon</hi> with a stealing pa●e, holding the key in his hand.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Soft, ſoft, ey ſo, hereafter Ages tell,</l>
                     <l>How <hi>Synons</hi> key vnlockt the gates of Hell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Pyrhus, Diomed,</hi> and the rest, leape from out the Horſe. And as if groping in the darke, meete with <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and the reſt: who after knowledge im|brace.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyrhus.</speaker>
                     <l>The Generall?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                     <l>Pyrhus?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Menelaus?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>Diomed?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>My Vrchin?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>What my Toade?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Well met in <hi>Troy</hi> great Lords.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Where are wee now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sy.</speaker>
                     <l>In the high ſtreet, nere to the Church of <hi>Pallas,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And this you paſt, the gate cal'd <hi>Dardanus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Then here begins <hi>Troyes</hi> fatall tragedy:</l>
                     <l>Princes of Greece, at once vnſheath your ſwords,</l>
                     <l>And heare proteſt with <hi>Neoptolemus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By our fore-father <hi>Peleus,</hi> grandam <hi>Thet●s,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Emperious goddeſſe of the Sea, that made</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Achilles,</hi> ſaue in th'heele, invulnerable,</l>
                     <l>And by my father great <hi>Aeacides,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His glorious name, his Armour which I weare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="59"/>
His bloody wounds, and his blacke ſepulchre;</l>
                     <l>I here abiure all reſpite, mercy, ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>Vntill this Citty be a place confus'd:</l>
                     <l>This murall girdle that begirts it round</l>
                     <l>A Cawſey for the <hi>Greekes</hi> to trample on,</l>
                     <l>The place a ſtone-heape ſwimming in an Ocean</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Troian</hi> blood, which ſhall from farre appeare</l>
                     <l>Like an high Rocke in the red Sea.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>A braue ſhow,</l>
                     <l>To ſee full Boates in blood of <hi>Troians</hi> rowe,</l>
                     <l>And the poore labouring Snakes with armes ſpread ſwimms</l>
                     <l>In luke-warme blood of their allyes and kin.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>Whence muſt this Ocean flowe?</l>
                     <l>From thouſand Springs</l>
                     <l>Of gentle and ignoble, baſe and Kings.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Set on then, none retire;</l>
                     <l>Waue in the one hand ſteele, in the other fire.</l>
                     <l>Loude Drummes and Trumpets ring <hi>Troyes</hi> fatall peale,</l>
                     <l>That now lyes drawing on, the word be vengeance,</l>
                     <l>Alarum, at that watch-word fire, and kill,</l>
                     <l>And wide-mouth'd <hi>Orchus</hi> with whole legions fill▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aloude Alarum. Enter a <hi>Troian</hi> in his night|gowne all unready.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tro.</speaker>
                     <l>T'was an alarum ſure that frighted mee</l>
                     <l>In my dead ſleepe, 'twas neare the <hi>Dardan</hi> port:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ioue</hi> grant that all be well.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter his wife as from bed.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Heauen! what tumult's this</l>
                     <l>That hurryes through the fatall ſtreetes of <hi>Troy▪</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I feare ſome treaſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tro.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay Wife, lay thine eare</l>
                     <l>Vnto the ground and liſt, if we can gather</l>
                     <l>Of what condition this ſtrange vproare is</l>
                     <l>That riots at this late vnſeaſoned houre?</l>
                     <l>Sure 'tis the noiſe of war, whence ſhould it grow?</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Greekes</hi> are ſayl'd hence, <hi>Troy</hi> needes feare no foe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="60"/>
                     <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                     <l>The horrid ſtirre comes on this way towards vs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Troi.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh whither ſhall we turne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A great cry within. Alarum, Enter <hi>Pyrhus</hi> with the rest their weapons draw and torches.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh ſaue mee husband.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Troi.</speaker>
                     <l>Succour me deere wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>Vengeance for <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Neoptolemus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>So flye the word along, dye old and young,</l>
                     <l>Mourne <hi>Troy</hi> in aſhes for <hi>Achilles</hi> loſſe,</l>
                     <l>Steele in one hand, in th'other fire-brands toſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt:</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Chorebus</hi> at one doore, at another <hi>Aeneas</hi> with their weapons drawne.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>This horrid clamour that hath cal'd mee vp</l>
                     <l>From my deepe reſt, much, much amazeth mee;</l>
                     <l>Tis on the right hand, now vpon the left,</l>
                     <l>It goes before me and it followes mee:</l>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Ioue</hi> expound the meaning of this horrour</l>
                     <l>Which the darke mid-night makes more terrible.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>this ſtreete is cleare, but now I climb'd a Turret,</l>
                     <l>And I might well difcernel alfe <hi>Troy</hi> in fire,</l>
                     <l>And by the flame the burniſ●t Helmets gliſter</l>
                     <l>Of men in Armes, whence <hi>Ioue Olympicke</hi> knowes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter a ſecond <hi>Troian.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Tro.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Where ſhall I hide me? Treaſon, <hi>Troyes</hi> betray'd;</l>
                     <l>The fatall horſe was full of armed <hi>Greekes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chore.</speaker>
                     <l>Of <hi>Greekes?</hi> damn'd <hi>Synon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Tro.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Prince <hi>Chorebus</hi> fly,</l>
                     <l>Fly great <hi>Aeneas.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Which way? where? or how?</l>
                     <l>Are we not rounded with a quick-ſet hedge</l>
                     <l>Of pointed ſteele? are not the gates poſſeſt</l>
                     <l>And ſtrongly man'd with <hi>Greekes?</hi> death euery where,</l>
                     <l>Then whither ſhould we flye?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Into the throng.</l>
                     <l>Where blowes are dealt, where our inflamed Turrets</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="60"/>
Burne with moſt fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Nobly ſpeakes <hi>Aeneas.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Then whither flames, and furies, ſhreiks and clamors,</l>
                     <l>Death, danger, and the deuils hurry vs,</l>
                     <l>Thither will we: follow where I ſhall lead,</l>
                     <l>Thouſands ſhall fall by vs ere we be dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Therſites</hi> with other <hi>Greekes.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Charge on theſe naked Troians, and cry thus,</l>
                     <l>Vengeance for <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Neoptolemus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Charge on theſe armed Grecians, and thus cry,</l>
                     <l>We may yet liue to ſee ten thouſand dye.</l>
                     <l>They charge the <hi>Greekes</hi> and kill them, <hi>Therſites</hi> runs away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Well fought braue ſpirits in our vtter ruine,</l>
                     <l>We are Conquerours yet: let's don theſe Greekiſh habits,</l>
                     <l>And mixe our ſelues amongſt their Armed ranks;</l>
                     <l>So vnexpected murder all we meete:</l>
                     <l>The darkeneſſe will aſſiſt our enterpriſe.</l>
                     <l>Theſe Greekiſh Armes this night by Troians Worne</l>
                     <l>Shall to the fall of many Grecians turne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter all the Greekes.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>Burne fire, and kill, as you wound cry thus,</l>
                     <l>Vengeance for <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Neoptolemus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Aeneas</hi> followed by <hi>Hectors</hi> ghoſt</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>What art thou that with ſuch a grim aſpect,</l>
                     <l>In this black night ſo darke and turbulent,</l>
                     <l>Haunts me in euery corner of my houſe</l>
                     <l>Which yet burnes o're mine eares?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hect.</speaker>
                     <l>Doeſt thou not know me?</l>
                     <l>Or can <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſo forget his friend?</l>
                     <l>This face did fright <hi>Achilles</hi> in the field,</l>
                     <l>And when I ſhooke theſe lockes, now knotted all,</l>
                     <l>As bak't in blood; all <hi>Greece</hi> hath quak't and trembled.</l>
                     <l>Looke on mine Heeles, and thou maiſt ſee thoſe thongs</l>
                     <l>By which ſo often I was dragg'd 'bout <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My body made an vniuerſall Wound</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="61"/>
By the vnnumbred hands of <hi>Mirmidons,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This th'hand that toſt ſo many wild-fire balls</l>
                     <l>Into the <hi>Arg●ue</hi> fleete, and this the body</l>
                     <l>That deck't in <hi>Aiax</hi> and <hi>Ac illes</hi> ſpoyles</l>
                     <l>Ridde from the fields triumphant thorow <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Prince <hi>Hector?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hect.</speaker>
                     <l>Hence <hi>Aeneas</hi> poſt from <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Reare that abroad the gods at home deſtroy.</l>
                     <l>The Citty burnes, <hi>Priam</hi> and <hi>Priams</hi> glory</l>
                     <l>Is all expir'd, and tumbled headlong downe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſſandraes</hi> long neglected propheſies</l>
                     <l>This night fulfils. If either ſtrength or might</l>
                     <l>Could haue protected <hi>Troy,</hi> this hand, this arms</l>
                     <l>That ſau'd it oft, had kept it ſtill from harme.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Troy</hi> is doom'd, here gins the fatall Story</l>
                     <l>Of her ſad ſacke and fall of all her glory.</l>
                     <l>Away, and beare thy Country gods along,</l>
                     <l>Thouſands ſhall iſſue from thy ſacred ſeede,</l>
                     <l>Citties more rich then this the Grecian ſpoyle,</l>
                     <l>In after times ſhall thy ſucceſſors build,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Hectors</hi> name ſhall liue eternally.</l>
                     <l>One <hi>Romulus,</hi> another <hi>Bruite</hi> ſhall reare,</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſhall nor Honours, nor iuſt Rectors want,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lumbardies</hi> roome, great Britaines <hi>Troy-nouant.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Heu fuge nate Dea, te{que} his pater eripe flammis;</l>
                     <l>Hostis habet muros, ruit alto a culmine Troia</l>
                     <l>Sacra, ſuoſ{que} tibi commendat Troia penates</l>
                     <l>Hos cape fatorum comites, his moenia quaere</l>
                     <l>Magna: pererrato ſtatues quae denique pont●.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>Soft lie thy bones and ſweetly may they reſt</l>
                     <l>Thou wonder of all worthyes, but <hi>Troy</hi> burnes:</l>
                     <l>Thouſands of Troian Corſes blocke the ſtreetes,</l>
                     <l>Some flying fall, and ſome their killers kill:</l>
                     <l>Where ſhall I meete thee death? before I flye,</l>
                     <l>Some Conquerours yet, ſhall brauely conquered die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <trailer>Explicit Actus ſecundus.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="act">
                  <pb facs="61"/>
                  <head>Acius Secundus: Scoena prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Priam</hi> in his night-gowne and ſlippers, after him <hi>Hecuba, Hellena, Andromache, Hellena, Caſſandra, Polyxena, Poli|tes, Aſtianax.</hi> An Alarum.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>All La.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh helpe vs father <hi>Priam,</hi> Oh the <hi>Greeks.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
                     <l>I haue done more then age would ſuffer me</l>
                     <l>They haue tilted maſts againſt my Pallace gates,</l>
                     <l>And burſt them open.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>All La.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh father <hi>Priam,</hi> whether ſhall we flye?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>We are incompaſt round with ſword &amp; fire,</l>
                     <l>'Las Daughters, 'las my young <hi>Astianax.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>All La.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh heauen, they come, where may we hide vs ſafe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>Safety and helpe are both fled out of <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And left behind nothing but maſſacre:</l>
                     <l>My Pallace is ſurpris'd my guard all ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe am wounded, but more with your ſhreeks,</l>
                     <l>Then by the ſwords of Grecians: come let's flie.</l>
                     <l>Vnto the ſacred Altar of the gods.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>All La.</speaker>
                     <l>May we be ſafe there father?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>Safe? Oh no;</l>
                     <l>Safety is fled. Death hath our liues in chaſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſince we needes muſt dye, let's chuſe this place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Alarum.</hi> Enter at the one doore <hi>Hellen,</hi> at the other <hi>Creſida.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Whither runnes <hi>Hellen?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>Whither ſhould I fly?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>See, <hi>Troy</hi> is not it ſelfe, oh wretched <hi>Hellen!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To ſhunne the Greekes to run into the fire,</l>
                     <l>Or flying fire, periſh by Greekiſh ſteele:</l>
                     <l>Which hadſt thou rather chuſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>Death, in what ſhape ſoeuer hee appeares</l>
                     <l>To me is welcome, I'le no longer ſhun him;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="62"/>
But here with <hi>Creſida</hi> abide him: here,</l>
                     <l>Oh, why was <hi>Hellen</hi> at the firſt ſo faire,</l>
                     <l>To be come ſubiect to ſo foule an end?</l>
                     <l>Or how hath <hi>Creſids</hi> beauty ſinn'd 'gainſt Heauen,</l>
                     <l>That it is branded thus with leproſie?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I in conceit thought that I might contend</l>
                     <l>Againſt Heauens ſplendor, I did once ſuppoſe,</l>
                     <l>There was no beauty but in <hi>Creſids</hi> lookes,</l>
                     <l>But in her eyes no pure diuinity:</l>
                     <l>But now behold mee <hi>Hellen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>In her I ſee</l>
                     <l>All beauties frailty, and this obiect makes</l>
                     <l>All faireneſſe to ſhow vgly in it ſelfe:</l>
                     <l>But to ſee breathleſſe Virgins pil'd on heape,</l>
                     <l>What leſſe can <hi>Hellen</hi> doe then curſe theſe Starres</l>
                     <l>That ſhin'd ſo bright at her natiuity,</l>
                     <l>And with her nayles teare out theſe ſhining balls</l>
                     <l>That haue ſet <hi>Troy</hi> on fire?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pyrhus, Agamemnon, Menelaus, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Pierce all the Troian Ladies with your ſwords,</l>
                     <l>Leaſt 'mongſt them you might ſpare <hi>Polixena.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, I ſhould know that face, tis <hi>Helena?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>My Queene?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>I am not <hi>Hellen,</hi> but <hi>Polixena:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Therefore reuengfull <hi>Neoptolemus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Doe Juſtice on me for thy fathers death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Polixena?</hi> by all <hi>Achilles</hi> honours</l>
                     <l>Ile part thee limbe from limbe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Creſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus</hi> forbeare,</l>
                     <l>It's the <hi>Spartan</hi> Queene.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>If <hi>Hellen,</hi> the adultorous ſtrumpet dyes,</l>
                     <l>Ile be her deathſ-man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>Strike home <hi>Menelaus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Death from thy hand is welcome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold I ſay,</l>
                     <l>Shee's <hi>Clitemneſtras</hi> ſiſter, for her ſake</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="62"/>
                        <hi>Hellen</hi> ſhall liue, and Kingly <hi>Menelaus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Receiue her into fauour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Agamemnon</l>
                     <l>Is too remiſſe, I haue ſworne all blood to ſpill</l>
                     <l>I meet with, and this one will <hi>Pyrhus</hi> kill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>And I this other.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>For our ſake <hi>Menelaus</hi> let her liue.</l>
                     <l>Was not our ſiſter borne againſt her will</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Sparta?</hi> for that wrong done by the Troians</l>
                     <l>Doth not <hi>Troy</hi> burne? and are not all our ſwords</l>
                     <l>Stain'd in the blood of <hi>Paris</hi> ſlaughtered friends?</l>
                     <l>You ſhall be reconcil'd to <hi>Helend,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And beare her backe to <hi>Greece.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Therſites.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hellen</hi> at ſhrift▪ alas poore penitent Queane,</l>
                     <l>Doſt heare me <hi>Menelaus?</hi> pardon her,</l>
                     <l>Take her againe to <hi>Sparta,</hi> thou'lt elſe want</l>
                     <l>So kind a bed-fellow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>Take backe my ſhame?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes for thy pleaſure.</l>
                     <l>There's in the world as rich and honourable</l>
                     <l>As thou, who lend the pleaſures of their bed</l>
                     <l>To others, and then take them backe agayne</l>
                     <l>As they can get them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men,</speaker>
                     <l>My brow ſhall neuer beare</l>
                     <l>Such Characters of ſhame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther,</speaker>
                     <l>Thy browes beares hornes already, but who ſees them?</l>
                     <l>When thou return'ſt to <hi>Sparta,</hi> ſome will thinke</l>
                     <l>Thou art a Cuckold, but who is't dare ſay ſo?</l>
                     <l>Thou art a King, thy ſinnes are clouded o're,</l>
                     <l>Where poore mens faults by tongues are made much more.</l>
                     <l>Of all men liuing, Kings are laſt ſhall heare</l>
                     <l>Of their diſhonours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>●ga.</speaker>
                     <l>What inferiour Beaſt</l>
                     <l>Dares tell the Lyon of his Tyranny,</l>
                     <l>Who is not torne aſunder with his pawes?</l>
                     <l>The King of <hi>Sparta</hi> therefore needs not feare</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="63"/>
The tongues of ſubiects bid our ſiſter riſe</l>
                     <l>To ſafety in thine armes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Doe <hi>Menelaus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>But will my <hi>Hellen</hi> then by future vertue</l>
                     <l>Redeeme her long loſt honour?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>If with teares</l>
                     <l>The Heauens may be appeas'd for <hi>Hellens</hi> ſinnes,</l>
                     <l>They ſhall haue penitent ſhowers: If <hi>Menclans</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May with the ſpirit of loue be ſatisfied,</l>
                     <l>He ten times rectifie my forfet honour</l>
                     <l>Before I tonch his bed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>Ariſe then <hi>Hellen, Menclans</hi> armes</l>
                     <l>Thus welcome thee to ſafety.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, ha, ha,</l>
                     <l>Why this is well, for he that's borne to dye</l>
                     <l>A branded Cuckhold, huggs his deſtiny:</l>
                     <l>Goe, get you after <hi>Pyrhus</hi> to the ſlaughter,</l>
                     <l>Ile looke to <hi>Hellen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Conueigh her to our guard.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hellen,</hi> hereafter ſee thou proou'ſt more wiſe,</l>
                     <l>If not more honeſt, yet be more preciſe,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Prince <hi>Chorebus</hi> with other <hi>Troians</hi> in <hi>Greekiſh</hi> habits.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe ſhapes thriue well, we haue guilt our Greeki● arm●</l>
                     <l>With blood of their owne nation▪ ſome we haue ſent</l>
                     <l>To euerlaſting darkneſſe, ſome repulſt</l>
                     <l>Backe to their ſhips: ſome we haue made to flye</l>
                     <l>Into their horſes bulke, whence <hi>Pyrhus</hi> firſt</l>
                     <l>Lept downe vpon his ſpeare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Synon, Therſites,</hi> and the <hi>Greekes</hi> dragging in <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn,</speaker>
                     <l>Come ſouldiers, this is ſtately tragicall,</l>
                     <l>The Greekes wade vp euen to the brawny thighes</l>
                     <l>In luke-warme blood of our deſpoyled foes.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="63"/>
Aboue <hi>Melpomene</hi>'s huge buskind top</l>
                     <l>We plunge at euery ſtepp, and brauely fought</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Troyes</hi> bright burning flame: that's now our light.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>More of our valiant mates, let's ioyne with them,</l>
                     <l>This ſtreete yet's vnaſſaulted and vnfir'd:</l>
                     <l>Some balls of wild-fire ſtreight, and hurle this Lady</l>
                     <l>Into the fury of the burning flame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>My wife <hi>Caſſandra?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Courage, let none ſcape</l>
                     <l>Fire, vengeance, blood, death, murder, ſpoyle and rape.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>All theſe on <hi>Greece</hi> and twenty thouſand more,</l>
                     <l>Till they like <hi>Troy</hi> be drown'd in teares and goare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Chorebus</hi> and therest beate off the <hi>Greekes,</hi> and reſcue <hi>Caſſandra.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>From Greekes to Greeks, from fire kept for the ſword, From one death to another.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſſandra</hi> no.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord the Prince <hi>Chorebus?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes the ſame,</l>
                     <l>Who hath preſeru'd thee both from ſword and flame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Aeneas</hi> with his father, who taking <hi>Chorebus</hi> for a Grecian by reaſon of his habite, fights with him and kils him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>More Greekes and ſee <hi>Caſſandra</hi> captiue made,</l>
                     <l>Aſſault them Troiaus, reſcue the faire Princeſſe;</l>
                     <l>This way deare father mount my backe againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh falſe <hi>Aeneas,</hi> thou haſt ſlaine thy friend:</l>
                     <l>Many a Greeke (thus ſhapt) he ſent to hell,</l>
                     <l>And being a Troian by a Troian fell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>He dy'd not by my hand, but his owne fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>And I forgiue thee good <hi>Aeneas,</hi> flie,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt ſuruiue, but <hi>Troy</hi> and wee muſt fall:</l>
                     <l>The hope of all our future memories</l>
                     <l>Are ſtor'd in thee, take vp thy ſacred load</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="64"/>
Reuerent <hi>Anchiſes</hi> bed-rid through his age,</l>
                     <l>We are all doom'd, faire <hi>Troy</hi> muſt periſh here,</l>
                     <l>But thou art borne a greater <hi>Troy</hi> to reare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aene.</speaker>
                     <l>The Heauens haue hand in all things, to their pleaſure</l>
                     <l>Wee muſt ſubſcribe: <hi>Creuſa,</hi> where's my wife?</l>
                     <l>In looſing her I ſaue but halfe my life.</l>
                     <l>Come reuerent father, on my ſhoulders mount,</l>
                     <l>Though thouſand dangers dogge vs at the heeles,</l>
                     <l>Yet will wee force our paſſage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>King <hi>Priam</hi> diſcouered kneeling at the Altar, with him <hi>Hecu|ba, Polixena, Andromache, Aftianax:</hi> to them enter <hi>Pyr|hus,</hi> and all the Greekes, <hi>Pyrhus</hi> killing <hi>Polytes Priams</hi> ſonne before the Altar.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Still let your voyces to hye Heauen aſpire</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Pyrhus</hi> vengeance, murdring ſteele and fire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>All the Ladies.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, oh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>My ſonne <hi>Polytes?</hi> oh thou more hard hearted</l>
                     <l>Then fatall <hi>Pyrhus</hi> or his fathers guard,</l>
                     <l>That in the ſhadow of this ſacred place</l>
                     <l>Durſt ſprinke the childs blood in the fathers face.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Priam?</hi> thanks ſweet reuenge, through ſwords &amp; armour,</l>
                     <l>Through mures, and Counter-mures of men and ſteele;</l>
                     <l>Through many a corner, and blind entries mouth</l>
                     <l>I haue followed this thy bleeding ſonne to death,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſwift perſuite hath traind me to this Altar</l>
                     <l>To be reueng'd on thee for the ſad fate</l>
                     <l>Of great <hi>Achilles.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou art <hi>Pyrhus</hi> then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>My acts ſhall ſpeake my name,</l>
                     <l>I am that <hi>Pyrhus</hi> who did mount you Horſe</l>
                     <l>Hyding mine armour in his deepe vaſt bulke,</l>
                     <l>The firſt that lept out of his ſpacious ſide,</l>
                     <l>And toſt conſuming fire in euery ſtreet,</l>
                     <l>Which climb'd, as if it meant to meete the ſtars,</l>
                     <l>I am that <hi>Pyrhus</hi> before whom <hi>Troy</hi> falls:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="64"/>
Before whom all the Vanes and Pinacles</l>
                     <l>Bend their high tops, and from the battlements</l>
                     <l>On which they ſtand, breake their aſpiring necks.</l>
                     <l>The proudeſt roofe and moſt imperious ſpyre</l>
                     <l>Hath vaild to vs and our all waſting fire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> I know thee for my deſtin'd plague,</l>
                     <l>I know the gods haue left vs to our weakneſſe,</l>
                     <l>I ſee our glories ended and extinct,</l>
                     <l>And I ſtand ready to abide their doome;</l>
                     <l>Onely for pitty and for pieties ſake</l>
                     <l>Be gracious to theſe Ladies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus</hi> no,</l>
                     <l>Such grace as they did to <hi>Achilles</hi> ſhew,</l>
                     <l>Let them all taſt; let grace be farre exil'd,</l>
                     <l>Kill from the elder to the ſucking child.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee's prone enough to miſchiefe of himſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Spurre not that fury on which ●unnes too faſt,</l>
                     <l>Nor adde thou to old <hi>Priams</hi> miſery</l>
                     <l>Which ſcarce can be augmented tis ſo great.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Dye in thy tortures then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hecu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh ſpare his life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>●ſti.</speaker>
                     <l>Good man kill not my Grandſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>Good man doe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hecu.</speaker>
                     <l>Kill mee for him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Asti.</speaker>
                     <l>No, ſhee's my Grandam too,</l>
                     <l>Indeed ſhee's a good woman, chuſe ſome other</l>
                     <l>If you muſt needes kill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>This then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aſti.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee's my Mother, you ſhall not hurt her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>This boy had a father,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hector</hi> his name, who had hee liu'd to ſee</l>
                     <l>A ſword bent 'gainſt his wife, this Queene, or me,</l>
                     <l>He would haue made all <hi>Greece</hi> as hot to hold him</l>
                     <l>As burning <hi>Troy</hi> is now to ſhelter vs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aſti.</speaker>
                     <l>Good Grandſire weepe not, Grandam, Mother, Aunt</l>
                     <l>Alas, what meane you? If you be good men</l>
                     <l>Put vp your ſwords and helpe to quench theſe flames,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="65"/>
Or if in killing you ſuch pleaſure haue,</l>
                     <l>Practiſe on him, kill that ill fauoured knaue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Mee bratt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Ʋlyſſes, Agancemnon. Menelaus,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon, Therſites,</hi> and you valiant Greekes;</l>
                     <l>Behold the vengeance wrathfull <hi>Pyrhus</hi> takes</l>
                     <l>On <hi>Priams</hi> body for <hi>Achilles</hi> death:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon,</hi> take thou that Syren <hi>Polixene,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And hew her peece-meale on my fathers Tombe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſites,</hi> make the wombe of fifty Princes</l>
                     <l>A royall ſheath for thy victorious blade:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diomed,</hi> let <hi>Caſſandra</hi> dye by thee,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Agamemnon</hi> kill <hi>Andromache:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And as my ſword through <hi>Priams</hi> bulke ſhall flie,</l>
                     <l>Let them in death conſort him, and ſo dye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>When, when, for <hi>Ioues</hi> ſake when?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Some expeditious fate this motion further,</l>
                     <l>Me thinks tis long ſince that I did a murder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Heauen, oh <hi>Ioue,</hi> Stars, Planets, fortune, fate,</l>
                     <l>To thinke what I haue beene, and what am now;</l>
                     <l>Father of fifty braue Heroick ſonnes,</l>
                     <l>But now no Father, for they all are ſlaine.</l>
                     <l>Queene <hi>Hecuba</hi> the Mother of ſo many,</l>
                     <l>But now no Mother: for her barren wombe</l>
                     <l>Hath not one child to ſhew, theſe fatall warres</l>
                     <l>Haue eate vp all our iſſue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aſti.</speaker>
                     <l>My deare Father,</l>
                     <l>And all my pri●cely Vnkles.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Andr.</speaker>
                     <l>My deare Husband,</l>
                     <l>And all my royall brothers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hecu.</speaker>
                     <l>Worthy <hi>Hector,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all my valiant ſonnes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                     <l>And now that <hi>Priam</hi> that commanded <hi>Aſia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſate inthron'd aboue the Kings of <hi>Gre●ce,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe dreaded Nany ſcowerd the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sees the rich towers hee built now burnt to aſhes:</l>
                     <l>The ſtately walls he reard, leuel'd and euen'd;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="65"/>
His Treaſures rifled and his people ſpoyl'd:</l>
                     <l>All that he hath on earth beneath the Sunne</l>
                     <l>Bereft him, ſauing his owne life and theſe,</l>
                     <l>And my poore life with theſe, are (as you ſee)</l>
                     <l>Worſe then the reſt: they dead, we dying bee.</l>
                     <l>Strike my ſterne foe, and proue in this my friend,</l>
                     <l>One blow my vniuerſall cares ſhall end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>And that blow <hi>Pirhus</hi> ſtrikes, at once ſtrike all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſo, ſo, this was ſtately tragicall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They are all fl●ine at once.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Asti.</speaker>
                     <l>Where ſhall I hide me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>So nimble <hi>Hectors</hi> baſtard?</l>
                     <l>My father ſlew thy father, I the ſonne:</l>
                     <l>Thus will I toſſe thy carkas vp on hie,</l>
                     <l>The brat aboue his fathers fame ſhall flie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>He toſſeth him about his head and kills him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>No, ſomewhat doth remayne,</l>
                     <l>Alarum ſtill, the peoples not all ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>Let not one ſoule ſuruiue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Then Trumpets ſound</l>
                     <l>Till burning <hi>Troy</hi> in Troian blood be drown'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                  <stage>The Alarum continued, ſhreiks and clamours are heard within. Enter with Drumme, Colours, and Souldiers <hi>Agamemnon, Pyrhus, Vlyſſes, Diomed, Menelaus, Hellen, Therſites, Synon, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>What more remaines t'accompliſh our reuenge?</l>
                     <l>The proudeſt Nation that great <hi>Aſia</hi> nurſt</l>
                     <l>Is now extinct in <hi>Lethe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>All by <hi>Hellen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh had that tempting beauty ne're beene borne,</l>
                     <l>By whom ſo many worthies now lie dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>A hot Peſt take the ſtrumpet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>And a miſchiefe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Twas this hot whore that ſet all <hi>Troy</hi> a fire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>Forgiue me <hi>Pyrhus</hi> for thy fathers death,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="66"/>
                        <hi>Troy</hi> for thy ſack, King <hi>Priam</hi> for thy ſonnes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Greece</hi> for an infinite ſlaughter, and you Husband or all your nuptiall wrongs, King <hi>Menelaus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>●inuſt confeſſe, my inconſiderate deed</l>
                     <l>Haue made a world of valiant hearts to bleed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>What, note is that which <hi>Pyrhus</hi> eye dwels on?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>The perfect number</l>
                     <l>Of Greekes and Troians ſlayne on either part.</l>
                     <l>The ſiege ten yeares, ten moneths, ten dayes indur'd,</l>
                     <l>In which there periſh't of the Greekes 'fore <hi>Troy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Eight hundred thouſand &amp; ſixe thouſand fighting men:</l>
                     <l>Of Troians fell ſixe hundred ſixe and fifty thouſand,</l>
                     <l>All ſouldiers; beſides women, children, babes,</l>
                     <l>Whom this night maſſacred.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>All theſe I ſlew.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, ſome this hand ſent packing, that's not true.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vlyſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aeneas,</hi> with twenty two ſhips well furniſh't,</l>
                     <l>(The ſelfe ſame ſhips in which young <hi>Paris</hi> ſayl'd</l>
                     <l>When hee from <hi>Sparta</hi> ſtole faire <hi>Helena,)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is fled to Sea.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Anthen●r</hi> with fiue hundred Troians more Scap't through the gate cal'd <hi>Dardan.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Let them goe,</l>
                     <l>That of <hi>Troyes</hi> ſack the world by them may know,</l>
                     <l>Where aboue thirty braue Heroick Kings</l>
                     <l>Haue breath'd their laſt: befides inferior Princes,</l>
                     <l>Barons and Knights, eighteene imperiall Monarches</l>
                     <l>With his owne hands renowned <hi>Hector</hi> ſlew:</l>
                     <l>My father beſides <hi>Troilus</hi> and that <hi>Hector,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Eight famous Kings that came in ayd of <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Three Troian <hi>Paris</hi> with his Arrowes ſlew,</l>
                     <l>Of which one was my father: <hi>Diomed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Foure Monarches with his bright ſword ſent to death.</l>
                     <l>Our ſelfe the warlike Queene of <hi>Aemazons,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And aged <hi>Priam.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Brauely boaſt he can,</l>
                     <l>A wretched woman and a weake old man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="66"/>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>And now <hi>Troyes</hi> warres sre ended, we in peace</l>
                     <l>With glorious conqueſt to ſayle backe to <hi>Greece.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their Nation's vaniſh'd like their Citties ſmoake,</l>
                     <l>Our enemies are all aſhes: worlds to come</l>
                     <l>Shall Cronicle our pittileſſe reuenge</l>
                     <l>In Bookes of Braſſe and leaues of Adamant.</l>
                     <l>Towards <hi>Greece</hi> victorious Leaders, our toyle's paſt;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Troy</hi> and <hi>Troyes</hi> people we haue burn't in flames,</l>
                     <l>And of them both left nothing but their names.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt▪</stage>
                  <trailer>Explicit Actus tertius.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="act">
                  <head>Actus Quartus: Scoena prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Prince <hi>Cethus</hi> the ſonne of King <hi>Naulus,</hi> and brother to <hi>Palamides.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>With wondrous ioy they ſay, the Greekes returne</l>
                     <l>With Triumphes and ouations piercing Heauen,</l>
                     <l>Where e're they ſet but foot loude Paeans ſung,</l>
                     <l>And Oades to ſpheare-like Notes tun'd in their prayſe:</l>
                     <l>Whil'ſt <hi>Cethus</hi> like a forlorne ſhadowe walkes</l>
                     <l>Diſpis'd, diſgrac't, neglected and deboſht;</l>
                     <l>Playing his melancholly, cares and ſorrowes</l>
                     <l>On his diſcordant Hart-ſtrings. Oh my fate!</l>
                     <l>Shall I, that haue this body aud this braine,</l>
                     <l>A royalty ſtampt on mee in my birth:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe wrongs haue beene of marke through all the World</l>
                     <l>Troubling each eare, and being diſputable</l>
                     <l>By euery tongue that hath beene taught to ſpeake,</l>
                     <l>Euen in the mouthes of Babes, all rating mee</l>
                     <l>Of cowardeſie and ſloth: ſleepe, an occaſion</l>
                     <l>Being fairely offered? No, awake reuenge,</l>
                     <l>Ile bring the now to action.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pilades.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>Heare you the newes</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="67"/>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oreſtes</hi> friend, the noble <hi>Filades?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inſtruct mine ignorance, I know of none.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>This day the Prince, great <hi>Agamem●nons</hi> heir●</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oreſtes</hi> whom you truely call your friend,</l>
                     <l>Betroths the young and faire <hi>Hermione</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Daugh●er to beauteous <hi>Hellen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hymens</hi> ioyes.</l>
                     <l>Crowne them with all true pleaſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>Shall we haue your preſence at the Contract?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Who's within?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>On●ly <hi>Egistus, Clitemnestras</hi> friend,</l>
                     <l>The Q●eene and faire <hi>Electra.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Witneſſe enough,</l>
                     <l>Then ſpare me for this time good <hi>Pilades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We●'le owe them greater ſeruice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                     <l>But t●s a duty that I owe my friend,</l>
                     <l>My abſence would diſtaſt him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Fare you well.</l>
                     <l>Doe, doe, contract and marry, ayme at Heauen,</l>
                     <l>But Hell is that they plunge in: Oh <hi>Palamedes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My baſely betray'd brother, ſold at <hi>Troy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As we would cheapen Horſes, yet a Prince:</l>
                     <l>A Prince? nay Generall of the Greekiſh hoſt.</l>
                     <l>Emperour and Keyſer, choſe to that command</l>
                     <l>By a full ●Iury of Kings, and by them rated</l>
                     <l>The prime &amp; worthieſt: who being far from equal</l>
                     <l>Could find in whole <hi>Greece</hi> no competitor.</l>
                     <l>Yet this peculiar man, this God of men,</l>
                     <l>By falſe <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> and <hi>Atreus</hi> ſonnes</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Menelaus,</hi> baſely ſupplanted;</l>
                     <l>Who, for they would conferre amongſt themſelnes</l>
                     <l>The ſoueraignty forg'd letters ſent from <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And coine withall mark't with King <hi>Priams</hi> ſtamp,</l>
                     <l>As if this father of his fame and Nation</l>
                     <l>Whoſe onely ends were aymd to honour <hi>Greece</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Would haue betrayde his people: this ſuggeſted,</l>
                     <l>My brother was arraign'd, conuiſt, condemn▪d;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="67"/>
For which I haue vow'd the vniuerſall ruine</l>
                     <l>Of all the Kings of that corrupted bench.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Palamides</hi> thy blood in <hi>Aſia</hi> ſhed</l>
                     <l>Shall make all <hi>Europe</hi> mourne ſince thou art dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Egiſtus, Clitemneſtra, Oreſtes, Pi|lades, Hermione, <hi>and</hi> Electra.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Meeenaes</hi> King and <hi>Sparta's</hi> would be proud</l>
                     <l>To ſee this happy and bleſt vnion made</l>
                     <l>Betweene their royall Familyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>This faire Virgine,</l>
                     <l>Second from <hi>Laeda</hi> to whom <hi>Ioue</hi> vouchſa●'t</l>
                     <l>The ſtrict Imbrace of his immortall arme,</l>
                     <l>Vnſpotted with her mothers proſtitution,</l>
                     <l>Wee'le thus receiue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hermi.</speaker>
                     <l>May my chaſt innocence</l>
                     <l>Breake through the Cloud which hath ecclips'd her fame▪</l>
                     <l>Whoſe luſter may out-ſhine my mothers fraileties,</l>
                     <l>And they through m● may bee forgot in <hi>Greece.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egi.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hermione,</hi> your words taſt of your breeding</l>
                     <l>Vnder this Queene your faire and Princely Aunt,</l>
                     <l>were young <hi>Electra</hi> but ſo well beſtowed,</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>A gamemnon</hi> in ſo braue a match</l>
                     <l>Would thinke himſelfe more grac'd, then in fruition</l>
                     <l>Of all the forraigne Trophies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>May ſhee prooue?</l>
                     <l>A whore like to her Mother: Prince <hi>Orestes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And you bright Lady <hi>Spartans</hi> ſecond light,</l>
                     <l>May all the vertues of this potent Queene</l>
                     <l>Take life in you, to prooue hereditary</l>
                     <l>That the great Arch-duke crown'd with fame and honour.</l>
                     <l>In his returne may adde a ſurpluſadge</l>
                     <l>To his already ſurfet: find his bed</l>
                     <l>By this adultreſſe baſely ſtrumpetted,</l>
                     <l>And make the Downe they lye on quaffe their blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>How doe you faire <hi>Electra</hi> in your iudgement</l>
                     <l>Applaude your brothers choyce?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="68"/>
                     <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                     <l>As of a contract.</l>
                     <l>Made by the gods aboue, and now by Princes</l>
                     <l>Here ratified on earth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>I would my friend</l>
                     <l>Were to you ſiſter, but as faſt betroth'd</l>
                     <l>As I to <hi>Hellens</hi> daughter: But deare <hi>Pilades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tis Time muſt perfect all things.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam you heare▪</l>
                     <l>This motion from your brother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                     <l>And I craue</l>
                     <l>Time to conſider on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis on foote,</l>
                     <l>Purſue it then with all aduantages,</l>
                     <l>Command my free aſſiſtance to beginne▪</l>
                     <l>Had you <hi>Electra</hi> friend, as I <hi>Hermione;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We were at firſt as forraigne as you two,</l>
                     <l>And euery way as ſtrange, but opportunity</l>
                     <l>That hath vnited vs, may make you one.</l>
                     <l>After ſome amorous parliance, let vs now</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Temple and there ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>Vnto the gods, that <hi>Greece▪</hi> no more may mourn●</l>
                     <l>But glory iu our fathers ſafe returne▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt,</speaker>
                     <l>His ſafety is our danger▪ for know Madam▪</l>
                     <l>Our loue hath bin too publick.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>That's the ground</l>
                     <l>On which to build my proiect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Grant it hath.</l>
                     <l>Cannot a more then nine yeares widdow-head</l>
                     <l>Excuſe mee being a woman? thinks the King</l>
                     <l>Wee can forget that leſſon in our age,</l>
                     <l>Which was by him firſt taught vs in our youth?</l>
                     <l>Or was't his ayme to ſhew vs choyce delights,</l>
                     <l>Then barre vs their fruition? Firſt to taſt</l>
                     <l>Our pallat, next to make vs appetite;</l>
                     <l>And when our ſtomacks are prepar'd and ſharpen'd</l>
                     <l>For Coſtly vionds plac't before our eyes,</l>
                     <l>Then to remooue the table? hee's vnkind;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="68"/>
And as hee hath dealt with vs, ſo muſt find.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Synon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>The Queene? to her my ſpeed is.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake on ſouldier.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I am the herald of moſt happy newes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Troy</hi> with the earth is leueld, ſackt, and burnt;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Priam</hi> with all his memory extinct,</l>
                     <l>Queene, daughters, ſonnes, and ſubiects ruin'd all.</l>
                     <l>Now like the vapour of their Citties ſmoake,</l>
                     <l>And of them no more found: And Madam now</l>
                     <l>The King your Lord, the Elder of the <hi>Atryd's,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Duke of the puiſſant and all conquering Hoſt,</l>
                     <l>His temples archt in a victorious orbe,</l>
                     <l>And wreth'd in all the glories earth can yeeld</l>
                     <l>Is landed in <hi>Mycene</hi> a Conquer our.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>How could they ſcape thoſe fierce fires <hi>Naulus</hi> made</l>
                     <l>In vengeance of his ſonne <hi>Palamides</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To ſplit their curſed Fleete vpon the rocks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Make repetition of their ioyes againe,</l>
                     <l>Beeing things that I cannot ●●eare too oft▪</l>
                     <l>And adde to them: Is <hi>Menelaus</hi> ſafe</l>
                     <l>My husbands brother? <hi>Hellen</hi> how fares ſhee?</l>
                     <l>Or is ſhee thence repurchaſt? fill mine eares</l>
                     <l>With ſuch ſweete Tones, 'tis all I can deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Take your full longing then, for though the Seas</l>
                     <l>With tempeſts, ſtormes, rocks, ſhipwracks, ſhelues and ſands</l>
                     <l>More dammag'd them then all the Troian ſiege.</l>
                     <l>Although the Beacons fir'd to draw their Fleete</l>
                     <l>Diſtreſſed and diſperſt vpon the rocks</l>
                     <l>Sunke many a goodly bottome: Yet the Generall</l>
                     <l>Scap't by the hand of <hi>Ioue,</hi> with him King <hi>Diomed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> and great <hi>Neoptolimus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With <hi>Spartan Menelaus</hi> late attend</l>
                     <l>With beauteous <hi>Hellen</hi> cauſe of all theſe broyles:</l>
                     <l>All theſe attend vpon the Generall</l>
                     <l>To bring him home victorious, and this night</l>
                     <l>Will lodge in the Kings Pallace,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="69"/>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Souldier thanks,</l>
                     <l>Theſe twice fiue yeares I haue a widdow beene,</l>
                     <l>Thy newes haue now new married mee: giue order</l>
                     <l>For the Kings intertainment, all the ſtate</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mycene</hi> can yeeld ſhall freely be expos'd</l>
                     <l>In honour of theſe Princes: your great haſt</l>
                     <l>Doth aske ſome reſt, therefore repoſe your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>And for your fortunate newes expect reward.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>The Queene is royall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>And now to that diuell</l>
                     <l>Which I muſt coniure vp: Is the Queene mad?</l>
                     <l>Or thou <hi>Egiſtus</hi> ſottiſh? ſee you not</l>
                     <l>The ſtake and ſcaffold, nay the Hang-man too;</l>
                     <l>And will you blind-fold run vpon your deaths</l>
                     <l>When there is way to'ſcape them?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>What horrid fright</l>
                     <l>Is this propos'd by <hi>Cethus?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>The King's return'd,</l>
                     <l>And doth not your veines guſh out of your temples</l>
                     <l>In ſanguine bluſhes? are not your adulteries</l>
                     <l>Famous as <hi>Hellens?</hi> nay, more infamous,</l>
                     <l>There was a rape to countenance what ſhee did,</l>
                     <l>You nought ſaue corrupt luſt and idleneſſe:</l>
                     <l>Tis blab'd in the Citty, talk't on in the Court,</l>
                     <l>All tongues ſurcharg'd, all eyes are fix't on you,</l>
                     <l>To ſee what fearefull vengeance he will take</l>
                     <l>For that your proſtitution.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee's a King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>True <hi>Clitemnestra,</hi> ſo he went from hence,</l>
                     <l>But is return'd a Tyrant fleſht in blood:</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou that he who queld his foes abroad,</l>
                     <l>Will ſpare at home domeſtick enemies?</l>
                     <l>That was ſo prone to puniſh others wrongs,</l>
                     <l>And can forget his owne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli,</speaker>
                     <l>If <hi>Menelaus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Haue pardon'd <hi>Hellen,</hi> may not he his brother</l>
                     <l>Make <hi>Spartaes</hi> King his noble preſident,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="69"/>
To doe the like to me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Tuſh ſhallow Queene,</l>
                     <l>How you miſtake; ſee imminent fate affront you,</l>
                     <l>And will not ſhun it comming? If his brother</l>
                     <l>Be branded as a ſcandall to the world,</l>
                     <l>What conſequence is it that he will grone</l>
                     <l>Vnder the ſelfe ſame burden? rather thinke</l>
                     <l>He hath propos'd a vengeance dire and horrid</l>
                     <l>To terrif●e, not countenance ſuch miſdeeds:</l>
                     <l>And this muſt fall on you, leſt time to come</l>
                     <l>Should Chronicle his family for a broode</l>
                     <l>Of Cuckolds and of Strumpets:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>This thy language</l>
                     <l>Strikes me with horrour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>And affrights mee too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Is hee not King? hath he not Linxes eyes,</l>
                     <l>And Gyants armes, the firſt to ſee farre off,</l>
                     <l>The laſt as farre to puniſh? was hee ſo poore</l>
                     <l>In friends at home, to lea●e no <hi>Argus</hi> here</l>
                     <l>To keepe his eyes ſtill waking? thinke it not</l>
                     <l>But that he knew the treaſon of his bed,</l>
                     <l>Hee had not faire <hi>Briſcis</hi> ſnatcht perforce</l>
                     <l>From th'armes of great <hi>Achilles.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>That I heard.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Why hath he a new miſtreſſe brought from <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But to ſtate her in <hi>Clitemnestraes</hi> ſtead,</l>
                     <l>And make her <hi>Micenes</hi> Qucene whilſt you poore wretches</l>
                     <l>Like malefactors ſuffer, mark't for the Stag</l>
                     <l>And moſt ridiculous ſpectacles.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſhew the danger,</l>
                     <l>But teach vs no preuention▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>See before vs</l>
                     <l>The obiects of our feares and difficulties,</l>
                     <l>But not the way to auoyde them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Heare me then,</l>
                     <l>Preuent your death's by his.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>How? kill the King?</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="70"/>
So we heape ſinne on ſinne and baſely adde</l>
                     <l>Vnto adultery murder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Per ſcelus ſemper tutum ſceleribus it er.</l>
                     <l>Boldly you haue begun, and being once in,</l>
                     <l>Blood will cure luſt, and miſchiefe phiſieke ſinne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps our guilt lies hid.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>In a Kings Pallace</l>
                     <l>Can luſt in ſuch great perſons be conceald?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>The firſt offence repents mee, and to that</l>
                     <l>I ſhould but adde a greater.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Periſh, doe.</l>
                     <l>Or what concernes this mee? I ſhall be ſafe,</l>
                     <l>I haue ſtrumpetted no <hi>Agamemnons</hi> Queene,</l>
                     <l>Nor baſtarded the iſſue of the <hi>Atrides:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or why ſhould I thus labour their ſecurities</l>
                     <l>Who ſtudy not their owne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Reſolue then Queene,</l>
                     <l>The Kings auſteere, and will extend his Iuſtice</l>
                     <l>Vnto ſome ſad example.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh but my husband.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>After ten yeares widdow-hood</l>
                     <l>Can <hi>Clitemneſtra</hi> thinke of ſuch a name?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>You haue halfe wone me, when ſhall this be done?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>When but this night? delayes are ominous:</l>
                     <l>Ere he haue time to thinke vpon his wrongs,</l>
                     <l>Or finde a tongue to whiſper, ere ſuſpicion</l>
                     <l>Can further be inſtructed or leaſt cenſure,</l>
                     <l>To call his wrongs in queſtion: inſtantly,</l>
                     <l>Euen in his height of ioy, fulneſſe of complement</l>
                     <l>With th' Argiue Kings: whilſt cups are brim'd with healths,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt iealouſies are drown'd in <hi>Bacchus</hi> boles.</l>
                     <l>This night before he ſleepe, or that his pillowe</l>
                     <l>Can giue him the leaſt counſell, ere he can ſpare</l>
                     <l>A minute for the ſmalleſt intelligence,</l>
                     <l>Or moment to conſider: I haue done</l>
                     <l>If you haue either grace in apprehenſion</l>
                     <l>Or ſpirit in performance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="70"/>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>I haue both,</l>
                     <l>What anſwers <hi>Clitemnestra?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>I am ſwayd,</l>
                     <l>And though I know there's difference of Juſtice</l>
                     <l>In Princes ſitting on the skarlethench,</l>
                     <l>And husbands dallying in the priuate bed:</l>
                     <l>I'le hold him as one ſits vpon my life,</l>
                     <l>Not one that lies inclos'd within mine armes;</l>
                     <l>Hee's now my Iudge, not Husband, here I vow</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſtance in his death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>And ſo ſuruiue</l>
                     <l>Secure and fortunate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>This night?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>The proiect I haue caſt with all ſecurity.</l>
                     <l>And ſafety for your perſon: ſmooth your browes,</l>
                     <l>And let there ſhine a welcome in your lookes</l>
                     <l>At the Kings intertainment: nay begone,</l>
                     <l>By this time you are expected; what remaines</l>
                     <l>Is mine in forme, but yours in action.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <l>Now father ſtile me a moſt worthy ſonne</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Palamides,</hi> a brother, what neither fires,</l>
                     <l>Nor rocks could doe, what neither <hi>Neptunes</hi> rage,</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Mars</hi> his fury, what the turbulent Seas,</l>
                     <l>Nor the combuſtious Land▪ that <hi>Cethus</hi> can:</l>
                     <l>Hee that ſucceedes my brother in his rule,</l>
                     <l>Shall firſt ſucceede in death: none that had hand</l>
                     <l>Or voyce in his ſubuerſion that ſhall ſtand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit:</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Therſites <hi>and</hi> Synon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Well met on Land kind brother, wee are now</l>
                     <l>Victorious: let's be proud on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ſay'ſt true,</l>
                     <l>Wee are Conquerours in our baſeſt cowardiſe,</l>
                     <l>Wee had not beene here elſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Valiant <hi>Hector,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Achilles, Troilus, Paris, Aiax <hi>too.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They are all falne, we ſtand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="71"/>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and will ſtiffe</l>
                     <l>When all the Grecian Princes that ſuruiue</l>
                     <l>Are crampt and ham-ſtring'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Waſt thou not ſea-ſicke brother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Horribly, and fear'd</l>
                     <l>In the rough ſeas to haue diſgorg'd my heart,</l>
                     <l>And there to haue fed Haddocks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Troians were fellowes</l>
                     <l>In all their fury to be parlied with:</l>
                     <l>But with the tempeſts, guſts, and <hi>Furicanes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The warring windes, the billowes, rocks and fires</l>
                     <l>There was no talking: theſe few times we pray'd,</l>
                     <l>The gods would heare no reaſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Twas becauſe</l>
                     <l>The billowes with their roaring, and the winds</l>
                     <l>Did with their. whiſtling keepe them from their eares:</l>
                     <l>But now all's huſht, could wee finde time to pray,</l>
                     <l>They might find time to heare vs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Shall wee be</l>
                     <l>Spectators of the royall inter-view</l>
                     <l>Betwixt the King and Queene?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Ten yeares diuorſt</l>
                     <l>Should challenge a kind meeting, let's obſerue</l>
                     <l>The forme and ſtate of this Court-complement,</l>
                     <l>(things I did neuer trade with:) Harke loud muſicke</l>
                     <l>Giues warning of their comming.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Loud muſicke. Enter at one doore</hi> Agamemnon, Vlyſſes, Dio|med, Pyrhus, Menelaus: Synon <hi>and</hi> Therſites <hi>falling into their trayne. At the other</hi> Egiſtus, Clitemneſtra, Cethus, Oreſtes, Pylades, Hermione, Electra, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnto our Country and our Houſhold-gods</l>
                     <l>Wee are at length return'd, trophied with honours,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Troyes</hi> ſubuerſion and rich <hi>Aſiaes</hi> ſpoyles,</l>
                     <l>This is a ſacred day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Such <hi>Troy</hi> had once.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="71"/>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnto the gods wel'e ſacrifice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>So <hi>Priam</hi> fell</l>
                     <l>Before the holy Altar.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>This Citty is not <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Where <hi>Hellen</hi> treades,</l>
                     <l>I hold the place no better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>See our Queene,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Orestes</hi> and <hi>Electra,</hi> for our ſake.</l>
                     <l>Princes of <hi>Greece</hi> daigne them your beſt ſalutes▪</l>
                     <l>Deare <hi>Clitemnestra.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clit.</speaker>
                     <l>Royall King and Husband.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>After their ſalute. All the rest complement as ſtrangers, but eſpecially <hi>Pyrhus</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes▪</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>What's he that kneeles ſo cloſe vnto our Queen●</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clit.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Egiſtus</hi> and your ſeruant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee was young</l>
                     <l>When we at firſt ſet ſayle from <hi>Aulis</hi> Gulfe,</l>
                     <l>Now growne from my remembrance: we ſhall ●●ude</l>
                     <l>Fit time to ſearch him further,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Marke you that.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and it toucht me deepely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>Our ſiſter, and this young <hi>Hermione,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Daughter to vs aud <hi>Hellen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Prity puppy.</l>
                     <l>Ofſuch a common brach.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>Young <hi>Neoptolem●s,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This is the Lady promiſt you at <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For your great ſeruice done there: ſhe's your owne,</l>
                     <l>Freely imbrace her then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſee we are like</l>
                     <l>To haue a iolly kindred.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> inioy</l>
                     <l>Her whom I haue in contract?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Beauteous Lady,</l>
                     <l>The great'ſt ambition <hi>Pyrhus</hi> aymes at now,</l>
                     <l>Is how to know you farther.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="72"/>
Hath beene ſo mighty to reuenge the wrongs</l>
                     <l>Of my faire mother, can from <hi>Hermione</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Challenge no leſſe then welcome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh you gods,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> thou wert more ſafe inburning <hi>Troy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With horrour, fury blood, fires, foes about the●.</l>
                     <l>Then in my fathers court.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Another Collumne</l>
                     <l>On which to build my ſlaughters. Patience Prince,</l>
                     <l>This is no time for braues and Menaces,</l>
                     <l>I further ſhall inſtruct you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I haue done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>See now the two Queenes meete, &amp; ſmack in publick,</l>
                     <l>That oft haue ki●● in corners▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Ther●●tes?</l>
                     <l>Thou art growne a monſter, a ſtrange thing ſearſe knowns</l>
                     <l>'Mongſt ſouldiers, wiues and daughters.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>They are two ſiſters.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and the two King-brothers royally</l>
                     <l>Betweene them two cornuted▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>We are to loud.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Princes of <hi>Greece,</hi> fi●ce we ha●e done a duty</l>
                     <l>To ſee our Generall mid▪ſt his people ſafe,</l>
                     <l>And after many dreadfull warres abroad</l>
                     <l>In peace at home. 'Tis fit we ſhould diſperſe</l>
                     <l>Vnto our ſeuerall Countries inſtantly,</l>
                     <l>I purpoſe for <hi>Aetolia,</hi> where my Queene</l>
                     <l>With longing waites my comming.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Not King <hi>Di●med,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till you haue ſeene <hi>Me●ana</hi>'s pompe and ſtat●</l>
                     <l>In amplieſt royalty expreſt at full,</l>
                     <l>Both taſted of our feaſts and Princely gifts.</l>
                     <l>The faire <hi>Aegiale,</hi> who hath ſo long</l>
                     <l>●orborne your preſence, will not I preſume</l>
                     <l>Deny to ſpare you to vs ſome few dayes,</l>
                     <l>To adde to the yeares number, though not as Generall</l>
                     <l>Yet will I lay on you a friends command▪</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="72"/>
Which muſt not be deny'de.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Great <hi>Agamemnon</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With mee was euer powerfull, I am his.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>And now faire ſiſter welcome back from <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be euer henceforth <hi>Spartaes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hei.</speaker>
                     <l>Your great care</l>
                     <l>In my enforced abſence (gracious Queene)</l>
                     <l>Expreſt vnto my deare <hi>Hermione,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath much obliged me to you. Oh my fate,</l>
                     <l>How ſwift time runnes: <hi>Oreſtes</hi> growne a man,</l>
                     <l>Whom I left in the Cradle ! Young <hi>Electra</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then (as I tak't) ſcarce borne, and now growne ripe,</l>
                     <l>Euen ready for an husband!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>In whoſe abſence</l>
                     <l>If but one handſome ſweete-heart come in place,</l>
                     <l>Shee'l not turne tayle for't, if ſhee do● but take</l>
                     <l>After mine old Naunt <hi>Hellen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter a Lord.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                     <l>The great and ſolemne preparation</l>
                     <l>Of the Court, ſtate and glory mighty Princes,</l>
                     <l>Attend for you within.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>All are conſecrated</l>
                     <l>Vnto your royall welcomes, enter then,</l>
                     <l>Wee'l feaſt like earthy gods, or god-like men▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Lo●d muſick. They poſſeſſe the Stage in all ſtate, <hi>●●thus</hi> ſtayeth behind.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>My brayne about againe, for thou haſt found</l>
                     <l>New proiect now to worke on, and 'tis here,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oreſtes</hi> hath receiu'd <hi>Hermione</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From <hi>Clitemnestra's</hi> hand, her ſonle is his▪</l>
                     <l>And hee her Genius, two combind in one:</l>
                     <l>Yet ſhee is by the fathers Oath conferd</l>
                     <l>On <hi>Pyrhus,</hi> which ſhallbreede a ſtormy flawe</l>
                     <l>Ne're to be peec't againe, but by the deaths</l>
                     <l>Of the two hopefull youths: perhaps the hazard</l>
                     <l>Of all theſe Kings if my reuenge ſtrike home.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="73"/>
(Of that at leaſure) but the bloody ſtage</l>
                     <l>On which to act, Generall this night is thine,</l>
                     <l>Thou lyeſt downe mortall, who muſt riſe diuine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Oreſtes</hi> to <hi>Cethus.</hi> Muſicke and healthing within.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Cethus</hi> what's this muſicke vnto me,</l>
                     <l>That are compoſ'd of diſcords? what are healths</l>
                     <l>To him that is ſtrucke heart-ſicke? all thoſe ioyes</l>
                     <l>Whoſe leaders ſeeme to pierce againſt the roofes</l>
                     <l>Of theſe high ſtructures, to him that is ſtruct downe</l>
                     <l>Halfe way below the Center?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Were you lower,</l>
                     <l>Yet here's a hand can rayſe you, deeper caſt</l>
                     <l>Then to the loweſt Abiſme: It lyes in me</l>
                     <l>To aduance you to the height of happineſſe,</l>
                     <l>Where you ſhall liue eternil'd from the reach</l>
                     <l>Of any humane malice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>Hadſt thou ſeene</l>
                     <l>Her, in whoſe breaſt my heart was paradiſ'd,</l>
                     <l>Kiſt, courted, and imbrac'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>By <hi>Pyrhus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt▪</speaker>
                     <l>Him:</l>
                     <l>What paſſionate and in●idiating lookes</l>
                     <l>Hee caſt on her, as if in ſcorne of me:</l>
                     <l>Shall hee inioy my birth-right, or inheri●e</l>
                     <l>Where I am heire apparant? ſhall he vſurpe▪</l>
                     <l>Or pleade my intereſt, where I am poſſeſt?</l>
                     <l>Rule where I raigne? where I am ſtated, ſit?</l>
                     <l>Braue me in my peculiar Soueraignty?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee muſt not, ſhall not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>Show mee to depoſe.</l>
                     <l>The proud Vſurper then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Prince, make't my charge.</l>
                     <l>In the meane time, from your diſtracted from</l>
                     <l>Exile all diſcontent, let not leaſt ra●e</l>
                     <l>Raigne in your eye, or harſhne●●e in your tongue,</l>
                     <l>Smooth waters are ſtill deep'ſt▪ wa●te on the King,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="73"/>
And be no ſtranger to your mothers eye,</l>
                     <l>Or forraigne to your Kindred: the feaſt ſpent,</l>
                     <l>And night with it: the morrow ſhall beget</l>
                     <l>Proiect of more import (ſcarſe thought on now.)</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I build vpon thy Counſell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Oreſtes.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Which hath proou'd,</l>
                     <l>Fixt as a rocke, ſtill conſtant, and vnmoou'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Egiſtus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>What <hi>●ethus</hi> here? why no ſuch matter now</l>
                     <l>No cauſe of feare, or leaſt ſuſpicion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Your reaſon?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>Tuſh, preſume it, we are ſafe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Obſerue it, they are ſtill ſecureſt, whom</l>
                     <l>The Diuell driues to ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>Harke, their healths</l>
                     <l>Carrowſing to the Generals Victories,</l>
                     <l>In all thy heate of ioy, and fire of wine,</l>
                     <l>No ſparke of iealouſly, all th' Argument</l>
                     <l>Of their diſcourſe, what they haue done at <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Still health on health, and the great Generall</l>
                     <l>So farre from ſeeming to haue leaſt diſtaſte,</l>
                     <l>That in all affable tearmes hee courts his Queene,</l>
                     <l>Nay more, cuts off all banquet Ceremonies,</l>
                     <l>To haſten his bed-pleaſures, as if times diſtance</l>
                     <l>Betwixt his boord and pallade, ſeemed more tedious</l>
                     <l>Then all his Ten yeares ſiege.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Goe, loſt man,</l>
                     <l>Sinke on firme ground, be ſhipwrackt in a Calme.</l>
                     <l>Theſe healthes are to your ruines, his reuenge:</l>
                     <l>Hath not <hi>Egistus</hi> read of a diſeaſe</l>
                     <l>Where men dye laughing: others that haue drunke</l>
                     <l>Poyſon in ſteed of Cordials, periſh ſo?</l>
                     <l>To dye tis nothing, ſince tis all men due:</l>
                     <l>But wretchedly to ſuffer, fall vnpittied,</l>
                     <l>Vnpittied? nay derided, moekt, and curſt:</l>
                     <l>To dye as a baſe Traytor, and a Thiefe,</l>
                     <l>The adulterator of his Soueraignes bed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="74"/>
The poyſon of the <hi>Atred●●</hi> family,</l>
                     <l>And ſcandall of his iſſue, ſo to dye?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egi.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Egistus</hi> will preuent, he by this hand</l>
                     <l>Muſt fal, 'fore whom all <hi>Aſia</hi> could not ſtand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>The banquet is broke vp, ſleep cals to reſt,</l>
                     <l>And mid-nights houre for murther, ſtill ſhowes beſt▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Loud muſicke. Enter <hi>Egiſtus</hi> with his ſword drawne, hi|deth himſelfe in the chamber behind the Bed-curtaines: all the Kings come next in, conducting the Generall and his Queene to their Lodging, and after ſome complement leaue them, enery one with torches vſhered to their ſeuerall chambers, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Methinkes this night, we <hi>Clitemneſtra</hi> meete,</l>
                     <l>At a new bridall; all Attendants leaue vs,</l>
                     <l>Wee now are onely for bed-priuacies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Great ſir, I that ſo long haue bin your widdow,</l>
                     <l>Will be this night your hand-mayde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>You told me, Queene,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oreſtes</hi> was a cunning horſe-man growne:</l>
                     <l>It pleaſde me much to heare it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Greece</hi> reports</l>
                     <l>No Centare can ride better▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>And young <hi>Electra,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In all th' indowments that may beſt become</l>
                     <l>A Princeſſe of her breeding, moſt compleate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>It was in your long abſence, all my care,</l>
                     <l>(Being my charge) that you at your returne</l>
                     <l>Might finde them to your wiſhes,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Thankes for that.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>How cunningly he ſeemes to carry it▪</l>
                     <l>But we muſt finde preuention.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Who's without there?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſtarted you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Not all the <hi>Aſian</hi> Legions, no not <hi>Hector</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Arm'd with his bals of wild-fire, had the power</l>
                     <l>To ſhake me like this tremor: Is our Pallace</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="74"/>
Leſſe ſafe in <hi>Greece,</hi> amidſt our ſubiects here,</l>
                     <l>Then were our Tents in <hi>Aſia?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Where, if not here in <hi>Clitemnestraes</hi> armes,</l>
                     <l>Can ſafety dwell?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>And faire Queene, it ſhould bee ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>But why ſir caſt you ſuch ſuſpicious eyes</l>
                     <l>About your Chamber? are wee not alone?</l>
                     <l>Or will you to the priuate ſweetes of night,</l>
                     <l>Call tell tale witneſſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Now tis gone agayne. Shall we to reſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>So pleaſe you royall Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>How hard this Doune feeles, like a monument</l>
                     <l>Cut out of marble. Beds reſemble Graues,</l>
                     <l>And theſe me-thinkes appeare like winding ſheets,</l>
                     <l>Prepar'd for corſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh how ominouſly</l>
                     <l>Doe you preſage: you much affright me ſir</l>
                     <l>In this our long-wiſht meeting.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>All's ſhooke off.</l>
                     <l>I now am arm'd for pleaſure: you commended</l>
                     <l>Late one <hi>Egiſtus</hi> to me, prithee Queene</l>
                     <l>Of what condition is he?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They both wound him, at which there is a greate thunder crack.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>Tyrant this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>And I am thus his ſecond.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Treaſon, murder, Treaſon:</l>
                     <l>This ſhowes, we Princes are no more then men.</l>
                     <l>Thankes <hi>Iou●</hi> tis fit when Monarches fall by Treaſon,</l>
                     <l>Thunder to al● the world, would ſhow ſome reaſon.</l>
                     <stage>he dies.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egi.</speaker>
                     <l>The deede is done, lets flye to ſome ſtrong Cittadell,</l>
                     <l>For our more ſafety.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee thus made diuine:</l>
                     <l>Now my <hi>Egiſtus,</hi> I am ſoly thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Anoyſe of vproare within. Enter all the Kings with other Seruants halfe vnready, as newly started from their Beds. <hi>Oreſtes, Hermione, Pillades, Electra, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſtrange tumultuous noyſe is this ſo late▪</l>
                     <l>To rouſe vs from our beds?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="75"/>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Prodigious ſure,</l>
                     <l>Sin●● 'tis confirm'd by Thunder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>In mine eares</l>
                     <l>Did neuer ſound ſeeme halfe to terrible.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor to your eyes, as this ſad obiect is,</l>
                     <l>See great <hi>Atrides</hi> groueling.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>What damn'd Villaine</l>
                     <l>Was auther of this proiect?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>Horrid ſight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Reſt you amazed all, as thunder ſtruke,</l>
                     <l>And without ſence or motion Apoplext,</l>
                     <l>And onely heare me ſpeake: <hi>Orestes,</hi> he</l>
                     <l>Who as if marbled by <hi>Meduſaes</hi> head,</l>
                     <l>Hath not one teare to fall, or ſigh to ſpend,</l>
                     <l>Till I finde out the murderer, and on him</l>
                     <l>Inflict remarkable vengance: for I vowe</l>
                     <l>Were it my father, brother, or his Queene,</l>
                     <l>Hadſt thou my weeping ſiſter hand in it.</l>
                     <l>If hee? whom equall, (if not rankt aboue)</l>
                     <l>I euer did, and ſhall loue <hi>Pylades?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wert ſhe whoſe wombe did beare me, where I l●y</l>
                     <l>Full nine moneths bedded ere I ſaw the Sunne,</l>
                     <l>Or the moſt abiect Traytor vnder Heauen,</l>
                     <l>Their doomes were all alike, and this I vowe.</l>
                     <l>Now you whom this ſilent and ſpeechleſſe King</l>
                     <l>Hath oft commanded, this now ſenceleſſe braine</l>
                     <l>As oft directed, this now ſtrengthleſſe hand</l>
                     <l>More oft protected in a warre, that ſhall</l>
                     <l>Be to all times example: Lend your ſhoulders</l>
                     <l>To beare him, who hath kept you all in life,</l>
                     <l>This is a blacke and mourning funerall right,</l>
                     <l>Deedes of this nature muſt be throughly ſearcht,</l>
                     <l>Nay be reueng'd: the gods haue ſayd tis good,</l>
                     <l>The morning Sunne ſhall riſe and bl●ſh in blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They beare him off with a ſad and funerall march, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <trailer>Explicit Actus quartus.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="act">
                  <pb facs="75"/>
                  <head>Actus Quintus: Scoena prima.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pyrhus, Hermione, Therſites, <hi>and</hi> Synon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Sweete Lady, can you loue:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                     <l>Forbeare my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Can ſuch a thing as loue be once nam'd here,</l>
                     <l>Where euery Marble that ſupports this roofe,</l>
                     <l>In emulation doth vye teares with vs?</l>
                     <l>Nay where the wounds of ſuch a mighty King</l>
                     <l>Haue yet ſcarſe bled their laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Tuſh faire <hi>Hermione,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Theſe ſights that ſeeme to Iadies terrible,</l>
                     <l>Are common to vs ſouldiers; when from field returning</l>
                     <l>All ſmear'd in blood, where Dukes and Kings li● ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>Yet in our Tents at mid-night it frights not vs</l>
                     <l>From courting a ſweete Miſtreſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee ſayth right,</l>
                     <l>And note of this how I can poetiſe:</l>
                     <l>This his great father of his Loue deſir'd.</l>
                     <l>When from the ſlaughter of his foes retyr'd</l>
                     <l>Hee doft his Cuſhes and vnarm'd his head,</l>
                     <l>To tumble with her on a ſoft day bed:</l>
                     <l>It did reioyce <hi>Briſoi●</hi> to imbrace</l>
                     <l>His bruiſed armes, and kiſſe his blood-ſtain'd face.</l>
                     <l>Theſe hands which he ſo often did imbrew</l>
                     <l>In blood of warlike Troians whom hee ſlew,</l>
                     <l>Were then imploy'd to tickle, touch and feele,</l>
                     <l>And ſhake a Lance that had no print of ſteele.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Continue in that ve●●e, I'le feed thy Muſe</l>
                     <l>With Crafi●h, Praunes and Lobſters.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                     <l>You brought theſe of purpoſe to abuſe m●e.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace <hi>Therſites,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Synon</hi> you no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="76"/>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee ſee by <hi>Agamemnon</hi> all are mortall,</l>
                     <l>And I but ſhew his neece <hi>Hermione</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The way of all fleſh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis an eaſie path,</l>
                     <l>(The Mother and the Aunt haue troad it both)</l>
                     <l>If ſhee haue wit to follow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Vlyſſes, Menelaus, Diomed <hi>with others.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>If it beſo, <hi>Egiſtus</hi> is a traytor,</l>
                     <l>And ſhee no more our ſiſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vlyſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis not poſſible</l>
                     <l>A Queene of her high birth and parentage</l>
                     <l>Should haue ſuch baſe hand in her husbands death,</l>
                     <l>Her husband and her ſoueraigne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>Double treaſon,</l>
                     <l>Could it be proou'd againſt her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                     <l>It appeares</l>
                     <l>So farre againſt humanity and nature</l>
                     <l>We dare not once ſuſpect it, but till proofe</l>
                     <l>Explaine it further, hold it in ſuſpence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vlyſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh but their ſuddaine flight and fortifying.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe are indeed preſumptions, but leaue that</l>
                     <l>To a moſt ſtrict inquiry euen for reuerence</l>
                     <l>Of Maieſty and Honour to all Queenes,</l>
                     <l>For loue of vs becauſe ſhee was our ſiſter,</l>
                     <l>Both for <hi>Orestes</hi> and <hi>Electra's</hi> ſake</l>
                     <l>Whoſe births are branded in ſo foule a deede</l>
                     <l>Till wee examine further circumſtances</l>
                     <l>Spare your ſeuerer cenſures.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vliſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis a buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>That leaſt concernes vs, but for Honours ſake</l>
                     <l>And that hee was our Generall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>What, prince ly <hi>Pyrhus</hi> courting our faire daughter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes ſir, but in a time vnſeaſonable</l>
                     <l>Euen as the ſuite it ſelfe is.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>All delayes</l>
                     <l>Shall be cut off and ſhe be ſwayd by vs.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="76"/>
Theſe Royall Princes ere they leaue <hi>Mycone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall ſee theſe ●uptiall rights ſolemnized,</l>
                     <l>Weele keepe our faith with <hi>Pyrhus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee our vowes</l>
                     <l>As conſtant to the bright <hi>Hermione.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Firſt ſee the royall Generall here interr'd</l>
                     <l>And buried like a ſouldier, 'tis his due:</l>
                     <l>To queſtion of his death concernes not vs,</l>
                     <l>Wee leaue it to Heauens iuſtice and reuenge.</l>
                     <l>The rights perform'd with faire <hi>Hermione,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then to our ſeuerall Countries each man poſt,</l>
                     <l>Captaines diſperſe ſtill when the General's loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Cethus, Oreſtes, <hi>and</hi> Pylades. <hi>diſguis'd.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Egistus?</hi> and our Mother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Am I <hi>Cethus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are you <hi>Orestes,</hi> and this <hi>Pyllades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So ſure they were his murderers: this diſguiſe</l>
                     <l>Will ſuite an act of death, full to the life</l>
                     <l>Hee ſtands vpon a ſtrict and ſecure guard,</l>
                     <l>I haue plotted your admittance, it will take</l>
                     <l>Doubt not, it cannot fayle, I haue caſt it ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>As ſent from <hi>Menelaus?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Whoſe name elſe</l>
                     <l>Can breake through ſuch ſtrong guards, where feare and guilt</l>
                     <l>Keepe hourely watch?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>It is enough, I haue't,</l>
                     <l>And thou the faithful'ſt of all friends deare <hi>Pillades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Doe but aſſiſt mee in my vowed reuenge</l>
                     <l>And inioy faire <hi>Electra.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                     <l>Next your friendſhip</l>
                     <l>It is the priſe ●ayme at, I am yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſlip you time and opportunity,</l>
                     <l>Or looke you after dreames?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>I am a wake.</l>
                     <l>And to ſend them to their eternall ſleepe.</l>
                     <l>In expedition there is ſtill ſucceſſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="77"/>
In all delayes defect: the traytor dyes</l>
                     <l>Were hee in league with all the deſtinies.</l>
                     <stage>Exe. Pilad. Oreſt.</stage>
                     <l>And tis a fruitfull yeare for villany,</l>
                     <l>And I a thrining Farmer. In this interim</l>
                     <l>I haue more plots on foote: King <hi>Menelaus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I haue incenc'd againſt proud <hi>Diom●d▪</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fyrhus</hi> againſt <hi>Orestes,</hi> hee 'gainſt him,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ʋlyſſes</hi> without parralell for wit</l>
                     <l>Againſt them all: ſo that the firſt combuſtion</l>
                     <l>Shall burne them vp to aſhes. Oh <hi>Palamides,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So deare was both thy loue and memory,</l>
                     <l>Not <hi>Hellen</hi> by her whoredome caus'd more blood</l>
                     <l>Streaming from Princes breſts, then <hi>Cethus</hi> ſhall</l>
                     <l>(Brother) for thine vntimely funerall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Egiſtus, Clitemneſtra</hi> with a ſtrong guard.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>Let none preſume to dare into our preſence</l>
                     <l>Or paſſe our guard, but ſuch well knowne to vs and to our Queene.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                     <l>The charge hath paſt vs round▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>When ſinnes of ſuch hye nature 'gainſt vs riſe,</l>
                     <l>Tis fit wee ſhould be kept with heedfull eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Preſume it my <hi>Egistus,</hi> we are ſafe,</l>
                     <l>The Fort wherein we liue impregnable:</l>
                     <l>Or ſay we were ſurpris'd by ſtratagem,</l>
                     <l>Or ſhould expoſe our liues vnto the cenſure</l>
                     <l>Of Law and Iuſtice, euen in theſe extreames</l>
                     <l>There were not the leaſt feare of difficulty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>Your reaſon Madam.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Whom doth this concerne</l>
                     <l>But our owne blood? ſhould <hi>Pyrhus</hi> grow inrag'd▪</l>
                     <l>I haue at hand my neece <hi>Hermione</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To calme his fury: what doth this belong to</l>
                     <l>Vlyſſes, <hi>or</hi> Aetolian Diomed?</l>
                     <l>Are they not ſtrangers? If it come in queſtion</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Menelaus,</hi> is hee not our brother▪</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="77"/>
Our ſiſter <hi>Hellen</hi> in his boſome ſleepes,</l>
                     <l>And can with him doe all things, feare not then,</l>
                     <l>Wee are euery way ſecure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh but <hi>Oreſtes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His ey's to mee like lightning, and his arme</l>
                     <l>Vp heau'd thus, ſhewes like <hi>Iones</hi> thunder-bolt</l>
                     <l>Aym'd againſt luſt and murder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee's our ſonne,</l>
                     <l>The filiall duty that's hereditary</l>
                     <l>Vnto a mothers name preuents theſe feares:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Electra</hi>'s young, and childiſh <hi>Pilades</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Swai'd by his friend: It reſts, could we but worke</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hellen</hi> and <hi>Menelaus</hi> to our faction,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Egistus</hi> ſhould be ſtated in <hi>Mycene,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wee liue his Queene and bride.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Feare's ſtill ſuſpicious.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter one of the guard.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                     <l>A Letter ſir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egi.</speaker>
                     <l>From whence?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis ſuperſcrib'd from the great <hi>Spartae's</hi> King,</l>
                     <l>And the Queene <hi>Hellen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egi.</speaker>
                     <l>Who the meſſenger?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                     <l>Two Gentlemen who much importune you</l>
                     <l>For ſpeedy anſwer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egi.</speaker>
                     <l>Bidde them waite without,</l>
                     <l>Now fates proue but propitious, then my kingdome</l>
                     <l>I ſhall preſume eſtabliſh't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>There's no feare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Orestes</hi> once remoou'd, and that's my charge</l>
                     <l>Either by ſword or poyſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egi.</speaker>
                     <l>See faire Queene,</l>
                     <l>Reade what your brother writes, by this we are</l>
                     <l>Eternis'd in our happineſſe, and our liues</l>
                     <l>Rooted in ſweete ſecurity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Queene reades.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee not ſuſpect you in our brothers death,</l>
                     <l>A deede too baſe for any Noble breſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="78"/>
Therefore in this neceſſity of ſtate,</l>
                     <l>And knowing in this forced vacancy</l>
                     <l>So great a kingdome cannot want a guide:</l>
                     <l>The ſoueraignty we thought good to conferre</l>
                     <l>On <hi>Clitemnestra,</hi> or whatſubſtiture</l>
                     <l>Shee in her beſt diſcretion ſhall thinke fit,</l>
                     <l>The vnited Kings of <hi>Greece</hi>●aue thus decre●d.</l>
                     <l>Your brother <hi>Menelaus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>We are happied euer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>A ioy ratified▪</l>
                     <l>And ſubiect to no change.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>Call in the meſſengers,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oreſtes</hi> and <hi>Electra</hi> once remoon'd,</l>
                     <l>Wee haue no riuall, no competitor,</l>
                     <l>Therefore no iealouſie at all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>None, none.</l>
                     <l>The gods haue with theſe Kings of <hi>Greece</hi> agreed</l>
                     <l>In his ſupplanting and inſtating thee,</l>
                     <l>Thee my moſt deare <hi>Egistus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Oreſtes</hi> and <hi>Pyllades</hi> diſguiſed are conducted in.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>You the men?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Thoſe, whom the <hi>Spartan</hi> King made ſpeciall choice of</l>
                     <l>To truſt this great affaire with.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egist.</speaker>
                     <l>And y'are welcome,</l>
                     <l>But are you men of action: ſuch I meane,</l>
                     <l>As haue beene Souldiers bred, whoſe eyes inur'd</l>
                     <l>To ſlaughter and combuſtions: at the like</l>
                     <l>Would not change face, or tremble?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>They that to ſee</l>
                     <l>Legges, armes, and heads ſtrowed on <hi>Scamander</hi> Plaine,</l>
                     <l>Kings by the common ſouldiers ſtew'd in goare,</l>
                     <l>And three parts hid with their imboweld Steedes,</l>
                     <l>Shadowing their mangled bodies from the Sunne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="78"/>
As if aboue the earth to bury them:</l>
                     <l>They that to ſee an <hi>Aſian</hi> Potentate</l>
                     <l>Kil'd at the holy Altar, his owne blood</l>
                     <l>Mixt with his ſonnes and daughters, Towers demoliſht</l>
                     <l>Cruſhing whole thouſands, of each ſexe and age</l>
                     <l>Beneath their ruines: and theſe horrid ſights</l>
                     <l>Lighted by ſcathe- fires, they that haue beheld</l>
                     <l>Theſe and more dreadfull obiects; can their eyes</l>
                     <l>Moue at a private ſlaughter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Y'are for vs,</l>
                     <l>Will you for hire, for fauour, or aduancement,</l>
                     <l>(Now warres are done) to be made great in Court,</l>
                     <l>And vndertake that one man eaſily ſpar'd</l>
                     <l>Amongſt ſo many millions (now ſuruiuing)</l>
                     <l>That ſuch a creature, no way neceſſary</l>
                     <l>But a meere burden to the world wee liue in,</l>
                     <l>Hee might no longer liue?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>But name the man,</l>
                     <l>And as I loue <hi>Egiſtus,</hi> honour you</l>
                     <l>And al that glory in ſuch noble deeds.</l>
                     <l>Be what hee will; hee's loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Orestes,</hi> then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Is there none then the world ſo well may ſpare</l>
                     <l>As young <hi>Oreſtes?</hi> Hee to doe't?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Hee kils <hi>Egiſtus,</hi> firſt diſcouering himſelfe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Vaine world farewell,</l>
                     <l>My hopes withall, no building long hath ſtood</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſleight foundation hath bin layd in blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le dye vpon his boſome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Secure the Fort my deare friend <hi>Pillades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And to your vtmoſt pacifie the guard:</l>
                     <l>Tell them we are <hi>Orestes</hi> and their Prince,</l>
                     <l>And what wee did was to reuenge the death</l>
                     <l>Of their dead Lord and Soueraig●e▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir i'le doe't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh mee, that thinking to haue catcht at Heauen,</l>
                     <l>Am plung'd into an hell of miſery.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Egistus</hi> dead? what comfort can I haue,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="79"/>
One foote Inthron'd, the tother in the graue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Can you finde teares for ſuch an abiect Groome,</l>
                     <l>That had not for an husband one to ſhed?</l>
                     <l>Oh monſtrous, monſtrous woman ● is this carrion,</l>
                     <l>Is this dead Dog, (Dog ſaid I?) nay what's worſe,</l>
                     <l>Worthy the ſigh or mourning of a Queene,</l>
                     <l>When a King lies vnpittied?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou a ſonne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>The name I am aſham'd of: oh Agamemnon,</l>
                     <l>How ſacred is thy name and memory!</l>
                     <l>Whoſe acts ſhall fill all forraigne Chronicles</l>
                     <l>With admiration, and moſt happy hee</l>
                     <l>That can with greateſt Art but booke thy deeds:</l>
                     <l>Yet whilſt this rottenneſſe, this gangreen'd fleſh</l>
                     <l>Whoſe carkas is as odious as his name</l>
                     <l>Shall ſtinking lie, able to breede a Peſt,</l>
                     <l>Hee with a Princeſſe teares to be imbalm'd,</l>
                     <l>And a King lie neglected?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Baſtard.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>If I be,</l>
                     <l>Damn'd be the whore my Mother, I, I am ſure</l>
                     <l>Nor my dead father had no hand in i●.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh that I could but lengthen out my yeares</l>
                     <l>Onely to ſpend in ●urſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon whom?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>On whom but thee for my <hi>Egistus</hi> death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>And I could wiſh my ſelfe a <hi>Neſtur●</hi> age</l>
                     <l>To curſe both him and thee for my dead father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Doeſt thou accuſe mee for thy fathers death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeede 'twould ill become me being a ſonne,</l>
                     <l>But were I ſure it were ſo, then I durſt;</l>
                     <l>Nay, more then that, reuenge it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon mee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                     <l>Were all the mothers of the earth in one,</l>
                     <l>All Empreſſes and Queenes caſt in one mould,</l>
                     <l>And I vnto that one a onely ſonne,</l>
                     <l>My ſword ſhould rauiſh that inceſtuous breast</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="79"/>
Of nature, and of ſtate▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>I am as innocent of that blacke deede,</l>
                     <l>As was this guiltleſſe Gentleman here dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh all you powers of Heauen I inuocate,</l>
                     <l>And if you will not heare me, let Hell do't:</l>
                     <l>Giue me ſome ſig●e from eyther feinds or angell,</l>
                     <l>I call you both as te●tates.</l>
                     <stage>Enter the Ghost of <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> poynting vnto his wounds: and then to <hi>Egiſtus</hi> and the Queene, who were his murderers, which done, hee vaniſheth.</stage>
                     <l>Godlike ſhape,</l>
                     <l>Haue you (my father) left the Elizium fieldes,</l>
                     <l>Where all the ancient Heroes line in bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>To bring your ſelfe that ſacred teſtimony,</l>
                     <l>To crowne my approbation: Lady ſee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>See what? thy former murder makes thee mad,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Reſt Ghoſt in peace, I now am ſatisfied,</l>
                     <l>And neede no further witneſſe: ſaw you nothing?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſhould I ſee ſaue this ſad ſpectacle,</l>
                     <l>Which blood-ſhootes both mine eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>And nothing elſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>Mine eyes are clearer ſighted then, and ſee</l>
                     <l>Into thy boſome. Murdreſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>How?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Inceſtuous ſtrumpet, whoſe adulteries,</l>
                     <l>When Treaſon could not hide, thou thoughts to couer,</l>
                     <l>With moſt inhumane murder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Meaning vs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Then, monſter, thou didſt firſt inſtruct mine hand,</l>
                     <l>How to write blood, when being a Wife and Queene,</l>
                     <l>Thou kildſt a King and husband, and haſt taught</l>
                     <l>Mee being a ſonne, how to deſtroy a mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>He wounds her.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh moſt vnnaturall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>That I learnt of thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnheard of cruelty, but heauens are ●uſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="80"/>
And all remarkeable ſinnes puniſh with marke,</l>
                     <l>One miſchiefe ſtill another doth beger,</l>
                     <l>Adultery murder: I am loſt, vndone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Shee dyes.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Being no wife, <hi>Orestes</hi> is no ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Cethus</hi> and <hi>Pillades</hi> with the guard.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>The guard all ſtand for you, acknowledging</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Orestes</hi> Prince and King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I now am neither.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>What obiect's this? Queene <hi>Clitemnestra</hi> ſ●aine?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope no ſonnes hand in't</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Orestes</hi> did it,</l>
                     <l>The other title's loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>All my plots take</l>
                     <l>Seyond my apprehe●ſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>This is an age</l>
                     <l>Of nothing but portents and prodigies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>The fathers hand as deepe was in her death</l>
                     <l>As was the ſonnes, hee pointed, and I ſtrooke:</l>
                     <l>Was hee not then as vnkind to a Wife,</l>
                     <l>As I was to a Mother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh my friend,</l>
                     <l>What haue you done?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>There is a <hi>Plaſma,</hi> or deepe pit</l>
                     <l>Iuſt in the Center fixt for Parricides,</l>
                     <l>I'l keepe my Court there, and <hi>Erinnis,</hi> ſhee</l>
                     <l>In ſtead of <hi>Hebe,</hi> ſhall attend my Cup,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Charon</hi> the Ferri-man of Hell ſhall bee</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Ganimed.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>The Prince is ſure diſtracted.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>New proiect ſtill for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le haue a guard of Furies which ſhall light mee</l>
                     <l>Vnto my nuptiall bed with funerall Teades,</l>
                     <l>The ●atall ſiſters ſhall my hand-maides b●e,</l>
                     <l>And waite vpon the faire <hi>Hermione.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hermione?</hi> ſhee is betroth'd to <hi>Pyrhus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And (mourning for your abſence) all the way</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Temple ſhee will ſtrowe with teares.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="80"/>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha? <hi>Pyrhus</hi> rape my deare <hi>Hermione?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hee that ſhall dare to interpoſe my purpoſe▪</l>
                     <l>Or croſſe mee in mine Hymineall rights,</l>
                     <l>I'le make him lie as flat on the cold earth</l>
                     <l>As doth this hound <hi>Egiſtus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>And I would ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                     <l>Would? ●ay I will, his father woare a ſmocks,</l>
                     <l>And in that ſhape rap't <hi>Deiadamia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hee ſhall not vſe my Loueſo, oh my Mother;</l>
                     <l>Friend take that obiect hence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>But you <hi>Hermione,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>My hand's yet deepe in blood, but to the wriſt,</l>
                     <l>It ſhall ſhall be to the elbowe: gods, nor men,</l>
                     <l>Angels, nor Furies ſhall my rage withſtand,</l>
                     <l>Not the graue Honour of th' aſſembled Kings,</l>
                     <l>Not Reuerence of the Altar, nor the Prieſt:</l>
                     <l>No ſuperſtition ſhall my fury ſlay▪</l>
                     <l>Till <hi>Pyrhus</hi> from the earth be ſwept away,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pillades</hi> attend your friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee's all my charge,</l>
                     <l>My life and his are twinnes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Their mines are countermin'd, <hi>Cethus,</hi> thy fall</l>
                     <l>Is either plotted, or to blowe vp all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Synon <hi>and</hi> Therſites.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>My head akes brother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>What a batchiler,</l>
                     <l>And troubled with the <hi>Spartan</hi> Kings diſeaſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>No, there's a wedding breeding in my braine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pyrhus</hi> the Bride-groome: thou ſtrange creature woman▪</l>
                     <l>To what may I compare thee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Canſt thou deuiſe ought bad inough?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis ſayd they looke like Angels, and of light▪</l>
                     <l>But for the moſt part, ſuch light Angels prooue,</l>
                     <l>Ten hundred thouſand of their honeſties</l>
                     <l>Will ſcarce weigh eleauen Dragmaes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Clite●neſtra,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="81"/>
And <hi>Hellen</hi> for example.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Young <hi>Hermi●ne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath face from both.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſharpe ſhrewes noſe, they hate hereditary.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſites,</hi> I commend that fellowes wit</l>
                     <l>Proffred a wife young, beautifull and rich,</l>
                     <l>Onely one fault ſhe had, ſhe wanted braine:</l>
                     <l>Who anſwered in a creature of that ſexe,</l>
                     <l>I nere deſire more wiſedome; then to know</l>
                     <l>Her husbands bed from anothers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>I commend him,</l>
                     <l>But tis not in th' <hi>Atrides</hi> family,</l>
                     <l>To finde out ſuch a woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>An Altar ſet fo●rth, Enter <hi>Pyrhus</hi> Lending <hi>Hermione</hi> as a bride, <hi>Menelaus, Vliſſes, Diomed.</hi> A great trayne, <hi>Pyrhus</hi> and <hi>Hermione</hi> kneele at the altar.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>See now the ſacred nuptiall rights proceede▪</l>
                     <l>The Prieſts prepare the Alter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fyr.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hymen</hi> to whom my vowes I conſecrate</l>
                     <l>As all my loue. To thee <hi>Hermione,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whom in the preſence of theſe Argiue Kings,</l>
                     <l>I heare contract, be thou auſpitious to vs:</l>
                     <l>This flamming ſubſtitute to <hi>Saturnes</hi> ſonne,</l>
                     <l>Within whoſe ſacred Temple wee are rooft▪</l>
                     <l>And before all theſe high Celeſtiall gods</l>
                     <l>And goddeſſes, in whoſe eyes now we kneele:</l>
                     <l>Eſpecially you <hi>I●n●</hi> Queene of marriage,</l>
                     <l>And faire <hi>Lucina,</hi> who haue child-births charge,</l>
                     <l>Your fauours I inuoake: Let your chaſt fires</l>
                     <l>Drye vp this Virgins teares; make her ſo fruitefull</l>
                     <l>That in her iſſue great <hi>Achilles</hi> name</l>
                     <l>And fame withall, may liue eternally▪</l>
                     <l>Proceede Prieſt to your other Ceremonies▪</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Oreſtes, Cethes,</hi> and <hi>Pilades,</hi> with the guard, all their weapons drawne, <hi>Oreſtes</hi>〈◊〉〈◊〉<hi>Pyrhus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="81"/>
                     <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Priam</hi> before the holy Alter fell,</l>
                     <l>Before the Alter bid thy life farwell:</l>
                     <l>Reſcue <hi>Hermione.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Achilles</hi> ſonne</l>
                     <l>Cannot reuengeleſſe dye, then witneſſe all,</l>
                     <l>Blood muſt flow high where ſuch great Princes fal.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pil.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oreſtes</hi> is in danger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mene.</speaker>
                     <l>Saue Prince <hi>Pyrhus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Cethus <hi>whiſpers with</hi> Dio|med.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>This plot was layd</l>
                     <l>Both for your life and Kingdome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dio.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Menelaus:</hi> ſhall neuer beare it ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vlyſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Fy <hi>Therſites,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy ſword againſt me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ther.</speaker>
                     <l>Curſe vpon all whoores.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A confuſed ſcuffle, in which <hi>Oreſtes</hi> kils <hi>Pyrhus: Pyrhus, Oreſtes: Cethus</hi> wounds <hi>Pillades, Diomed, Menelaus, Vliſſes, Therſites, &amp;c.</hi> All fall dead ſane <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> who beareth thence <hi>Hermione:</hi> which done, <hi>Cethus</hi> riſeth vp from the dead bodies and ſpeakes.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>What all aſleepe? and are theſe goſſiping tongues,</l>
                     <l>That boaſted nought faue Warre and Victory,</l>
                     <l>Now mute and ſilent? Oh thou vgly rogue,</l>
                     <l>Where's now thy rayling? and thou parracide,</l>
                     <l>Thy madneſſe is now tam'd, thou need'ſt no chaines</l>
                     <l>To bring thee to thy wits, darkneſſe hath don't.</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Diomed?</hi> who dar'd to encounter <hi>Mars,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſayd to wound faire <hi>Ʋenus</hi> in the hand:</l>
                     <l>Where's your valour now? <hi>Aegiale,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vnleſſe (as ſome ſay) ſhe be better ſtor'd,</l>
                     <l>Is like to lye without a bed-fellow:</l>
                     <l>Riſe <hi>Pillades,</hi> and helpe to awake thy friend,</l>
                     <l>What doth your friendſhip ſleepe now? <hi>Menelaus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hellen</hi>'s with a new ſweete-heart ith'next roome,</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou be ſtill a Cuckold? winke at errors</l>
                     <l>As pandors do and wittoles? <hi>Cethus</hi> now</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="82"/>
Be crown'd in Hyſtory for a reuenge,</l>
                     <l>Which in the former World wants preſident:</l>
                     <l>Methinks, as when the Giants warr'd'gainſt heauen,</l>
                     <l>And dar'd for primacy with <hi>Ioue</hi> himſelfe▪</l>
                     <l>Hee darting 'gainſt their mountaines thunder-boles▪</l>
                     <l>Which ſhattred them to peeces: the warre done,</l>
                     <l>I like the great Olimpicke <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Walke ore my ruines, tread vpon my ſpoyles</l>
                     <l>With maieſty, I pace vpon this floore</l>
                     <l>Pan'd with the trunkes of Kings and Potentates,</l>
                     <l>For what leſle could haue ſated my reuenge?</l>
                     <l>This arch-rogue falne amongſt them? he whoſe eie●</l>
                     <l>Had the prepoſterous vertue to fire <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now is thy blacke ſoule for thy periuries</l>
                     <l>Swimming in red damnation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Synon</hi> who had before counterfeited death, riſeth vp, and anſwereth.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, not yet,</l>
                     <l>All pollicies liue not in <hi>Cethus</hi> brayne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Synon</hi> hath ſhare, and know if thou haſt craft,</l>
                     <l>I haue reſeru'd ſome cunning: ſee my body</l>
                     <l>Free and vntoucht from wounds.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake, ſhall we then</l>
                     <l>Diuide theſe dead betwix● vs, and both liue?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>If two Sunnes cannot ſhine within one ſpheare,</l>
                     <l>Then why ſhould two arch-villaines? thou haſt diſcouered</l>
                     <l>Projects almoſt beyond me, and for which</l>
                     <l>I haue ingroſt a mortall enuy here,</l>
                     <l>I will be ſole, or none.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>Ceaſe then to be,</l>
                     <l>That I may liue without Competitor.</l>
                     <l>Cauſe <hi>Synons</hi> name be rae'd out of the World,</l>
                     <l>And onely mine remembred.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>Thine's but frailty,</l>
                     <l>My ●ame ſhall be immortall; made more glorious</l>
                     <l>In treading vpon thee, as thou on theſe;</l>
                     <l>●●oope thou my Vnderling.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="82"/>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſtill ſhall ſtand</l>
                     <stage>They fight, and kill one another.</stage>
                     <l>Rooted.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>And yet cut downe by <hi>Synons</hi> hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ceth.</speaker>
                     <l>I now am duſt like theſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syn.</speaker>
                     <l>One ſingle fight</l>
                     <l>Ends him, who millions ruin'd in one night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Hellena, Electra, <hi>and</hi> Hermione.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                     <l>Can you behold this ſlaughter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hel.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and dye</l>
                     <l>Atſight of it: for why ſhould <hi>Hellen</hi> liue▪</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hellen</hi> the cauſe of all theſe Princes deaths▪</l>
                     <l>Ceaſe to lament, reach me my Glaſſe <hi>Hermione,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sweete Orphant do; thy fathers dead already,</l>
                     <l>Nor will the fates lend thee a mother long.</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Hermione</hi> with a looking glaſſe, then exit.</stage>
                     <l>Thankes, and ſo leaue me. Was this wrinkled fore-head</l>
                     <l>When 'twas at beſt, worth halfe ſo many liues?</l>
                     <l>Where is that beauty? liues it in this face</l>
                     <l>Which hath ſet two parts of the World at warre,</l>
                     <l>Beene ruine of the <hi>Aſian</hi> Monarchy,</l>
                     <l>And almoſt this of <hi>Europe?</hi> this the beauty</l>
                     <l>That launch'd a thouſand ſhips from <hi>Aulis</hi> gulfe?</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a poore repurchaſe, now decayde?</l>
                     <l>See fayre ones, what a little Time can doe;</l>
                     <l>Who that conſiders when a ſeede is ſowne,</l>
                     <l>How long it is ere it appeare from th'earth,</l>
                     <l>Then ere it ſtalke, and after ere it blade,</l>
                     <l>Next ere it ſpread in leaues, then bud, then flower:</l>
                     <l>What care in watring, and in weeding tooke,</l>
                     <l>Yet crop it to our vſe: the beauties done,</l>
                     <l>And ſmel: they ſcarſe laſt betwixt Sunne and Sunne▪</l>
                     <l>Then why ſhould theſe my blaſtings ſtill ſuruiue,</l>
                     <l>Such royall ruines: or I longer liue,</l>
                     <l>Then to be termed <hi>Hellen</hi> the beautifull.</l>
                     <l>I am growne old, and Death is ages due,</l>
                     <l>When Courtiers ſooth, our glaſſes will tell true.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="83"/>
My beauty made me pittied, and ſtill lou'd,</l>
                     <l>But that decay'd, the worlds aſſured hate</l>
                     <l>Is all my dowre, then <hi>Hellen</hi> yeeld to fate▪</l>
                     <l>Here's that, my ſoule and body muſt diuide,</l>
                     <l>The guerdon of Adultery, Luſt, and Pride.</l>
                     <stage>Shee stran|gles her ſelfe</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Ʋlyſſe●.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vlyſ.</speaker>
                     <l>In thee they are puniſh t: of all theſe Princes,</l>
                     <l>And infinite numbers that oppoſed <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And came in <hi>Hellens</hi> quarrell (ſaue my ſelfe).</l>
                     <l>Not one ſuruies, (thankes to the immortall powers)</l>
                     <l>And I am purpoſde now to acquire by Sea,</l>
                     <l>My Kingdome and my deare <hi>Penelope,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſince I am the man ſoly reſeru'd,</l>
                     <l>Accept me for the Authors Epilogue.</l>
                     <l>If hee haue beene two bloody? tis the Story,</l>
                     <l>Truth claimes excuſe, and ſeekes no farther glory,</l>
                     <l>Or if you thinke he hath done your patience wrong</l>
                     <l>(In teadious Sceanes) by keeping you ſo long,</l>
                     <l>Much matter in few words, hee bad me ſay</l>
                     <l>Are hard to expreſſe, that lengthned out his Play.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>Explicit Actus quintus.</trailer>
               </div>
               <trailer>Here ends the whole Hiſtory of the destruction of <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         </TEI>

