<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
            <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>225 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99852323</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22221.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1105-6.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">17639</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
                  <title type="alt">Tragedies. English</title>
                  <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
                  <author>Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598,</author>
                  <author>Neville, Alexander, 1544-1614,</author>
                  <author>Studley, John, 1545?-1590?,</author>
                  <author>T. N. d. 1617,</author>
                  <author>Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 65, 64-217, [1] leaves.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>In Fleetstreete neere vnto Saincte Dunstans church by Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Editor's dedication signed: Thomas Newton.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>In verse.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>A reprinting of the following translations previously published separately: "Hercules furens", "Thyestes", and "Troas" by Jasper Heywood; "¦edipus" by Alexander Neville (a revised version); "Medea" and "Agamemnon" by John Studley; and "Octavia" (not by Seneca) by Thomas Nuce. Prints for the first time "Hippolytus" and "Hercules Oetæus" translated by Studley, and "Thebais" translated by Thomas Newton.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <body>
        <div type="title_page">
           <pb facs="1"/>
           <pb facs="1"/>
           <p>SENECA
              HIS TENNE TRA|GEDIES,
              TRANSLA|TED
              INTO
              Englyſh.</p>
           <p>Mercurij nutrices, horae.</p>
           <p>IMPRINTED
              AT LONDON IN
              Fleetſtreete neere vnto
              <hi>Saincte Dunſtans</hi>
              church by Tho|mas
              Marſh.
              1581</p>
        </div>
        <div type="dedication">
           <pb facs="2"/>
           <pb facs="2"/>
           <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR|SHIPEVL,
              SIR THOMAS HEN|NEAGE
              KNIGHT, TREASVRER OF
              HER MAIESTIES CHAMBER:
              Thomas Newton wisheth all abundaunce
              of Felicitie, and Spirituall bene|dictions
              in Chriſte.
              {invertedl ⁂}</head>
           <p>_YOV may think Sir, ſome want of
              diſcretion in mee, for thus bold|ly
              preſuminge to thrust into your
              handes theſe Tragedies of SE|NECA.
              From whych boldneſſe,
              the very Conſcience of myne own
              vnworthynes, might eaſely haue
              diſſuaded mee, had not certayne
              learned Gentlemen of good credite and worship thereun|to
              perſuaded &amp; animated mee. Aſſuring mee (where of
              I thought my ſelfe afore aſſured) that your VVorship (ſuch
              is your loue to learning, &amp; the generoſity of your Heroi|call
              mynde) would daygne not onely to diſpence with my
              temerity, but alſo take in worth my affectionate ſimpli|city.
              And yet (all this notwithstandinge) well durst I
              not haue geuen the aduēture to approch your preſence, vp|on
              trust of any ſingularity, that in this Booke hath vn|ſki●fully
              dropped out of myne owne penne, but that I hoped
              the perfection of others artificiall workmāſhip, that haue
              trauayled herein aſwell as my ſelfe ſhould ſomewhat couer
              my nakednèſſe 〈◊〉 pùrchaſe my pardon. And hard were
              <pb facs="3"/>
              the dealing, if in payment of a good round gubbe of Gold
              of full wayght and poyſe, one poore peece ſomewhat clypped
              and lighter then his fellowes may not be foysted in amōg
              the reſt, and paſſe in pay for currant coigne. Theirs I know
              to be deliuered with ſinguler dexterity: myne, I confeſſe
              to be an vnflidge neſtling, vnhable to flye: an vnnatural
              abortion, and an vnperfect Embryon: neyther throughlye
              laboured at Aristophanes and Cleanthes candle, neither
              yet exactly waighed in Critolaus his preciſe ballaūce. Yet
              this dare I ſaye, I haue deliuered myne Authors meaning
              with as much perſpicuity, as ſo meane a Scholler, out of ſo
              meane a ſtoare, in ſo ſmal a time, and vpon ſo ſhort a war|ning
              was well able to performe. And whereas it is by ſome
              ſqueymiſh Areopagites ſurmyzed, that the readinge of
              theſe Tragedies, being enterlarded with many Phraſes
              and ſentēces, literally tending (at the firſt ſight) ſome time
              to the prayſe of Ambition, ſometyme to the mayntenaūce
              of cruelty, now and then to the approbation of inconti|nencie,
              and here and there to the ratification of tyranny,
              can not be digeſted without great daūger of infection: to
              omit all other reaſons, if it might pleaſe thē with no fore|ſtalled
              iudgmēt, to mark and conſider the circumſtaunces,
              why, where, &amp; by what maner of perſons ſuch ſentences are
              pronoūced, they cānot in any equity otherwiſe chooſe, but
              find good cauſe ynough to leade thē to a more fauourable
              and milde reſolutiō. For it may not at any hād be thought
              and deemed the direct meaning of SÈNECA himſelfe,
              whoſe whole wrytinges (penned with a peereleſſe ſublimi|ty
              and loftineſſe of Style, are ſo farre from còuntenaun|cing
              Vice, that I doubt whether there bee any amonge all
              the Catalogue of Heathen wryters, that with more gra|uity
              <pb facs="3"/>
              of Philoſophicall ſentences, more waightynes of ſappy
              words, or greater authority of ſoūd matter beateth down
              ſinne, looſe lyfe, diſſolute dealinge, and vnbrydled ſenſu|ality:
              or that more ſenſibly, pithily, and bytingly layeth
              downe the guerdon of filthy luſt, cloaked diſsimulation &amp;
              odious treachery: which is the dryft, wherunto he leueleth
              the whole yſſue of ech one of his Tragedies. Howſoeuer &amp;
              whatſoeuer it be, your VVorships curteous acceptaūce shal
              eaſily counterpoyſe any of our imperfections. Vnto whoſe
              learned Cenſure, wee humbly ſubmit theſe the exerciſes of
              our bluſshing Muſes. The Lord God in mercy long pre|ſerue
              you in health and dignity with daily encreaſe of ma|ny
              his gracious gyfts, already rychly abounding in you: to
              the propagation, and aduauncement of his truth (where|of
              yee are a zealous Profeſſor, to the honoure of her Ma|ieſtye,
              to whom you are a moſt loyall ſeruitour, and to the
              generall benefite of your Countrey, whereof you are a rare
              and moſt worthy Ornament.</p>
           <closer>
              <dateline>From Butley in Cheſſhyre <date>the 24. of Aprill.
                 1581.</date>
              </dateline>
              <signed>Your Worſhippes moſt humble,
                 Thomas Newton.</signed>
           </closer>
        </div>
        <div type="table_of_contents">
           <pb facs="4"/>
           <head>THE NAMES OF
              THE TRAGEDIES OF
              SENECA, AND
              by whom each of
              them was tran|ſlated.</head>
           <list>
              <item>1 Hercules Furens,</item>
              <item>2 Thyeſtes,</item>
              <item>6 Troas,
                 <list>
                    <item>By Iaſper Heywood.</item>
                    <item>1560.</item>
                 </list>
              </item>
              <item>5 Oedipus,
                 <list>
                    <item>By Alex. Neuile.</item>
                 </list>
              </item>
              <item>4 Hippolytus,</item>
              <item>7 Medea,</item>
              <item>8 Agamemnon,</item>
              <item>10 Hercules Octaeus
                 <list>
                    <item>By Iohn Studley.</item>
                 </list>
              </item>
              <item>9 Octauia,
                 <list>
                    <item>By T. Nuce.</item>
                 </list>
              </item>
              <item>3 Thebais.
                 <list>
                    <item>By Thomas Newton.</item>
                 </list>
              </item>
           </list>
        </div>
     </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
