<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A13613">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The two first comedies of Terence called Andria, and the Eunuch newly Englished by Thomas Newman. Fitted for scholler priuate action in their schooles.</title>
            <author>Terence.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>88 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 December (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99838757</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 23897.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">3145</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13613</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">The two first comedies of Terence called Andria, and the Eunuch newly Englished by Thomas Newman. Fitted for scholler priuate action in their schooles.</title>
                  <title type="alt">Andria. English</title>
                  <title type="alt">Andria.</title>
                  <title type="add">Eunuchus.</title>
                  <author>Terence.</author>
                  <author>Newman, Thomas, fl. 1627,</author>
                  <author>Terence.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 110 [i.e. 108], [2] p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M[iller] and are to be sold at the house of M. Fenricus next to the Grayhound Tauerne in the Black-Friers,</publisher>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Verse translations, by Thomas Newman, of Terence's Andria and Eunuchus.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>The Eunuch begins on verso of F2 [i.e. E2].</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Pages 50-51 repeated in number only; 60-61 and 63-64 missing in number only; 56-57 misnumbered 58-59; E2 missigned F2.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Errata on recto of H8, final leaf.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Preliminary pages and 81-82 torn. Beginning-page 1 and 76-101 from Folger Shakespeare Library copy spliced at end.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="8"/>
            <head>The Andrian Woman.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The ARGVMENT according to <hi>Muretus</hi> collection.</head>
               <p>_THere were two brethren Citizens of Athens, the one called <hi>Chremes</hi> the o|ther <hi>Phania. Chremes</hi> being to trauell into Aſia left the charge of his then onely daughter <hi>Baſibula</hi> an infant with his brother <hi>Phania.</hi> Shortly after his departure out of Attica, <hi>Phania</hi> alſo to auoid the rage of warre growing hot in Greece, ſhipped himſelfe thence with his little niece, directing his courſe towards the place where he ſuppoſed <hi>Chremes</hi> aboad: but ſuffering ſhipwracke was caſt with the little one, vpon the ſhoare of the Iſle of Andros, where getting entertainement of a poore Iſlander he ſhortly after died. His hoſt after his deceaſe, changeth the childs name from <hi>Paſibula</hi> into <hi>Glycerium;</hi> and hauing bred her vp for ſome yeares in e|quall education with his owne naturall child called <hi>Chry|ſis,</hi> himſelfe alſo dyeth. <hi>Chremes</hi> in the <hi>Interim</hi> had returned to Athens, and there had another daughter named <hi>Philu|mena:</hi> And all this while ſuppoſed his brother and his o|ther daughter to haue long ſince periſhed at ſea. <hi>Chriſis</hi> being left fatherleſſe and poore leaues <hi>Andros,</hi> and taking <hi>Glycerium</hi> with her ſailes to Athens; where they dwell to|gether as reputed ſiſters. <hi>Chriſis</hi> turnes harlot: her louers draw along with them to her houſe one <hi>Pamphilus</hi> ſonne of <hi>Simo</hi> an antient Athenian Citizen. <hi>Pamphilus</hi> falling in loue with <hi>Glycerium</hi> gets her with child, and affianceth
<pb facs="8"/>himſelfe to her. <hi>Chremes</hi> vpon a publique fame of <hi>Pamphi|lus</hi> his vertues treates with <hi>Simo</hi> for a match betweene their children <hi>Pamphilus</hi> and <hi>Philumena:</hi> and a marriage is agreed vpon betweene the two old fathers, <hi>Pamphilus</hi> be|ing not made acquainted. <hi>Chryſis</hi> ſoone after dies, at whoſe funerals <hi>Pamphilus</hi> occaſionally diſcouered ſignes of very ardent affection to <hi>Glycerium;</hi> which <hi>Chremes</hi> hearing of, renounceth him for ſonne in law as one apparantly be|ſotted and intangled with extraordinarie loue to a ſtrag|ling ſtrumpet (ſo ignorantly he ſtiled the iſſue of his pro|per loynes) <hi>Pamphilus</hi> (now firſt hearing of the determi|ned match) is glad ſuch marriage is diſappointed. <hi>Simo</hi> frets at it. And now is the prefixed day of marriage come, be|ing the day containing the argument of this Coinedie. <hi>Simo</hi> makes ſhew to all the people of his familie, as if the marriage were on this day to be ſolemnized, and this he did out of a foxlike ſubtiltie to feele his ſonnes inclinati|on to marriage, and vpon his refuſall to haue iuſt occa|ſion of complaint againſt him, which hitherto he had not. And if his ſonne ſhould declare readineſſe to entertaine the match, he then thought it would proue no ſuch diffi|cult matter to cuerrule <hi>Chremes;</hi> and ſo the buſineſſe to go on as it was firſt determined. <hi>Simo</hi> hauing thus proie|cted matters, meets his ſonne; and wils him to pray to the gods for ſucceſſe vpon his marriage inſtantly to bee a|compliſhed. The ſonne at his fathers ſalutation ſtands thunderſtrucken, ignorant what courſe to take for pre|uention. <hi>Dauus</hi> comes to him in this diſtraction, at what time one <hi>Charinus</hi> was with him. This <hi>Charinus</hi> was a yong man inflamed with the loue of <hi>Philumena,</hi> the intended bride; and was now in a manner deſperate, when he vn|derſtood that <hi>Pamphilus</hi> was that day to marrie her: <hi>Pam|philus</hi> aſſuers him of his purpoſed reſolution to the con|trarie. This was the theame of their diſcourſe when <hi>Dauus</hi> came vpon them. <hi>Dauus</hi> (now) was <hi>Simoes</hi> ſeruant, a fellow
<pb facs="9"/>of good reach: and he vpon grounds reaſonable had con|ceiued his old maſters fetch in this pretended marriage, which (hauing ſent away <hi>Charinus</hi>) he opens to <hi>Pamphilus:</hi> reſoluing him that in all likelihood the old man did but caſt out a hooke to catch at his inclination to <hi>Glycerium:</hi> wiſhing him therefore without all ſcruple to promiſe his father all obedience and readineſſe in imbracing this fa|ced marriage; he further intimates, that no hazard was likely hereby to inſue: for that <hi>Chremes</hi> hauing once open|ly refuſed him, would not (at leaſt ſo ſuddenly) intertaine him for a ſonne in law. <hi>Pamphilus</hi> puts the aduice in exe|cution. <hi>Simo</hi> and <hi>Dauus</hi> venter either of them vpon the ha|zard, but <hi>Simo</hi> his lucke carries it. For <hi>Chremes</hi> is wonne to a new conſent, and now is <hi>Pamphilus</hi> in danger to bee caſt vpon a preſent marriage, where hee neuer intended. What may <hi>Dauus</hi> how do? author of a counſell not ſo vn|likely as vnluckie? Chance preſents him occaſion, and he hath good braine to make vſe of the leaſt offered occaſi|on: what is that? <hi>Glycerium</hi> is brought to bed: the new borne child is by her maid, but by <hi>Dauus</hi> direction) laid at <hi>Simo's</hi> doore: and this is done iuſt when <hi>Chremes</hi> muſt of neceſſitie ſee it: <hi>Dauus</hi> further ſo carries the matter, that <hi>Chremes</hi> vnderſtands who is father, who is mother to the child. Theſe things inſtly mone <hi>Chremes</hi> to a ſecond re|nunciation: Hence great ſtirie ariſeth: <hi>Crito</hi> a man of <hi>Andros</hi> (arriued at Athens vpon newes of <hi>Cryſis</hi> her death, being next heire to her eſtate) ends all; by diſcovering <hi>Glyceriums</hi> freedome &amp; parentage. <hi>Pamphilus</hi> marries <hi>Gly|cerium</hi> now againe knowne by her firſt name <hi>Paſibula; Charinus</hi> marries the other ſiſter <hi>Philumena.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="dramatis_personae">
               <pb facs="9"/>
               <head>The Actors and their Characters.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SImo</hi> An old man carefull of his ſonne, whom hee loued at firſt for his reported vertues: and after he once doubted his carriage, ſhewed his greater loue in his care of him. In the firſt Seene he carries himſelfe milde in diſcourſe and behauiour: and ſtill after in|creaſeth in angry moode, till at length he growes to rage and paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pamphilus.</hi> Sonne to <hi>Simo,</hi> a well qualified young man and faithfull louer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauus</hi> Seruant of the family, ſubtile wife, conſident.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dromo.</hi> Another ſeruant, onely vſed for <hi>Dauus</hi> puniſh|ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Soſia. Snno's</hi> freed-man, a protaticke perſon brought in onely, to whom the ground of the argument might be opened.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chremes.</hi> an old man of a quiet and tranquill ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Glycerium.</hi> Daughter of <hi>Chremes</hi> not preſented on the Stage; neither ſpeakes but within doores in labor of child-birth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lesbia.</hi> Her midwife.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miſis.</hi> Hermaid-ſeruant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charinus.</hi> A young man, ſimple and ignorant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Byrrhia.</hi> His man for wit aboue his maſter. Diſcreete.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Crito.</hi> A ſtranger of Andros, poore yet honeſt, wiſe and of a good ſpirit and ſtomach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prologue">
               <head>The Prologue.</head>
               <l>OVr Poet firſt ſetting his mind to write,</l>
               <l>Deemd this the ſole maine charge vpon him laid,</l>
               <l>To pleaſe the people with the playes he made:</l>
               <pb facs="10"/>
               <l>But now he finds that he miſreckond quite.</l>
               <l>For, that he cannot (Prologue wiſe) now lay</l>
               <l>The argument of this his play aright,</l>
               <l>Is cauſd by an old rank'rous Poets ſpite;</l>
               <l>Who drutes him to cleare faultes, leaue the meant way.</l>
               <l>Now pray obſerue their cauellings: thoſe playes</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andria</hi> and <hi>Perinthia,</hi> which <hi>Menander wrote,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Know one, know both) not much vnlike in plot,</l>
               <l>Are different yet both in their ſtile and phraſe.</l>
               <l>He not denies that from <hi>Perinthia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe things which ſeemd conuenient in the ſame,</l>
               <l>He (as his owne) hath drawne into the frame,</l>
               <l>And courſe of this preſented <hi>Andria.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This is the thing they challenge: and they braule</l>
               <l>That in ſuch ſort a cleanely Comedie</l>
               <l>Should not be hotch-potchd. Theſe men verily</l>
               <l>While much they ſeeme, ſhew they know nought at all:</l>
               <l>Who him accuſing draw his preſidents</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nauius, Plautus, Ennius,</hi> in like crime,</l>
               <l>To whoſe miſtakings he would rather climbe,</l>
               <l>Then follow theſe mens obſcure diligence.</l>
               <l>I further wiſh'hem hence ſoorth keepe'hem ſtill;</l>
               <l>And ceaſe with euill language him to ſting;</l>
               <l>Leſt their ill doing in their eares do ring.</l>
               <l>Spectators kind, of you we craue good will;</l>
               <l>In ſilence ſhewne and kinde attention;</l>
               <l>That without preiudice our play y'ould heare:</l>
               <l>Thence you may fully know, if it reſt cleare,</l>
               <l>That all our future purpoſd action</l>
               <l>Of new made playes be to be baniſht quite;</l>
               <l>Without aduentring your hereafter ſight:</l>
            </div>
            <div type="play_proper">
               <pb n="1" facs="10"/>
               <head>THE ANDRIAN VVOMAN.</head>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <head>Act. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Simo <hi>and</hi> Soſia <hi>with two or three ſeruanes more bearing prouiſion from the Market.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Simo.</speaker>
                        <p>_YOu ſirs haue thoſe things in: away I ſay.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt the ſeruants.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſia</speaker>
                        <p>draw neere; I am to ſpeak with you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I thinke th'errand giu'n;</l>
                        <l>your meaning is</l>
                        <l>I looke to thoſe things carefull cookery.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>No: tis another matter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Pray ſay on</l>
                        <l>What tis, my art may further doe for you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Here's neede of no ſuch art, in what I purpoſe;</l>
                        <l>But of thoſe parts which I haue euer noted</l>
                        <l>To dwell in thee; truſt, and true ſecrecie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I waite your pleaſure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Since I bought thee firſt</l>
                        <l>Being then a yongling, in what gentle ſort,</l>
                        <l>In what due courſe, thou ledſt thy ſeruice with me,</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelfe well know'ſt: and for I found thee carefull</l>
                        <l>In thy imployments, the beſt good I had</l>
                        <l>To anſwer it, I gaue thee; libertie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="2" facs="11"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I ●●●re it ſir in minde.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>And I repent nor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>〈◊〉 is my harts ioy Maſter, if I did</l>
                        <l>Or 〈◊〉 can doe, ought to your ſatisfaction;</l>
                        <l>And further owe you thankes that you acknowledge</l>
                        <l>I well accepted: yet it troubles me,</l>
                        <l>For this remembrancing your benefit,</l>
                        <l>Seemes to vpbraid me, as forgetting it.</l>
                        <l>Pray in one word acquaint me with your pleaſure.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I will; but firſt I tell thee of this thing,</l>
                        <l>This which thou thinkſt is no meant marriage.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why make you as it were then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt heare</l>
                        <l>From the beginning all: and by that meanes</l>
                        <l>Shalt better know my Sonnes forepaſſed life,</l>
                        <l>My preſent purpoſe, and thy future charge.</l>
                        <l>My Sonne hauing paſt his childhood <hi>Soſia</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Hath now more ſcope allowed him; before</l>
                        <l>How could one know or fiſt his diſpoſition,</l>
                        <l>While tender age, ſeare, tutors awed him?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, you ſay right.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>What almoſt all youth doe,</l>
                        <l>To ſet their minde on one ſome choſen courſe;</l>
                        <l>That to breede Herſe, this Hounds, and both to hunt,</l>
                        <l>A third to ſtudy of Phyloſophie:</l>
                        <l>He none of theſe followed profeſſedly,</l>
                        <l>Aboue the reſt: but yet all moderately.</l>
                        <l>I ioyd at it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, not without good cauſe:</l>
                        <l>"For to oredoe no one thing, in my ſence</l>
                        <l>"To mans life is of chiefeſt conſequence.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Such his behauiour; all thoſe gently</l>
                        <l>To beare and forbeare, that he kept withall;</l>
                        <l>Apply himſelfe to pleaſe and humor all;</l>
                        <l>Croſſe none, nor proudly ſeeke to ouertop</l>
                        <l>His young companions: ſo that eaſily</l>
                        <l>He got him friends and praiſe; yet without enuie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>He bare him wiſely: for in this times ſtate</l>
                        <l>Sweet yeelding procures friends; blunt truth gets hate.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="3" facs="11"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Meane while a certaine woman three yeeres ſince</l>
                        <l>Drawne by her wants and kindreds negligence,</l>
                        <l>From <hi>Anaros</hi> Iſle came to our neighborhood;</l>
                        <l>Of paſſing beautie, flouring womanhood.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſeare this <hi>Andrian</hi> woman bodes no good.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>She at the firſt a ſparing chaſte life led;</l>
                        <l>At Rocke and Loome, hard labord to get bread:</l>
                        <l>But when a firſt, a ſecond, a third came;</l>
                        <l>Tendring their loues, gifts promiſ'd with the ſame,</l>
                        <l>(As all our natures are prone commonly</l>
                        <l>From labour vnto wanton libertie)</l>
                        <l>She ſtoop'd to lure, began the gainfull trade.</l>
                        <l>By thoſe that then chiefe loue vnto her made,</l>
                        <l>My Sonne was drawne along occaſionally</l>
                        <l>To banquet with 'hem; keepe 'hem company.</l>
                        <l>I to my ſelfe — Sure the young frie is tane:</l>
                        <l>H'as catcht the poiſoned bait; with it, his bane.</l>
                        <l>Theſe louers ſeruants paſſing to and fro</l>
                        <l>I eu'rie morning watch; and calling to</l>
                        <l>One that I ſpied, thus queſtion; Prethee lad,</l>
                        <l>Who yeſterday yond <hi>Chryſis</hi> company had?</l>
                        <l>So was the <hi>Andrian</hi> call'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir. I conceaue you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>The anſwer was, <hi>Phoedrus,</hi> or <hi>Nicerate,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Or <hi>Clinias</hi> (for at that time thoſe three</l>
                        <l>Her ioyntly lou'd.) I reply preſently,</l>
                        <l>And what did <hi>Pamphilus?</hi> what? (anſwers he.)</l>
                        <l>He ſtak'd his ſhare, and ſupp'd: this gladded me.</l>
                        <l>At other times I caſt more newes to learne;</l>
                        <l>Still nothing found that did my Sonne concerne.</l>
                        <l>I thought him now proofe-temper'd gainſt exceſſe,</l>
                        <l>Great patterne of a ſetled ſtaiedneſſe.</l>
                        <l>For he that deales with natures of this kinde,</l>
                        <l>Yet thereby growes not ſlagg'ring in his minde;</l>
                        <l>To ſuch a mans owne hands thou maiſt be bold</l>
                        <l>To leaue the free reignes of his life in hold.</l>
                        <pb n="4" facs="12"/>
                        <l>As this gaue me moſt ſatisfying pleaſure,</l>
                        <l>So all tongues talk'd my good, proclaim'd my treaſure,</l>
                        <l>In hauing ſuch a qualified Sonne.</l>
                        <l>What ſhould I make further relation?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chremes</hi> our neighbour drawne by this ſame bruit,</l>
                        <l>Freely comes to me; and makes earneſt ſuit</l>
                        <l>To place his daughter, yea his onely one</l>
                        <l>With a large dowre as wife vnto my Sonne:</l>
                        <l>I agreed the marriage, on his motion;</l>
                        <l>And this the day, it is appointed on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>What barie now ſtoppeth? why in very deede</l>
                        <l>According to the ſhew, it not proceede?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile tell thee: few dayes after this befell,</l>
                        <l>Our neighbour <hi>Chryſis</hi> died.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>That's chanced well.</l>
                        <l>You haue reuin'd me; I much doubted her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>With <hi>Chryſis</hi> louers ſtill my Sonne comes there</l>
                        <l>Alike her funerall lookes to; alike cheere</l>
                        <l>Sometimes of ſadneſſe ſhewes, ſometimes alike</l>
                        <l>Weepes with 'hem: I his carriage well did like</l>
                        <l>Thus argued I; Her death how tenderly</l>
                        <l>For very ſmall acquaintance doth he take?</l>
                        <l>What, if himſelfe had lou'd her? what for me,</l>
                        <l>What will he doe for me, his Fathers ſake?</l>
                        <l>All this I thought in my ſimplcitie,</l>
                        <l>Meerely the functions of humilitie,</l>
                        <l>And of kinde heart. Why leng then I my tale?</l>
                        <l>My ſelfe for his ſake tend the funerall.</l>
                        <l>Dreaming as yet no euill.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! what meanes this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile cauſe thee know. The dead corps is brought out;</l>
                        <l>Along we goe; now there amidſt the throng</l>
                        <l>Of wonten, I a maiden very young</l>
                        <l>Perchance eſpied; of perſon—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Perhaps handſome.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I, and of countenance <hi>Soſia</hi> ſo delightſome,</l>
                        <l>So modeſt, faire, that nothing might her ſtaine:</l>
                        <l>Who for ſhe ſeem'd to me, in all the traine</l>
                        <l>Moſt to lament; and was aboue the reſt</l>
                        <pb n="5" facs="12"/>
                        <l>Of ſweet and comely perſonage and face.</l>
                        <l>I preſt neere to the Maids, askt what ſhe was:</l>
                        <l>They told me <hi>Chryſis</hi> ſiſter. Inſtantly</l>
                        <l>It ſtrooke me cold at heart. Oh God! thought I,</l>
                        <l>Hence grew his teares: his tenderneſſe ſhe breeds.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>How I doe feare whither your tale proceeds.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>The Funerall goes on: we attend the ſame</l>
                        <l>To th'Sepulchre ſhe's come: into the flame</l>
                        <l>She's put: all weepe. The maid I named late</l>
                        <l>Approacht the fire, as careleſſe, deſperate;</l>
                        <l>To her euident danger: here my frighted Sonne</l>
                        <l>Well ſhewed his long concealed affection</l>
                        <l>So cloſe diſſembled: to her hies he faſt,</l>
                        <l>And both his armes folding about her waſt,</l>
                        <l>My deere <hi>Glycerium</hi> ſaies he, how dooſt? ſay,</l>
                        <l>What cauſe haſt thou to make thy ſelfe away?</l>
                        <l>Then ſhe (that all their indeard loue might ſpie)</l>
                        <l>Caſt her ſelfe on him, weeping tenderly.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>How? what doe you ſay?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Home I get mee ſtreight,</l>
                        <l>Inrag'd and fretting; yet no cauſe of weight</l>
                        <l>Appeard to me to chide him: he might plead,</l>
                        <l>What foule fact haue I done? what merited?</l>
                        <l>Or wherein faulted, Father? one that ſought</l>
                        <l>To burne her ſelfe, I hindred (as I ought)</l>
                        <l>And ſau'd her life. It were a faire reply.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <l>You weigh things well; for if deſeruedly</l>
                        <l>He may be chidden which help'd life to ſaue,</l>
                        <l>Who hurts or ſpoiles one, what ſhould that man haue?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Next day comes <hi>Chremes</hi> to me, vrging thus,</l>
                        <l>Oh caſe to be lamented! <hi>Pamphilus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>(I finde cleare) holds yond ſtranger harlotrie</l>
                        <l>In place of a iuſt wife: this earneſtly</l>
                        <l>I doe denie, he ſtifly holds. In fine,</l>
                        <l>I ſo part with him, as one vtterly</l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="13"/>
                        <l>Denies to giue his Daughter to my Sonne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Chid you not <hi>Pamphilus</hi> yet?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Nor yet I ſaw</l>
                        <l>A grounded cauſe to build a chiding on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why I pray?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Thus my Sonne might vrge his law:</l>
                        <l>Your ſelfe ſir ſet a limitation</l>
                        <l>To this my courſe: the time is comming on,</l>
                        <l>I muſt my ſelfe to anothers will apply:</l>
                        <l>Let meath interim mine owne ſatisfie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>For what cauſe then of blaming will you 〈◊〉</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>If for looſe loue he ſhall dome to marrie</l>
                        <l>That is the firſt occaſion that I ſeeke</l>
                        <l>Againſt him; and the preſent way I make</l>
                        <l>By this ſelfe marriage, if he ſhew miſlike</l>
                        <l>Is hereby true pretence of blame to take.</l>
                        <l>Beſides, if wicked <hi>Dauus</hi> haue a foot</l>
                        <l>Any contriuement, that he now conſume</l>
                        <l>His ſtocke of knauerie whil'ſt it cannot hurt</l>
                        <l>Who (I imagine) tooth and naile will practiſe,</l>
                        <l>And that with purpoſe rather to croſſe me</l>
                        <l>Then pleaſe my Sonne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſhould you ſo conceaue?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Mak'ſt thou a queſtion? euill mindes, ill manners.</l>
                        <l>Whom if in any thing I ſhall diſcouer —</l>
                        <l>But what neede talke? if happily it fall</l>
                        <l>(As I doe wiſh) my Sonne be nothing backward,</l>
                        <l>It onely reſts, that I perſwade with <hi>Chremes:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which I hope may be wrought. Now, be't your charge</l>
                        <l>Well to beare vp this ſeeming marriage;</l>
                        <l>Fright <hi>Dauus;</hi> obſerue my Sonnes carriage;</l>
                        <l>And note their conſultations.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis enough; Ile ſee to 't: ſhall we in.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Goe before, I follow.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Soſia.</stage>
                        <l>There is no queſtion, my Sonne would decline</l>
                        <l>This marriage; that I markt in <hi>Dauus</hi> ſeare,</l>
                        <pb n="7" facs="13"/>
                        <l>When he had heard tht wedding did goe forward.</l>
                        <l>But he himſelfe comes forth.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>Enter Dauus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>I Marld if this would end ſo, and ſtill doubted</l>
                        <l>Whereto my Maſters caline remiſneſſe tended:</l>
                        <l>Who when he ſaw his Sonne could haue no wife,</l>
                        <l>Neuer made word to vs on't; nor gaue ſigne</l>
                        <l>Of being troubled at it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Now he will</l>
                        <l>Talke to you on't; and as I doe ſuppoſe</l>
                        <l>To your no little coſt.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>This was his cunning,</l>
                        <l>To lead vs on in ſaire fooles paradiſe;</l>
                        <l>And in our ſecure dreaming take vs napping,</l>
                        <l>Hauing no time to caſt preuention.</l>
                        <l>A fox ifaith.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What iſt the knaue talkes on?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>My Maſter, and vnheeded!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dauus—</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha, what is the affaire?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Come you hither to me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What now trow is in working?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What faiſt thou?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What ſir the buſineſſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Doſt thou demand that?</l>
                        <l>Folke talke my Sonne's in loue.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>That birladie</l>
                        <l>Concernes the world to thinke on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Doſt marke me</l>
                        <l>In what I ſay or not?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, yes ſir well.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>But now of this for me to make inquirie</l>
                        <l>Were no kinde Fathers part. What hitherto</l>
                        <l>H'as done, I paſſe not: while the time permitted</l>
                        <l>I gaue him way to take his courſe and pleaſures:</l>
                        <l>His yeares now call for a new life, new manners.</l>
                        <l>Henceforward <hi>Dauus</hi> I require, or rather</l>
                        <l>(If the word may befit me) I requeſt thee,</l>
                        <l>Retriue my Sonne from this looſe libertie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="8" facs="14"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What may this meane?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>All theſe looſe libertines</l>
                        <l>That wantonly doe loue, cannot indure</l>
                        <l>To heare of wiuing.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>So indeede they ſay</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Beſide, if ſuch one chance to light vpon</l>
                        <l>Some patron of his inclination,</l>
                        <l>His raw greene ſickly minde he commonly</l>
                        <l>Wonts to the worſer part ſtill to apply.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Troth ſir I vnderſtand you not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>How, not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>No verily: I am your plaine man <hi>Dauus;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>No riddle-teller, cunning Oedipus.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Thould'ſt then in plaine tearmes haue me ſpeake my minde?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, pray at any hand ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>If I finde</l>
                        <l>That thou to day vſe any cunning crotchet,</l>
                        <l>Whereby to hinder this intended wedding;</l>
                        <l>Or faine wouldſt ſhew thy wits ſine nimbleneſſe:</l>
                        <l>When I haue firſt well whipt thee, in the Mill</l>
                        <l>Ile thruſt thee, to thy very dying day:</l>
                        <l>With this prouiſo and condition,</l>
                        <l>If euer I thence free thee, Ile grinde for thee.</l>
                        <l>What, vnderſtand'ſt me yet, or not yet neither?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes clearely now; y'haue vſ'd no round-abouts,</l>
                        <l>But come to th' matter roundly.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>In ought elſe</l>
                        <l>Saue this, I better could indure a ſlighting.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray ſir good words yet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Mak'ſt thou a ieſt on't?</l>
                        <l>I know thee to a haire: but I doe tell thee,</l>
                        <l>Leaſt thou ſhouldſt raſhly venture. Doe not ſay</l>
                        <l>But th'haſt had faire warning giu'n thee: looke to't.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Simo.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>VPon my faith now <hi>Dauus</hi> here's no leaſure</l>
                        <l>Left thee, to reſt or dreame vpon the matter;</l>
                        <pb n="9" facs="14"/>
                        <l>For ought I gather of the old mans purpoſe</l>
                        <l>Touching this wedding. which not wiſely holpen</l>
                        <l>Me or young Maſter vndoes vtterly.</l>
                        <l>Not can I iudge my beſt courſe, him to ſuccour,</l>
                        <l>Or leane to the old mans counſell: forſake him?</l>
                        <l>I doubt his life; aſſiſt him? th'others threats;</l>
                        <l>Whom to o're reach it's hard. Firſt h'as diſcouerd</l>
                        <l>All of their loue: then keepes hard watch o're me,</l>
                        <l>Leaſt I ſhould lead ſome trumping card in th'way:</l>
                        <l>Which if he finde, I'm loſt: or elſe at pleaſure</l>
                        <l>Heele take occaſion, be it right, be it wrong;</l>
                        <l>And to the Mill I ſhall be tumbled headlong.</l>
                        <l>To all theſe hazards comes another miſchiefe:</l>
                        <l>This <hi>Andrian</hi> woman, be ſhe his wiſe, or lemman,</l>
                        <l>Is great with childe by him. Now, tis worth nothing</l>
                        <l>To heare their bold aduenture: none can iudge it</l>
                        <l>Fond louers fancie, but meere frenzie rather:</l>
                        <l>For whether boy or girle ſhe ſhall bring forth,</l>
                        <l>They haue reſolu'd to keepe and nouriſh it.</l>
                        <l>Beſides they coyne a prettie cunning fable,</l>
                        <l>Among themſelues, that ſhee's free <hi>Atticke</hi> borne.</l>
                        <l>There was long ſince (ſay they) an ancient Merchant</l>
                        <l>Shipwrackt on <hi>Andros</hi> Iland; who there died;</l>
                        <l>And that with him then ſaued, <hi>Chryſis</hi> Father</l>
                        <l>Tooke vp a little girle. Conceited fiction!</l>
                        <l>To me it ſeemes vnlikely: yet they ſooth</l>
                        <l>Themſelues ith' tale. But ſee <hi>Myſis</hi> comming <stage>Enter Myſis.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>From out <hi>Glyceriums</hi> houſe. Ile to the Market</l>
                        <l>To ſeeke out <hi>Pamphilus:</hi> for feare his Father</l>
                        <l>Vnwates doe preſſe him with this buſineſſe. <stage>Exit Dauus.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>GOod God <hi>Archillis,</hi> I doe heare you woman:</l>
                        <l>You would haue <hi>Lesbia</hi> fetcht; vpon my word</l>
                        <pb n="10" facs="15"/>
                        <l>She is a drunken goſſip, and vnheedie:</l>
                        <l>And one ſcarce fit to whom you may commit</l>
                        <l>A woman in firſt childbirth: Yet He fetch her.</l>
                        <l>Note you the old ones importunitie!</l>
                        <l>None but her pot companion will ſerue turne.</l>
                        <l>But I pray God grant this a good deliuery:</l>
                        <stage>Enter Pamphilus.</stage>
                        <l>And that the Midwife rather may elſewhere</l>
                        <l>Neglect, then here. But what may be the cauſe</l>
                        <l>I <hi>Pamph' us</hi> ſee ſo much diſquieted?</l>
                        <l>I feare what it may be. Ile ſtay a while</l>
                        <l>To know the reaſon of his troubled geſture.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>IS this kinde dealing? courteous attempt?</l>
                        <l>Is this a Fathers carriage?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>What is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh gods and men your faith! what can be ſaid,</l>
                        <l>Neglect, diſgrace, or ſcorne, if this be none?</l>
                        <l>Say he had ment to marry me to day;</l>
                        <l>Ought I not haue foreknowne it? ought I not</l>
                        <l>Haue bin made priuie to it?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Out alas,</l>
                        <l>Wretch that I am, what doe I heare him talke of?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>What ſhould I thinke of <hi>Chremes?</hi> who denied</l>
                        <l>To truſt me as a husband with his daughter?</l>
                        <l>Changeth he minde, becauſe I reſt vnchang'd?</l>
                        <l>That he ſhould ſtill thus obſtinately indeauor</l>
                        <l>Me moſt accurſed to diuorce and ſeuer</l>
                        <l>From my <hi>Glycertam?</hi> which, if it fall out,</l>
                        <l>I am vndone for euer. Amongſt men</l>
                        <l>Was euer yet found out one more diſgracefull?</l>
                        <l>More euery way vnhappy then my ſelfe?</l>
                        <l>Men, gods aſſiſt me! is there left no way</l>
                        <l>For me to ſhunne <hi>Chremes</hi> affinitie?</l>
                        <l>How many wayes haue I bin ſcorn'd? refuſ'd?</l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="15"/>
                        <l>(All done, all ended) the other day caſt of</l>
                        <l>Ain now againe required: and why ſo?</l>
                        <l>Vnleſſe (I gueſſe) h'has ſome deformed piece,</l>
                        <l>Which when he cannot faſten vpon any,</l>
                        <l>He ſeekes to 〈◊〉 on me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>This talke of his</l>
                        <l>Kils me poore wretch with ſeare.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>For what ſhould I</l>
                        <l>Now of my Father ſpeake? Oh God! that he</l>
                        <l>So weightie a thing ſhould doe ſo careleſly.</l>
                        <l>Paſſing now by me in the Market-place,</l>
                        <l>Goe, get you home, ſaies he; and fit your ſelfe:</l>
                        <l>This day you muſt be married <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To m● his words ſeem'd of ſuch ſound and ſence,</l>
                        <l>As he had ſaid, get home and hang thy ſelfe.</l>
                        <l>I ſtood confounded at it. Doe you thinke</l>
                        <l>I had a word to vtter? any excuſe?</l>
                        <l>Though fooliſh, falſe, vnſitting? I ſtood dumbe.</l>
                        <l>Yet had I known't afore, what could I doe?</l>
                        <l>If any now ſhould aske me, I would ſurely</l>
                        <l>Vſe other courſe, then (as I did) keepe ſilence.</l>
                        <l>But now what firſt thing ſhall I enter on?</l>
                        <l>So many cares, ſeuerall diſtraction,</l>
                        <l>Puzzles my minde: loue, pittie of her, feare</l>
                        <l>About this marriage ſo loath'd, ſo neare:</l>
                        <l>Then the reſpect I owe my Father, who</l>
                        <l>So mildely hath me ſuffied hitherto</l>
                        <l>Without reſtraint to runne my owne free race,</l>
                        <l>In euery courſe I liſted: with what face</l>
                        <l>May I now croſſe his pleaſure? wretched me!</l>
                        <l>I know not what to reſt on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I poore woman</l>
                        <l>Doubt th'end of this irreſolution.</l>
                        <l>But now tis very needfull that I draw him</l>
                        <l>To ſpeake with her; or elſe of her</l>
                        <l>Finde ſome diſcourſe to him. Whil'ſt yet his minde</l>
                        <l>Hangs wauering, euery little moment turnes it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Who iſt talkes hereabout? <hi>Myſis</hi> well met.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="12" facs="16"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Pamphilus</hi> and you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>How does my deareſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>How does ſhe? marie ſir in pangs of trauaile:</l>
                        <l>And many troublous thoughts come in her minde</l>
                        <l>About this day, once purpos'd for your wedding.</l>
                        <l>She further doubts, leaſt you may minde to leaue her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>May I be thought to minde a thing ſo foule?</l>
                        <l>And through my fault ſuffer mine owne deare ſoule</l>
                        <l>To be abus'd? truſting her heart, her life</l>
                        <l>To me? whom I haue made my deareſt wife?</l>
                        <l>May I permit her chaſte well trained minde</l>
                        <l>Inforced by foule want to change it kinde?</l>
                        <l>No, I will neuer doe it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>If it lay</l>
                        <l>In you, I neede not feare: but how you may</l>
                        <l>Be forced by your Father, is the doubt.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>What <hi>Myſis</hi> doſt thou thinke me ſuch a loue?</l>
                        <l>So ingratefull further? ſo inhumane, beſtiall?</l>
                        <l>That nor acquaintance, loue, or ſhame, at all</l>
                        <l>May moue or prompt me to keepe plighted faith?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>One thing I know, that ſhe deſerued hath</l>
                        <l>That you ſhould minde her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Should minde her <hi>Myſis?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Euen now the very lateſt words of <hi>Chryſis</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Touching <hi>Glycerium,</hi> reſt imprinted here;</l>
                        <l>Here at my heart. Her laſt houre drawing neere,</l>
                        <l>She cald for me: I came to her: all you</l>
                        <l>Voided the roome: being alone we two</l>
                        <l>She thus began. Kinde <hi>Pamphilus</hi> you ſee</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Glyceriums</hi> youth and beautie; verily</l>
                        <l>Two weake vnſafe guards (as your ſelfe perceiue)</l>
                        <l>To keepe her ch●ſte, guard the ſmall ſtocke I leaue.</l>
                        <l>Wherefore by this right hand I craue of thee,</l>
                        <l>By thy good nature, thy fidelitie:</l>
                        <l>I adiure thee by her here vnfriendedneſſe</l>
                        <l>Thou wouldſt not leaue her: doe not part from her.</l>
                        <l>If as a brother I thee ſtill reſpected,</l>
                        <pb n="13" facs="16"/>
                        <l>If ſhe of all men hath thee beſt affected,</l>
                        <l>As ſhe in all things ſought thy full contentment</l>
                        <l>In true obſeruance, due obedience.</l>
                        <l>I leaue thee as a friend, a guardian, Father,</l>
                        <l>A husband to her. All the little wealth</l>
                        <l>I leaue behinde, I truſt to thy diſpoſing.</l>
                        <l>Then her hand taking, in my hand ſhe claſp'd it;</l>
                        <l>And forthwith died. I then there recein'd her;</l>
                        <l>Receiu'd will keepe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Indeede ſir I hope ſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>But why doſt now come from her?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I am ſent</l>
                        <l>To fetch the Midwife.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh, I prethee haſten.</l>
                        <l>And heare you? ſee you mention not a word</l>
                        <l>About the marriage: leaſt it may perhaps</l>
                        <l>Adde to her weakneſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe minde it ſir.</p>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt</hi> Pamphilus <hi>and</hi> Myſis <hi>ſeuerall waies.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <head>Act. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Charinus <hi>and</hi> Byrrhia <hi>his man.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha</speaker>
                        <l>VVHat ſaiſt thou <hi>Byrrhia?</hi> muſt ſhe then to day</l>
                        <l>Be married vnto <hi>Pamphilus?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byrr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chae.</speaker>
                        <p>How doſt thou know it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <l>But ene very now</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dauus</hi> ſo told me in the Market-place.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Accurſed, wretched me! how hitherto</l>
                        <l>My thoughts haue waited vpon hope and feare?</l>
                        <l>But hope now being fled, my fainting ſpirits</l>
                        <l>Waſted with care, yeeld to confuſion.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <l>Pray, for Gods loue <hi>Charinus,</hi> ſince that things</l>
                        <l>Cannot be as you would, ſeeke to deſire</l>
                        <l>What you may compaſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>There is nothing elſe</l>
                        <l>In all the world I wiſh, but <hi>Philumen.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <l>But how much better were it, to endeauour</l>
                        <pb n="14" facs="17"/>
                        <l>To vnlodge this idle loue out of your heart,</l>
                        <l>Then thus to talke of that which addes more fewell</l>
                        <l>To this your bootleſſe vaine affection?</l>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Pamphilus <hi>walking in a dumpe.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>All men in health can eaſily preſcribe</l>
                        <l>To the ſicke patient good directions.</l>
                        <l>If thou wert in my caſe thy minde would alter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>Well ſir then doe your pleaſure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>But lo yonder</l>
                        <l>Where <hi>Pamphilus</hi> is. I doe meane to venture</l>
                        <l>All trials yet, ere I doe fully periſh.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>What meanes he now to doe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>I will requeſt,</l>
                        <l>Beſeech him, open to him all my loue.</l>
                        <l>I hope I may obtaine of him at leaſt,</l>
                        <l>For ſome few dayes to put the wedding of.</l>
                        <l>I truſt in th'Interim ſomewhat may be done.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>That ſomewhat is iuſt nothing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Byrrhia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>What think'ſt thou of it? ſhall I goe to him?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <l>What elſe? if he will yeeld to nothing, yet</l>
                        <l>Let him ſuſpect, you haue good minde to horne him</l>
                        <l>If he ſhall marrie her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Away lience varlet,</l>
                        <l>With this thy lewd ſuſpition.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Charinus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>God ſaue you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>And you alſo <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I was a comming to you, with deſire</l>
                        <l>To craue hope, helpe, health, counſell at your hands.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Troth I haue neither place for counſell left,</l>
                        <l>Nor meanes to helpe. but what's the matter man?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you to day to marrie?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>So they ſay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>If you doe <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> I can aſſure you,</l>
                        <l>This is the laſt day you ſhall euer ſee me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>How ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>I ſhame to tell it, <hi>Birrhia</hi> prithee</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Declare</hi> the matter to him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, I will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>What is it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, he loues your wiſe that ſhall be.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Troth he and I are of two ſeuerall mindes:</l>
                        <l>I can aſſure thee. Prithee hearken hither</l>
                        <pb n="15" facs="17"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Charinus;</hi> ha'ſt not had to doe with her</l>
                        <l>More, then thy man here talkes of.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pamphilus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>No o'my troth. <hi>I am.</hi> Oh, how I wiſh thou haddeſt.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Now I intreat thee by our friendſhip, loue;</l>
                        <l>Firſt that you would not marrie her at all.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile (what I can) auoid it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>If't full ſo,</l>
                        <l>You cannot ſhun it, or doe elſe affect it—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Affect it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet deferre it of awhile,</l>
                        <l>That I may void hence ſomewhere, and not ſee't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Charinus,</hi> now heare me. I doe not think't</l>
                        <l>At any time a part of honeſtie,</l>
                        <l>When one deſerues nought, to expect for thankes.</l>
                        <l>Ide rather ſhun this match then thou obtain't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>You put new life into me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>If thou canſt now,</l>
                        <l>Or this this thy man here; worke, inuent, faſhion,</l>
                        <l>Take all the courſe you can to make her thine:</l>
                        <l>I will finde meanes, that mine ſhe ſhall not be.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Dauus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue enough.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>And in good time I ſee</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Danus,</hi> whoſe counſell I rely vpon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>But thou dull head canſt nothing caſt about</l>
                        <l>Worth knowing. Can you leaue vs?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and gladly.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Byrrhia.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>GOod God! what good newes bring I?</l>
                        <l>But where●row may I finde <hi>Pamphilus</hi> out?</l>
                        <l>To ●●d his feares, and ſill his heart with comfort.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>He is iocund, at what I know not.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Tut, man, tis, nothing.</l>
                        <l>The miſchiefe now afoot, he yet not heares of.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Who if he haue heard of this prepared wedding —</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe you not heare him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>I gueſſe verily</l>
                        <l>Hunts all the towne ore for me, like a madman.</l>
                        <pb n="16" facs="18"/>
                        <l>But where ſhall I looke for him? to what place</l>
                        <l>Firſt bend my courſe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſpeake you not vnto him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile get me hence, and ſeeke him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dauus,</hi> ſtay:</l>
                        <l>Come hither.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Who iſt cals? Oh <hi>Pamphilus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I ſought you: you here too <hi>Charinus?</hi> braue.</l>
                        <l>Both in the nicke. Y'are the men, I lookt for.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Dauus</hi> I me vndone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Tut, liſt to me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I am for euer loſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Your feare I know.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>My life now lies at ſtake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Yours I know too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I muſt be married.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>That I alſo know.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I, but this very day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>You weary me</l>
                        <l>With newes, that I am perfect in already.</l>
                        <l>You feare to haue her; you to miſſe her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Th'haſt it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I that's the point.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, and I ſay the point</l>
                        <l>Has then no danger in it. Obſerue me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>For Gods ſake rid me quickly of this feare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Lo, I fice thee. <hi>Chremis</hi> now's not minded</l>
                        <l>To trouble you with a wife.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>How doeſt know it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Father tooke me by the ſleeue e'en now,</l>
                        <l>And told me this day he would marrie you:</l>
                        <l>Adding much more, which now's no time to talke on.</l>
                        <l>Preſently haſtning to acquaint you with it,</l>
                        <l>I ranne to the Market-place: there miſſing you</l>
                        <l>I got to a high rais'd ground, and round about</l>
                        <l>Look'd to eſpie you; could not. Then by ch●●ce</l>
                        <l>I ſaw <hi>Charinus</hi> ſeruant, <hi>Birrhia:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of him I ask'd, he ſaid he had not ſeene you:</l>
                        <l>It vex'd me: ſtill I caſt what I ſhould doe.</l>
                        <l>Returning thence, a certaine realouſie</l>
                        <l>By circumſtances bred came in my minde.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>V●ph!</hi> heres ſmall roſt; the old man ſad, a wedding?</l>
                        <l>It ſcarce hangs well together.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Whereto this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>I bie me ſtreight to <hi>hremes;</hi> thither come,</l>
                        <l>I note a ſilent ſtilneſſe at the doore.</l>
                        <l>Now, this gaue me good heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Well ſaid, goe on.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="17" facs="18"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Somewhile I there continue: all that while</l>
                        <l>I ſaw no creature paſſing out or in;</l>
                        <l>No matron there; no decking of the houſe;</l>
                        <l>No ſtirre; I neerer came, and peeped in.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I know they are good coniectures.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Doe ſuch things</l>
                        <l>Thinke you agree vnto a nuptiall day?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>In troth I thinke not <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Doe you ſay, thinke?</l>
                        <l>You conſtrue things not well: the caſe is plaine.</l>
                        <l>Beſides, thence going I met <hi>Chremes</hi> ſeruant</l>
                        <l>With hearbs and ſmall ſprots for the old mans ſupper.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dauus,</hi> through thee I am now rid of care.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay of my faith not ſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Why man prethee?</l>
                        <l>For thou conclud'ſt, he will not giue her him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Conceited pate! as if it therefore followed,</l>
                        <l>If he not haue her, you muſt marrie her.</l>
                        <l>Vnleſſe you lookt toot, make your ſuit, and meanes</l>
                        <l>T'her fathers friends, you may hap hop wiueleſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou promptſt me well; Ile goe about it ſtreight.</l>
                        <l>Though ought this hope haue faild me: fare ye well.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Charinus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>VVHat meanes my father then?</l>
                        <l>Why doubles he?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile tell you. If he now ſhould chafe at you,</l>
                        <l>Cauſe <hi>Chremes</hi> will not let you haue his daughter,</l>
                        <l>Himſelfe may ſee he plainly iniur'd you:</l>
                        <l>If he ſhould preſſe you on, before he knew</l>
                        <l>How your minde ſtood inclined to the match.</l>
                        <l>But if you ſhall ſtiffely denie to wed her;</l>
                        <l>Then he will iuſtly lay the blame on you:</l>
                        <l>Then ſhall we haue a coyle on't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="18" facs="19"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>What would'ſt haue me</l>
                        <l>To vndergoe this marriage?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pamphilus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>He is your Father: and it will be hard</l>
                        <l>T'oppoſe him: this your ſweet heart too (you know)</l>
                        <l>Is friendleſſe here. Heele finde cauſe eaſily</l>
                        <l>To thruſt her out o'th'towne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Out o'th towne man?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſpeedily too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Counſell me then <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>What I ſhould doe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Tell him you'l marrie her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>How?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What's the matter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Should I tell him ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Why not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I nere will deo't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Denie me not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Perſwade me not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Note, what hence will follow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>To be ſhut out from her, mew'd vp to this.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>No, no ſuch thing. I gueſſe your father thus</l>
                        <l>Will ſay to you: my purpoſe <hi>Pamphilus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Is that this day you wed: then anſwer you,</l>
                        <l>Sir, I am ready: pray you tell me now</l>
                        <l>For what cauſe can he chide you? by this meanes</l>
                        <l>His ſetled plots you ſhall diſorder cleane:</l>
                        <l>Your ſelfe yet runne no hazard; for the thought</l>
                        <l>Is groundleſſe, vaine, that <hi>Chremes</hi> may be wrought</l>
                        <l>To giue his daughter: nor doe you let fall</l>
                        <l>Your courſe, leaſt he his purpoſe ſhould recall.</l>
                        <l>Tell you your Father that you like the Bride:</l>
                        <l>That, when he would, he haue no cauſe to chide.</l>
                        <l>And for the dangerous paſſage that you feare;</l>
                        <l>Ile ſteare your courſe, and waft you ouer cleare.</l>
                        <l>No man will giue his daughter as a wife</l>
                        <l>To one diſcouerd of your wanton life.</l>
                        <l>Heele with ſome poore man rather ſeeke to place her,</l>
                        <l>Then ſuffer you to iniure or diſgrace her.</l>
                        <l>But if your father ſee you quiet take</l>
                        <l>This his command, you ſhall him retchleſſe make.</l>
                        <pb n="19" facs="19"/>
                        <l>At leaſure heele ſeeke out ſome other wife,</l>
                        <l>Meane time your fathers death may end the ſtrife</l>
                        <l>Or ſome like good chance happen.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Thinkſt thou ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>There is no doubt ith' world on't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Take you heede to what you lead me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you ſir be quiet?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile tell my father as thou bidſt me: but</l>
                        <l>There muſt be care had, he by no meanes know</l>
                        <l>ſhe's with childe by me; for I haue promiſ'd</l>
                        <l>To giue it breeding.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh bold enterpriſe!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>She begg'd this promiſe of me, as aſſurance</l>
                        <l>That I would not forſake her.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Simo.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile looke toot.</l>
                        <l>Your Father's here: let him not note you ſad.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I Come to obſerue their carriage, note their plots.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>He thinkes now ſurely, youle refuſe to marrie:</l>
                        <l>And comes from ſome lone place premeditate,</l>
                        <l>Thinking to puzzle you with a ſet ſpeech:</l>
                        <l>Therefore collect your ſelfe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, as I can.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>In this thing <hi>Pamphilus</hi> you ſhall take my word,</l>
                        <l>You ſhall not now change two croſſe ſillables,</l>
                        <l>If you but ſay, you readie are to marrie.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Byrrhia <hi>liſtening the incounter betweene</hi> Simo <hi>and his Sonne.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <l>MY Maſter will'd me (all things elſe ſet of)</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pamphilus</hi> watch: &amp; learn what courſe he takes</l>
                        <pb n="20" facs="20"/>
                        <l>About the Bride. This cauſ'd me dogge him hither:</l>
                        <l>And loe, where he is with <hi>Dauus.</hi> To my taske.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſee 'hem both together.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Now ſir looke toot.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Looke you backe as on the ſodaine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, you my father?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I, that's well carried.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>As I late told thee, tis my purpoſe Sonne</l>
                        <l>That thou this day be married.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Now I feare</l>
                        <l>His anſwer on our ſide.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, or in this</l>
                        <l>Or in what elſe I wait vpon your pleaſure.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Mute.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>What ſaid he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou doſt now my Sonne</l>
                        <l>As well becomes thee, when ſo graciouſly</l>
                        <l>Thou yeeldſt to what I craue.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Was I not right?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <p>My Maſter (as I heare) hath loſt his wife.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Get you now in that when the time requires,</l>
                        <l>We be not driu'n to ſtay for you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes ſir.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Pamphilus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                        <l>That in nothing one man may truſt another!</l>
                        <l>It is an old ſaid ſaying, and as common,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>All to themſelues wiſh beſt.</hi> My ſelfe haue ſeene</l>
                        <l>The maiden, and remember her a faire one.</l>
                        <l>Which makes me better beare with <hi>Pamphilus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If he himſelfe had rather nightly bed her,</l>
                        <l>Then let my Maſter. Ile beare backe this newes:</l>
                        <l>That he may pay me well, for my ill tidings.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Byrrhia.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>MY Maſter thinkes now I haue ſome deuice</l>
                        <l>A foot: and that, for that end I ſtay here.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What iſt, thou talkeſt <hi>Dauus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Eene iuſt ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="21" facs="20"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What, nothing? ha?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Indeede ſir nothing, I.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſure did looke to heare ſome newes from thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>I know tis chanced quite beſides his aime:</l>
                        <l>That's it which nettles him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Iſt poſſible</l>
                        <l>I get thee tell me a truth?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Moſt readily.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Doos this ſame wedding grieue him any thing,</l>
                        <l>By reaſon of the acquaintance that he holds</l>
                        <l>With yonder ſtranger?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Truely I thinke not.</l>
                        <l>Or if it doe, the matter of his trouble</l>
                        <l>Will be at moſt two or three daies diſquiet:</l>
                        <l>(Conceiue you ſir?) then it will clearely vaniſh.</l>
                        <l>For with himſelfe h'as tane a due account,</l>
                        <l>And ſet all cleare that way.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe commend him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Whilſt he had leaue, &amp; his green youth did ſuffer'r</l>
                        <l>He wencht a little; but yet priuately:</l>
                        <l>He euer had a care to keepe his name</l>
                        <l>Vntoucht; as did become a wiſe yong man.</l>
                        <l>Now mariage fits, he frames his minde that way.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>And yet me thought he appeared ſomewhat ſad.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Nothing about this buſineſſe; but there's cauſe</l>
                        <l>That makes him ſomewhat angry with you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>A trifle.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What iſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Nothing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Tell me what?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>He ſaies y'are ouerniggardiſh in Coſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Who, I?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>That you haue ſcarce disbuſd ten groats</l>
                        <l>In your prouiſion for his wedding ſupper:</l>
                        <l>What (ſaies he) is this like a Sonnes nuptials</l>
                        <l>Whom chiefely of my fellow batchelors</l>
                        <l>May I inuite (quoth he) to ſuch a banquet?</l>
                        <l>And to ſpeake that which may be ſaid herein;</l>
                        <l>Intruth you are too too ſparing, I lik't not.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold your tongue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue gald him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I will ſee</l>
                        <l>That all ſhall be well carried. What meanes this?</l>
                        <pb n="22" facs="21"/>
                        <l>What iſt this old fox-hunt doth hammer on?</l>
                        <l>If there be any knauerie, his pare forg'd it.</l>
                        <stage>Exeunt Simo and Dauus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="act">
                  <head>Act. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lesbia, <hi>the Midwiſe and</hi> Myſis <hi>Glyceriums ma●de at onedsore,</hi> Simo <hi>and</hi> Dauus <hi>at another.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I, Indeede <hi>Lesbia</hi> you haue ſaid aright:</l>
                        <l>A woman hardly findes a faithfull louer.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Belongs this maide to th' <hi>Andrian</hi> here?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>But this kinde <hi>Pamphilus</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What iſt ſhe ſaies?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Hath giuen her full aſſurance—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Out alas!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Would either he were deaſe now or ſhe dumbe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>That ſonne or daughter, he will foſter it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh <hi>Iupiter!</hi> what newes is this I heare?</l>
                        <l>All is loſt vtterly; if ſhe ſpeake truth.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                        <p>You doe deſcribe a yong man honeſt natur'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh, the beſt natur'd gentleman — but pray,</l>
                        <l>Follow me in, for feare ſhe ſtay for you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes I follow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What helpe for this now, trow?</p>
                        <stage>Exet Lesbya and Myſis.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>What, is he mad? a looſe land loping ſtrumpet?</l>
                        <l>Oh! I haue it: old dulhead (as I was)</l>
                        <l>I fearce at length could hit on't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What has he hit on, ſaies he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>This firſt knauiſh practiſe</l>
                        <l>Of my man here is now thus put vpon me:</l>
                        <pb n="23" facs="21"/>
                        <l>She is to be in child birth, to flight <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Glycerium</hi> with|in doores. <hi>Iuno, Lucina</hi> helpe; ſaue mee, I pray thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Horda ſuch ſpeede? ha, ha, ridiculous</l>
                        <l>As ſoone as are ſhe heard me at the doore,</l>
                        <l>The throwes come on: ſcarce fitly a'my word,</l>
                        <l>You ranke and place your times ſcarce ſitly <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Or haue your Actors miſt their Cues?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not what you meane, ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>If this fellow</l>
                        <l>Had ſet vpon me, being vnprouided</l>
                        <l>In a true marriage oh, what pageants</l>
                        <l>Would he haue plaid me? Let him now make ſure</l>
                        <l>His owne aduenture; ●m●ith port ſecure.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lesbia <hi>ſpeaking to the Nurſe within doores.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                        <l>AS yet <hi>Archillis</hi> I doe note in her</l>
                        <l>All vſuall matters, and good ſignes of health</l>
                        <l>Firſt ſee her cleanſd, and then deliuer her</l>
                        <l>That drinke, in meaſure as I gaue in charge:</l>
                        <l>Ile be here ſtraight againe: as God ſhall helpe me.</l>
                        <l>She hath brought <hi>Pamphilus</hi> a goodly boy.</l>
                        <l>If it pleaſe God, may it liue to be a man:</l>
                        <l>Seeing the father is of diſpoſition</l>
                        <l>So honeſt; and makes conſcience to wrong</l>
                        <l>This good young woman.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Lesbia.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Who did euer know thee</l>
                        <l>That would not ſweare, this thy contriuing now?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, what?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>She cannot in the houſe giue order,</l>
                        <l>For what is needfull to the childebed woman:</l>
                        <l>But comming forth a doores, proclaimes ith'ſtrect</l>
                        <pb n="24" facs="22"/>
                        <l>Her minde to them within: what? what ſir <hi>Dauus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Slight you me ſo? or deem'ſt me now at length</l>
                        <l>Such a fine eaſie propertie, thou maiſt</l>
                        <l>So plainly paſſe thy iugling tricks vpon me?</l>
                        <l>At leaſt yet, it was circumſpectly carried;</l>
                        <l>And ſhewd your awe, if'twere diſcouer'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Troth his owne cunning cheats him now; not I.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Did I not forewarne thee? threaten further</l>
                        <l>If thou ſhould'ſt dare attempt this? haſt thou yet</l>
                        <l>Stood in feare of't? hath it in ought preuail'd?</l>
                        <l>Think'ſt thou I doe beleeue this woman here</l>
                        <l>Hath had a childe now by my <hi>Pamphilus?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I now finde his miſtaking, know my courſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſpeak'ſt thou not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>What talke you of your thinking?</l>
                        <l>As if y'had had no notice of the matter?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I notice?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Why good ſir, tell me I pray</l>
                        <l>Found you of your ſelfe that this was counter faited?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I'm flouted.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Come, come, it has bin told you:</l>
                        <l>How elſe a Gods name could you dreame of it?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>How? cauſe I well did know thy qualities.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>You thinke it then a thing of my direction.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I, and I know tis.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Truely ſir I ſee</l>
                        <l>You throughly doe not know me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Not I, thee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>But when I ſeeke to tell you any thing,</l>
                        <l>You ſtreight ſuppoſe, I put ſome tricke vpon you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis falſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>So that I dare ſcarce ſpeake to you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>This one thing I am ſure on; heer's no childe born.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Are you ſo ſure? yet ſir notwithſtanding</l>
                        <l>They ſtreight will lay a childe before your doore.</l>
                        <l>I tell you on't aforehand, for your knowledge:</l>
                        <l>Leaſt you ſhould ſay hereafter, <hi>Dauus</hi> plots</l>
                        <l>And cunning manag'd all. I very faine</l>
                        <pb n="25" facs="22"/>
                        <l>Would worke my ſelfe out of your iealouſie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>How knowſt it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue heard ſo and beleeue it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>They are many &amp; thoſe grounded circumſtances,</l>
                        <l>Which my coniectures build on. Nere before</l>
                        <l>Named ſhe her ſelfe with childe by <hi>Pamphilus;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And that is falſe, vnleſſe my iudgement erre:</l>
                        <l>But ſeeing now a wedding is preparing,</l>
                        <l>A midwife ſtreight is ſent for, by the maid,</l>
                        <l>Who was to bring a young borne childe with her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Vnleſſe you ſee a childe, the wedding ſtill</l>
                        <l>Stands fairely.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I but, ſirra tell me this,</l>
                        <l>When thou hadſt found they plotted this among them, her?</l>
                        <l>Why told you not it ſtreight to <hi>Pamphilus?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Pray, but my ſelfe then who hath drawn him from</l>
                        <l>We know how fondly he did dote vpon her:</l>
                        <l>Now he deſires a wife to liue withall.</l>
                        <l>In fine, truſt me with this whole buſineſſe:</l>
                        <l>Yet purſue you, to make the marriage vp;</l>
                        <l>And I doe hope the Gods will further it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, get you in; there ſee you ſtay my comming:</l>
                        <l>And haue ſuch things as need in readineſſe.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Dauus</stage>
                        <l>He hath not drawne me yet to giue full credit</l>
                        <l>To this he ſaies; nor to conclude all true.</l>
                        <l>But I regard it little: the maine thing</l>
                        <l>I reſt on, is the promiſe of my Sonne.</l>
                        <l>Ile now goe ſpeake with <hi>Chremes,</hi> and deſire</l>
                        <l>He would beſtow his daughter: that obtaind,</l>
                        <l>Why ſhould I linger? and not now this day</l>
                        <l>Finiſh the match a foot? doubtleſſe my Sonne</l>
                        <l>Will ſtand t'his word: if not, what hinders me</l>
                        <stage>Enter Chremes.</stage>
                        <l>But I may force him? and in good time ſee</l>
                        <l>Where <hi>Chremes</hi> is, <hi>Chremes</hi> good time of day.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <pb n="26" facs="23"/>
                     <head>Scen. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>OH! you are the man I ſought for.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>And I you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are come as I would wiſh: a many men</l>
                        <l>Haue preſs'd vnto me; who report as heard</l>
                        <l>From you, that on this very day your Sonne</l>
                        <l>Should wed my daughter. Now I come to ſee</l>
                        <l>Whether or you or they be from their wits?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Pray liſt a while, and I will ſatisfie</l>
                        <l>This doubt: and withall acquaint you further</l>
                        <l>What ſuit I haue vnto you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>I attend.</l>
                        <l>Say what you pleaſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Chremes I requeſt you</l>
                        <l>For loue of God; and for the vnfeigned friendſhip</l>
                        <l>Which in our youth begunne along together</l>
                        <l>Hath growne vp with our yeares; by the reſpect</l>
                        <l>You beare your onely child; for my Sonnes cauſe</l>
                        <l>Chiefe power of whoſe preſeruing lies in you,</l>
                        <l>Lend me your furtherance in this buſineſſe,</l>
                        <l>That the match this day meant may ſo go on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh! I pray craue it not, as if 't were fit</l>
                        <l>I ſhould in this thing liſten to your ſuit?</l>
                        <l>Thinke you me alterd from the man I was,</l>
                        <l>When late I made you promiſe? if 't may be</l>
                        <l>For both our welſares, take my daughter to you</l>
                        <l>But if hereby more harme then good will follow</l>
                        <l>To either of vs by it, then I pray</l>
                        <l>Caſt for the common good: as if my daughter</l>
                        <l>Were yours, I father to your <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, that's my meaning <hi>Chremes:</hi> and I doe</l>
                        <l>Craue nothing of you but vpon ſuch tearmes:</l>
                        <l>Nor would I aske it of you, if the caſe</l>
                        <l>It felſe did not require it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, how is't?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>There's iarre betweene <hi>Glycerium</hi> and my ſonne.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="27" facs="23"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>I heare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>So great, I hope't will ſunder them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>A tale.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>In very deede tis ſo</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Indeede</l>
                        <l>It will iuſt ſo (as I ſhall tell thee) proue;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The iarres of louers giue freſh life to loue.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I, but I pray you let vs preuent that,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt his loues flame is ſmotherd by abuſe:</l>
                        <l>Before this harlots leaud deſignes, falſe teares</l>
                        <l>Reduce his ſickly minde to paſſion,</l>
                        <l>Lets marrie 'hem.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chremes</speaker>
                        <l>I haue good hope,</l>
                        <l>Faire wedlocke and a wiues experienc'd loue</l>
                        <l>Will eas'ly plucke him out of theſe feard ils.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>You thinke ſo: but I deeme't impoſſible</l>
                        <l>That either they will alwaies liue together,</l>
                        <l>Or I may indure their iarring.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>How doe you know,</l>
                        <l>Vnleſſe you make a triall?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>But 'twere hard</l>
                        <l>For me to make ſuch triall in my childe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Why, all the inconuenience which can happen</l>
                        <l>Should the worſt fall (which I pray God forbid)</l>
                        <l>Were at the moſt a ſeparation.</l>
                        <l>In counterpoiſe now weigh the benefits</l>
                        <l>That will inſue, if my ſonne proue reclaim'd:</l>
                        <l>Firſt you reſtore t' your friend his ſonne: your ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Gaine a faſt ſonne in law: your childe a husband.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Why, if you thinke it ſo commodious,</l>
                        <l>For my part I will be no hindrance too't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I iuſtly alwaies held you my beſt friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>But as to that you ſaid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Marrie how know you</l>
                        <l>There's now debate betweene 'hem.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dauus</hi> ſelfe</l>
                        <l>(who is their Counſels inward ſecretarie)</l>
                        <l>So told me; and withall aduiſd me further</l>
                        <l>To haſte the marriage with all ſpeed I could.</l>
                        <l>Thinke you he would doe thus, but that he knowes.</l>
                        <pb n="28" facs="24"/>
                        <l>My ſonne deſires it likewiſe? you your ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Shall heate him. Ho there, one call <hi>Dauus</hi> forth.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Dauus.</stage>
                        <l>But loe, I ſee him comming out a doores.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I Was a comming to you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What's the matter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Why is the bride not ſent for? it growes late.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Doe you now heare him? I will tell thee <hi>Dauus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I lately had thee in ſome iealouſie;</l>
                        <l>That thou didſt take the courſe moſt ſeruants hold,</l>
                        <l>By ſeeking to delude me in the matter.</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Pamphilus</hi> wanton louing.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Who, I ſit?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I thought ſo: and for that I kept from you</l>
                        <l>A ſecret, Ile now vtter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What was that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile tell thee; for I almoſt now doe truſt thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>At length you finde what ſeruant you haue of me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>This was not to haue bin a marriage</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What, no.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>But I therefore counterfaited,</l>
                        <l>That I might feele your mindes.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What iſt you ſay?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Iuſt as thou hear'ſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>La yee; I could neuer,</l>
                        <l>Thinke ſuch a matter: oh fine cunning plot?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Liſt this; when hence I bad thee get thee in,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chremes</hi> came fitly to me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Are we troe</l>
                        <l>Not loſt for euer?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I told all to him</l>
                        <l>Thou late toldſt me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What heare I?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Begg'd of him,</l>
                        <l>And ſcarce at length won him to giue his daughter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I am vndone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What ſaiſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Excellently done.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Now he's not backward.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chre.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile ſtraight get me home,</l>
                        <l>And leaue word all be had in readineſſe!</l>
                        <pb n="29" facs="24"/>
                        <l>Thence giue you notice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Now I prechee <hi>Dauus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <stage>Exit Chremes</stage>
                        <l>Since thou alone haſt wrought this marriage for vs—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes ſure, I was th'onely worker.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Doe now</l>
                        <l>Indeauour further to reclaime my ſonne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes truely, I will looke toot carefully.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou maiſt now do it, whil'ſt his minde is vexed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray take no Care.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Looke toot then:</l>
                        <l>But where now is he himſelfe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis marle but he's at home.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile too him then, and to himſelfe deliuer</l>
                        <l>All I told thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>I am now iuſt nothing. <stage>Exit Simo.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>What hinders, but I fairely take my way</l>
                        <l>Directly to the mill, and fall a grinding?</l>
                        <l>Intreatie may doe nothing; I haue drawne</l>
                        <l>All things to ſuch confuſion: firſt deceiu'd</l>
                        <l>My Maſter: then haue headlong thruſt his ſonne</l>
                        <l>Vpon a marriage, that he look'd not for:</l>
                        <l>And cleane againſt his will: and this to day</l>
                        <l>To be made vp, by my alone procurement.</l>
                        <l>Pray marke th'end of cunning: had I ſat ſtill,</l>
                        <l>No euill in the world had happened.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Pamphilus.</stage>
                        <l>And ſee where he is. I am a meere dead man.</l>
                        <l>Would I had any meanes to breake my necke now.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>VVHere is the villaine has vndone me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I Am a plaine caſtaway.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>But I confeſſe</l>
                        <l>Tis iuſtly fall'n vpon me; ſince I am</l>
                        <l>So idle, vaine, and inconſiderate:</l>
                        <l>Ought I to truſt my whole ſtate to a ſlaue;</l>
                        <l>A prating ſlaue? I haue my follies hire:</l>
                        <l>But vnreueng'd he nere ſhall ſcape with it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile nere doubt tempeſt, if I ſcape this ſtorme.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="30" facs="25"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>But now what anſwer ſhall I make my father?</l>
                        <l>Shall I denie to marrie, who but now</l>
                        <l>Conſented to it? with what impudence</l>
                        <l>May I dare doe it? neither with my ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Know I what courſe to take.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Troth nor I, neither</l>
                        <l>But I am canuaſſing my braines about it.</l>
                        <l>Ile tell him Ile forthwith finde out ſome meanes</l>
                        <l>A little to put off his threatned vengeance.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I'm ſpide.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh, you ſir, honeſt fellow</l>
                        <l>Come neerer: what ſaiſt to me? doe you ſee now</l>
                        <l>How I am puzled through your goodly counſell?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile preſently make all cleare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou make cleare?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Pamphilus</hi> indeede I will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I, as erewhile.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, I hope better</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Truſt thee pillorie?</l>
                        <l>Or thou make good a caſe perplexed, loſt?</l>
                        <l>See what a ſuresby I haue truſted too;</l>
                        <l>Who from a quiet ſtate I late ſtood in,</l>
                        <l>This day haſt thruſt me on a mariage:</l>
                        <l>Did I not tell thee it would thus fall out?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>You did.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>What haſt then deſerued</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Hanging.</l>
                        <l>A little yet let me collect my ſelfe.</l>
                        <l>Ile ſtreight finde out ſome helpe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh me accurſt:</l>
                        <l>Why want I time to plague thee as I would?</l>
                        <l>This ſcarce will ſerue my danger to preuent,</l>
                        <l>Permits me not purſue thy puniſhment.</l>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt</hi> Pamphilus <hi>and</hi> Dauus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="act">
                  <pb n="31" facs="25"/>
                  <head>Act. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Charinus <hi>at one doore;</hi> Pamphilus <hi>and</hi> Dauus <hi>at another.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>MAy't be beleeu'd? or may it once be talk'd on?</l>
                        <l>That any ſhould be ſo ſelfe-wild peruerſe,</l>
                        <l>As to take pleaſure in anothers harmes?</l>
                        <l>Or thinke his owne gaine ſweeter, if procur'd</l>
                        <l>By others diſaduantage? oh good God!</l>
                        <l>Is this a brood of men? Men let them be;</l>
                        <l>Worſt are they of the generation.</l>
                        <l>They ſhew a little trickſey modeſtie,</l>
                        <l>Not to denie a craued curteſie:</l>
                        <l>But when performance comes, they then declare</l>
                        <l>(Nature will ſhew it ſelfe) what men they are.</l>
                        <l>They are aſham'd a little, but in triall</l>
                        <l>Their temper burſteth forth to flat deniall.</l>
                        <l>Then ſhall you heare their ſhameleſſe Oratorie—</l>
                        <l>Pray who are you? are what at leaſt to me.</l>
                        <l>Why yeeld my loue to you? good ſir attend,</l>
                        <l>I am vnto my ſelfe the neereſt friend.</l>
                        <l>Touch them with faith and troth, they bluſh no whit:</l>
                        <l>So that when no conſtraint inforceth it,</l>
                        <l>They make ſome ſcruple; when it comes to th' pinch,</l>
                        <l>Then at the proofe your hollow friend doth flinch.</l>
                        <l>But what's my beſt courſe? ſhall I to him ſtreight,</l>
                        <l>And with him this his wrong expoſtulate?</l>
                        <l>And ply him with harſh tearmes? but ſome may ſay,</l>
                        <l>What good ſhall I procure my ſelfe that way?</l>
                        <l>Yes much: I ſhall both chafe him, and giue eaſe</l>
                        <l>To my grieu'd heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Charinus,</hi> leſſe God pleaſe</l>
                        <pb n="32" facs="26"/>
                        <l>To ſuccour vs, I haue both thee and me</l>
                        <l>Againſt my will vndone vnwarily.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Vnwarily: is that word now thought on?</l>
                        <l>Y'haue broke your promiſd faith.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>As how, I pray?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Seeke you againe with faire words to abuſe me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>What meanes this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>After I ſaid I lou'd her,</l>
                        <l>You muſt needes like her too. Oh me accurſt,</l>
                        <l>That ſcantled out your dealing by mine owne!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>You are miſtaken.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Seem'd your content not full,</l>
                        <l>Vnleſſe you fool'd, and with falſe hope traind on</l>
                        <l>A wretched louer? much good doe ye; take her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I take her? oh I perceiue thou knowſt not</l>
                        <l>In what a gulfe of miſerie I am plung'd:</l>
                        <l>What pecke of troubles this my torturer</l>
                        <l>Hath brought me to, by harkning to his counſell.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>No marle: he takes his preſident from you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>You would not ſay this, if you fully knew</l>
                        <l>Or me, or her I'ue ſet my fancie on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, I doe know; you were at hot high words</l>
                        <l>Late with your father; and haue angred him,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe he cannot make you marrie her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, which diſcouers thou leſſe knowſt my griefe,</l>
                        <l>This mariage neuer was prepar'd for me:</l>
                        <l>Nor did now any force me to a wife.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I know't your owne will forc'd you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Tarrie, yet thou knowſt not all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I know thou'ſt marrie her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Why doe you thus torment me? heare but this</l>
                        <l>He neuer ceaſed to be vrgent on me,</l>
                        <l>That I ſhould tell my father I would marrie:</l>
                        <l>To intreat, perſwade, till he had drawne me to it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>What man did this.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>This <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dauus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dauus</hi> brings all things out of ſquare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="33" facs="26"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>What the inducement?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I nothing know, except this one thing onely,</l>
                        <l>That I well ſee the Gods are much diſpleaſed</l>
                        <l>With me, for liſtning to him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha</speaker>
                        <p>Did you thus <hi>Dauus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I did.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha, what faiſt thou caitife?</l>
                        <l>The gods giue thee a death futing thy doings.</l>
                        <l>Sir tha, but tell me; ſay that all his foes</l>
                        <l>Had laid their heads together for a plot</l>
                        <l>To yoake him to a wife, what ſtratagem</l>
                        <l>Could they haue fram'd more ſpeeding then this was?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I am deceiu'd, but faint not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I, I know't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>It thriu'd not this way, weele attempt ſome other.</l>
                        <l>Vnleſſe you iudge becauſe at firſt we ſped not,</l>
                        <l>There's no meanes ieſt vs to ſalue vp the miſchiefe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay more, I well beleeue if thou watch for it,</l>
                        <l>Of one thoult make me out a double marriage.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>I <hi>(Pamphilus)</hi> by reaſon of my bondage</l>
                        <l>Owe you thus much: to doe, goe, night and day</l>
                        <l>To indeauour all I may, with my liues hazard,</l>
                        <l>For your aduantage: it is yet your part</l>
                        <l>To beare with me, if things come croſſe my hopes:</l>
                        <l>My plots faile; yet I vſe all carefulneſſe:</l>
                        <l>Your ſelfe elſe frame things wiſeher, diſcharge me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I craue thou leaue me in that ſtate thou foūdſt me;</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>But't muſt be ſtreight.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>How now! hiſt, ſtay.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Glyceriums</hi> doore did creake.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>That's nought to thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I am a forging.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>How, is't now to forge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>But I will giu't you faſhion'd preſently.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>Enter Myſis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>VVHere ere he be, Ile finde your <hi>Pamphilus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And bring him with me ſtreight;</l>
                        <pb n="34" facs="27"/>
                        <l>Meane while good heart vex not your ſelfe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Myſis?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>What's the matter?</l>
                        <l>Oh, was't you <hi>Pamphilus?</hi> you are well met.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>What newes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>My Miſtreſſe praies you of all loue</l>
                        <l>To come to her: ſhe longs to ſpeake with you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I am a ſorlorne wretch: the miſchiefe ſpreads.</l>
                        <l>That ſhe and I ſhould both be thus perplexed</l>
                        <l>By meanes of thee? for I am therefore ſent for</l>
                        <l>Becauſe ſhe heares my wedding is prepared.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>From which how eaſily had you now bin quiet,</l>
                        <l>Had he bin quiet?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, ſo, goe on:</l>
                        <l>If of himſelfe he be not vexd inough,</l>
                        <l>Vrge him on further.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I indeede tis that</l>
                        <l>Does now afflict her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Myſis,</hi> I doe ſweare</l>
                        <l>By all the Gods vnto thee, I will neuer</l>
                        <l>Forſake her: no, though I were ſure thereby</l>
                        <l>To vndergoe the whole worlds enmitie.</l>
                        <l>I did deſire her; haue obtaind her; ſee</l>
                        <l>That we both iumpe in mindes, and qualitie.</l>
                        <l>Farewell to all that ſeeke vs two to ſeuer:</l>
                        <l>But death none takes her from me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I recouer</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I doe deſire (if't may be ſo borne vp)</l>
                        <l>My father ſhould not thinke I am the cauſe</l>
                        <l>The marriage holds not: if that cannot be,</l>
                        <l>Ile take the next courſe: that he may perceiue</l>
                        <l>I croſſe it. What kinde of man dooſt thinke me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith euery way as wretched as my ſelfe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I caſt for helpe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I, thou haſt a good heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>And will effect it for you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>'T muſt be now.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, I ha't now.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>What is it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>You miſtake;</l>
                        <l>It is for him, not you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I am content.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Say, what wilt doe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>I haue ſcarce day enough</l>
                        <pb n="35" facs="27"/>
                        <l>To finiſh it I feare: and thinke me not</l>
                        <l>At leaſure therefore now, to tell you it.</l>
                        <l>But get y'hence both; you, now but hinder me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile viſite her here.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>And you, whither you? <stage>Exit Pamphilus.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Wilt thou I tell thee truth?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay ſee, he makes a prologue to a tale.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>What dooſt for me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh impudent! is't not inough I giue thee</l>
                        <l>Some houres; by putting off his marriage?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet <hi>Dauus</hi> —</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, what?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>That I may haue her. —</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Ridiculous!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet if thou canſt do ought —</l>
                        <l>Come home to me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>To what end ſhould I come?</l>
                        <l>I nothing haue to helpe thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I but if—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, I will come.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>If thou canſt thinke of ought</l>
                        <l>Ile be at home.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Charinus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Myſis,</hi> while I goe hence</l>
                        <l>Stay here a little for me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>To what end?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis needfull now, thou do ſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Make haſt then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I will be here ſtraightway againe with thee.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Dauus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>THat no one holdeth any thing in certaine?</l>
                        <l>Your helpe good Gods! I thought this <hi>Pamphilus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Had bin my Miſtreſſes firme, chiefeſt good;</l>
                        <l>Tooke him to be her friend, her louer, husband;</l>
                        <l>Ready at all eſſaies to ſtand to her:</l>
                        <l>And yet what griefe ſuſtaines ſhe now through him?</l>
                        <l>Hence ſure more ill ſhe reapes then good from him.</l>
                        <l>But here comes <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <stage>Enter Dauus.</stage>
                        <l>What's that prithee friend? the childe?</l>
                        <l>Whither dooſt beare it?</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <pb n="36" facs="28"/>
                     <head>Scen. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>MYſis,</hi> now I</l>
                        <l>neede thy readreſt memorie and wit</l>
                        <l>In this I goe about.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>What art to doe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Take the childe from me ſtreight, &amp; lay it downe</l>
                        <l>Before our doore.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>What on the bare ground pray?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Take a few ſtrewings from the altar there—</l>
                        <l>And lay 'hem vnder.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why dooſt not thou thy ſelfe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>That if perchance my Maſter vrge my oath</l>
                        <l>Twas not my doing, I may ſafely ſweare it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I vnderſtand you: but pray tell me whence</l>
                        <l>This now new tender conſcience comes vpon thee?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Stir you more quicke; that you may further know</l>
                        <l>What tis I haue in hand. Oh <hi>Iupiter!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <stage>Enter Chremes.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>What?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>The father of the bride is come on vs. leaue the courſe which I at firſt intended.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not what you talke on?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>My ſelfe too</l>
                        <l>Will make as if I came from the right hand.</l>
                        <l>Haue you a care now as occaſion ſerues</l>
                        <l>You marke my talke, and ſuit your words to mine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I vnderſtand nothing you goe about:</l>
                        <l>But if in any thing you neede my helpe</l>
                        <l>Or ſee more then my ſelfe, I here will ſtay,</l>
                        <l>That I may be no hindrance in your way.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Dauus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>HAuing prepared all in readineſſe</l>
                        <l>Was needfull to my Daughters marriage,</l>
                        <l>I now returne to will 'hem ſend for her.</l>
                        <l>But what is here? ſo helpe me God, a childe!</l>
                        <l>Weman, laid you this childe here?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="37" facs="28"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Where is hee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Dooſt not anſwer me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Woes me, out of ſight.</l>
                        <l>Alas, <hi>Dauus</hi> has left me: and is gone. <stage>Enter Dauus.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Faith of the Gods!</l>
                        <l>What coile's yond'at the Market?</l>
                        <l>What throng of wranglers braule there? and beſide</l>
                        <l>Corne beares exceſſiue price. I know not now</l>
                        <l>What other words to vſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>For Gods ſake man</l>
                        <l>Why left you me alone here?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Hoida what</l>
                        <l>Denice is this? you <hi>Myſis,</hi> whence this childe?</l>
                        <l>Or who here laid it?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Are you in your wits,</l>
                        <l>To aske me that?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Of whom elſe ſhould I aske,</l>
                        <l>That ſee none elſe here?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>I marle whence it is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Wo●● tell me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Au!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Come here, o'my right ſide.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Th'art mad did not your ſelfe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Looke thou beware</l>
                        <l>Thou vtter not a word, but what I aske thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>D'yee threaten me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>From whence is it? ſpeake out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>From you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha, ha, he, iſt newes, if women</l>
                        <l>Of your condition doe grow impudent?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>This maid belongs to th' <hi>Andrian,</hi> as I thinke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Seeme we ſuch fitting perſons to you, troe</l>
                        <l>That you ſhould play on vs?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>I came in time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Therefore with ſpeede take you the childe away</l>
                        <l>Ilence from our doore: yet ſtay, ſee thou ſtirre not</l>
                        <l>One inch out of this place.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>The Gods confound thee</l>
                        <l>That me poore woman frightſt thus.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Do I ſpeake to thee, or not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>What would you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Askt thou ſtill?</l>
                        <l>Say, tell me whoſe childe tis thou haſt laid here?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe not you know?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Talke not of what I know,</l>
                        <pb n="38" facs="29"/>
                        <l>But tell me that I aske.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis of your houſe</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Whoſe, of vs?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha, what, <hi>Pamphilus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Iſt not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>I alwaies rightly ſhunn'd this match.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh notable vile practiſe!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why exclaimſt thou?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Which childe did not my ſelfe ſee yeſternight</l>
                        <l>Brought late to you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh moſt audacious fellow</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis truth, I ſaw <hi>Canthara</hi> thicke ſtuft out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>I thanke the Gods yet, that ſome Citie wiues</l>
                        <l>Were preſent at the labour.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>She not knowes</l>
                        <l>Him (I aſſure thee) for whoſe cauſe ſhe plots this.</l>
                        <l>She thinkes if <hi>Chremes</hi> ſee a child laid here,</l>
                        <l>Heel'e not beſtow his daughter: yes of truth,</l>
                        <l>For this the rather.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith but he will not though.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Now therefore, for thy knowledge, take it hence</l>
                        <l>Or I will tumble it in the high way;</l>
                        <l>And further lay thee by it in the kennell.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou certainly art drunke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>One cunning pranke</l>
                        <l>Treads on anothers heele. I heare it whiſperd</l>
                        <l>She's a free-borne <hi>Athenian.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chre.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>And that</l>
                        <l>He ſhall be fore'd by law to marrie her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſir I pray you, i● ſhe not free-borne?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>I had almoſt vnawares ieſted my ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Into a dangerous miſchiefe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Who talkes here?</l>
                        <l>Oh <hi>Chremes</hi> you are come in happy time.</l>
                        <l>Pray liſten ſir—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue heard all already.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>How all ſay you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>I, from the beginning all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Haue you pray heard it? ſee their villanies!</l>
                        <l>Tis fit ſhe were hence hurried to the racke.</l>
                        <l>This is the man I talk'd of: doe not thinke</l>
                        <l>You play your trickes on <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh wretched mee!</l>
                        <l>Indeede (good old Sir) I haue ſpoke no falſhood.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="39" facs="29"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>I know all to the full: but is your Maſter</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Simo</hi> within?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes Sir.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Chremes.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Roague hand me not.</l>
                        <l>Troth if <hi>Glycerium</hi> know not of all this—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Attend you foole, thou knowſt not what is done:</l>
                        <l>This the brides father: by no other meanes</l>
                        <l>Could he be made to know what we would haue him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why then you ſhould haue told me on't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Doeſt thinke</l>
                        <l>There no great difference, when a thing is carried</l>
                        <l>The naturall way, and when premeditate.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>Enter Crits.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>TIs told me <hi>Chryſis</hi> dwelt in this ſame ſtreet:</l>
                        <l>Who rather choſe heere leaudly to grow rich,</l>
                        <l>Then in her Countrie honeſtly liue poore:</l>
                        <l>She dead, the Law hath caſt her ſtate on me.</l>
                        <l>But now I ſee ſome I may queſtion:</l>
                        <l>God ſaue you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh good God whom doe I ſee?</l>
                        <l>Is not this <hi>Crito, Chriſis</hi> Cozen German?</l>
                        <l>Tis he.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Myſis!</hi> you are well met.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>The Gods</l>
                        <l>Proſper you <hi>Crito.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Chryſis</hi> then is—well?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes truely ſhe has left vs, to th'wide world.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>And you, what ſhift d'ye make? any thing well?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <l>We? faith e'en according to the prouerbe;</l>
                        <l>Liue as we can, ſince cannot as we would.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Glycerium</hi>—what, hath ſhe yet ſound her parents?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I would ſhe had.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>What not yet? I came hither</l>
                        <l>In an vnluckie houre: for had I knowne it</l>
                        <l>I ſure would ne'er haue ſtirr'd a ſoot this way.</l>
                        <l>She alwaies was both ſaid and deem'd her ſiſter</l>
                        <pb n="40" facs="30"/>
                        <l>And holds all that was hers: now for me their</l>
                        <l>To follow law ſuits being here a ſtranger,</l>
                        <l>How eaſie and commodious 'tmay be</l>
                        <l>Rife precedents of other men do warne me.</l>
                        <l>Beſides, I iudge by this ſhe has got her ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Some friend and patron: for when ſhe came thence</l>
                        <l>She had well-neere attained to ripe yeeres</l>
                        <l>Men will cry out I am a ſycophant,</l>
                        <l>A begger laying claime to others right:</l>
                        <l>Withall, my ſelfe liſt not impoueriſh her:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Good <hi>Crito,</hi> you ſtill hood your ancient courſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>Bring me vnto her, ſince I am come hither,</l>
                        <l>I may at leaſt yet ſee her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes I will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau</speaker>
                        <p>Ile follow yet the old man ſhall not ſee me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>Myſis <hi>and</hi> Crito <hi>enter</hi> Glyceriums <hi>houſe and</hi> Dauus <hi>followes them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="act">
                  <head>Act. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Chremes <hi>and</hi> Simo <hi>out of</hi> Simoes <hi>houſe.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>SImo</hi> enough, I haue enough tride your friend ſhip:</l>
                        <l>Venturd ſufficient hazard, pray now leaue</l>
                        <l>Intreating. Whilſt I ſeeke to pleaſure you</l>
                        <l>I almoſt triſled my childes liſe away.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, but I earneſtly begge and craue <hi>Chremes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>This your good turne now late begun in words</l>
                        <l>You would in deedes make vp.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr</speaker>
                        <l>Note how vniuſt</l>
                        <l>You grow, through earneſtneſſe to worke your aimes:</l>
                        <l>You nor conſider bounds in curteſies,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet what tis you crame: for if you did,</l>
                        <l>Yould ceaſe to load me with theſe iniuries.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What iniuties?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh, doe you queſtion them?</l>
                        <pb n="41" facs="30"/>
                        <l>You wrought me to beſtow my onely childe</l>
                        <l>To one intangled in a ſtrangers loue:</l>
                        <l>A wilde yong youth abhorring marriage:</l>
                        <l>To moſt ſure diſcord, marriage as inſure;</l>
                        <l>That by her griefe and ſorrow I might phiſicke</l>
                        <l>Your riotous ſonne: this y'obtain'd: I went on,</l>
                        <l>Whil'ſt things permitted: now that the caſe not brooks it,</l>
                        <l>You muſt brooke my deniall. Tis affirmd</l>
                        <l>This ſtranger is fice borne; hath a childe by him:</l>
                        <l>Leaue troubling vs.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>By all the Gods I beg</l>
                        <l>You would not bend your minde to truſt theſe people,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe beſt aduantage tis, to make him worſt.</l>
                        <l>Theſe things are onely ſeign'd and faſhioned</l>
                        <l>To daſh the wedding: take away the cauſe</l>
                        <l>Moues them to this, they'll ſtraight way leaue contrining.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are wide: My ſelfe ſaw a maide ſcolding here</l>
                        <l>With <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I know't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>I but this was done</l>
                        <l>In good ſad earneſt; neither of them both</l>
                        <l>Knowing that I was neere.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I doe beleeue it</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Dauus</hi> late told me it would be ſo.</l>
                        <l>I know not how I did forget to tell you,</l>
                        <l>As I had meant.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter.</hi> Dauus <hi>out of</hi> Glyceriums <hi>houſe.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I Will you now reſt quiet —</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>See, here's <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Whence comes he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Through my furthrance and this gueſts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What new miſchiefe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Man, time, comming fitter, I neuer ſaw.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Who iſt, the roague ſo praiſes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>All's now ſecure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Ceaſe I to ſpeake to him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau</speaker>
                        <p>My Maſter! what's my courſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="42" facs="31"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh <hi>Simo,</hi> oh our <hi>Chremes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>All things are now in readineſſe within.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Th'haſt lookt too 't well.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>When you pleaſe, ſend for her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis very well; but that courſe now here failes vs.</l>
                        <l>But may I know, what thou hadſt there to doe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Me meane you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, meane thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I went in but now —</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>As if I ask 't thee, when?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Together with your ſonne.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Is my ſonne there?</l>
                        <l>I wretch am ſet o'th racke. Diddſt not hangman</l>
                        <l>Tell me, they were at deadly oddes together?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>They are.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What does he there then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Hee? what thinkſt?</l>
                        <l>I warrant railing at her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay but <hi>Chremes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ile tell you now of a ſtrange accident.</l>
                        <l>I know not what old man is newly come,</l>
                        <l>Note him, a man both confident and wiſe,</l>
                        <l>When you ſhall ſee him, you'l much value him.</l>
                        <l>A graue auſterity reſts on his face;</l>
                        <l>And in his words dwell faith.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What newes bring'ſt thou?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>No other, then I heard that man report.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>And what doo's he report?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>That he doo's know</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Glycerium</hi> here, a free <hi>Athenian</hi> borne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Hoe <hi>Dromo, Dromo.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <stage>Enter Dromo. Sim. Dromo.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
                        <p>What's the matter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Heare me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>If thou ſpeakeſt one word more—<hi>Dromo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe beſeech you heare me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
                        <p>What would y'haue?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Hoiſt in this fellow here, hence ſpeedily.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="43" facs="31"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
                        <p>Whom?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Why?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>For it is my pleaſure.</l>
                        <l>Away with him I ſay.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>What haue I done?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>In with him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>If you ſhall finde I haue ly'de</l>
                        <l>In any thing, then kill me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile heare nothing.</l>
                        <l>Ile ſtreightway put thee into motion.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Though that I ſaid the truth?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Though — ſee you</l>
                        <l>Ile be kept bound; and heare you, bound all foure.</l>
                        <l>Ile ſhew thee, what tis to abuſe a Maſter,</l>
                        <l>If I but liue this day: and teach the other</l>
                        <l>What tis to croſſe a father.</l>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Dromo <hi>with</hi> Dauus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, I pray you rage not ſo much.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chremes</hi> dooſt not, ſeeing</l>
                        <l>How vnkindely he deales with me, pittie me?</l>
                        <l>That I ſhould toyle and care for ſuch a ſonne?</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Pamphitus</hi> you, come you out <hi>Pamphilus:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Doth any ſhame poſſeſſe thee?</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>Enter Pamphilus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>VVHo cald me?</l>
                        <l>I am loſt, it is my father.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>What ſaiſt now?</l>
                        <l>Thou of all—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh, rather goe to th'point man:</l>
                        <l>And ſpare ill ſpeaking.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>As if any thing</l>
                        <l>Can be ſpoke ill inough of ſuch a one?</l>
                        <l>But Sirrha ſay, is your <hi>Glycerium</hi> now</l>
                        <l>Free borne of <hi>Athens?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>So they ſay of her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Doe they ſay ſo? Monſtrous audaciouſneſſe!</l>
                        <l>Conſiders he his words? grieues at his deedes?</l>
                        <l>Or ſhewes his colour any note of ſhame?</l>
                        <l>That he ſhould be of ſuch deboſhed manners,</l>
                        <pb n="44" facs="32"/>
                        <l>That cleare beyond all precedent of freemen,</l>
                        <l>Againſt the forme of law, in oppoſition</l>
                        <l>Of me his father, he ſhould bend to haue her</l>
                        <l>Though 't reach to th'higheſt pitch of infamie?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh me moſt wretched!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Dooſt thou now at length</l>
                        <l>Perceiue that <hi>Pamphilus?</hi> that word of old</l>
                        <l>Of old that word then truely ſitted thee,</l>
                        <l>When firſt thou ſetſt thy heart to pleaſe thy ſelfe;</l>
                        <l>Though at what rate ſoeuer compaſſed.</l>
                        <l>But wherefore doe I thus? why yex my ſoule?</l>
                        <l>Why waſte my ſelfe away? why doe I grieue</l>
                        <l>My old and fainting age with his youths follies?</l>
                        <l>Shall I indure the pennance of his faultings?</l>
                        <l>No, let him haue her; I, God ſpeede him well;</l>
                        <l>Yes, let him keepe with her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam</speaker>
                        <p>Oh my father—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Why call'ſt me father? as if thou hadſt neede</l>
                        <l>Of me to be thy father? a houſe, wiſe,</l>
                        <l>Children are had maugre thy fathers will:</l>
                        <l>Fellowes are hir'd ſhall beare her vp freeborne.</l>
                        <l>Y'haue got the maſt'tie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I beſeech you father,</l>
                        <l>May I haue leaue to vtter a few words.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What wilt ſay to me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Vet heare him <hi>Simo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I heare him: what iſt <hi>Chremes</hi> I ſhould heare him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Permit him tell you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, tell he: I permit</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam</speaker>
                        <l>I doe confeſſe I loue this woman here</l>
                        <l>If it be faultie, I confeſſe that too.</l>
                        <l>Further I yeeld me vp to your full pleaſure,</l>
                        <l>Lay any taske, any command vpon me.</l>
                        <l>Will you I marrie that, leaue this? I will</l>
                        <l>Indure it as I may. But this one thing</l>
                        <l>I begge of you, that you would not imagine</l>
                        <l>That this old man is by my meanes brought in</l>
                        <l>Suffer me cleare my ſelfe, and fetch him hither</l>
                        <pb n="45" facs="32"/>
                        <l>Into your preſence</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Fetch him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Let mee pray.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>He craues but reaſon, grant it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I pray ſir.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Pamphilus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, I doe: I wiſh <hi>Chremes</hi> ought be proued,</l>
                        <l>So that I finde he doos not iuggle with me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Sleight accuſation in a ſonnes offence</l>
                        <l>Sufficeth for a father.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>Enter Crito and Pamphilus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>CEaſe to intreat.</l>
                        <l>Each of the reaſons you haue vſ'd, perſwade me</l>
                        <l>To your requeſt? either your owne ſelfe cauſe,</l>
                        <l>Or for it is a truth, or cauſe I wiſh</l>
                        <l>All furtherance vnto <hi>Gl ceriuns.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Doe I not ſee <hi>Crito</hi> of <hi>Andros</hi> there?</l>
                        <l>Tis he. <hi>Crito</hi> you are here well met:</l>
                        <l>You haue bin long a ſtranger here: what chance</l>
                        <l>Hath brought you now to <hi>Athens.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>An occaſion.</l>
                        <l>But is this <hi>Simo?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim</speaker>
                        <l>Aske you for me?</l>
                        <l>D'yee heare ſir, is it you that doe affirme</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Clycerium</hi> to be free borne of <hi>Athens?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you one, doe denie it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Is 't eene ſo?</l>
                        <l>Come you ſo well prepared too?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>Wherefore?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>Dooſt thou vſe queſtion? thinkſt thou to eſcape</l>
                        <l>Fairely thus of with 't? ſeekeſt thou to worke on</l>
                        <l>The eaſie natures of vnguided youth,</l>
                        <l>Peruerting our well nurtur'd children?</l>
                        <l>Winning their hearts with fawning promiſes.</l>
                        <l>And this, in <hi>Athens.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you in your wits?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>And harlot-loues knit'ſt vp in marriage?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>If you knew this man <hi>Simo</hi> thoroughly,</l>
                        <l>You would not iudge ſo: he is an honeſt man.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="46" facs="33"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>An honeſt man; to come iumpe in th'inſtant</l>
                        <l>Of doſing hands, and nere ſeene here before?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chremes,</hi> may ſuch a man be credited?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>If I not doubted to diſpleaſe my father</l>
                        <l>I eaſily could prompt him to that point.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Cauelling ſycophant —</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>How?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Forbeare <hi>Crito;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>It is his temper.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>Let him regard his temper:</l>
                        <l>If he will vent his pleaſure vpon me</l>
                        <l>He ſhall be forc'd to heare what will diſpleaſe him.</l>
                        <l>Trouble I his matters? or yet care for'hem?</l>
                        <l>Cannot you beare your owne ils patiently?</l>
                        <l>For my part, it may inſtantly be knowne</l>
                        <l>Whether 't be falſe or true, you heard me ſay</l>
                        <l>A certaine man of <hi>Athens,</hi> now long ſince</l>
                        <l>Shiprackt at ſea, was caſt on <hi>Andros</hi> Iſle;</l>
                        <l>And with him this <hi>Glycerium,</hi> then a childe:</l>
                        <l>He being poore had harbour at the houſe</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Chr ſi,</hi> father.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>He begins a tale.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray giue him leaue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>Does he diſturbe me thus?</l>
                        <l>He that entertaind him was my kinſman:</l>
                        <l>Of him I then heard, that this ſhipwrack'd man</l>
                        <l>Was an <hi>Ithenian.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, what was his name?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>His name ſo ſodainly? <hi>Pha—Pha-nia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, my heart!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes ſure, I thinke twas <hi>Phania.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>This I well know, he nam'd himſelfe of <hi>Ramnes.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Iupiter!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>A many moe in <hi>Andros</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Then heard it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>I beſeech the Gods, it proue</l>
                        <l>According to my hopes: but pray you <hi>Crito,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>What ſaid he of the childe, that twas his owne?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>No.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Whoſe then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>The daughter of his brother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis certainly mine owne.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>What doe you ſay?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="47" facs="33"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>What ſay you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Pamphilus</hi> giue heed to this.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Why thinke you ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>That <hi>Phania</hi> was my brother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>I knew him well, and know that he was ſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>He flying hence to auoid the rage of warre,</l>
                        <l>Trauaild toward <hi>Aſia</hi> in purſuit of me;</l>
                        <l>And feard withall to leaue the childe behinde:</l>
                        <l>Since whence, now I heare the firſt newes of him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I ſcarcely feele my ſelfe: my mind's ſo toſt</l>
                        <l>Twixt feare, and hope, and ioy, and wondring,</l>
                        <l>At this ſo great, ſo ſodaine happineſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>In truth I much reioyce, ſhe is found yours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I doe beleeue you father.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>But there reſts</l>
                        <l>One ſcruple yet, which ſomewhat troubles me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                        <p>You are worthy now of hate, with theſe your ſcruples</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>What is 't?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>The name agrees not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <l>She had ſure</l>
                        <l>Another being young.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>What was it <hi>Crito?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Canſt thou remember?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>I am thinking on 't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Shall I permit his tardie memorie</l>
                        <l>To ſlacken my ioyes current, being able</l>
                        <l>Herein to giue my ſelfe a remedie?</l>
                        <l>No, I will not: harke you hither <hi>Chremes;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The name you doubt of is <hi>Paſibula.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Crit.</speaker>
                        <p>That's it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis right.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I heard it of her ſelfe</l>
                        <l>At leaſt a thouſand times.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <l>I beleeue <hi>Chremes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>You thinke we all ioy at it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>As may the Gods</l>
                        <l>Aſſiſt me, I doe thinke ſo.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>What reſts father?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>The caſe it ſelfe now reconcileth vs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh my moſt louing father and you <hi>Chromes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Change nothing in the wife I now poſſeſſe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>The cauſe is iuſt, your father ſo agreeing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Thus much—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Yea marrie—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <p>Her dowre <hi>Pamphilus</hi> I make ten talents.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="48" facs="34"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>I accept of it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile forthwith ſee my daughter: <hi>Crito,</hi> pray</l>
                        <l>Goe with me; for I thinke ſhe knowes me not.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Why cauſe you not your wife be brought to vs?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>You warne me well, Ile eene giue <hi>Dauus</hi> charg out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>He cannot now effect it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray why ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Has more and greater charge vpon himſelfe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>What?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Hee's bound.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam</speaker>
                        <p>Hee's not bound rightly father.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>No; I did will him be bound otherwiſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray order he be looſd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, be it ſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>But good ſir, haſte.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile in and ſee it done.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Simo.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh happie, oh this proſperous bleſſed day.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>Scen. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>Enter Charinus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I Come to ſee how <hi>Pampirlus</hi> ſpeeds, and loe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Some man perhaps may think I feed on dreames:</l>
                        <l>But now I pleaſe to thinke all reall truth.</l>
                        <l>I on this ground iudge the Gods liues eternall,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe heir pleaſure's certainly their owne</l>
                        <l>For I my ſelfe haue gaind immortall ſtate,</l>
                        <l>If with this ioy no griefe ere intermeddle</l>
                        <l>But who might I now wiſh eſpecially</l>
                        <l>Here at this time, to tell the tidings to?</l>
                        <stage>Enter Dauus.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Chae.</speaker>
                        <p>What ioy is that he talkes of?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I now ſee</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dauus</hi> our man: there is no liuing one,</l>
                        <l>I rather would haue had. I know he wil?</l>
                        <l>Full truely ioy in the true ioy I feele.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <pb n="49" facs="34"/>
                     <head>Scen. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>VVhere is this <hi>Pamphilus</hi> trow?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dauus Dau.</hi> Who's that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis I.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Pamphilus!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou knoweſt not what has befall'n me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>True: yet know, what has chanc'd me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſo do I.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Why this happes iuſt oth'faſhion,</l>
                        <l>That you my ill lucke learne, ere I your good.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Glycerium</hi> hath found out her parents.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Good.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>How's that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Her father our chiefe friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Who iſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh braue!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>Nor now is any ſtay,</l>
                        <l>But that I take her home forthwith to wife.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Dreames he trow, of things he deſires waking?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Now <hi>Dauus,</hi> for the child?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <l>Leaue of I pray:</l>
                        <l>The gods ſure purpoſe him their minion.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>I am a made man, if theſe things be true</l>
                        <l>Ile ſpeake to'hem.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>O <hi>Charinus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thou com'ſt in a fit time.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh happie newes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <p>Haſt heard ont then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes all: pray thinke on me,</l>
                        <l>Now in the height of your felicitie.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chremes</hi> is now your owne, and I do know</l>
                        <l>Hele yeeld to any thing you motion.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                        <l>I mind it. But 't would now be ouer-long</l>
                        <l>Heere to attend, till he come forth to vs.</l>
                        <l>Follow me in; he's with <hi>Glycerium.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Get you home <hi>Dauus,</hi> haſten; and procure</l>
                        <l>Some that may beare her hence: why ſtand'ſt thou ſo?</l>
                        <l>Why ſtaieſt thou ſtill?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir Ile go preſently.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt Pamphilus, and Charinus. Epilogue.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <pb n="50" facs="35"/>
               <head>Epilogue by <hi>Dauus.</hi> Addition, by way of paraphraſe on <hi>Dauus</hi> laſt words in the Scene.</head>
               <l>I Note you ſit with kind attention bent,</l>
               <l>As pleaſd with what hath paſſed; and expect</l>
               <l>The further iſſue of our argument;</l>
               <l>And on the marrage now your minds reflect.</l>
               <l>We pray you ceaſe ſuch expectation;</l>
               <l>For we haue done: the bride you do conceiue</l>
               <l>But newly brought to bed; night comming on</l>
               <l>Women ſhall beare her hence, at <hi>Sionoes</hi> leaue.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chremes</hi> hs younger daughter <hi>Philumen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charinus</hi> gets, at ſure of <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crito</hi> of Andros, who has beene the meane</l>
               <l>The long loſt child ſhould be diſcouerd thus,</l>
               <l>What courſe he now ſhall take to obtaine his right</l>
               <l>In <hi>Chryſis</hi> goods, I here not mention will;</l>
               <l>Nor in leede can I: I haue no inſight</l>
               <l>In law points, triable at <hi>Mars</hi> his hill.</l>
               <l>Yet knowing <hi>Chremes</hi> nature tractable,</l>
               <l>Seeing withall he hath dealt liberally</l>
               <l>In portion, ſo that <hi>amph lus</hi> is able</l>
               <l>To beare the loſſe, though-common honeſtic</l>
               <l>Did not exact it I not doubt they will</l>
               <l>Vſe the poore ſtranger well. Me you haue ſcene heis</l>
               <l>Venture to binding, grinding in the Mill:</l>
               <l>That fell on me, this was approaching neare.</l>
               <l>I purpoſe further in their ioy to ſue</l>
               <l>My preſent freedome: <hi>Pamphilus</hi> loue I haue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glyceriums</hi> alſo; both I thinke of due:</l>
               <l>My Maſters chaſe is off I onely craue</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="35"/>
               <l>Your furtherance in the matter; which if gaind,</l>
               <l>I haue good hope: for I haue heard it ſed</l>
               <l>By men ith' <hi>Periclaean</hi> lawes well read,</l>
               <l>If I make you my friends, my ſute's obtaind:</l>
               <l>For they haue told me my diſcharge now ſtands</l>
               <l>not vpon whiſpering voyces; but clapt hands.</l>
               <trailer>Finis Andriae.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         
      </body>
      
   </text>
</TEI>