<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Francis Beaumont and Iohn Fletcher ...</title>
            <author>Beaumont, Francis, 1584-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>473 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno type="marc">12491932</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing B1581.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">52257</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Francis Beaumont and Iohn Fletcher ...</title>
                  <author>Beaumont, Francis, 1584-1616.</author>
                  <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625.</author>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
                  <author>Lowin, John, 1576-1659.</author>
                  <author>Taylor, Joseph, 1586?-1653?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[53], 75, 143, [1], 165, [3], 71, [1], 172, 92, 50 [i.e. 52], 28, 25-48 p. : port.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Robinson ... and for Humphrey Moseley ...,</publisher>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>"Never printed before, and now published by the authours originall copies"</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>First folio; includes the plays not hitherto printed, except the Wild-goose chase, which was missing, but recovered and printed in 1652. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>"The Epistle dedicatorie" is signed by John Lowin, Joseph Taylor, and eight others; "To the reader" signed by Ja. Shirley, who is usually regarded as the editor.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Portrait of Fletcher by Marshall.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>For complete contents of this edition, see NUC pre-1956 imprints.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="play">
                        <pb facs="211"/>
                        <pb n="149" facs="211"/>
                        <head>THE NICE VALOVR, OR, The Paſsionate Mad-man.</head>
                        <div n="1" type="act">
                           <head>Actus primus.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="scene">
                              <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                              <stage>Duke, Shamount, and <hi>4</hi> Gentlemen.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>_SHamount,</hi> welcome; we have miſt thee long,</l>
                                 <l>Though abſent but two daies: I hope your ſports</l>
                                 <l>Anſwer your time and wiſhes.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Very nobly ſir:</l>
                                 <l>We found game worthy your delight my Lord,</l>
                                 <l>It was ſo royall.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>I've enough to heare on't,</l>
                                 <l>Prethee beſtow't upon me in diſcourſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>What is this Gentleman Coz? you are a Courtier,</l>
                                 <l>Therefore know all their inſides.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>No farther then the Taffitie goes good Coz,</l>
                                 <l>For the moſt part, which is indeed the beſt part</l>
                                 <l>Of the moſt generall inſide: marry thus far</l>
                                 <l>I can with boldneſſe ſpeake this ones mans Character,</l>
                                 <l>And upon honour paſſe it for a true one;</l>
                                 <l>He has that ſtrength of many merit in him,</l>
                                 <l>That it exceeds his Soveraignes power of gracing;</l>
                                 <l>He's faithfully true to valour, that he hates</l>
                                 <l>The man from <hi>Caſars</hi> time, or farther off,</l>
                                 <l>That ever tooke diſgrace unreveng'd:</l>
                                 <l>And if he chance to read his abject ſtory,</l>
                                 <l>He teares his memory out, and holds it vertuous,</l>
                                 <l>Not to let ſhame have ſo much life amongſt us;</l>
                                 <l>There is not ſuch a curious piece of courage</l>
                                 <l>Amongſt mans fellowſhip, or one ſo jealous</l>
                                 <l>Of honours loſſe, or reputations glory:</l>
                                 <l>There's ſo much perfect, of his growing ſtory.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Twould make one dote on vertue as you tell it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ha' told it to much loſſe, beleeve it Coz.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>How the Duke graces him? what is he brother?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>4</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Do you not yet know him? a vain-glorious coxcombe,</l>
                                 <l>As proud as he that fell for't:</l>
                                 <l>Set but aſide his valour, no vertue,</l>
                                 <l>Which is indeed, not fit for any Courtier;</l>
                                 <l>And we his fellowes are as good as he,</l>
                                 <l>Perhaps as capable of favour too,</l>
                                 <l>For one thing or another, if 'twere look'd into:</l>
                                 <l>Give me a man, were I a Soveraigne now,</l>
                                 <l>Has a good ſtroake at Tennis, and a ſtiffe one,</l>
                                 <l>Can play at <hi>Equinoctium</hi> with the Line,</l>
                                 <l>As even as the thirteenth of <hi>September,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>When day and night lye in a ſcale together:</l>
                                 <l>Or may I thrive as I deſerve at Billiards;</l>
                                 <l>No otherwiſe at Cheſſe, or at Primero:</l>
                                 <l>Theſe are the parts requir'd, why not advanc'd?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Truſt me, it was no leſſe then excellent pleaſure,</l>
                                 <l>And I'm right glad 'twas thine. How fares our kinſman?</l>
                                 <l>Who can reſolve us beſt?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>I can my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>There if I had a pitty without bounds,</l>
                                 <l>It might be all beſtowed — A man ſo loſt</l>
                                 <l>In the wild waies of paſſion, that he's ſenſible</l>
                                 <l>Of nought but what torments him?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>True my Lord,</l>
                                 <l>He runs through all the Paſſions of mankind,</l>
                                 <l>And ſhifts 'em ſtrangely too: one while in love,</l>
                                 <l>And that ſo violent, that for want of buſineſſe,</l>
                                 <l>Hee'l court the very Prentice of a Laundreſſe,</l>
                                 <l>Though ſhe have kib'd heeles: and in's melancholly agen,</l>
                                 <l>He will not brooke an Empreſſe, though thrice fairer</l>
                                 <l>Then ever <hi>Maud</hi> was; or higher ſpirited</l>
                                 <l>Then <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> or your Engliſh Counteſſe:</l>
                                 <l>Then on a ſudden he's ſo merry againe,</l>
                                 <l>Out-laughs a waiting woman, before her firſt Child:</l>
                                 <l>And turning of a hand, ſo angry—</l>
                                 <l>'Has almoſt beate the Northen fellow blind;</l>
                                 <l>That is for that uſe only; if that mood hold my Lord,</l>
                                 <l>'Had need of a freſh man; I'le undertake,</l>
                                 <l>He ſhall bruiſe three a month.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>I pitty him dearely:</l>
                                 <l>And let it be your charge, with his kind brother,</l>
                                 <l>To ſee his moods obſerv'd; let every paſſion</l>
                                 <l>Be fed ev'n to a ſurfet, which in time</l>
                                 <l>May breed a loathing: let him have enough</l>
                                 <l>Of every object, that his ſence is rapt with;</l>
                                 <l>And being once glutted, then the taſte of folly</l>
                                 <l>Will come into his relliſh. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ſhall ſee</l>
                                 <l>Your charge my Lord moſt faithfully effected:</l>
                                 <l>And how does noble <hi>Shamount?</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Never ill man</l>
                                 <l>Untill I heare of baſeneſſe, then <hi>I</hi> ſicken,</l>
                                 <l>I am the healthful'ſt man i'th' Kingdome elſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Be arm'd then for a fit, <stage>Enter Lapet.</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Here comes a fellow</l>
                                 <l>Will make you ſicke at heart, if baſeneſſe do't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let me be gone: what is he?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let me tell you firſt,</l>
                                 <l>It can be but a qualme, pray ſtay it out ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Come, y'ave borne more then this.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Borne? never any thing</l>
                                 <pb n="150" facs="212"/>
                                 <l>That was injurious.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ha, I am far from that.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>He lookes as like a man as I have ſeene one:</l>
                                 <l>What would you ſpeake of him? ſpeake well I prethee,</l>
                                 <l>Even for humanities cauſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>You'd have it truth though?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>What elſe ſir? I have no reaſon to wrong heav'n</l>
                                 <l>To favour nature; let her beare her owne ſhame</l>
                                 <l>If ſhe be faultie.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Monſtrous faultie there ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>I'm ill at eaſe already.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray beare up ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>I Prethee let me take him down with ſpeed then.</l>
                                 <l>Like a wild object that I would not looke upon.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Then thus: he's one that will endure as much</l>
                                 <l>As can be lay'd upon him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>That may be noble:</l>
                                 <l>I'm kept too long from his acquaintance.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>O ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Take heed of raſh repentance, y'are too forward</l>
                                 <l>To find out vertue where it never ſetled:</l>
                                 <l>Take the particulars firſt of what he endures;</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Videlicet,</hi> Baſtinadoes by the great.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>How!</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Thumps by the dozen, and your kicks by whole ſale.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>No more of him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>The twinges by the noſtril he ſnuffes up,</l>
                                 <l>And holds it the beſt remedy for ſneazing.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Away.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Has been thrice ſwitz't from ſeven a clock till nine,</l>
                                 <l>Yet with a Cart-Horſe ſtomack fell to break-faſt,</l>
                                 <l>Forgetfull of his ſmart.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay, the diſgrace on't;</l>
                                 <l>There is no ſmart but that: baſe things are felt</l>
                                 <l>More by their ſhames then hurts Sir, I know you not,</l>
                                 <l>But that you live an injury to nature:</l>
                                 <l>I'm heartily angry with you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray give your blow or kicke, and begon then:</l>
                                 <l>For I ne're ſaw you before, and indeed,</l>
                                 <l>Have nothing to ſay to you, for I know you not.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why wouldſt thou take a blow?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>I would not ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Unleſſe 'twere offer'd me; and if from an enemy—</l>
                                 <l>I'de be loth to deny it from a ſtranger.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>What, a blow?</l>
                                 <l>Endure a blow? and ſhall he live that gives it?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Many a faire yeare—why not ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let me wonder!</l>
                                 <l>As full a man to ſee too, and as perfect—</l>
                                 <l>I prethee live not long—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let me intreat it:</l>
                                 <l>Thou doſt not know what wrong thou doſt mankind,</l>
                                 <l>To walke ſo long here; not to dye betimes.</l>
                                 <l>Let me adviſe thee, while thou haſt to live here,</l>
                                 <l>Ev'n for mans honour ſake, take not a blow more.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>You ſhould adviſe them not to ſtrike me then ſir,</l>
                                 <l>For Ile take none I aſſure you, leſſe then are given.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>How faine would I preſerve mans forme from ſhame,</l>
                                 <l>And cannot get it done? however ſir,</l>
                                 <l>I charge thee live not long.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>This is worſe then beating.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Of what profeſſion art thou, tell me ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Beſides a Taylor? for Ile know the truth.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>A Taylor? I'm as a good a Gentleman—</l>
                                 <l>Can ſhew my armes and all.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>How black and blew they are?</l>
                                 <l>Is that your manifeſtation? upon paine</l>
                                 <l>Of pounding thee to duſt, aſſume not wrong fully,</l>
                                 <l>The name of Gentleman, becauſe I am one,</l>
                                 <l>That muſt not let thee live.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>I have done, I have done ſir,</l>
                                 <l>If there be any harme, beſhrew the Herald,</l>
                                 <l>I'em ſure I ha not been ſo long a gentleman,</l>
                                 <l>To make this anger: I have nothing no where,</l>
                                 <l>But what I dearely pay for. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>Groom begone;</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> never was ſo heart-ſick yet of man.</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Enter Lady, the Dukes ſiſter, Lapets wife.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Here comes a cordiall Sir from tother ſex,</l>
                                 <l>Able to make a dying face look chearfull.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>The bleſſedneſſe of Ladies —</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                                 <l>Y'are well met ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>The ſight of you has put an evill from me,</l>
                                 <l>Whoſe breath was able to make vertue ſicken.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                                 <p>I'me glad <hi>I</hi> came ſo fortunately. What was't ſit?</p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>A thing that takes a blow, lives and eates after it,</l>
                                 <l>In very good health; you ha' not ſeen the like Madam,</l>
                                 <l>A monſter worth your ſixpence, lovely worth,</l>
                                 <l>Speak low Sir; by all likely-hoods 'tis her husband,</l>
                                 <l>That now beſtow'd a viſitation on me. Farewell ſir. <stage>Ex.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>Husband? is't poſſible that he has a wife?</l>
                                 <l>Would any creature have him? 'twas ſome forc'd match,</l>
                                 <l>If he were not kick'd toth' Church oth' wedding day,</l>
                                 <l>Ile never come at Court. Can be no otherwiſe:</l>
                                 <l>Perhaps he was rich, ſpeak Miſtris <hi>Lapet,</hi> was it not ſo?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>VVife.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay, that's without all queſtion.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>O ho, he would not want kickers enow then;</l>
                                 <l>If you are wiſe, I much ſuſpect your honeſty;</l>
                                 <l>For wiſedome never faſtens conſtantly,</l>
                                 <l>But upon merit: If you incline to foole,</l>
                                 <l>You are alike unfit for his ſocietie;</l>
                                 <l>Nay if it were not boldneſſe in the man</l>
                                 <l>That honours you, to adviſe you, troth his company</l>
                                 <l>Should not be frequent with you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>VViſe.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis good counſell ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh I am ſo carefull where I reverence,</l>
                                 <l>So juſt to goodneſſe, and her precious purity,</l>
                                 <l>I am as equallie jealous, and as fearefull,</l>
                                 <l>That any undeſerved ſtaine might fall</l>
                                 <l>Upon her ſanctified whiteneſſe, as of the ſin</l>
                                 <l>That comes by wilfulneſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>VVife.</speaker>
                                 <l>Sir, I love your thoughts,</l>
                                 <l>And honour you for your counſell and your care.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>We are your ſervants.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>VVife.</speaker>
                                 <l>Hee's but a gentleman oth' chamber, he might have kiſt me:</l>
                                 <l>Faith, where ſhall one finde leſſe courteſie, then at Court?</l>
                                 <l>Say <hi>I</hi> have an undeſerver to my husband:</l>
                                 <l>That's ne're the worſe for him: well ſtrange lipt men,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis but a kiſſe loſt, there'll more come agen. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <stage>Enter the Paſſionate Lord, the Dukes Kinſman, makes a congie or two to nothing.</stage>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Look who comes here ſir, his love fit's upon him;</l>
                                 <l>I know it, by that ſet ſmile, and thoſe congies.</l>
                                 <l>How courteous hee's to nothing? which indeed,</l>
                                 <l>Is the next kin to woman; onely ſhadow</l>
                                 <l>The elder Siſter of the twaine, becauſe 'tis ſeen too.</l>
                                 <l>See how it kiſſes the fore-finger ſtill;</l>
                                 <pb n="151" facs="212"/>
                                 <l>Which is the laſt edition, and being come</l>
                                 <l>So neare the thumbe every Cobler has got it?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>What a ridiculous peice, humanity</l>
                                 <l>Here makes it ſelfe?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay, good give leave a little ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Y'are ſo preciſe a manhood—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>It afflicts me</l>
                                 <l>When <hi>I</hi> behold unſeemelineſſe in an Image</l>
                                 <l>So neare the Godhead, 'tis an injurie</l>
                                 <l>To glorious Eternity.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray uſe patience ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I do confeſſe it freely precious Lady,</l>
                                 <l>And loves ſuit'is ſo, the longer it hangs</l>
                                 <l>The worſe it is; better cut off ſweet Madam;</l>
                                 <l>O that ſame drawing in your nether lip there,</l>
                                 <l>Foreſhewes no goodneſſe Lady: make you queſtion on't?</l>
                                 <l>Shame on me but I love you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Who is't ſir,</l>
                                 <l>You are at all this paines for? may I know her?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>For thee thou faireſt, yet the falſeſt woman,</l>
                                 <l>That ever broke mans heart-ſtrings.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>How? how's this ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>What, the old tricke of Ladies? mans apparrell,</l>
                                 <l>Wil't nere be left amongſt you? ſteale from Court in't?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ſee the fit growes ſtronger.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray let's talke a little.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>I can endure no more.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Good, let us alone a little:</l>
                                 <l>You are ſo exact a worke: love light things ſomewhat ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Th'are all but ſhames.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>What is't you'd ſay to me ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Can you be ſo forgetfull to enquire it Lady?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes truly ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>The more I admire your ſtintineſſe:</l>
                                 <l>What cauſe have I given you, illuſtrious Madam,</l>
                                 <l>To play this ſtrange part with me?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Cauſe enough,</l>
                                 <l>Do but looke backe ſir into your memorie,</l>
                                 <l>Your love to other women ô lewd man,</l>
                                 <l>'Tas almoſt kil'd my heart, you ſee I'm chang'd with it,</l>
                                 <l>I ha' loſt the faſhion of my Sexe with griefe on't,</l>
                                 <l>When I have ſeen you courting of a Dowdie;</l>
                                 <l>Compar'd with me, and kiſſing your fore-finger</l>
                                 <l>To one o'th' black-guards Miſtreſſes: would not this</l>
                                 <l>Cracke a poore Ladies heart, that beleev'd love,</l>
                                 <l>And waited for the comfort? but 'twas ſaid ſir,</l>
                                 <l>A Lady of my haire cannot want pittying:</l>
                                 <l>The Countries coming up, farewell to you ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Whither intend you ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>A long journey ſir:</l>
                                 <l>The truth is, I'm with child, and goe to travell.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>With child? I never got it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>I heard you were buſie</l>
                                 <l>At the ſame time ſir, and was loath to trouble you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why, are not you a whore then, excellent Madam?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>O by no meanes, 'twas done ſir in the ſtate</l>
                                 <l>Of my beliefe in you, and that quits me,</l>
                                 <l>It lies upon your falſhod.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Does it ſo?</l>
                                 <l>You ſhall not carry her though ſir, ſhe's my contract.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>I prethee thou four Elements ill brued,</l>
                                 <l>Torment none but thy ſelfe; away I ſay</l>
                                 <l>Thou beaſt of paſſion, as the drunkard is</l>
                                 <l>The beaſt of wine; diſhonour to thy making,</l>
                                 <l>Thou man in fragments.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Heare me pretious Madam.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Kneele for thy wits to heaven.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Lady, I'le father it,</l>
                                 <l>Who ere begot it: 'tis the courſe of greatneſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>How vertue groanes at this?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I'le raiſe the Court, but I'le ſtay your ſlight.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>How wretched is that peice? <stage>Ex. Paſ. Lord.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>He's the Dukes kinſman ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>That cannot take a paſſion away ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Nor cut a fit, but one poore houre ſhorter,</l>
                                 <l>He muſt endure as much as the pooreſt begger,</l>
                                 <l>That cannot change his money; there's the equality</l>
                                 <l>In our impartiall eſſence:</l>
                                 <l>What's the newes now? <stage>Ent. a Servant.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>Your worthy brother ſir, has left his charge,</l>
                                 <l>And come to ſee you. <stage>Ent. Shamounts brother a Souldier.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>O the nobleſt welcome</l>
                                 <l>That ever came from man, meet thy deſervings:</l>
                                 <l>Methinkes I've all joyes treaſure in mine armes now,</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>You are ſo fortunate in prevention brother,</l>
                                 <l>You alwaies leave the anſwerer barren ſir,</l>
                                 <l>You comprehend in few words ſo much worth—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis all too little for thee: come th'art welcome,</l>
                                 <l>So I include all: take eſpeciall knowledge pray,</l>
                                 <l>Of this deare Gentleman, my abſolute friend,</l>
                                 <l>That loves a Souldier far above a Miſtris,</l>
                                 <l>Thou excellently faithfull to 'em both.</l>
                                 <l>But love to manhood, ownes the purer troath. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="act">
                           <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="scene">
                              <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                              <stage>Enter Shamonts brother a Souldier, and a Lady the Dukes ſiſter.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lady</speaker>
                                 <l>THere ſhould be in this gallery—on th'are here,</l>
                                 <l>Pray ſit downe; beleeve me ſir I'm weary.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>It well becomes a Lady to complaine a little</l>
                                 <l>Of what ſhe never feeles: your walke was ſhort Madam,</l>
                                 <l>You can be but affraid of wearineſſe;</l>
                                 <l>Which well employes the ſoftneſſe of your Sexe,</l>
                                 <l>As for the thing it ſelfe, you never came to't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>La.</speaker>
                                 <l>Y'are wonderouſly well read in Ladies ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>Shall I thinke ſuch a creature as you Madam,</l>
                                 <l>Was ever borne to feele paine, but in travell?</l>
                                 <l>There's your full portion,</l>
                                 <l>Beſides a little toothache in the breeding,</l>
                                 <l>Which a kind husband too, takes from you Madam.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>La.</speaker>
                                 <l>But where do Ladies ſir, find ſuch kind husbands?</l>
                                 <l>Perhaps you have heard</l>
                                 <l>The Rhumaticke ſtory of ſome loving Chandler now,</l>
                                 <l>Or ſome ſuch melting fellow, that you talke</l>
                                 <l>So prodigall of mens kindneſſe: I confeſſe ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Many of thoſe wives are happy, their ambition</l>
                                 <l>Does reach no higher, then to love and ignorance,</l>
                                 <l>Which makes an excellent husband, and a fond one:</l>
                                 <l>Now ſir, your great ones aime at height, and cunning,</l>
                                 <l>And ſo are oft deceiv'd, yet they muſt venture it;</l>
                                 <l>For 'tis a Ladies contumely ſir,</l>
                                 <l>To have a Lord an Ignorant; then the worlds voice</l>
                                 <l>Will deeme her for a wanton ere ſhe taſte on't:</l>
                                 <l>But to deceive a wiſe man, to whoſe circumſpection,</l>
                                 <l>The world reſignes it ſelfe with all his envy;</l>
                                 <l>'Tis leſſe diſhonour to us then to fall,</l>
                                 <l>Becauſe his beleev'd wiſdome keepes out all.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                                 <l>Would I were the man Lady, that ſhould venture</l>
                                 <pb n="152" facs="213"/>
                                 <l>His wiſedome to your goodneſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>You might faile</l>
                                 <l>In the returne, as many men have done ſir:</l>
                                 <l>I dare not juſtifie what is to come of me,</l>
                                 <l>Becauſe I know it not, though I hope vertuouſly;</l>
                                 <l>Marry what's paſt or preſent, I durſt put</l>
                                 <l>Into a good mans hand, Which if he take</l>
                                 <l>Upon my word for good, it ſhall not couzen him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>No, nor her after?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>It may hap ſo too ſir:</l>
                                 <l>A womans goodneſſe, when ſhe is a wiſe,</l>
                                 <l>Lies much upon a mans deſert, believe it ſir,</l>
                                 <l>If there be fault in her, Ile pawn my life on't,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis firſt in him, if ſhe were ever good,</l>
                                 <l>That makes one; knowing not a husband yet,</l>
                                 <l>Or what he may be, I promiſe no more vertues,</l>
                                 <l>Then I may well performe, for that were couſenage.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>Happy were he that had you with all feares,</l>
                                 <l>That's my opinion, Lady.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Shamont &amp; a ſervant liſtning.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>What ſay you now ſir?</l>
                                 <l>Dare you give confidence to your owne eyes?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Not yet I dare not.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>No?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Scarce yet, or yet:</l>
                                 <l>Although I ſee 'tis he. Why can a thing,</l>
                                 <l>That's but my ſelfe divided be ſo falſe?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay doe but marke how the chaire plaies his part too:</l>
                                 <l>How amorouſly 'tis bent.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Hell take thy bad thoughts,</l>
                                 <l>For they are ſtrange ones. Never take delight</l>
                                 <l>To make a torment worſe. Look on 'em heaven,</l>
                                 <l>For that's a brother: ſend me a faire enemy,</l>
                                 <l>And take him; for a fouler fiend there breathes not:</l>
                                 <l>I will not ſin, to think there's ill in her,</l>
                                 <l>But what's of his producing.</l>
                                 <l>Yet goodneſſe, whoſe incloſure is but fleſh,</l>
                                 <l>Holds out oft times but ſorrily. But as black ſir,</l>
                                 <l>As ever kindred was: I hate mine owne bloud,</l>
                                 <l>Becauſe it is ſo neare thine. Live without honeſty,</l>
                                 <l>And maiſt thou dye with an unmoiſtned eye,</l>
                                 <l>And no teare follow thee. <stage>Ex. Shamont, Servant.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>Y'are wondrous merry ſir; I would your Brother heard you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>O my ſiſter</l>
                                 <l>I would not out oth' way, let fall my words Lady,</l>
                                 <l>Por the precizeſt humour.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Paſſionate Lord.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yea, ſo cloſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>Th'are merry, that's the worſt you can report on 'em;</l>
                                 <l>Th'are neither dangerous, nor immodeſt.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>So ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Shall I believe you, think you?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>Who's this Lady?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>O the Dukes Couſen; he came late from travel ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>Reſpect belongs to him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>For as I ſaid Lady,</l>
                                 <l>Th'are merry that's the worſt you can report of em:</l>
                                 <l>Th'are neither dangerous, nor immodeſt.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>How's this?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>And there I think I left.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>Abuſes me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now to proceed, Lady; perhaps I ſwore I lov'd you,</l>
                                 <l>If you believe me not, y'are much the wiſer.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>He ſpeaks ſtill in my perſon, and derides me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>For I can cog with you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>You can all doe ſo.</l>
                                 <l>We make no queſtion of mens promptneſs that way.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>And ſmile, &amp; wave a chair with comely grace too,</l>
                                 <l>Play with our Taſtle gently, and doe fine things,</l>
                                 <l>That catch a Lady ſooner then a vertue.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>I never us'd to let man live ſo long</l>
                                 <l>That wrong'd me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                                 <l>Talke of Battalions, wooe you in a skirmiſh;</l>
                                 <l>Divine my mind to you Lady; and being ſharp ſet,</l>
                                 <l>Can court you at halfe pike: or name your weapon,</l>
                                 <l>We cannot faile you Lady. <stage>Enter <hi>1</hi> Gen.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now he dies:</l>
                                 <l>Were all ſucceeding hopes ſtor'd up within him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ge.</speaker>
                                 <l>O fie, i'th' Court ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>I moſt dearely thanke you ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ge.</speaker>
                                 <l>Tis rage ill ſpent upon a paſſionate mad-man.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>That ſhall not priviledge him for ever ſir:</l>
                                 <l>A mad-man call you him? I have found too much reaſon</l>
                                 <l>Sound in his injurie to me, to beleeve him ſo.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ge.</speaker>
                                 <l>If ever truth from mans lips may be held</l>
                                 <l>In reputation with you, give this confidence;</l>
                                 <l>And this his love-fit, which we obſerve ſtill,</l>
                                 <l>By's flattering and his finenes: at ſome other time,</l>
                                 <l>Hee'l goe as ſlovenly as heart can wiſh.</l>
                                 <l>The love and pity that his Highneſſe ſhewes to him,</l>
                                 <l>Makes every man the more reſpectfull of him:</l>
                                 <l>Has never a paſſion, but is well provided for,</l>
                                 <l>As this of Love, he is full fed in all;</l>
                                 <l>His ſwinge as I may tearme it: have but patience,</l>
                                 <l>And ye ſhall witneſſe ſomewhat.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>Still he mocks me:</l>
                                 <l>Looke you, in action, in behaviour ſir;</l>
                                 <l>Hold ſtill the chaire, with a grand miſchiefe to you,</l>
                                 <l>Or Ile ſet ſo much ſtrength upon your heart sir—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                                 <l>I feele ſome power has reſtrain'd me Lady:</l>
                                 <l>If it be ſent from love, ſay, I obey it,</l>
                                 <l>And ever keep a voice to welcome it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                                 <body>
                                    <head>Song.</head>
                                    <sp>
                                       <l>THou Deitie, ſwift winged love,</l>
                                       <l>Sometimes below, ſometimes above,</l>
                                       <l>Little in ſhape, but great in power,</l>
                                       <l>Thou that makeſt a heart thy Tower,</l>
                                       <l>And thy loop-holes, Ladies eyes,</l>
                                       <l>From whence thou ſtrik'ſt the fond and wiſe.</l>
                                       <l>Did all the ſhafts in thy faire quiver</l>
                                       <l>Stick faſt in my ambitious liver;</l>
                                       <l>Yet thy power would I adore,</l>
                                       <l>And call upon thee to ſhoot more.</l>
                                       <l>ſhoot more, ſhoot more.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                              <stage>Enter one like a Cupid offring to ſhoot at him.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> prethee hold though, ſweet Caeleſtiall boy;</l>
                                 <l>I'm not requited yet with love enough,</l>
                                 <l>For the firſt arrow that <hi>I</hi> have within me:</l>
                                 <l>And if thou be an equall archer <hi>Cupid,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Shoot this Lady, and twenty more for me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>Me ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Tis nothing but device, feare it not Lady;</l>
                                 <l>You may be as good a maid after that ſhaft Madam,</l>
                                 <l>As ere your mother was at twelve and halfe:</l>
                                 <l>Tis like the boy that drawes it, 'tas no ſting yet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
                                 <l>Tis like the miſerable maid that drawes it—<hi>aſide.</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>That ſees no comfort yet, ſeeing him ſo paſſionate.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Strike me the Ducheſſe of Valois in love with me,</l>
                                 <l>With all the ſpeed thou canſt, and two of her women.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <pb n="153" facs="213"/>
                                 <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                                 <l>You ſhall have more. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Tell 'em I tarry for 'em.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Who would be angry with that walking trouble now</l>
                                 <l>That hurts none but it ſelfe?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>I am better quieted.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile have all women-kind ſtrucke in time for me</l>
                                 <l>After thirteene once:</l>
                                 <l>I ſee this <hi>Cupid</hi> will not let me want,</l>
                                 <l>And let him ſpend his forty ſhafts an houre,</l>
                                 <l>They ſhall be all found from the Dukes Exchequer;</l>
                                 <l>He's come already.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter againe the ſame Cupid, two brothers, <hi>6</hi> women Maſkers, Cupids bow bent all the way towards them, the first woman ſinging and playing, A Prieſt.</stage>
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                                 <body>
                                    <head>The Song.</head>
                                    <sp>
                                       <l>O turne thy bow,</l>
                                       <l>Thy power we feele and know,</l>
                                       <l>Faire Cupid turne away thy bow:</l>
                                       <l>They be thoſe golden Arrowes,</l>
                                       <l>Bring Ladies all their ſorrowes,</l>
                                       <l>And till there be more truth in men,</l>
                                       <l>Never ſhoot at maid agen.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>What a felicity of whores are here?</l>
                                 <l>And all my concubines, ſtrucke bleeding new:</l>
                                 <l>A man can in his life time make but one woman,</l>
                                 <l>But he may make his fifty Queanes a month.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                                 <l>Have you remembred a Prieſt honeſt brothers?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes ſiſter, and this is the young gentleman,</l>
                                 <l>Make you no queſtion of our faithfulneſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>His growing ſhame ſiſter provokes our care.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Prieſt.</speaker>
                                 <l>He muſt be taken in this fit of love Gentlemen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>What elſe ſir? he ſhall do't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Enough.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Be cheerefull wench. <stage>A dance, Cupid leading.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now by the ſtroake of pleaſure, a deep oath,</l>
                                 <l>Nimbly hopt Ladies all; what height they beare too?</l>
                                 <l>A ſtory higher then your common ſtatures;</l>
                                 <l>A little man muſt go up ſtaires to kiſſe 'em:</l>
                                 <l>What a great ſpace there is</l>
                                 <l>Betwixt loves dyning Chamber, and his Garret?</l>
                                 <l>Ile trie the utmoſt height—the Garret ſtoopes methinkes;</l>
                                 <l>The roomes are made all bending, I ſee that,</l>
                                 <l>And not ſo high as a man takes 'em for.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now if you'l follow me ſir, I've that power,</l>
                                 <l>To make them follow you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Are they all ſhot?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                                 <l>All, all ſir, every mothers daughter of 'em.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Then there's no feare of following; if they be once ſhot,</l>
                                 <l>They'l follow a man to th' devill—As for you ſir— <stage>Ex. with the lady, &amp; the Maskers.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>Me ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay ſweet ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>A noiſe, a threatning; did you not heare it ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Without regard ſir, ſo would I heare you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>This muſt come to ſomething, never talke of that Sir,</l>
                                 <l>You never ſaw it otherwiſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay deare merit —</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>Me above all men?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Troth you wrong your anger.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>I will be arm'd my honourable Letcher.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>O fie ſweet ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>That devoures womens honeſties by lumps,</l>
                                 <l>And never chawſt thy pleaſure.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>What do you meane ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>What does he meane t'ingroſſe all to himſelfe?</l>
                                 <l>There's others love a whore, as well as he ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh an' that be part o'th furie, we have a Citty</l>
                                 <l>Is very well provided for that caſe;</l>
                                 <l>Let him alone with her, ſir we have women</l>
                                 <l>Are very charitable to proper men,</l>
                                 <l>And to a Souldier that has all his limbes;</l>
                                 <l>Marry the ſicke and lame gets not a penny:</l>
                                 <l>Right womens charity, and the husbands follow't too:</l>
                                 <l>Here comes his highneſſe ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Duke, and Lords.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile walke to coole my ſelfe. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Who's that?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>The brother of <hi>Shamont.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>He's Brother then</l>
                                 <l>To all the Courts love, they that love diſcreetly,</l>
                                 <l>And place their friendlineſſe upon deſert:</l>
                                 <l>As for the reſt, that with a double face</l>
                                 <l>Looke upon merit, much like fortunes viſage,</l>
                                 <l>That lookes two waies, both to lifes calmes and ſtormes,</l>
                                 <l>Ile ſo provide for him, chiefly for him,</l>
                                 <l>He ſhall not wiſh their loves, nor dread their envies.</l>
                                 <l>And here comes my <hi>Shamont.</hi>
                                    <stage>Enter Shamont.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>That Ladies vertues are my only joyes,</l>
                                 <l>And he to offer to lay ſiedge to them?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Shamont.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Her goodneſſe is my pride; in all diſcourſes,</l>
                                 <l>As often as I here raſh tongued gallants,</l>
                                 <l>Speake rudely of a woman, preſently</l>
                                 <l>I give in but her name, and th'are all ſilent:</l>
                                 <l>O who would loſe this benefit?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Come hether ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis like the gift of healing, but diviner;</l>
                                 <l>For that but cures diſeaſes in the body,</l>
                                 <l>This workes a cure on fame, on reputation:</l>
                                 <l>The nobleſt piece of Surgery upon earth.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Shamont;</hi> he minds me not.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>A Brother do't?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Shamont</hi> I ſay. <hi>Gives him a touch with his ſwitch.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ha?</l>
                                 <l>If he be mortall, by this hand he periſhes; <stage>Drawes.</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Unleſſe it be a ſtroake from heaven, he dies for't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why, how now ſir? 'twas I.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>The more's my miſerie.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why, what's the matter prethee?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Can you aske it ſir?</l>
                                 <l>No man elſe ſhould; ſtood forty lives before him</l>
                                 <l>By this I would have op'd my way to him;</l>
                                 <l>It could not be you ſir, excuſe him not,</l>
                                 <l>What ere he be, as y'are deere to honour,</l>
                                 <l>That I may find my peace agen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Forbeare I ſay.</l>
                                 <l>Upon my love to truth, 'twas none but I.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Still miſerable?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Come, come, what ailes you ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Never ſate ſhame cooling ſo long upon me,</l>
                                 <l>Without a ſatisfaction in revenge,</l>
                                 <l>And heaven has made it here a ſin to wiſh it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Harke you ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>O y'ave undone me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Cruelly undone me;</l>
                                 <l>I have loſt my peace, and reputation by you:</l>
                                 <l>Sir pardon me, I can never love you more. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>What language call you this ſirs?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <pb n="154" facs="214"/>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Truth my Lord, I've ſeldome heard a ſtranger.—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent,</speaker>
                                 <l>He is a man of a moſt curious valour,</l>
                                 <l>Wondrous preciſe, and punctuall in that vertue.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>But why to me ſo punctuall? my laſt thought</l>
                                 <l>Was moſt intirely fixt on his advancement:</l>
                                 <l>Why, I came now to put him in poſſeſſion</l>
                                 <l>Of his faire fortunes: what a miſ-conceiver 'tis?</l>
                                 <l>And from a Gentleman of our Chamber meerely,</l>
                                 <l>Made him Vice-Admirall; I was ſetled in't,</l>
                                 <l>I love him next to health: call him Gentlemen;</l>
                                 <l>Why would not you, or you ha' taken as much,</l>
                                 <l>And never murmur'd? <stage>Exit. <hi>1</hi> Gent.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Troath, I thinke we ſhould my Lord,</l>
                                 <l>And there's a fellow walkes about the Court,</l>
                                 <l>Would take a hundred of 'em.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>I hate you all for't,</l>
                                 <l>And rather praiſe his high pitch'd fortitude,</l>
                                 <l>Though in extreames for niceneſſe: now I thinke on't,</l>
                                 <l>I would I had never done't.—Now ſir, where is he?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter <hi>1</hi> Gentleman.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>His ſute is only ſit to be excuſ'd.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>He ſhall not be excus'd, I love him dearelier:</l>
                                 <l>Say we intreat him; goe, he muſt not leave us. <stage>Ex. <hi>2</hi> Gen.</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>So vertue bleſſe me, I nere knew him parraleld;</l>
                                 <l>Why, he's more pretious to me now, then ever.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter <hi>2</hi> Gent. and Shamont.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>With much faire language, w'ave brought him?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Thankes—Where is he?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yonder ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Come forward man.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray pardon me, I'm aſham'd to be ſeene ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Was ever ſuch a touchie man heard of?</l>
                                 <l>Prethee come nearer.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>More into the light?</l>
                                 <l>Put not ſuch crueltie into your requeſts my Lord,</l>
                                 <l>Firſt to diſgrace me publikely, and then draw me</l>
                                 <l>Into mens eyeſight, with the ſhame yet hot</l>
                                 <l>Upon my reputation.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>What diſgrace ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>What?</l>
                                 <l>Such as there can be no forgiveneſſe for,</l>
                                 <l>That I can find in honour.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>That's moſt ſtrange ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yet I have ſeartch'd my boſome to find one,</l>
                                 <l>And wreſled with my inclination,</l>
                                 <l>But 't will not be: would you had kild me ſir,</l>
                                 <l>With what an eaſe had I forgiven you then?</l>
                                 <l>But to endure a ſtroke from any hand</l>
                                 <l>Under a punniſhing Angels, which is juſtice,</l>
                                 <l>Honour diſclame that man, for my part chiefly:</l>
                                 <l>Had it been yet the malice of your ſword.</l>
                                 <l>Though it had cleft me, 'thad been noble to me;</l>
                                 <l>You ſhould have found my thankes paid in a ſmile</l>
                                 <l>If I had fell unworded; but to ſhame me,</l>
                                 <l>With the correction that your horſe ſhould have,</l>
                                 <l>Were you ten thouſand times my royall Lord,</l>
                                 <l>I cannot love you never, nor deſire to ſerve you more.</l>
                                 <l>If your drum call me. I am vowed to valour,</l>
                                 <l>But peace ſhall never know me yours agen,</l>
                                 <l>Becauſe I've loſt mine owne, I ſpeake to dye ſir;</l>
                                 <l>Would you were gratious that way to take off ſhame,</l>
                                 <l>With the ſame ſwiftneſſe as you powre it on:</l>
                                 <l>And ſince it is not in the power of Monarches</l>
                                 <l>To make a Gentleman, which is a ſubſtance</l>
                                 <l>Only begot of merit, they ſhould be carefull</l>
                                 <l>Not to deſtroy the worth of one ſo rare,</l>
                                 <l>Which neither they can make; nor loſt, repaire. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Y'ave ſet a faire light ſir before my judgement,</l>
                                 <l>Which burnes with wondrous clearnes; I acknowledge it,</l>
                                 <l>And your worth with it: but then ſir, my love,</l>
                                 <l>My love — what gone agen?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>And full of ſcorne my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>That language will undoe the man that keeps it,</l>
                                 <l>Who knows no difference twixt contempt and manhood.</l>
                                 <l>Upon your love to goodnes, gentlemen, <stage>Enter a Huntſman</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Let me not loſe him long: how now?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Huntſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>The game's at height my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Confound both, thee and it: hence breake it off;</l>
                                 <l>He hates me brings me newes of any pleaſure:</l>
                                 <l>I felt not ſuch a conflict ſince I cou'd;</l>
                                 <l>Diſtinguiſh betwixt worthineſſe and bloud <stage>Ex.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="act">
                           <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="scene">
                              <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                              <stage>Enter the two brothers, <hi>1</hi> Gentleman, with thoſe that were the Maskers, and the Cupid.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>I I heartily commend your project Gentlemen,</l>
                                 <l>'Twas wiſe and vertuous.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Twas for the ſafety</l>
                                 <l>Of pretious honour ſir, which neere bloud binds us to:</l>
                                 <l>He promis'd the poore eaſie foole there marriage,</l>
                                 <l>There was a good maiden-head loſt i'th' beliefe on't,</l>
                                 <l>Beſhrew her haſty confidence.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>O no more ſir,</l>
                                 <l>You make her weep agen; alas poore Cupid:</l>
                                 <l>Shall ſhe not ſhift her ſelfe?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>O by no meanes ſir:</l>
                                 <l>We dare not have her ſeen yet, all the while</l>
                                 <l>She keepes this ſhape, 'tis but thought device,</l>
                                 <l>And ſhe may follow him ſo without ſuſpition,</l>
                                 <l>To ſee if ſhe can draw all his wilde paſſions,</l>
                                 <l>To one point only, and that's love, the maine point:</l>
                                 <l>So far his highneſſe grants, and gave at firſt,</l>
                                 <l>Large approbation to the quicke conceit,</l>
                                 <l>Which then was quicke indeed.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>You make her bluſh inſooth.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>I feare 'tis more the flagg of ſhame, then grace ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>They both give but one kind of colour ſir:</l>
                                 <l>If it be baſhfulneſſe in that kind taken,</l>
                                 <l>It is the ſame with grace; and there ſhe weepes agen.</l>
                                 <l>In truth y'are too hard, much, much too bitter ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Unleſſe you meane to have her weepe her eyes out,</l>
                                 <l>To play a Cupid truly.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Come, ha' done then:</l>
                                 <l>We ſhould all feare to ſin firſt; for 'tis certaine,</l>
                                 <l>When 'tis once lodg'd, though entertain'd in mirth,</l>
                                 <l>It muſt be wept out, if it ere come forth.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now 'tis ſo well, I'le leave you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Faithfully welcome ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Go Cupid to your charge; hee's your owne now;</l>
                                 <l>If he want love, none will be blam'd but you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                                 <l>The ſtrangeſt marriage, and unfortunat'ſt Bride</l>
                                 <l>That ever humane memory contain'd;</l>
                                 <l>I cannot be my ſelfe for't. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh Gentlemen? <stage>Enter the Clowne.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>How now ſir, what's the matter?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>His melancholly paſſion is halfe ſpent already,</l>
                                 <l>Then comes his angry fit at the very taile on't,</l>
                                 <l>Then comes in my pain gentlemen; 'has beate me e'ne to a Cullis.</l>
                                 <pb n="155" facs="214"/>
                                 <l>I am nothing, right worſhipfull, but very pap,</l>
                                 <l>And jelly: I have no bones, my body's all one buſines,</l>
                                 <l>They talk of ribs, &amp; chines moſt freely abroad i'th' world,</l>
                                 <l>Why, I have no ſuch thing; who ever lives to ſee me dead</l>
                                 <l>Gentlemen, ſhall find me all mummie good to fill galipots</l>
                                 <l>And long dildo glaſſes: I ſhall not have a bone to throw</l>
                                 <l>At a dog.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                                 <l>Alas poore vaſſall, how he goes?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>O Gentlemen,</l>
                                 <l>I am unjoynted, do but thinke o' that:</l>
                                 <l>My breaſt is beat into my mawe, that what I eate,</l>
                                 <l>I am faine to take't in all at mouth with ſpoones;</l>
                                 <l>A lamentable hearing; and 'tis well knowne, my belly</l>
                                 <l>Is driven into my backe.</l>
                                 <l>I earn'd foure Crowns a month, moſt dearely Gentlemen,</l>
                                 <l>And one he muſt have when the fit's upon him,</l>
                                 <l>The privy purſe allowes it, and 'tis thriftineſſe,</l>
                                 <l>He would breake elſe ſome fourty pounds in caſements,</l>
                                 <l>And in five hundred yeares undo the Kingdome:</l>
                                 <l>I have caſt it up to a quarrell.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>There's a fellow kickt about court, I would</l>
                                 <l>He had his place brother, but for one fit of his indignation.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>And ſuddenly I have thought upon a means for't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>I Prethee how?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis but preferring Brother</l>
                                 <l>This ſtockfiſh to his ſervice, with a letter</l>
                                 <l>Of commendations, the ſame way he wiſhes it,</l>
                                 <l>And then you win his heart: for o' my knowledge</l>
                                 <l>He has laied waite this halfe yeare for a fellow</l>
                                 <l>That will be beaten; and with a ſafe conſcience</l>
                                 <l>We may commend the carriage of this man in't;</l>
                                 <l>Now ſervants he has kept, luſty tall feeders,</l>
                                 <l>But they have beate him, and turn'd themſelves away:</l>
                                 <l>Now one that would endure, is like to ſtay,</l>
                                 <l>And get good wages of him; and the ſervice too</l>
                                 <l>Is ten times milder Brother, I would not wiſh it elſe.</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> ſee the fellow has a ſore cruſh'd body,</l>
                                 <l>And the more need he has to be kickt at eaſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>I</hi> ſweet Gentlemen, a kick of eaſe, ſend me to ſuch a Maſter.</p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>No more <hi>I</hi> ſay, we have one for thee, a ſoft footed Maſter,</l>
                                 <l>One that weares wooll in's toes.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                                 <l>O Gentlemen, ſoft garments may you weare,</l>
                                 <l>Soft skins may you wed,</l>
                                 <l>But as plump as pillowes, both for white and red.</l>
                                 <l>And now will <hi>I</hi> reveale a ſecret to you,</l>
                                 <l>Since you provide for my poore fleſh ſo tenderly,</l>
                                 <l>'Has hir'd meere Rogues, out of his Chamber window,</l>
                                 <l>To beate the Souldier, Mounſier <hi>Shamonts</hi> Brother.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>That nothing concernes us ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>For no cauſe Gentlemen,</l>
                                 <l>Unleſſe it be for wearing ſhoulder points,</l>
                                 <l>With longer taggs then his.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Is not that ſomewhat?</l>
                                 <l>Billakin ſir, the difference of long taggs,</l>
                                 <l>Has coſt many a mans life, and advanc'd other ſome,</l>
                                 <l>Come follow me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>See what a gull am <hi>I:</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Oh every man in his profeſſion;</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> know a thumpe now, as juditiouſly,</l>
                                 <l>As the proudeſt he that walkes, I'le except none;</l>
                                 <l>Come to a tagge, how ſhort I fall? I'm gone. <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Lapet.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> have been ruminating with my ſelfe,</l>
                                 <l>What honour a man loſes by a kicke:</l>
                                 <l>Why, what's a kicke? the fury of a foote,</l>
                                 <l>Whoſe indignation commonly is ſtampt</l>
                                 <l>Upon the hinder quarter of a man;</l>
                                 <l>Which is a place very unfit for honour,</l>
                                 <l>The world will confeſſe ſo much:</l>
                                 <l>Then what diſgrace I pray, does that part ſuffer</l>
                                 <l>Where honour never comes, I'd faine know that?</l>
                                 <l>This being well forc'd, and urg'd, may have the power</l>
                                 <l>To move moſt Gallants to take kickes in time,</l>
                                 <l>And ſpurne out the duelloes out o'th' kingdome,</l>
                                 <l>For they that ſtand upon their honour moſt,</l>
                                 <l>When they conceive there is no honour loſt,</l>
                                 <l>As by a table that I have invented</l>
                                 <l>For that purpoſe alone, ſhall appeare plainly,</l>
                                 <l>Which ſhewes the vanity of all blowes at large,</l>
                                 <l>And with what eaſe they may be tooke of all ſides,</l>
                                 <l>Numbring but twice one the Letters Patience</l>
                                 <l>From <hi>C.P.</hi> to <hi>E.</hi> I doubt not but in ſmall time</l>
                                 <l>To ſee a diſſolution of all bloudſhed,</l>
                                 <l>If the Reform'd Kick do but once get up:</l>
                                 <l>For what a lamentable folly 'tis,</l>
                                 <l>If we obſerv't, for every little juſtle,</l>
                                 <l>Which is but the ninth part of a ſound thump,</l>
                                 <l>In our meeke computation, we muſt fight forſooth, yes,</l>
                                 <l>If kill, I'm hang'; if I be kil'd my ſelfe,</l>
                                 <l>I dye for't alſo: is not this trim wiſdome?</l>
                                 <l>Now for the Con, a man may be well beaten,</l>
                                 <l>Yet paſſe away his foureſcore yeares ſmooth after:</l>
                                 <l>I had a father did it, and to my power</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> will not be behind him. <stage>Enter Shamont.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>O well met.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now a fine punch or two, I looke for't duly.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>I've been to ſeeke you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let me know your lodging ſir,</l>
                                 <l>I'le come to you once a day, and uſe your pleaſure ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>I'm made the fitteſt man for thy Society:</l>
                                 <l>I'le live and dye with thee: come ſhew me a Chamber;</l>
                                 <l>There is no houſe but thine, but only thine,</l>
                                 <l>That's fit to cover me: I've tooke a blow ſirrah.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> would you had indeed: why, you may ſee ſir;</l>
                                 <l>You'l all come to't in time, when my booke's out.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Since <hi>I</hi> did ſee thee laſt, I've tooke a blow.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <p>Pha ſir that's nothing; <hi>I</hi> ha' tooke fourty ſince.</p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>What? and <hi>I</hi> charg'd thee thou ſhouldſt not?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> ſir, you might charge your pleaſure,</l>
                                 <l>But they would giv't me, whether <hi>I</hi> would or no.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh <hi>I</hi> walke without my peace, I've no companion now;</l>
                                 <l>Prethee reſolve me, for <hi>I</hi> cannot aske</l>
                                 <l>A man more beaten to experience,</l>
                                 <l>Then thou art in this kind, what manner of blow</l>
                                 <l>Is held the moſt diſgracefull, or diſtaſtefull?</l>
                                 <l>For thou doſt only cenſure 'em by the hurt,</l>
                                 <l>Not by the ſhame they do thee: yet having felt</l>
                                 <l>Abuſes of all kindes, thou mayſt deliver,</l>
                                 <l>Though't be by chance, the moſt injurious one.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>You put me to't ſir; but to tell you truth,</l>
                                 <l>Th'are all as one with me, little exception.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>That little may do much, let's have it from you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>With all the ſpeed <hi>I</hi> may: firſt then, and formoſt,</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> hold ſo reverently of the Baſtinado ſir,</l>
                                 <l>That if it were the deareſt friend i'th' world,</l>
                                 <l>I'd put it into his hand.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Go too, I'le paſſe that then.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Y'are the more happy ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Would <hi>I</hi> were paſt it too:</l>
                                 <l>But being accuſtom'd to't, It is the better carried.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Will you forward?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Then there's your ſowce, your wherrit, and your dowſt,</l>
                                 <pb n="156" facs="215"/>
                                 <l>Tuggs on the haire, your bob o'th' lips, a whelpe on't,</l>
                                 <l>I nere could find much difference: Now your thumpe,</l>
                                 <l>A thing deriv'd firſt from your Hemp-beaters,</l>
                                 <l>Takes a mans wind away, moſt ſpitefully:</l>
                                 <l>There's nothing that deſtroyes a Collicke like it,</l>
                                 <l>For't leaves no wind i'th' body.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>On ſir, on.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray give me leave, I'm out of breath with thinking ont.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>This is far off yet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>For the twinge byth' noſe,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis certainly unſightly, ſo my tables ſaies,</l>
                                 <l>But helpes againſt the head-ache, woundrous ſtrangely.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Is't poſſible?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>O your cruſh'd noſtrils ſlakes your opilation</l>
                                 <l>And makes your pent powers fluſh to wholſome ſneezes.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>I never thought there had been halfe that vertue</l>
                                 <l>In a wrung noſe before.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>O plenitude ſir:</l>
                                 <l>Now come we lower, to our moderne kick,</l>
                                 <l>Which has been mightily in uſe of late,</l>
                                 <l>Since our young men dranke Coltsfoot: and I grant you,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis a moſt ſcornefull wrong, cauſe the foot plaies it;</l>
                                 <l>But marke agen, how we that take't, requite it</l>
                                 <l>With the like ſcorne, for we receive it backeward;</l>
                                 <l>And can there be a worſe diſgrace retorted?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>And is this all?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>All but a lugg byth' eare,</l>
                                 <l>Or ſuch a trifle.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Happy ſufferer,</l>
                                 <l>All this is nothing to the wrong I beare:</l>
                                 <l>I ſee the worſt diſgrace, thou never felt'ſt yet;</l>
                                 <l>It is ſo far from thee, thou canſt not thinke on't;</l>
                                 <l>Nor dare I let thee know, it is ſo abject.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>I would you would though, that I might prepare for't,</l>
                                 <l>For I ſhall ha't at one time or another:</l>
                                 <l>If't be a thwacke, I make account of that;</l>
                                 <l>There's no new faſhion'd ſwappe that ere came up yet,</l>
                                 <l>But I've the firſt on 'em, I thanke 'em for't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter the Lady, and Servants.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>Haſt thou enquir'd?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>But Can heare nothing Madam.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>If there be but ſo much ſubſtance in thee</l>
                                 <l>To make a ſhelter for a man diſgrac'd,</l>
                                 <l>Hide my departure from that glorious woman</l>
                                 <l>That comes with all perfection about her:</l>
                                 <l>So noble, that I dare not be ſeene of her,</l>
                                 <l>Since ſhame tooke hold of me: upon thy life</l>
                                 <l>No mention of me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>I'le cut out my tongue firſt,</l>
                                 <l>Before I'le looſe my life, there's more belongs to't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>See there's a Gentleman, enquire of him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>For Mounſier <hi>Shamont</hi> Madam?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>For whom elſe ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why, this fellow dares not ſee him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Shamont</hi> Madam?</l>
                                 <l>His very name's worſe then a feavour to him,</l>
                                 <l>And when he cries, there's nothing ſtils him ſooner;</l>
                                 <l>Madam, your Page of thirteene is to hard for him,</l>
                                 <l>'Twas trid i'th' wood-yard.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>Alas poore grieved Merit!</l>
                                 <l>What is become of him? if he one faile,</l>
                                 <l>Vertue ſhall find ſmall friendſhip: farewell then</l>
                                 <l>To Ladies worths, for any hope in men,</l>
                                 <l>He lov'd for goodneſſe, not for Wealth, or luſt,</l>
                                 <l>After the worlds foule dotage, he nere courted</l>
                                 <l>The body but the beauty of the mind,</l>
                                 <l>A thing which common courtſhip never thinkes on:</l>
                                 <l>All his affections were ſo ſweet and faire,</l>
                                 <l>There is no hope for fame if he diſpaire. <stage>Ex. Lad. and Ser.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter the Clowne. He kicks Lapet.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Good morrow to you agen moſt heartily ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Crie you mercy I heard you not, I was ſomewhat buſie.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>He takes it as familiarly, as an Ave,</l>
                                 <l>Or pretious ſalutation: I was ſicke till I had one,</l>
                                 <l>Becauſe I am ſo us'd to't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How ever you deſerve, your friends &amp; mine, here</l>
                                 <l>Give you large commendations i' this Letter,</l>
                                 <l>They ſay you will endure well.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>I'd be loath</l>
                                 <l>To prove 'em liers: I've endur'd as much</l>
                                 <l>As mortall pen and Inke can ſet me downe for.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Say you me ſo?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>I know and feele it ſo ſir,</l>
                                 <l>I have it under black and white already;</l>
                                 <l>I need no pen to paint me out.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>He fits me,</l>
                                 <l>And hits my wiſhes pat, pat: I was nere</l>
                                 <l>In poſſibility to be better man'd,</l>
                                 <l>For he's halfe lam'd already, I ſee't plaine,</l>
                                 <l>But take no notice on't, for feare I make</l>
                                 <l>The Raſcall proud, and deare, to advance his wages;</l>
                                 <l>Firſt let me grow into particulars with you;</l>
                                 <l>What have you indur'd of worth? let me heare.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Marry ſir, I'm almoſt beaten blind.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>That's pretty well for a begining,</l>
                                 <l>But many a milhorſe has endur'd as much.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Shame o' the millers heart for his unkindneſſe then.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Well ſir, what then?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <p>I've been twice throwne down ſtaires, juſt before ſupper.</p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Puh, ſo have I, that's nothing.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> but ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Was yours pray before ſupper?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>There thou poſeſt me.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>I marry, that's it, 't'ad been leſſe griefe to me,</l>
                                 <l>Had <hi>I</hi> but fil'd my bellie, and then tumbled,</l>
                                 <l>But to be flung downe faſting, there's the dolour.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>It would have griev'd me, that indeed: proceed ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> have been pluck'd &amp; tugg'd bith' haire o'th' head</l>
                                 <l>About a gallerie, halfe an Acre long.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes, that's a good one, <hi>I</hi> muſt needs confeſſe,</l>
                                 <l>A principall good one that, an abſolute good one,</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> have bin trod upon, and ſpurn'd about,</l>
                                 <l>But never tugg'd byth' haire, <hi>I</hi> thanke my fates.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>O 'tis a ſpitefull paine.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Peace, never ſpeake on't,</l>
                                 <l>For putting men in mind on't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>To conclude,</l>
                                 <l>I'm burſten ſir: my belly will hold no meat.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>No? that makes amends for all.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Unleſſe't be puddings,</l>
                                 <l>Or ſuch faſt food, any looſe thing beguiles me, I'm nere the better for't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Sheepheads will ſtay with thee?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes ſir, or Chaldrons.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Very well ſir:</l>
                                 <l>Any your burſten fellowes muſt take heed of ſurfets:</l>
                                 <l>Strange things it ſeemes, you have endur'd;</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Too true ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>But now the queſtion is, what you will endure</l>
                                 <l>Hereafter in my ſervice?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Any thing</l>
                                 <l>That ſhall be reaſon ſir, for I'm but froath;</l>
                                 <pb n="157" facs="215"/>
                                 <l>Much like a thing new calv'd, or come more nearer ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Y'ave ſeen a Cluſter of Frog-ſpawns in <hi>April,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>E'ne ſuch a ſtarche am I, as weak and tender</l>
                                 <l>As a green woman yet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now I know this,</l>
                                 <l>I will be very gently angry with thee,</l>
                                 <l>And kick thee carefully.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>O I ſweet ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Peace, when thou art offer'd well, leſt I begin now.</l>
                                 <l>Your friends and mine have writ here for your truth,</l>
                                 <l>They'll paſſe their words themſelves, and I muſt meet 'em.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Then have you all: <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>As for my honeſty there is no feare of that,</l>
                                 <l>For I have ne're a whole bone about me, <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Muſick, Enter the paſſionate Couſen, rudely, and careleſly Apparell'd, unbrac'd, and untruſt: The Cupid following.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
                                 <l>Think upon love, which makes all creatures handſome,</l>
                                 <l>Seemly for ey-ſight; goe not ſo diſfuſedly,</l>
                                 <l>There are great Ladies purpoſe ſir to viſit you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Grand plagues, ſhut in my caſements, that the breaths</l>
                                 <l>Of their Coach-mares reek not into my Noſtrills;</l>
                                 <l>Thoſe beaſts are but a kinde of Bawdy fore-runners.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
                                 <l>It is not well with you,</l>
                                 <l>When you ſpeak ill of faire Ladies.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Faire miſchiefs, give me a neſt of Owles, and take 'em;</l>
                                 <l>Happy is he ſay I, whoſe window opens</l>
                                 <l>To a browne Bakers chimney, he ſhall be ſure there</l>
                                 <l>To heare the Bird ſometimes after twi-light:</l>
                                 <l>What a fine thing 'tis me thinks to have our garments</l>
                                 <l>Sit looſe upon us thus, thus careleſlely,</l>
                                 <l>It is more manly, and more mortifying;</l>
                                 <l>For w'are ſo much the readier for our ſhrouds:</l>
                                 <l>For how ridiculous wer't, to have death come,</l>
                                 <l>And take a fellow pinn'd up like a Miſtris?</l>
                                 <l>About his neck a Ruffe, like a pincht Lanthorne,</l>
                                 <l>Which Schoole-boyes make in winter; and his dublet</l>
                                 <l>So cloſe and pent, as if he fear'd one priſon</l>
                                 <l>Would not be ſtrong enough, to keep his ſoule in;</l>
                                 <l>But's Tailor makes another:</l>
                                 <l>And truſt me, for I know't when I lov'd <hi>Cupid,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>He does endure much paine, for the poore praiſe</l>
                                 <l>Of a neat ſitting ſuit.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
                                 <l>One may be handſome ſir,</l>
                                 <l>And yet not pain'd, nor proud.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>There you lie <hi>Cupid,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>As bad as <hi>Mercurie:</hi> there is no handſomeneſſe,</l>
                                 <l>But has a waſh of Pride and Luxury,</l>
                                 <l>And you goe there too <hi>Cupid.</hi> Away diſſembler,</l>
                                 <l>Thou tak'ſt the deeds part which befooles us all;</l>
                                 <l>Thy Arrow heads ſhoot out ſinners: hence away,</l>
                                 <l>And after thee Ile ſend a powerfull charme,</l>
                                 <l>Shall baniſh thee for ever.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
                                 <l>Never, never,</l>
                                 <l>I am too ſure thine owne. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                                 <body>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <stage>Sings.</stage>
                                       <l>HEnce all you vaine Delights,</l>
                                       <l>As ſhort as are the nights,</l>
                                       <l>Wherein you ſpend your folly,</l>
                                       <l>Ther's nought in this life ſweet,</l>
                                       <l>If man were wiſe to ſee't,</l>
                                       <l>But onely Melancholy,</l>
                                       <l>O ſweeteſt melancholy.</l>
                                       <l>Welcome folded Armes, and fixed eyes,</l>
                                       <l>A ſigh that piercing mortifies,</l>
                                       <l>A look that's faſtned to the ground,</l>
                                       <l>A tongue chain'd up without a ſound.</l>
                                       <l>Fountaine heads, and pathleſſe Groves,</l>
                                       <l>Places which pale paſſion loves:</l>
                                       <l>Moon-light walkes, when all the fowles</l>
                                       <l>Are warmly hous'd, ſave Bats and Owles;</l>
                                       <l>A mid-night Bell, a parting groane,</l>
                                       <l>Theſe are the ſounds we feed upon;</l>
                                       <l>Then ſtretch our bones in a ſtill gloomy valley,</l>
                                       <l>Nothing's ſo daintie ſweet as lovely melancholy.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                              <stage>Enter at another doore Lapet, The Cupids Brothers watching his comming.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Br.</speaker>
                                 <l>So, ſo, the Wood-cock's gin'd;</l>
                                 <l>Keep this doore faſt brother.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile warrant this.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile goe incenſe him inſtantly;</l>
                                 <l>I know the way to't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Wil't not be too ſoon think you,</l>
                                 <l>And make two fits break into one?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pah, no, no; The taile of his melancho</l>
                                 <l>Is alwayes the head of his anger, and followes as cloſe,</l>
                                 <l>As the Report followes the powder.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>This is the appoynted place, and the houre ſtruck,</l>
                                 <l>If I can get ſecurity for's truth,</l>
                                 <l>Ile never minde his honeſty: poore worme,</l>
                                 <l>I durſt lay him by my wife, which is a benefit</l>
                                 <l>Which many maſters ha' not: I ſhall ha' no maid</l>
                                 <l>Now got with childe, but what I get my ſelfe,</l>
                                 <l>And that's no ſmall felicity: In moſt places</l>
                                 <l>Th'are got by th' men, and put upon the Maſters:</l>
                                 <l>Nor ſhall I be reſiſted when I ſtrike,</l>
                                 <l>For he can hardly ſtand; theſe are great bleſſings.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I want my food, deliver me a varlet. <stage>within.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How now: from whence comes that?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I am allow'd a Carcaſſe to inſult on;</l>
                                 <l>Where's the villaine?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>He meanes not me I hope.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>My maintenance raſcals; my Bulk, my exhibition.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Bleſſe us all,</l>
                                 <l>What names' are theſe? would I were gone agen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>The paſſionate man enters in furie, with a Truncheon,</stage>
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                                 <body>
                                    <sp>
                                       <stage>He Sings:</stage>
                                       <l>A Curſe upon thee for a ſlave,</l>
                                       <l>Art thou here, and heard'ſt me rave?</l>
                                       <l>Fly not ſparkles from mine eye,</l>
                                       <l>To ſhew my indignation nye?</l>
                                       <l>Am I not all foame, and fire?</l>
                                       <l>With voice as hoarſe, as a Towne-crier?</l>
                                       <l>How my back opes and ſhuts together,</l>
                                       <l>VVith furie, as old mens with weather?</l>
                                       <l>Could'ſt thou not heare my teeth knaſh hither?</l>
                                    </sp>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>No truely ſir, <hi>I</hi> thought t'had been a Squirrell,</l>
                                 <l>Shaving a Hazle-nut.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Death, hell, fiends, and darkneſſe,</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> will thraſh thy mangy carcaſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>O ſweet ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <pb n="158" facs="216"/>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>There cannot be too many Tortures,</l>
                                 <l>Spent upon thoſe louzie Quarters.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Hold, oh. <stage>Falls down for dead.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Thy bones ſhall rue, thy bones ſhall rue,</l>
                                 <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                                    <body>
                                       <l>Thou nafly, ſcurvie, mongrill Toad, <stage>Sings again.</stage>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>Miſchief on thee;</l>
                                       <l>Light upon thee,</l>
                                       <l>All the plagues</l>
                                       <l>That can confound thee</l>
                                       <l>Or did ever raigne abroad:</l>
                                       <l>Better a thouſand lives it coſt,</l>
                                       <l>Then have brave Anger ſpilt or loſt. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                       </l>
                                    </body>
                                 </floatingText>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>May I open mine eyes yet, and ſafely peep?</l>
                                 <l>Ile trie a groane firſt—oh—Nay then hee's gone.</l>
                                 <l>There was no other policy but to dye,</l>
                                 <l>He would ha' made me elſe. Ribs are you ſore?</l>
                                 <l>I was ne're beaten to a tune before.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter the two Brothers.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Lapet.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Agen? <stage>Falls againe.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Look, look, hee's flat agen,</l>
                                 <l>And ſtretched out like a Coarſe a handfull longer</l>
                                 <l>Then he walks truſt me brother. Why <hi>Lapet.</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>I hold my life we ſhall not get him ſpeak now.</l>
                                 <l>Monſieur <hi>Lapet;</hi> it muſt be a privie token,</l>
                                 <l>If any thing fetch him, hee's ſo far gone.</l>
                                 <l>We come to paſſe our words for your mans truth.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>O gentlemen y'are welcom: I have been thraſht i'faith.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>How? thraſht ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap</speaker>
                                 <l>Never was Shrove-tueſday Bird</l>
                                 <l>So cudgel'd gentlemen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray how? by whom ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay that I know not.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Not who did this wrong?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Only a thing came like a walking ſong.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>What beaten with a Song?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Never more tightly, gentlemen:</l>
                                 <l>Such crotchets happen now and then, methinks,</l>
                                 <l>He that endures well, of all waters drinks. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="act">
                           <head>Actus Quartus.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="scene">
                              <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                              <stage>Enter Shamonts Brother, the Souldier, and <hi>1.</hi> Gent.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>YEs, yes, this was a Madman, ſir, with you,</l>
                                 <l>A paſſionate Madman.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Who would ha' lookt for this ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>And muſt be priviledg'd? a pox priviledge him:</l>
                                 <l>I was never ſo dry beaten ſince I was borne,</l>
                                 <l>And by a litter of rogues, meer rogues, the whole twenty</l>
                                 <l>Had not above nine elbowes amongſt 'em all too:</l>
                                 <l>And the moſt part of thoſe left-handed raſcalls,</l>
                                 <l>The very vomit, Sir, of hoſpitalls,</l>
                                 <l>Bridewells, and Spittle-houſes; ſuch naſty ſmellers,</l>
                                 <l>That if they'd been unfurniſh'd of Club-Trunchions,</l>
                                 <l>They might have cudgel'd me with their very ſtinks,</l>
                                 <l>It was ſo ſtrong, and ſturdy: and ſhall this,</l>
                                 <l>This filthy injurie, be ſet off with madneſſe?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay take your owne blouds councel ſir, hereafter,</l>
                                 <l>Ile deale no further in't: if you remember,</l>
                                 <l>It was not come to blowes, when I advis'd you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>No, but I ever ſaid, 'twould come to ſomething,</l>
                                 <l>And 'tis upon me, thank him: were he kin</l>
                                 <l>To all the mighty Emperours upon earth,</l>
                                 <l>He has not now in life three houres to reckon;</l>
                                 <l>I watch but a free time.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Shamont.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <p>Your noble brother, ſir, Ile leave you now. <stage>Ex.</stage>
                                 </p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Souldier I would I could perſwade my thoughts</l>
                                 <l>From thinking thee a brother, as I can</l>
                                 <l>My tongue from naming on't: thou haſt no friend here,</l>
                                 <l>But fortune and thy owne ſtrength, truſt to them.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>How? what's the incitement, ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Treacherie to vertue;</l>
                                 <l>Thy treacherie, thy faithleſſe circumvention:</l>
                                 <l>Has Honour ſo few daughters, never fewer,</l>
                                 <l>And muſt thou aime thy treacherie at the beſt?</l>
                                 <l>The very front of vertue? that bleſt Lady? the Dukes ſiſter?</l>
                                 <l>Created more for admirations cauſe,</l>
                                 <l>Then for loves ends; whoſe excellency ſparkles</l>
                                 <l>More in divinity, then mortall beauty;</l>
                                 <l>And as much difference 'twixt her minde and bodie,</l>
                                 <l>As 'twixt this earths poore center and the Sun:</l>
                                 <l>And couldſt thou be ſo injurious to faire goodneſſe,</l>
                                 <l>Once to attempt to court her down to frailty?</l>
                                 <l>Or put her but in minde that there is weakneſſe,</l>
                                 <l>Sin, and deſire, which ſhe ſhould never heare of?</l>
                                 <l>Wretch, thou'ſt committed worſe then Sacrilege,</l>
                                 <l>In the attempting on't, and oughtſt to dye for't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>I rather ought to doe my beſt, to live, ſir;</l>
                                 <l>Provoke me not; for I've a wrong ſits on me,</l>
                                 <l>That makes me apt for miſchiefe; I ſhall loſe</l>
                                 <l>All reſpects ſuddainly of friendſhip, Brother-hood,</l>
                                 <l>Or any ſound that way.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>But 'ware me moſt;</l>
                                 <l>For I come with a two-edg'd injurie;</l>
                                 <l>Both my diſgrace, and thy apparent falſhood,</l>
                                 <l>Which muſt be dangerous.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>I courted her, ſir:</l>
                                 <l>Love ſtarve me with delayes when I confeſſe it not.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>There's nothing then but death</l>
                                 <l>Can be a pennance fit for that confeſſion.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>But farre from any vitious taint.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>O ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Vice is a mighty ſtranger growne to courtſhip.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay then the fury of my wrong light on thee.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter <hi>1.</hi> Gentleman, and others.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Forbeare, the Duke's at hand.</l>
                                 <l>Here, hard at hand, upon my reputation.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                                 <l>I muſt doe ſomething now. <stage>Ex. Sold.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile follow you cloſe ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>We muſt entreat you muſt not; for the Duke</l>
                                 <l>Deſires ſome conference with you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let me goe,</l>
                                 <l>As y'are gentlemen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Faith we dare not ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Dare ye be falſe to honour, and yet dare not</l>
                                 <l>Doe a man juſtice? give me leave—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Good ſweet ſir.</l>
                                 <l>H'as ſent twice for you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Is this brave, or manly?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>I prethee be conform'd.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Death— <stage>Enter Duke.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Peace, hee's come introth.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh have you betraid me to my ſhame afreſh?</l>
                                 <l>How am I bound to loath you?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Shamont,</hi> welcome,</l>
                                 <l>I ſent twice.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>But my Lord, he never heard on't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <pb n="159" facs="216"/>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray pardon him, for his falſeneſſe, I did Sir,</l>
                                 <l>Both times; I'de rather be found rude then faithleſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du</speaker>
                                 <l>I love that bluntneſſe darely: ha's no vice,</l>
                                 <l>But is more manly then ſome others vertue,</l>
                                 <l>That lets it out onely for ſhew or profit.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Wil't pleaſe you quit me ſir, I've urgent buſines?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Come, you'r ſo haſty now: I ſent for you</l>
                                 <l>To a better end.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>And if it be an end,</l>
                                 <l>Better or worſe, I thank your goodneſſe for't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>I've ever kept that bounty in condition,</l>
                                 <l>And thankfulneſſe in bloud, which well becomes</l>
                                 <l>Both Prince and Subject, that where any wrong</l>
                                 <l>Beares my impreſſion, or the haſty figure</l>
                                 <l>Of my repented anger, I'me a Law</l>
                                 <l>Ev'n to my ſelfe, and doome my ſelfe moſt ſtrictly</l>
                                 <l>To Juſtice, and a noble ſatisfaction:</l>
                                 <l>So that, what you in tenderneſſe of honour,</l>
                                 <l>Conceive to be loſſe to you, which is nothing</l>
                                 <l>But curious opinion, Ile reſtore agen,</l>
                                 <l>Although <hi>I</hi> give you the beſt part of <hi>Genoa,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>And take to boot but thanks for your amends.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>O miſerable ſatisfaction,</l>
                                 <l>Ten times more wretched then the wrong it ſelfe;</l>
                                 <l>Never was ill better made good with worſe:</l>
                                 <l>Shall it be ſaid that my poſterity</l>
                                 <l>Shall live the ſole heires of their fathers ſhame?</l>
                                 <l>And raiſe their wealth and glorie from my ſtripes?</l>
                                 <l>You have provided nobly bounteous ſir,</l>
                                 <l>For my diſgrace, to make it live for ever,</l>
                                 <l>Out-laſting Braſſe or Marble:</l>
                                 <l>This is my feares conſtruction, and a deep one,</l>
                                 <l>Which neither argument nor time can alter:</l>
                                 <l>Yet <hi>I</hi> durſt ſweare, I wrong your goodneſſe in't ſir,</l>
                                 <l>And the moſt faire intent on't, which I reverence</l>
                                 <l>With admiration, that in you a Prince,</l>
                                 <l>Should be ſo ſweet and temperate a condition,</l>
                                 <l>To offer to reſtore where you may ruine,</l>
                                 <l>And do't with juſtice, and in me a ſervant,</l>
                                 <l>So harſh a diſpoſition, that I cannot</l>
                                 <l>Forgive where I ſhould honor, and am bound to't.</l>
                                 <l>But <hi>I</hi> have ever had that curioſity</l>
                                 <l>In bloud, and tenderneſs of reputation,</l>
                                 <l>Such an antipathy againſt a blow,</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> cannot ſpeak the reſt: Good ſir diſcharge me,</l>
                                 <l>It is not fit that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſerve you more,</l>
                                 <l>Nor come ſo neare you; I'me made now for privacy,</l>
                                 <l>And a retir'd condition, that's my ſuit,</l>
                                 <l>To part from Court for ever, my laſt ſuit.</l>
                                 <l>And as you profeſse bounty, grant me that, Sir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>I would deny thee nothing.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Health reward you; ſir. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>He's gone agen already, and takes hold</l>
                                 <l>Of any opportunity, not riches</l>
                                 <l>Can purchaſe him, nor honours, peaceably,</l>
                                 <l>And force were brutiſh: what a great worth's gone with him,</l>
                                 <l>And but a gentleman? well, for his ſake,</l>
                                 <l>Ile nere offend more thoſe <hi>I</hi> cannot make:</l>
                                 <l>They were his words, and ſhall be deare to memorie.</l>
                                 <l>Say <hi>I</hi> deſire to ſee him once agen;</l>
                                 <l>Yet ſtay, hee's ſo well forward of his peace,</l>
                                 <l>'Twere pitty to diſturbe him: he would groane</l>
                                 <l>Like a ſoule fetch'd agen; and that were injurie,</l>
                                 <l>And I've wrong'd his degree too much already.</l>
                                 <l>Call forth the gentlemen of our chamber inſtantly.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Serv.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> ſhall my Lord. <stage>Within.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>I may forget agen,</l>
                                 <l>And therefore will prevent: The ſtrain of this</l>
                                 <l>Troubles me ſo, one would not hazard more:</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter <hi>1.</hi> Gent. and divers others.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Your will my Lord?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes; I diſcharge you all.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>My Lord—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Your places ſhall be otherwiſe diſpos'd of.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>4</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Reply not, I diſmiſſe you all:</l>
                                 <l>Y'are gentlemen, your worths will find you fortunes;</l>
                                 <l>Nor ſhall your farewell taxe me of ingratitude,</l>
                                 <l>Ile give you all noble remembrances,</l>
                                 <l>As teſtimonies 'gainſt reproach and malice,</l>
                                 <l>That you departed lov'd.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>This is moſt ſtrange, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>But how is your grace furniſh'd, theſe diſmis'd?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Seek me out Grooms.</l>
                                 <l>Men more inſenſible of reputation,</l>
                                 <l>Leſſe curious and preciſe in termes of honour,</l>
                                 <l>That if my anger chance let fall a ſtroak,</l>
                                 <l>As we are all ſubject to impetuous paſſions,</l>
                                 <l>Yet it may paſſe unmurmur'd, undiſputed,</l>
                                 <l>And not with braver fury proſecuted. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>It ſhal be done, my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Know you the cauſe ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Not I kinde gentlemen, but by conjectures,</l>
                                 <l>And ſo much ſhall be yours, when you pleaſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>4</speaker>
                                 <l>Thanks ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>VVe ſhall ith' mean time think our ſelves guilty</l>
                                 <l>Of ſome foule fault, through ignorance committed.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>No, 'tis not that, nor that way.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>4</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>For my part.</l>
                                 <l>I ſhall be diſ-inherited, I knew ſo much.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why ſir, for what?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>4</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>My ſire's of a ſtrange humour,</l>
                                 <l>Hee'll forme faults for me, and then ſweare 'em mine,</l>
                                 <l>And commonly the firſt begins with leacherie.</l>
                                 <l>He knowes his owne youthes treſpaſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Before you goe,</l>
                                 <l>Ile come and take my leave, and tell you all ſirs.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>3</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Thou wer't ever juſt and kinde. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>That's my poore vertue ſir,</l>
                                 <l>And parcell valiant; but it's hard to be perfect:</l>
                                 <l>The chuſing of theſe fellowes now will puzzle me,</l>
                                 <l>Horribly puzzle me; and there's no judgement,</l>
                                 <l>Goes true upon mans out-ſide, there's the miſchiefe:</l>
                                 <l>He muſt be touch'd, and try'd, for gold or droſſe;</l>
                                 <l>There is no other way for't, and that's dangerous too;</l>
                                 <l>But ſince I'me put in truſt, I will attempt it:</l>
                                 <l>The Duke ſhal keep one daring man about him: <stage>Enter a Gallant</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Soft, who comes here? a pretty bravery this:</l>
                                 <l>Every one goes ſo like a gentleman,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis hard to finde a difference, but byth' touch.</l>
                                 <l>Ile trie your mettall ſure.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why what doe you meane ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay, and you underſtand it not, I doe not.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes, would you ſhould well know,</l>
                                 <l>I underſtand it for a box o'th' eare Sir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>And o' my troth, that's all I gave it for.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Twere beſt it be ſo.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>This is a brave Coward,</l>
                                 <l>A jolly threatning Coward; he ſhall be Captaine:</l>
                                 <l>Sir, let me meet you an houre hence i'th' Lobby.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>Meet you? the world might laugh at me then i'faith.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ge.</speaker>
                                 <l>Lay by your ſcorn &amp; pride, the're ſcurvy qualities,</l>
                                 <pb n="160" facs="217"/>
                                 <l>And meet me, or Ile hox you while I have you,</l>
                                 <l>And carrie you gambril'd thither like a Mutton.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay, and you be in earneſt, here's my hand</l>
                                 <l>I will not faile you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis for your owne good.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>Away.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Too much for your own good, ſir, a pox on you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>I prethee curſe me all day long ſo.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Hang you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal:</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile make him mad; hee's loth to curſe too much to me;</l>
                                 <l>Indeed I never yet took box oth' eare,</l>
                                 <l>But it redounded, I muſt needs ſay ſo—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Will you be gone?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                                 <l>Curſe, curſe, and then I goe.</l>
                                 <l>Look how he grins, I've anger'd him toth' kidnyes. <stage>Ex.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Was ever ſuch a prigging coxcombe ſeen?</l>
                                 <l>One might have beat him dumbe now in this humour,</l>
                                 <l>And hee'd ha' grind it out ſtill: <stage>Enter a plain fellow.</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>O here's one made to my hand,</l>
                                 <l>Methinks looks like a Craven;</l>
                                 <l>Leſſe paines will ſerve his triall: ſome ſlight juſtle.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pl. f.</speaker>
                                 <l>How? take you that ſir:</l>
                                 <l>And if that content you not—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes very well ſir, I deſire no more.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pl. f.</speaker>
                                 <l>I think you need not;</l>
                                 <l>For you have not loſt by't. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Who would ha' thought this would have prov'd a gentleman?</l>
                                 <l>Ile never truſt long chins and little legs agen,</l>
                                 <l>Ile know 'em ſure for gentlemen hereafter:</l>
                                 <l>A griſtle but in ſhew, but gave his cuffe</l>
                                 <l>With ſuch a fetch, and reach of gentrie,</l>
                                 <l>As if h'had had his armes before the floud;</l>
                                 <l>I have took a villanous hard taske upon me;</l>
                                 <l>Now I begin to have a feeling on't.</l>
                                 <stage>Enter Lapet, and Clowne his ſervant, and ſo habited.</stage>
                                 <l>O here comes a tri'd piece, now, the reformed kick.</l>
                                 <l>The millions of punches, ſpurnes, and nips</l>
                                 <l>That he has endur'd? his Buttock's all black Lead,</l>
                                 <l>He 's halfe a Negro back-ward; he was paſt a Spaniard</l>
                                 <l>In eighty eight, and more Egyptian-like;</l>
                                 <l>His Table and his Book come both out ſhortly,</l>
                                 <l>And all the Cowards in the Towne expect it;</l>
                                 <l>So, if I faile of my full number now,</l>
                                 <l>I ſhall be ſure to finde 'em at Church corners,</l>
                                 <l>Where <hi>Dives,</hi> and the ſuff'ring Ballads hang.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Well, ſince thou art of ſo milde a temper,</l>
                                 <l>Of ſo meek a ſpirit, thou maiſt live with me,</l>
                                 <l>Till better times doe ſmile on thy deſerts.</l>
                                 <l>I am glad I am got home againe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>I am happy in your ſervice, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>You'll keep me from the Hoſpitall.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>So, bring me the laſt proofe, this is corrected.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>I, y'are too full of your correction, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap</speaker>
                                 <l>Look I have perfect Books within this half houre.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Bid him put all the Thumps in Pica Roman,</l>
                                 <l>And with great Tees, (you vermin) as Thumps ſhould be.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Then in what Letter will you have your Kicks?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>All in Italica, your Backward blowes</l>
                                 <l>All in Italica, you Hermophrodite:</l>
                                 <l>When ſhall I teach you wit?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>O let it alone,</l>
                                 <l>Till you have ſome your ſelfe ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>You mumble?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>The Victualls are lockt up;</l>
                                 <l>I'me kept from mumbling. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>He prints my Blows upon pot-paper too, the rogue,</l>
                                 <l>Which had been proper for ſome drunken Pamphlet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Monſieur <hi>Lapet?</hi> how the world rings of your ſir?</l>
                                 <l>Your name ſounds far and neare.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>A good report it beares, for an enduring name—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>What luck have you ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why, what's the matter?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>I'me but thinking on't.</l>
                                 <l>I've heard you wiſh this five yeare for a place.</l>
                                 <l>Now there's one fall'n, and freely without money too;</l>
                                 <l>And empty yet, and yet you cannot hav't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>No? what's the reaſon? Ile give money for't,</l>
                                 <l>Rather then goe without ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>That's not it, ſir;</l>
                                 <l>The troth is, there's no gentleman muſt have it</l>
                                 <l>Either for love or money: 'tis decreed ſo;</l>
                                 <l>I was heartily ſorrie when I thought upon you,</l>
                                 <l>Had you not been a gentleman I had fitted you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Who I a gentleman? a pox I'me none, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How? why did you ever think <hi>I</hi> was?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>What? not a gentleman?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>I would thou'dſt put it upon me i'faith.</l>
                                 <l>Did not my Grand-father cry Coney-skins?</l>
                                 <l>My father Aquavitae? a hot gentleman:</l>
                                 <l>All this <hi>I</hi> ſpeak on i' your time and memorie too;</l>
                                 <l>Onely a rich Unckle dy'd and left me chattells,</l>
                                 <l>You know all this ſo well too—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Pray excuſe me, ſir, ha' not you Armes?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes, a poore couple here.</l>
                                 <l>That ſerve to thruſt in wild-fowle.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Heralds Armes,</l>
                                 <l>Symbols of gentrie, ſir: you know my meaning;</l>
                                 <l>They've been ſhewn and ſeen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>They have.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> fex have they.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why I confeſſe, at my wives inſtigation once,</l>
                                 <l>(As women love theſe Heralds kickſhawes naturally)</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> bought 'em: but what are they think you? puffs.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why, that's proper to your name being <hi>Lapet.</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Which is <hi>La fart,</hi> after the engliſh letter.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>The Herald, ſir, had much a doe to finde it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>And can you blame him?</l>
                                 <l>Why 'tis the onely thing that puzzles the devill.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>At laſt he lookt upon my name agen,</l>
                                 <l>And having well compar'd it, this he gave me,</l>
                                 <l>The two Cholliques playing upon a winde inſtrument.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>An excellent proper one: but I pray tell me,</l>
                                 <l>How does he expreſſe the Cholliques?</l>
                                 <l>They are hard things.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>The Cholliques? with hot trenchers at their bellies,</l>
                                 <l>There's nothing better, Sir, to blaze a Chollique.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>And are not you a gentleman by this ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>No, <hi>I</hi> diſclaime't: no belly-ake upon earth</l>
                                 <l>Shall make me one: he ſhall not think</l>
                                 <l>To put his gripes upon me,</l>
                                 <l>And wring out gentrie ſo, and ten pound firſt.</l>
                                 <l>If the winde inſtrument will make my wife one,</l>
                                 <l>Let her enjoy't, for ſhe was a Harpers Grand-childe:</l>
                                 <l>But ſir, for my particular, <hi>I</hi> renounce it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Or to be call'd ſo?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ſir, or imagin'd.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>None fitter for the place: give me thy hand.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>A hundred thouſand thanks, beſide a Bribe ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>You muſt take heed</l>
                                 <l>Of thinking toward a gentleman, now.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <pb n="161" facs="217"/>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Piſh, I am not mad, I warrant you: nay more ſir,</l>
                                 <l>If one ſhould twit me i'th' teeth that I'me a gentleman,</l>
                                 <l>Twit me their worſt, <hi>I</hi> am but one ſince Lammas,</l>
                                 <l>That <hi>I</hi> can prove, if they would ſee my heart out.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Marry in any caſe keep me that evidence.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Clowne.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Here comes my ſervant, Sir, <hi>Galoſhio,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Has not his name for nought, he will be trod upon:</l>
                                 <l>What ſayes my Printer now?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Heres your laſt proof Sir.</l>
                                 <l>You ſhal have perfect Books now in a twinkling.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Theſe marks are ugly.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>He ſayes, ſir, they're proper:</l>
                                 <l>Blows ſhould have marks, or elſe they are nothing worth.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>La.</speaker>
                                 <l>But why a Peel-crow here?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>I told 'em ſo ſir:</l>
                                 <l>A Scar-crow had been better.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How Slave? looke you Sir,</l>
                                 <l>Did not I ſay, this Whirrit, and this Bob,</l>
                                 <l>Should be both Pica Roman.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>So ſaid I Sir, both Picked Romans,</l>
                                 <l>And he has made 'em Welch Bills,</l>
                                 <l>Indeed I know not what to make on 'em.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Hay-day; a Souſe, Italica?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes, that may hold Sir,</l>
                                 <l>Souſe is a <hi>bonaroba,</hi> ſo is Flops too.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>But why ſtands Baſtinado ſo farre off here?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Alas you muſt allow him room to lay about him, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>La.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why lyes this Spurne lower then that Spurn, ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Marry this ſignifies one kickt downe ſtaires, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>The other in a Gallerie: I ask'd him all theſe queſtions.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Your Books name?</l>
                                 <l>Prethee <hi>Lapet</hi> minde me, you never told me yet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>La.</speaker>
                                 <l>Marrie but ſhall ſir: 'tis call'd The up-riſing of the kick,</l>
                                 <l>And the downfall of the Duello.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Bring that to paſſe you'll prove a happy member,</l>
                                 <l>And doe your Countrey ſervice: your young blouds</l>
                                 <l>Will thank you then, when they ſee foure-ſcore.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I</hi> hope</l>
                                 <l>To ſave my hundred Gentlemen a month by't,</l>
                                 <l>Which will be very good for the private houſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Look you, your Table's finiſh'd ſir already.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why then behold my Maſter-piece: ſee, ſee, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Here's all your Blowes, and Blow-men whatſoever,</l>
                                 <l>Set in their lively colours, givers, and takers.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Troth wondrous fine, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay, but mark the poſtures,</l>
                                 <l>The ſtanding of the takers I admire more then the givers,</l>
                                 <l>They ſtand ſcornfully, moſt contumeliouſly, I like not thē,</l>
                                 <l>Oh here's one caſt into a comely figure.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>My Maſter meanes him there that's caſt downe headlong.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How ſweetly does this fellow take his Dowſt?</l>
                                 <l>Stoops like a Cammell, that Heroick beaſt,</l>
                                 <l>At a great load of Nut-megs; and how meekly</l>
                                 <l>This other fellow here receives his Whirrit?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh Maſter here's a fellow ſtands moſt gallantly,</l>
                                 <l>Taking his kick in private behinde the hangings,</l>
                                 <l>And raiſing up his hips to't. But oh, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>How daintily this man lies trampled on?</l>
                                 <l>Would I were in thy place, what e're thou art:</l>
                                 <l>How lovely he endures it?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <p>But will not theſe things, ſir, be hard to practiſe, think you?</p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh, eaſie, ſir: Ile teach 'em in a Dance.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>How? in a dance?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile loſe my new place elſe,</l>
                                 <l>What ere it be; I know not what 'tis yet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>And now you put me in minde, I could employ it well,</l>
                                 <l>For your grace, ſpecially: For the Dukes cozen</l>
                                 <l>Is by this time in's violent fit of mirth,</l>
                                 <l>And a deviſe muſt be ſought out for ſuddainly,</l>
                                 <l>To over-cloy the paſſion.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Say no more, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Ile fit you with my Schollers, new practitioners,</l>
                                 <l>Endurers of the time.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Whereof I am one ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>You carry it away ſmooth; give me thy hand, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="act">
                           <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
                           <div n="1" type="scene">
                              <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                              <stage>Enter the <hi>2.</hi> Brothers.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ha, ha, ha. <stage>Within.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Hark, hark, how lowd his fit's growne.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Now let our ſiſter loſe no time, but ply it</l>
                                 <l>With all the power ſhe has.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Her ſhame growes big, brother;</l>
                                 <l>The <hi>Cupids</hi> ſhape will hardly hold it longer,</l>
                                 <l>'Twould take up half an Ell of <hi>China</hi> Damask more,</l>
                                 <l>And all too little: it ſtruts per'louſly:</l>
                                 <l>There is no tamp'ring with theſe <hi>Cupids</hi> longer,</l>
                                 <l>The meere conceit with woman-kinde works ſtrong.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>The laugh comes nearer now,</l>
                                 <l>'Twere good we were not ſeen yet. <stage>Ex. Broth.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Paſſion. and Baſe his Jeſter.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                 <l>And was he baſtinado'd to the life? ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                 <l>I prethee ſay, Lord Generall, how did the Raſcals</l>
                                 <l>Entrench themſelves?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſe</speaker>
                                 <l>Moſt deeply, politickly, all in ditches.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis thought he'll ne're beare armes ith' field agen,</l>
                                 <l>Has much adoe, to lift 'em to his head, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I would he had.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſe</speaker>
                                 <l>On either ſide round Truncheons plaid ſo thick,</l>
                                 <l>That Shoulders, Chines, nay Flanks were paid toth' quick.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Well ſaid Lord Generall: ha, ha, ha.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>But pray how grew the difference firſt betwixt you?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>There was never any ſir; there lies the jeſt man;</l>
                                 <l>Onely becauſe he was taller then his brother;</l>
                                 <l>There's all my quarrell to him; and me thought</l>
                                 <l>He ſhould be beaten for't, my minde ſo gave me, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>I could not ſleep for't; Ha, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                 <l>Another good jeſt quickly, while 'tis hot now;</l>
                                 <l>Let me not laugh in vaine: ply me, O ply me,</l>
                                 <l>As you will anſwer't to my Cozen Duke.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Alas, who has a good jeſt?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I fall, I dwindle in't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ten Crowns for a good jeſt: ha' you a good jeſt, ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                                 <l>A pretty morall one.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let's ha't, what ere it be.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                                 <l>There comes a <hi>Cupid</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Drawne by ſix fooles.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>That's nothing.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Help it, help it then.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ha' known ſix hundred fooles drawn by a <hi>Cupid.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>I that, that, that's the ſmarter Morall: ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                 <pb n="162" facs="218"/>
                                 <l>Now I begin to be Song-ripe methinks.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ile ſing you a pleaſant aire, ſir, before you ebb.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                                 <body>
                                    <head>Song.</head>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Oh how my Lungs doe tickle? ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Oh how my Lungs doe tickle? oh, oh, ho, ho.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <stage>Sings.</stage>
                                       <l>Set a ſharp Jeſt</l>
                                       <l>Againſt my breaſt,</l>
                                       <l>Then how my Lungs doe tickle?</l>
                                       <l>As Nightingales,</l>
                                       <l>And things in Cambrick railes,</l>
                                       <l>Sing beſt againſt a prickle.</l>
                                       <l>Ha, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Ho, ho, ho, ho, ha.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Laugh.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Laugh.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Laugh.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Laugh.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Wide.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Loud.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>And vary.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>A ſmile is for a ſimpering Novice.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>One that ne're taſted Caveare,</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Nor knowes the ſmack of deare Anchovis.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Ho, ho, ho, ho, ho.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>A gigling waiting wench for me,</l>
                                       <l>That ſhewes her teeth how white they be.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>A thing not fit for gravitie,</l>
                                       <l>For theirs are foule and hardly three.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Ho, ho, ho.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Democritus,</hi> thou ancient Fleerer,</l>
                                       <l>Now I miſſe thy laugh, and ha' ſince.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>There you nam'd the famous Geerer,</l>
                                       <l>That ever geer'd in <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Athens.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>Ho, ho, ho.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>How brave lives he that keeps a foole,</l>
                                       <l>Although the rate be deeper?</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>But he that is his owne foole ſir,</l>
                                       <l>Does live a great deale cheaper.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <p>Sure I ſhal burſt, burſt, quite break thou art ſo witty.</p>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>'Tis rare to break at Court for that belongs toth' City.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                       <p>Ha, ha, my ſpleen is almoſt worne to the laſt laughter.</p>
                                    </sp>
                                    <sp>
                                       <speaker>Baſ.</speaker>
                                       <l>O keep a corner for a friend, a jeſt may come hereaf|ter.</l>
                                    </sp>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                              <stage>Enter Lapet and Clowne, and foure other like fooles, dancing, the Cupid leading, and bearing his Table, and holding it up to Lapet at every ſtrain, and acting the poſtures.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Twinge all now, twinge, I ſay.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>2 Straine.</stage>
                              <stage>Sowſe upon Souſe.</stage>
                              <stage>3 Straine.</stage>
                              <stage>Douſes ſingle.</stage>
                              <stage>4 Straine.</stage>
                              <stage>Juſtle ſides.</stage>
                              <stage>5 Straine.</stage>
                              <stage>Knee Belly.</stage>
                              <stage>6 Straine.</stage>
                              <stage>Kickſee Buttock.</stage>
                              <stage>7 Straine.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>La.</speaker>
                                 <l>Downe derry.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Soldier, Shamonts Brother, his ſword drawne.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>Not angry Law, nor doores of Braſſe ſhal keep me</l>
                                 <l>From my wrongs expiation, to thy Bowels,</l>
                                 <l>I returne my diſgrace; and after turne</l>
                                 <l>My face to any death that can be ſentenc'd.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Baſe</speaker>
                                 <l>Murder, O murder, ſtop the murderer there—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>I am glad hee's gone; h'as almoſt trod my guts out;</l>
                                 <l>Follow him who liſt for me, Ile ha' no hand in't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh 'twas your luck and mine to be ſquelch'd Mr.</l>
                                 <l>Has ſtamp'd my very Puddings into Pancakes.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
                                 <l>O Brothers, oh, I fear 'tis mortall: help, O helpe,</l>
                                 <l>I'me made the wretched'ſt woman, by this accident,</l>
                                 <l>That ever love beguil'd. <stage>Enter <hi>2.</hi> Brothers.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>We are undone Brother,</l>
                                 <l>Our ſhames are too apparent: Away receptacle</l>
                                 <l>Of Luxury, and diſhonour, moſt unfortunate,</l>
                                 <l>To make thy ſelfe but luckie to thy ſpoile,</l>
                                 <l>After thy Sexes manner: lift him up Brother;</l>
                                 <l>He breathes not to our comfort, hee's too waſted</l>
                                 <l>Ever to cheere us more: A Chirurgeon ſpeedily;</l>
                                 <l>Hence; the unhappieſt that ere ſtept aſide,</l>
                                 <l>Shee'll be a Mother before ſhee's known a Bride.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
                                 <l>Thou hadſt a moſt unfortunate conception,</l>
                                 <l>What ere thou prov'ſt to be; in midd'ſt of mirth</l>
                                 <l>Comes ruine, for a welcome, to thy birth. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                           </div>
                           <div n="2" type="scene">
                              <head>Scaene 2.</head>
                              <stage>Enter Shamont.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>This is a beautifull life now; privacie</l>
                                 <l>The ſweetneſſe and the benefit of eſſence:</l>
                                 <l>I ſee there is no man, but may make his paradice;</l>
                                 <l>And it is nothing, but his love, and dotage</l>
                                 <l>Upon the worlds fowle joyes, that keeps him out on't:</l>
                                 <l>For he that lives retir'd in minde, and ſpirit,</l>
                                 <l>Is ſtill in paradice, and has his innocence,</l>
                                 <l>Partly allow'd for his companion too,</l>
                                 <l>As much as ſtands with juſtice: here no eyes</l>
                                 <l>Shoot their ſharp pointed ſcornes upon my ſhame;</l>
                                 <l>They know no termes of reputation here,</l>
                                 <l>No punctuall limits, or preciſe dimenſions;</l>
                                 <l>Plaine downe-right honeſtie is all the beauty</l>
                                 <l>And elegancy of life found amongſt ſhepheards;</l>
                                 <l>For knowing nothing nicely, or deſiring it,</l>
                                 <l>Quits many a vexation from the minde,</l>
                                 <l>With which our quainter knowledge does abuſe us;</l>
                                 <l>The name of envy is a ſtranger here,</l>
                                 <l>That dries mens blouds abroad, robs health and reſt,</l>
                                 <l>Why here's no ſuch fury thought on: no, nor falſehood,</l>
                                 <l>That brotherly diſeaſe, fellow-like devill,</l>
                                 <l>That plaies within our boſome, and betrayes us.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter <hi>1</hi> Gent.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh are you here?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>La Nove,</hi> 'tis ſtrange to ſee thee.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ha' rid one horſe to death,</l>
                                 <l>To finde you out, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>I am not to be found of any man</l>
                                 <l>That ſaw my ſhame, nor ſeen long.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Good, your attention:</l>
                                 <l>You ought to be ſeen now, and found out ſir,</l>
                                 <l>If ever you deſire before your ending</l>
                                 <l>To performe one good office, nay a deare one,</l>
                                 <l>Mans time can hardly match it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Bee't as pretious</l>
                                 <l>As reputation; if it come from Court</l>
                                 <l>I will not heare on't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>You muſt heare of this, Sir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Muſt?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>You ſhall heare it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>I love thee, that thoul't dye.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Twere nobler in me,</l>
                                 <l>Then in you living: you will live a murderer,</l>
                                 <l>If you deny this office.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>Ev'n to death ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <pb n="163" facs="218"/>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Why then you'l kill your brother.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham,</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>Your Brother ſir:</l>
                                 <l>Beare witneſſe heaven, this man deſtroyes his brother</l>
                                 <l>When he may ſave him, his leaſt breath may ſave him:</l>
                                 <l>Can there be wilfuller deſtruction?</l>
                                 <l>He was forc'd to take a moſt unmanly wrong,</l>
                                 <l>Above the ſuffring vertue of a Soldier,</l>
                                 <l>Has kill'd his Injurer, a work of honour;</l>
                                 <l>For which, unleſſe you ſave him, he dyes ſpeedily</l>
                                 <l>My conſcience is diſcharg'd, I'me but a friend,</l>
                                 <l>A Brother ſhould goe forward where I end. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Dyes?</l>
                                 <l>Say he be naught, that's nothing to my goodneſſe,</l>
                                 <l>Which ought to ſhine through uſe, or elſe it loſes</l>
                                 <l>The glorious name 'tis knowne by: hee's my brother;</l>
                                 <l>Yet peace is above bloud: Let him goe; I,</l>
                                 <l>But where's the nobleneſſe of affection then?</l>
                                 <l>That muſt be car'd for too, or I'me imperfect,</l>
                                 <l>The ſame bloud that ſtood up in wrath againſt him,</l>
                                 <l>Now in his miſerie runs all to pity;</l>
                                 <l>I'de rather dye than ſpeak one ſillable</l>
                                 <l>To ſave my ſelfe: but living as I am,</l>
                                 <l>There's no avoiding on't, the worlds humanity</l>
                                 <l>Expects it hourely from me: curſe of fortune,</l>
                                 <l>I took my leave ſo well too: Let him dye,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis but a brother loſt; ſo pleaſingly,</l>
                                 <l>And ſwiftly I came off, 'twere more then irkſomneſſe,</l>
                                 <l>To tread that path agen; and I ſhall never</l>
                                 <l>Depart ſo handſomly: But then where's poſterity?</l>
                                 <l>The conſummation of our houſe and name?</l>
                                 <l>I'me torne in pieces betwixt love and ſhame. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                           </div>
                           <div n="3" type="scene">
                              <head>Scaene 3.</head>
                              <stage>Enter Lapet, Clown, Poultrot, Moulbazon, and others, the new Court Officers.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Good morrow fellow <hi>Poltrot,</hi> and <hi>Moulbazon,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Good morrow fellowes all.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                                 <l>Mounſieur <hi>Lapet?</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Look, I've remembred you, here's books a piece for you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Moul.</speaker>
                                 <l>O ſir, we dearely thank you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>So you may;</l>
                                 <l>There's two impreſſions gone already ſirs.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                                 <l>What no? in ſo ſhort a time?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis as I tell you ſir,</l>
                                 <l>My Kick ſells gallantly, I thank my ſtars.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                                 <l>So does your Table; you may thank the Moon too.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis the Book ſells the Table.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>But 'tis the Book-ſeller</l>
                                 <l>That has the money for 'em, I'me ſure o'that.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Twill much enrich the Company of Stationers,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis thought 'twill prove a laſting benefit,</l>
                                 <l>Like the Wiſe Maſters, and the Almanacks,</l>
                                 <l>The hundred Novells, and the Book of Cookerie,</l>
                                 <l>For they begin already to engroſſe it,</l>
                                 <l>And make it a ſtock-book, thinking indeed</l>
                                 <l>'Twill prove too great a benefit, and help,</l>
                                 <l>For one that's new ſet up: they know their way,</l>
                                 <l>And make him Warden, ere his beard be gray.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Moul.</speaker>
                                 <l>Is't poſſible ſuch vertue ſhould lye hid,</l>
                                 <l>And in ſo little paper?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How? Why there was the Carpenter,</l>
                                 <l>An unknowne thing, an odoriferous Pamphlet,</l>
                                 <l>Yet no more Paper, by all computation,</l>
                                 <l>Then <hi>Ajax Telamon</hi> would uſe at once,</l>
                                 <l>Your Herring prov'd the like, able to buy</l>
                                 <l>Another <hi>Fiſhers</hi> Folly, and your <hi>Paſquill</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Went not below the mad-caps of that time,</l>
                                 <l>And ſhall my elaborate Kick come behinde think you?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes, it muſt come behinde, 'tis in <hi>Italica</hi> too,</l>
                                 <l>According to your humour.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Not in ſale, varlet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>In ſale, ſir? it ſhall ſaile beyond 'em all I troe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>What have you there now? oh, Page, 21.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <p>That Page is come to his yeares, he ſhould be a ſerving-man.</p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>La.</speaker>
                                 <l>Mark how I ſnap up the Duello there:</l>
                                 <l>One would not uſe a dog ſo,</l>
                                 <l>I muſt needs ſay; but's for the common good.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nay ſir, your Commons ſeldome fight at ſharp,</l>
                                 <l>But buffet in a ware-houſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>This will ſave</l>
                                 <l>Many a gentleman of good bloud from bleeding ſirs,</l>
                                 <l>I have a curſe from many a Barber Surgeon;</l>
                                 <l>They'd give but too much money to call't in;</l>
                                 <l>Turne to Page 45. ſee what you finde there.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>O out upon him,</l>
                                 <l>Page 45. that's an old theefe indeed.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Duke, the Lady his ſiſter, <hi>1</hi> Gent.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>The Duke, clap down your Books; away <hi>Galoſhio.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
                                 <l>Indeed I am too foule to be ith' preſence,</l>
                                 <l>They uſe to ſhake me off at the chamber door ſtill. <stage>Ex.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                                 <l>Good my Lord, grant my ſuit; let me not riſe</l>
                                 <l>Without the comfort on't: I have not often</l>
                                 <l>Been tedious in this kinde.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Siſter, you wrong your ſelfe,</l>
                                 <l>And thoſe great vertues that your fame is made of,</l>
                                 <l>To waſte ſo much breath for a Murderers life.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>You cannot hate th' offence more then I doe, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Nor the offender, the reſpect I owe</l>
                                 <l>Unto his abſent brother, makes me a ſuitor,</l>
                                 <l>A moſt importunate ſiſter; make me worthy</l>
                                 <l>But of this one requeſt.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                                 <l>I am deafe</l>
                                 <l>To any importunacy, and ſorry</l>
                                 <l>For your forgetfulneſſe; you never injur'd</l>
                                 <l>Your worth ſo much, you ought to be rebuk'd for't:</l>
                                 <l>Purſue good wayes, end as you did begin,</l>
                                 <l>'Tis halfe the guilt to ſpeak for ſuch a ſin.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lad.</speaker>
                                 <l>This is loves beggerie right, that now is ours,</l>
                                 <l>When Ladies love, and cannot ſhew their powers. <stage>Ex.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>La Nove?</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>My Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Are theſe our new attendants?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>We are my Lord, and will endure as much</l>
                                 <l>As better men, my Lord, and more I truſt.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>What's hee?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>My Lord, a decay'd Gentleman,</l>
                                 <l>That will doe any ſervice.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>A decay'd one?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>A renounc'd one indeed; for this place only.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>We renounce him then, go, diſcharge him inſtantly.</l>
                                 <l>He that diſclaimes his gentry for meere gaines,</l>
                                 <l>That man's too baſe to make a vaſſaile on.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>What ſaies the Duke?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Faith little to your comfort ſir,</l>
                                 <l>You muſt be a gentleman agen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>There's no remedy.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>Marry, the fates forfend: ne're while I breath ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>The Duke will have it ſo, there's no reſiſting.</l>
                                 <l>He ſpide it i' your fore-head.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>My wife's doing.</l>
                                 <pb n="164" facs="219"/>
                                 <l>She thought ſhe ſhould be put below her betters now,</l>
                                 <l>And ſu'd to ha' me a gentleman agen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>And very like ſir:</l>
                                 <l>Marry Ile give you this comfort when all's done,</l>
                                 <l>You'll never paſſe but for a ſcurvey one,</l>
                                 <l>That's all the helpe you have: come ſhew your pace.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lap.</speaker>
                                 <l>The heavieſt gentleman that e're loſt place;</l>
                                 <l>Beare witneſſe I am forc't to't. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                                 <l>Though you have a courſer title yet upon you,</l>
                                 <l>Then thoſe that left your places, without blame,</l>
                                 <l>Tis in your power to make your ſelves the ſame:</l>
                                 <l>I cannot make you gentlemen, that's a work</l>
                                 <l>Rais'd from your owne deſervings; merit, manners,</l>
                                 <l>And in-borne vertue doe's it. Let your own goodneſſe</l>
                                 <l>Make you ſo great, my power ſhall make you greater;</l>
                                 <l>And more t'encourage you, this I adde agen,</l>
                                 <l>There's many Grooms now exact Gentlemen.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Shamont.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Me thinks 'tis ſtrange to me to enter here:</l>
                                 <l>Is there in nature ſuch an awfull power,</l>
                                 <l>To force me to this place? and make me doe this?</l>
                                 <l>Is mans affections ſtronger then his will?</l>
                                 <l>His reſolution? was I now reſolv'd</l>
                                 <l>Never to ſee this place more? Doe I beare</l>
                                 <l>Within my breaſt one bloud that confounds th'other?</l>
                                 <l>The bloud of love, and will, and the laſt weakeſt?</l>
                                 <l>Had I ten Millions, I would give it all now,</l>
                                 <l>I were but paſt it, or 'twould never come;</l>
                                 <l>For I ſhall never do't, or not do't well,</l>
                                 <l>But ſpoyle it utterly betwixt two paſſions.</l>
                                 <l>Yonder's the Duke himſelfe, I will not do't now,</l>
                                 <l>Had twenty lives their ſeverall ſufferings in him. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                                 </l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                                 <l>Who's that went out now?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ſaw none, my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Nor you?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Moul.</speaker>
                                 <l>I ſaw the glimpſe of one my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>What ere it was, methought it pleas'd me ſtrangly,</l>
                                 <l>And ſuddenly my joy was ready for't.</l>
                                 <l>Did you not marke it better?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Pol. &amp; Moul.</speaker>
                                 <l>Troth my Lord,</l>
                                 <l>We gave no great heed to't.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Shamont.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>'Twill not be anſwer'd,</l>
                                 <l>It brings me hither ſtill; by maine force hither:</l>
                                 <l>Either I muſt give over to profeſſe humanity,</l>
                                 <l>Or I muſt ſpeak for him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                                 <l>'Tis here agen:</l>
                                 <l>No marvaile 'twas ſo pleaſing, 'tis delight</l>
                                 <l>And worth it ſelfe, now it appeares unclouded.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>My Lord—</l>
                                 <l>He turnes away from mee: by this hand</l>
                                 <l>I am ill-us'd of all ſides: 'tis a fault</l>
                                 <l>That fortune ever had, t' abuſe a goodneſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                                 <l>Methought you were ſaying ſomewhat.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Marke the Language,</l>
                                 <l>As coy as face; I ſee 'twill nere be granted.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>We little look'd in troth to ſee you here yet.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Not till the day after my brothers death, I think.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Sure ſome great buſineſſe drew you.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
                                 <l>No inſooth, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Onely to come to ſee a brother dye ſir,</l>
                                 <l>That I may learne to goe too; and if he deceive me not,</l>
                                 <l>I think he will doe well in't of a ſouldier,</l>
                                 <l>Manly, and honeſtly: and if he weep then,</l>
                                 <l>I ſhall not think the worſe on's man-hood for't,</l>
                                 <l>Becauſe hee's leaving of that part that has it.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                                 <l>Has ſlaine a noble gentleman, thinke on't, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>I would I could not ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                                 <l>Our Kinſman too.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>All this is but worſe ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>When 'tis at worſt,</l>
                                 <l>Yet ſeeing thee, he lives.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>My Lord—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>He lives,</l>
                                 <l>Believe it as thy bliſſe, he dyes not for't:</l>
                                 <l>Will this make ſatisfaction for things paſt?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Oh my Lord—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Will it? ſpeak.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sh.</speaker>
                                 <l>With greater ſhame to my unworthineſſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Riſe then, wee're ev'n: I never found it harder</l>
                                 <l>To keep juſt with a man: my great work's ended.</l>
                                 <l>I knew your brothers pardon was your ſuit, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>How ever your nice modeſtie held it back.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>I take a joy now, to confeſſe it, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter <hi>1.</hi> Gent.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gent.</speaker>
                                 <l>My Lord—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Heare me firſt, ſir, what e're your newes be:</l>
                                 <l>Set free the Souldier inſtantly.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>Tis done, my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>In effect: 'twas part of my newes too,</l>
                                 <l>There's faire hope of your noble kinſmans life ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>What ſaiſt thou?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>And the moſt admired change</l>
                                 <l>That living fleſh e're had; he's not the man my Lord;</l>
                                 <l>Death cannot be more free from paſſions, ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Then he is at this inſtant: hee's ſo meek now,</l>
                                 <l>He makes thoſe ſeem paſſionate, was never thought of:</l>
                                 <l>And for he feares his moods have oft diſturb'd you ſir,</l>
                                 <l>Hee's onely haſty now for his forgiveneſſe,</l>
                                 <l>And here behold him ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Paſſion. the Cupid, and two brothers.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Let me give thanks firſt: our worthy Couſen—</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Your unworthy trouble ſir;</l>
                                 <l>For which, with all acknowledg'd reverence,</l>
                                 <l>I aske your pardon; and for injurie</l>
                                 <l>More knowne and wilfull, I have choſe a wiſe,</l>
                                 <l>Without your counſell, or conſent, my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                                 <l>A wife? where is ſhe ſir?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>This noble Gentlewoman.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                                 <l>How?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Whoſe honour my forgetful times much wrong'd.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Hee's madder then he was.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Gen.</speaker>
                                 <l>I would ha' ſworne for him.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>The <hi>Cupid,</hi> couſen?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
                                 <l>Yes, this worthy Lady, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Still worſe and worſe.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Our ſiſter under pardon, my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>What?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>2</hi> Bro.</speaker>
                                 <l>Which ſhape Love taught her to aſſume.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Is't truth then?</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>
                                    <hi>1</hi> Ge.</speaker>
                                 <l>It appears plainly now below the waſte my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Shamont,</hi> didſt ever read of a ſhe-<hi>Cupid?</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>Never in fiction yet: but it might hold ſir;</l>
                                 <l>For Deſire is of both Genders.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter the Dukes ſiſter.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Make that good here: <stage>He joyns Shamonts hand and his Siſters.</stage>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>I take thee at thy word, ſir.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>O my Lord,</l>
                                 <l>Love would appeare too bold, and rude from me,</l>
                                 <pb n="165" facs="219"/>
                                 <l>Honour and admiration are her rights,</l>
                                 <l>Her goodneſſe is my Saint, my Lord.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                                 <l>I ſee,</l>
                                 <l>Y'are both too modeſt to beſtow your ſelves:</l>
                                 <l>I'le ſave that vertue ſtill; 'tis but my paines: come,</l>
                                 <l>It ſhall be ſo.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sham.</speaker>
                                 <l>This gift does but ſet forth my poverty.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Lady</speaker>
                                 <l>Sir, that which you complaine of is my riches.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Enter Shamonts brother the Souldier.</stage>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                                 <l>Soldier, now every noiſe ſounds peace, th'art welcome.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                                 <l>Sir my repentance ſues for your bleſt favour,</l>
                                 <l>Which once obtain'd, no injury ſhall loſe it;</l>
                                 <l>Ile ſuffer mightier wrongs.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                                 <l>Riſe, lov'd and pardon'd;</l>
                                 <l>For where hope fail'd, nay Art it ſelfe reſign'd,</l>
                                 <l>Thou'ſt wrought that cure, which skil could never find;</l>
                                 <l>Nor did there ceaſe, but to our peace extend;</l>
                                 <l>Never could wrongs boaſt of a nobler end.</l>
                              </sp>
                              <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
                  <back>
                     <div type="prologue">
                        <head>The Prologue at the reviving of this Play.</head>
                        <l>IT's growne in faſh'on of late in theſe dayes,</l>
                        <l>To come and beg a ſufferance to our Playes;</l>
                        <l>Faith Gentlemen our Poet ever writ</l>
                        <l>Language ſo good, mixt with ſuch ſprightly wit,</l>
                        <l>He made the Theatre ſo ſoveraigne</l>
                        <l>With his rare Scaenes, he ſcorn'd this crowching veine:</l>
                        <l>We ſtabb'd him with keene daggers when we pray'd</l>
                        <l>Him write a Preface to a Play well made.</l>
                        <l>He could not write theſe toyes; 'twas eaſier farre,</l>
                        <l>To bring a Felon to appeare at th' Barre,</l>
                        <l>So much he hated baſeneſſe; which this day,</l>
                        <l>His Scaenes will beſt convince you of in's Play,</l>
                     </div>
                     <div type="epilogue">
                        <head>The Epilogue.</head>
                        <l>OUr Poet bid us ſay for his owne part,</l>
                        <l>He cannot lay too much forth of his Art:</l>
                        <l>But feares our over-acting paſſions may,</l>
                        <l>As not adorne, deface his labour'd Play:</l>
                        <l>Yet ſtill he is reſolute for what is writ</l>
                        <l>Of Nicer valour, and aſſumes the wit:</l>
                        <l>But for the Love-Scaenes which he ever meant,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cupid</hi> in's Petticoat ſhould repreſent,</l>
                        <l>Hee'll ſtand no ſhock of cenſure; the Plaie's good,</l>
                        <l>He ſayes he knowes it, (if well underſtood.)</l>
                        <l>But we (blinde god) begge, if thou art divine,</l>
                        <l>Thou'lt ſhoot thy Arrowes round, this Play was thine.</l>
                     </div>
                     <div type="verse_letter">
                        <pb facs="220"/>
                        <head>M. <hi>Francis Beaumonts</hi> Letter to <hi>Ben Johnſon,</hi> written before he and Maſter <hi>Fletcher</hi> came to <hi>London,</hi> with two of the precedent Comedies then not finiſht, which deferred their merry meetings at the Mermaid.</head>
                        <l>THE Sun which doth the greatest comfort bring</l>
                        <l>To abſent friends, becauſe the ſelf-ſame thing</l>
                        <l>They know they ſee, however abſent is,</l>
                        <l>(Here our beſt Hay-maker forgive me this,</l>
                        <l>It is our Countries ſtile) In this warme ſhine,</l>
                        <l>I lye and dreame of your full Mermaid wine.</l>
                        <l>O we have water mixt with Claret Lees,</l>
                        <l>Drinke apt to bring in dryer hereſies,</l>
                        <l>Then beere, good only for the Sonnets ſtraine,</l>
                        <l>With fuſtian metaphors to ſtuffe the braine,</l>
                        <l>So mixt, that given to the thirstieſt one,</l>
                        <l>'Twill not prove almes, unleſſe he have the ſtone:</l>
                        <l>I thinke with one draught mans invention fades,</l>
                        <l>Two Cups had quite ſpoil'd <hi>Homers</hi> Illiades;</l>
                        <l>'Tis liquor that will find out <hi>Sutcliffs</hi> wit,</l>
                        <l>Lye where he will, and make him write worſe yet;</l>
                        <l>Fil'd with ſuch moiſture in moſt grievous qualmes,</l>
                        <l>Did <hi>Robert Wiſdome</hi> write his ſinging Pſalmes;</l>
                        <l>And ſo must I doe this, and yet I thinke</l>
                        <l>It is a potion ſent us downe to drinke,</l>
                        <l>By ſpeciall Providence, keeps us from fights,</l>
                        <l>Makes us not laugh, when we make leggs to Knights.</l>
                        <l>'Tis this that keeps our minds fit for our States,</l>
                        <l>A Medicine to obey our Magiſtrates:</l>
                        <l>For we doe live more free then you, no hate,</l>
                        <l>No envy at one anothers happy ſtate</l>
                        <l>Moves us, we are all equall every whit:</l>
                        <l>Of Land that God gives men here is their wit:</l>
                        <l>If we conſider fully, for our beſt,</l>
                        <l>And graveſt men will with his maine houſe jeſt,</l>
                        <l>Scarſe pleaſe you; we want ſubtilty to doe</l>
                        <l>The Citie tricks, lye, hate, and flatter too:</l>
                        <l>Here are none that can beare a painted ſhow,</l>
                        <l>Strike when you winch, and then lament the blow:</l>
                        <l>Who like Mils ſet the right way for to grinde,</l>
                        <l>Can make their gaines alike with every winde:</l>
                        <pb facs="220"/>
                        <l>Only ſome fellows with the ſubtil'ſt pate</l>
                        <l>Amongſt us, may perchance aequivocate</l>
                        <l>At ſelling of a horſe, and thats the moſt.</l>
                        <l>Methinks the little wit I had is loſt</l>
                        <l>Since I ſaw you, for wit is like a reſt</l>
                        <l>Held up at Tennis, which men doe the beſt,</l>
                        <l>With the beſt gameſters: What things have we ſeen</l>
                        <l>Done at the Mermaid! heard words that have been</l>
                        <l>So nimble, and ſo full of ſubtill flame,</l>
                        <l>As if that every one from whence they came,</l>
                        <l>Had meant to put his whole wit in a jeſt,</l>
                        <l>And had reſolv'd to live a foole the reſt</l>
                        <l>Of his dull life; then when there hath been throwne</l>
                        <l>Wit able enough to juſtifie the Towne</l>
                        <l>For three dayes paſt, wit that might warrant be</l>
                        <l>For the whole City to talke fooliſhly</l>
                        <l>Till that were cancel'd, and when that was gone,</l>
                        <l>We left an aire behind us, which alone,</l>
                        <l>Was able to make the two next companies</l>
                        <l>Right witty; though but downright fools, more wiſe.</l>
                        <l>When I remember this, and ſee that now</l>
                        <l>The Country gentlemen begin to allow</l>
                        <l>My wit for dry bobbs, then I needs muſt cry,</l>
                        <l>I ſee my days of ballating grow nigh;</l>
                        <l>I can already riddle, and can ſing</l>
                        <l>Catches, ſell bargains, and I feare ſhall bring</l>
                        <l>My ſelf to ſpeak the hardeſt words I find,</l>
                        <l>Over as oft as any, with one wind,</l>
                        <l>That takes no medicines: But one thought of thee</l>
                        <l>Makes me remember all theſe things to be</l>
                        <l>The wit of our young men, fellows that ſhow</l>
                        <l>No part of good, yet utter all they know:</l>
                        <l>Who like trees of the Guard, have growing ſoules.</l>
                        <l>Only ſtrong deſtiny, which all controules,</l>
                        <l>I hope hath left a better fate in ſtore,</l>
                        <l>For me thy friend, then to live every poore,</l>
                        <l>Baniſht unto this home; fate once againe</l>
                        <l>Bring me to thee, who canſt make ſmooth &amp; plain</l>
                        <l>The way of Knowledge for me, and then I,</l>
                        <l>Who have no good but in thy company,</l>
                        <l>Proteſt it will my greateſt comfort be</l>
                        <l>To acknovvledge all I have to flovv from thee.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ben,</hi> vvhen theſe <hi>Scaenes</hi> are perfect vvee'l taſte vvine;</l>
                        <l>Ile drink thy Muſes health, thou ſhalt quaff mine.</l>
                     </div>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </back>
               </text>
               </TEI>

