<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
            <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>325 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 November (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12417588</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing K450.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">61734</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
                  <title type="alt">Works. 1664</title>
                  <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 8 [i.e. 5]-576, 80 p. : port.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Each play has special t.p. and is dated 1663.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="259"/>
THE SECOND PART OF Bellamira her Dream: OR, THE Love of Shadows. A TRAGI-COMEDY, The Scene <hi>NAPLES</hi> and <hi>SICILY.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Written in <hi>VENICE,</hi> BY <hi>THOMAS KILLIGREW.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>DEDICATED TO THE Lady <hi>ANN VILLIERS COUNTESSE</hi> OF <hi>SUSSEX.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the sign of the <hi>Blew Anchor,</hi> in the lower Walk of the <hi>New-Exchange.</hi> 1663.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="260"/>
                     <head>The Names of the Actors:</head>
                     <item>The King of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ortho,</hi> Brother of the King, slain in a Battel.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> Prince of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Naples.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Almanzor,</hi> Prince of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roderigo,</hi> His Lieutenant General.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bellamira,</hi> Sister to <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fidelia,</hi> A Lady of the Court.</item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Pollidor,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Two Foresters.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Phillora</hi> his Sister,</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ravack,</hi> A banished Lord, of dead <hi>Ortho</hi>'s party.</item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Nigro,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">Three Lords of <hi>Ortho</hi>'s party, in Arms in <hi>Gaietta.</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Clytus,</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Cleon,</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Palantus,</hi> General of the Horse to the King of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Naples.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philemon,</hi> An old Lord at Court.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Satyr,</hi> In Love with <hi>Phillora.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arcus,</hi> A Moor, Slave to <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Juba,</hi> A Moor, Friend to <hi>Arcus,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Both Prisoners.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Cadess,</hi> his Sister.</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> such as the Scene Requires.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <pb n="519" facs="260"/>
                  <head>THE SECOND PART OF Bellamira her Dream: OR, THE Love of Shadows.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter two</hi> Souldiers, <hi>with</hi> Leopoldo <hi>bound.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>NO Mutiny Friend, the Day being ours, our Swords have given us Title to all you have.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Your Throat is mine too, and be still while he geld your Pocket, or I shall spoil your Drinking.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Can you answer this to your Officer? He commanded you to see me safe to his Tent, else no such base hands as yours should have had power to have bound me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Come Sir; these hands are as proper to pick your Poc|ket as the best in the Army, What's here? A Chain, by my faith, <stage>
                              <hi>The</hi> Souldi|ers <hi>plucks a chain out of his pocket, and puts it about his neck.</hi>
                           </stage> and Gold too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>D'ye hear, Brother, no pocketing; lay all down, fair play, and when we have done, divide.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Yes, yes, what's that? A Jewel? Is't right?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>If it prove false we'll have his—in the room; this was no small Fool.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1.</speaker>
                        <p>And his Ransom will be no Bauble, and let me alone to use him ill enough to make him hasten it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Let me go, and I'll pay it, to either, and by all the Gods swear secrecy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Ha! hum!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="520" facs="261"/>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>What is't he sayes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Something that carries reason if we durst trust him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>D' ye hear? either trust him and let him go, or cut his Throat; for if he lives to see the Prince, he'll tell what he has lost; and then we must not onely restore all, but put fair for hanging.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>And 'twould be a sad business to change this Gold chain for a halter; My Friend, turn to the Tree and pray, for I am resolved not to lose one link of this chain for your span of dayes; How fine my Girl will be when she has it on!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Just as fine as mine, 'twill burn your fingers else; that as the rest must be divided.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>No, no, 'tis pity to spoile it; take you his Clothes in consideration of half; Come Friend, dispatch this matter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain, wilt thou rob me and murther me too? Take heed, thy wants may plead for the one, but no excuse will save thee <stage>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>The</hi> Souldier <hi>holds his sword against his Breast.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>He catches hold of the chaine.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>They strive for the chain.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </stage> from that vengeance that sees thee if thou shalt act the other; The Blood thou shed'st in the heat of battle may find some excuse, as drawn from an Enemy, though Treason brought thee there.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Nay, nay, no sentences; Pray, if you can, or die, overseen, and say you were fairly advised; 'twill be so, indeed it will; I cannot afford it cheaper, will you dispach?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Yet 'ere you do it, I shall make bold with this.—(Half is my right, and I'll have it.)</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>It may be so, but I shall see you prove that right ere I quit it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Hell that gave a Mind to men full of Avarice, and corrup|ted Souls, Lust for wealth, send Discord the fruit of that cursed metal to fill their Hearts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Let it go. <stage>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>The first</hi> Souldier <hi>strikes, they fight.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>He slips down his hands, gets the dagger out, and cuts the strings that binds them.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I will not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>So, so, that blow will be reveng'd, I hope; I have a weapon in my boot, could I come but to use it; I might gain my freedom by this strife.—'Tis done, now I am free; But 'ere 'tis known, let me get within reach of them; Hold, as you are <hi>Souldiers,</hi> hold, do not strive for trifles at the rate of lives too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Stand you off, or I shall spoile your expectation; You had hope a good from this, but you are couzen'd: keep off, or I shall find a spare thrust shall do your business.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>For wishing your good?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>A pox on your Charity and your baubles; I would you been both hanged when I met with you; the Rogue has hurt me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>If that Villain scapes me I am strangely couzen'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I am wounded too, will you divide yet? And not let him laugh at both; he's like to be our Heir and Executor if we agree not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I am content; We are Friends, and thou shalt have half; Here's my Hand, and let's dispatch him.—Oh, he has kill'd me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>While they embrace, the Prince stabs the second</hi> Souldier, <hi>and takes his sword, he falls. The first</hi> Souldier <hi>sets upon the Prince, they fight; the</hi> Souldier falls, <hi>his perriwig drops off.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="521" facs="261"/>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Ye gods, that thus have arm'd in defence of my Inno|cency, to you I acknowledge this strange deliverance; I am free, but whither to go to keep that liberty, you that miraculously have sent it direct me too; I would find <hi>Phillora,</hi> but I know not where to seek her known and pursu'd in this habit, though not for the Prince, yet as an Enemy, will be dangerous.—ha! see what fate presents in this Extremity; 'tis a Perriwig, why not use it, and change habits with this Souldier, and so attempt to pass as one of them? it must be so, my wounds will be my excuse too, for being behind my Fellows; Thus, like an Enemy to my self I'll prove a Friend, and from these bitter flowers this honey gather; and by Fortune made equal to my love, safely enjoy the conversation of that maid, in this private habit, which was refus'd as Prince, when fortune frown'd.—I start not at this misery at all; nor will I <stage>
                              <hi>He strips the Souldier, and carries the Clothes off the stage; the Picture</hi> Pa|lantus <hi>had lost drops out of the Soul|diers pocket unseen of the Prince.</hi>
                           </stage> upbray'd the gods for these afflictions, 'tis the common fate of the best of Princes; no story but is fill'd with these blots of Treason, and the certain Vengeance that pursues 'em; And who e're he be that will venture into the troubled Seas that Empire Sails in must set out with a mind resolv'd for all fortunes; Princes are but men, and when they have resolv'd wisely let them Act with Honour, and leave the rest to Fate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bellamira, Fidelia, Arcus, <hi>and</hi> Philemon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>GOod heaven, what a day was this! My soul trembles to retain the sadness in my thoughts; the cries and groans still fill my Ears, The wounds and death that lies in thousand places are still before my eyes; The horrour of so many kindes of Entrances for death makes my soul sad, to think any man can be proud of conquest when they consider at what a Rate of misery and Cruelty 'tis purchas'd; Oh <hi>Fidelia,</hi> the sad means and La|mentations that the deceived hopes will breed from the fate of this day!—slaughter yet flying over the Field, waited on by death, who visits the Innocent, the Coward and the valiant, none can refuse him. Yet nothing is fuller of wonder then mine own part, who, this day, the thought of a friends danger would have begot a tear from, yet now am forced to tread upon the blood, and suck in at my Nostrils the souls of wretched men, whose last thick breath hath fill'd the Air.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Madam, cease to weep, and employ all your pa|tience to resist the violence of this storm; your Innocency will save us all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Fidelia,</hi> This horrour, nor the divers dangers of the times, is the load my soul shrinks under; 'tis the loss of my Royal Father, and poor <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> that bows me to the Earth; yet, in midst of these miseries and fears my eyes abuse me, if I saw not this day in the battle that fatal Figure my dreams have thus long convers'd withall.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="522" facs="262"/>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas sure the same the Prince met this morning.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, I saw her too; this was not unlike her, in habit, I confess I have labour'd with my grief, and the weak|ness of my Sex, thus far, to see if fate would guide me once more to his sight.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I pray be pleased, Madam, to repose here, whilst <hi>Arcus</hi> and myself see what horse those were that entred the wood.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Arcus <hi>and</hi> Philemon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>If there be in nature such a blessing as you imagine, I shall yet smile; for my heart tells me his sight concludes our miseries; yet what can be stranger then the things we have seen and suffred this day? how our fears have reconciled us even to this habit!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>We have not leisure to consider those lesser things now; Yesterday I should have blush'd to let <hi>Fidelia</hi> see what is now ex|posed to the view of dommon men; Behold the power of Parents, whose command hides all, and my obedience is as modest as my Coats; but when I consider my mind, and what fate imposes upon me, thus to pursue a flying shadow, ye gods behold, and pity a Virgin wooing, and a Virgin armed; stranger things then these no maidens fortunes know; Yet if I should see him, I can do any thing sooner then tell him that I love (and that too I fear) sooner then leave to do so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>From one that has felt the same sting pray take a little counsel, and resolve not what you will do, or say, until you see him; for to hope to be wise, thus far afore, in business of Love, is Madness; The heart only prepares love a perfect well-come; They are too much themselves that can speak sence; at such a time your worst Lover will tell his Tale best.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, no more, 'tis a Riddle, all; The wise man is not sure to read it, nor is't impossible to the Fool.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>I am yet afraid we are not safe: for the Enemy pursues us in all places, and therefore let us retreat into this wood; yet whi|ther should we fly but from our selves, that carry our griefs along with us?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>This sword too, if all fear'd it as I do, though by mine own side, Repehtance cannot make this day so Innocent as my fears would have preserved it; Behold ye powers, A maid, whose feeble prayers could not reach your throne, thus upbraids ye; &amp; as a more powerful weapon draws her Sword; your anger thus has arm'd our Sex, which has still been taught, Maids can so little glory gain in fights, that they can scarce be modestly angry.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>Treacherous and Injurious men give us a dispensation; and nothing is more lawful nor modest then those wounds a Virgin gives in defence of her Honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> arm'd women have as far out-shot their mark as cowardly men fall short of theirs; fighting women can add so little to their Fame themselves, that 'tis scarce for their honour to be sought for; and if men cannot add to womens fame by fighting, (which is their Idol virtue,) sure we catch at Shadows when we draw their Swords: and to speak really, that womans ho|nour
<pb n="523" facs="262"/>
that must be held by a Sword is not worth a Swords cure; For who has once been doubted may be innocent, but never fully cleared; for such a doubt, if it do's not stain, yet it dyes the minds of the best friends; Men, reasonable enough, fear there was some|thing call'd, some looks or words, some motion, that becken'd him to come, and made her subject to the boldness of that Sex; some negligence that bad him hope a Surprize, e're the boldest durst at|tempt such a fort as a modest mind; if there had not been some intelligence within, or at least the guards of virtue sleeping, they durst not (I say) hope; And this is my guilt, who, in my sleeps, have given up that mind and heart to a shadow, in my Dreams, that waking defended it self against the world; and now the Con|querour insults.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Madam, leave to repine at a Fate you cannot change; but calmly obey the gods; your virtue was not wont to dispute their wills; Remember, Madam, you have much to expect from hea|ven e're <stage>They sit upon the ground.</stage> you can reap your wishes; and obedience is the only well|come price Mortalls can pay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure I am not stubborn, <hi>Fidelia;</hi> Obedience is all I plead; for I am so far from refusing what they command, that thou see'st I follow a shadow because they sent it; and I believe all these desires but so many calls, so many becknings to come, which I shall cheerfully Obey; I know there must be some divine providence shut up in that Figure, some hidden secret some knot in fate that heaven has appointed my mortal hand to untie; It cannot be they should pick me out of a Nation onely to make me miserable; No, no <hi>Fidelia,</hi> 'tis but to make our joys taste the sweeter, that they pass them through these difficulties and fears.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>Now I prophesie we shall be happy; and give me leave to say, your former doubts have been one cause of these sufferings; for to doubt their power or mercy is the great sin; for when men dare confine the gods to the capacities of their narrow minds then they cleave the Air with Thunder, and in some high Example speak their Anger; hark, I hear a noise of weapons, we have talk'd away our safety.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Arcus <hi>and</hi> Philemon, <hi>pursued by the Enemy.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Haste, haste, Madam, or we are lost; this cursed colour of mine is known to be one that fought on the princes side to day; This brand of shame, not onely sent to be my curse, but yours; fly, and I'll kill my self, and let them believe I dy'd of wounds in the battle, 'tis only me, me that they pursue, and what wretch is he, would live, when he might die, to serve?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>He turns his Sword as if he would fall upon't.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, <hi>Arcus,</hi> thy faith shall live to be admir'd, as I have a
<pb n="524" facs="263"/>
life and Honour, if thou lay'st the least violent hands upon thy self, here I'll stay, and expect the worst of Fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Fly then, for Heavens sake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>We have lost the way, and know not where to go.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Enter this wood, Madam, that though we find not the Prince we may not lose each other.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Innocence! where's thy home? Alas, she has none! Inno|cence as restless is as her Servants, sent upon Journyes, as Fortune, or Oppression pleases; no certain place assign'd her, They wander still over the Earth; Courts and Temples are but Inns to virtue, where she lodges for a Night, but early next day she must be gone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis sad, the while, when the Palaces of Princes, nor Em|pire (beyond which the ambitious Sword aspires not) cannot ter|minate her wandring steps, nor the Temples Sacred Odours breathe air pure enough for her to live in. But these sad contemplations are not proper now; leave them, Madam, and seek a safety, for fear of worse evils then we have yet met.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven I obey, and but follow, where thou lead'st the way.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, Roderigo <hi>and</hi> Souldiers, <hi>in pursuit of</hi> Bellamira, Fidelia, Arcus, <hi>and</hi> Philemon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>PUrsue them, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> they hide in every Bush, victory and smiling Fortune beckens us to come.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis a sullen kind of Courage that despair and anger gives 'em; they have defended themselves to this place, with a strange daring, and a kind of miracle in success.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis but this desperate handfull that remains.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Pollidor, Phillora, <hi>and the</hi> Satyr.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>IT is the Princes party that disputes the hill, I saw the slave, I cannot be mistaken dear <hi>Pollidor,</hi> I know the Moor; my Imagination, nor my Love, which so oft you have upbraided, can|not change colours, <hi>Pollider.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Poll.</speaker>
                        <p>See my Reason, Blood, All I have freely given to your Passion; Follow thy Fate; for since my Father's satisfied, I shall without dispute obey you; though his news surprize me, being not apt to believe the Prince though he offer'd marriage; but hea|ven has time to punish and reward.—hark, I hear the noise of wea|pons, step into this Wood, and see what it means. <stage>Noise of wea|pons within.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="525" facs="263"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bellamira <hi>and</hi> Fidelia <hi>with their Swords drawn,</hi> Philemon <hi>and</hi> Arcus <hi>making their Retreat.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Fly, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>O whither, <hi>Fidelia?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phillora, <hi>and sides with the Princes party, and meet</hi> Bellamira <hi>and</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>See, see the Slave I spoke of, and certain they must be Friends to the Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Among the Trees.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>The odds makes the rest our Enemies, and honour calls Swords to their party. Stand, What are you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>We are two that would fain be Friends to thy Fortune what ere it be. O <hi>Fidelia,</hi> this is the same fatal Figure agen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>The Word?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Bellamira.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Pass that way while we endeavour your safety here.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt</hi> Bellamira <hi>and</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>How they tremble! their fears ly heavy upon them; some secret bosom-sin which they are loth to part with makes the fear of death worse than death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phillora <hi>take part with</hi> Arcus, <hi>and beat the Enemy.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bellamira <hi>and</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>This way, <hi>Fidelia;</hi> 'tis the Deity that in visions made his visits here, I cannot be mistaken, Love and Fate have stamp'd the Figure in my virgin-minde, let us follow and tell him so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Stay, Madam, Whither will your distracted griefs transport you? if you be discover'd you are lost for ever; your Honour too calls you back; when Women pursue how full of blushes are the most innocent actions?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>But if he goes ere I speak to him my soul will wither still in the fear that this should be a Dream too. O <hi>Fidelia,</hi> it is a cruel Fate that forces me to these precipices; Is there no possibility to be happy, but we must lose some grains of our value? Has Ho|nour no Holy-days? Is her service all toil of minde and body, no reward? Are Chains and Slavery the sole marks she desires to be known by? All Sting, all Thorns, no Roses, no Flowers, no Ho|ney? Why should Man endow'd with a reasonable minde sacrifice to such an Enemy for such shadows as these?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Madam, is this a time to dispute the power and will of Heaven? Let us seek a safety first before new dangers finde us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> I fear no new danger; could I finde a cure for this old wound I would despise all the Conquerour, either with
<pb n="526" facs="264"/>
Sword or Chains could bring; Why should his youth by fate be made so fit for my love, and then be set so far out of my reach? See how he hunts for honour, how greedy of my dangers, onely as they are glories; for he knows not me; his gentle Sister too faith|ful by his side without fear of wounds seeks them with more fury than we tremble at the thought, and gives the lie to all that we have said this day, giving and receiving wounds; Yet a Virgin, in whom no stains nor blush can dwell; What would these two have been? What stories would they have made if Fate had set them free, unfetter'd into the world! What parts would they have acted, had not these Minds been hedged in and confin'd with private births! Had not that cloud hung o're 'em, who could have beheld the brightness of that Virtue which shines through their humble Fortune? And since my Dreams were not safe from his shadow one|ly, what would the real Figure do? Oh <hi>Fidelia!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>Why these tears? Why this grief, when you ought to re|joyce? This day has remov'd a seven years doubt, the fears of an Age are blown over in this one object; That 'twas a shadow is now removed; there rests onely fitness now to compleat your hap|piness; Heretofore you were to wish a being to your Love; now when your great Heart can descend to meet a private virtue your may be happy. Remember, Madam, your Dream, and how strange a cure was appointed to heal this troubled Age, the marry|ing of a Tree; and see the sacred plants, the health and wealth of the Forest, designed for that great work.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>To Love and Fate I bow; and what they shall appoint most readily I shall submit to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>The night will suddenly joyn in our security; This way, Madam, we must expect the faithful <hi>Arcus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Pollidor <hi>from the Rescue of</hi> Bellamira.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Poll.</speaker>
                        <p>THis Girls passion makes my life a burden to me; but for love of her that's dearer than my self this Sword should with a kinde wound release me, that I should see her doat upon the Son of him that ruin'd us, my self too hunting their dangers, and in our bloud write our selves Friends to what we hate—What have we here? a poor youth slain, and a Picture by him, of his <stage>He findes the Picture, the Souldiers bo|dy lies by the Stage-side till n●w.</stage> Mistris sure; what may be miserable is still so; I never yet knew that blinde froward, humoursom Deity; Fortune omit a mischief that lay in her power; this Wretch that had but one thing dear to him, and was no doubt precious himself in the eyes of some|body. See how early her malice has found her youth, and cut him off in his first dangers; while to me she has this day afforded a mi|raculous <stage>He takes the Picture and looks upon it, and at the sight of it is amazed.</stage> Victory onely to vex me; had I been unwilling or afraid to dy she would have sought death for me; but finding me weary of life she aids me still against my wishes that has no business here—Ha! What does my eyes behold? I dream sure—Ye Gods
<pb n="527" facs="264"/>
What is your will? Why this strange way to new miseries? What kinde of Curse is this you have sent me? 'tis the sacred Figure sure of some Deity prophan'd and ravish'd by this Wretch, whose Sacriledge has from Heaven met a punishment—O speak, speak, di|vine Spirit, command me and I'll revenge thee. 'I will not speak, 'tis some Witchcraft sure—I'll fly and call help from Heaven—What is it that pulls me back? I feel something oppress my breast, <stage>He throws the Picture down: and offers to out.</stage> my thoughts grow too great and powerful for Reason to com|mand: This Disorder is not unlike <hi>Phillora's</hi> love, thus she descri|bed him. O thou art a Prophetess, I fain would go, but without this strange new acquaintance my heart says no.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>He stoops, takes up the Picture, and gazes on't.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas the same my heart told me, I knew the Moor; O <hi>Pol|lidor,</hi> this was fortunate; to rescue the Princes Friends, he mindes me not. <hi>Pollidor,</hi> Brother, what is that his eyes are fix'd upon? a Pi|cture<hi>—Pollidor,</hi> Brother! Heaven, what ails he? 'Tis a Picture, and of a lively form, divinely grac'd. Do, start, and sigh, and <stage>She looks up|on the Pi|cture.</stage> change colour; that paleness shews the fright and allarm his heart has taken at those eyes: Heavens you are just; and Love, if ever a virgins heart given freely to thy power found grace, be propitious to my prayers, and feed the flame thou hast kindled in his frozen breast, till thy great name has fill'd his minde, and sick with love let him taste that bitter Cup he made me drink so deep of, insensi|ble of the pain he never felt—So, so, does your heart grow too big for your breast, while your ears are deaf, and your eyes blinde <stage>Pollidor <hi>sighs.</hi>
                           </stage> to all other objects? Yes, yes, talk on, she'll hear thee as thoudidst me. So, so, now thy minde has business of it's own<hi>—Pollidor,</hi> what, talking to thy self? <stage>She lays hold on him.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Phillora,</hi> Sister.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He throws the Picture down, and looks on his Sword.</hi> Phillora <hi>takes it up and hold it.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Ne're cast this from you, in vain thou think'st to be rid of it; a cunning and a great Master has graved it with a powerful hand in thy heart, try thy Philosophy now, forget her, <hi>Pollidor;</hi> See what <hi>Lethe</hi> can prevail; haste to <hi>Ga●etta;</hi> try if some new Figure, some fresh object can relieve thy minde; Does <hi>Pollidor</hi> now begin to finde there was something like Reason I said to day; O <hi>Pollidor,</hi> I was thy wonder to day, but thou wilt be mine to morrow, and thy own for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Enough, enough, <hi>Phillora,</hi> unless thy heart hunt revenge; remember 'twas but mistaken kindness; I then was a stranger to love, and therefore ought to be forgiven if I mistook thy passion; but what canst thou plead, after having made acquaintance with the God, if thou despise his Priest? Have but patience, and thou
<pb n="528" facs="265"/>
shalt reap all thy revenge, and with innocence of thy heart be pleased with it, and see thy Brother miserable even to pity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> 'tis far from me to seek Revenge against thee; yet I must confess I cannot be sorry to see thee a Lover, 'twill po|lish thy heart; 'twas too harsh, too severe before, a knotty rough|ness hid much of that beauty which now will shine when this passi|on shall illustrate it; Love will weed thy minde, and prune all that barbarous wildness that wanted sense for others pains; and thenthy awaked honour and armed thoughts will defend Love and thee against the world, and make thee, if it were possible, more welcome to <hi>Phillora.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Come near <hi>Phillora;</hi> Does not thy heart finde a decay of my love? Hast thou not mist, this hour, the diligent minde that was employed, solicitous for thy good onely?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Not I, me thinks <hi>Pollidor</hi> is as kinde as ever, and much more lovely in this passion than in all the reason thou wert so proud of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Why then I fear,—she, this divine figure remains alone <stage>
                              <hi>He takes the Picture from</hi> Phillora.</stage> still, though my heart be gone to finde her alone, as when the dead, cold hand of her murder'd Lover held her, and none but I, (wretched I) feel this fatal change; sure there's Magick in't, how could itbe made? my minde is ty'd to it, no other thoughts can finde a place; hunger and thirst I feel not but what the drought of longing love begets, and that (I fear) will lick up all the warm bloud that circles my heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, no more; let us first attend our safety, and at leisure seek a remedy for this ill, the Enemy pursues us close.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Tell not me of safety, an Enemy at my foot is not so pleasing a sight as this; though it be full of despair, 'tis a poisonous fire, <hi>Phil|lora,</hi> that's crept in at my eyes, it burns here, and the pain is beyond that which Poets describe Lust, Ambition, or Famine by. Yet my vain heart would fain promise it self something of happiness and pleasure from this strange thing. Victory nor Conquest is not half so welcome to my heart as this object; no such musick as the har|mony of this face; it has smooth'd my brow, and calm'd my heart; all forms of past affection, either of love or hate, are cancell'd, all the impressions of former joy or anger one sight of this has de|stroyed; those eyes have even melted my soul, and <hi>Pollidor</hi> lies ready to receive what form she'll impose.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>The Gods have heard my prayers since <hi>Pollidor</hi> is become a Lover, and I shall now hope my words will again be Reason.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>I love thee, <hi>Phillora,</hi> but thou art not half so handsome as this; Prithee do not leave me, lest I forget thee and my self too: for all the world will vanish from my minde beholding this; I have already lost my anger, and can forgive <hi>Leopoldo</hi> and the King, so she'll but smile. O that the divine hand that fram'd thee had but given thee a tongue too; 'tis all thou wantest to beget a worship, yet we'll carry it home, and set it upon <hi>Diana's</hi> Altar.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>All but Sacriledge I'll joyn in; take heed, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> how you incense the greater Deity; remember how the youthful God has reveng'd himself, remember; I say, and tremble.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="529" facs="265"/>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>It cannot be they should be true gods; flies play with 'em and worms destroy them; when they fall we are fain to raise them; I cannot worship my own creature, 'tis a contradiction to make my god; but suppose what thou believest, would <hi>Pallas, Uenus, Juno, Minerva,</hi> or the rest of that glorious number, affect such odd poor forms as we adore at home, and give to a mortal this divine frame? See, see if there be not mercy in her eyes, calm peace in that brow, innocence and justice in those fair hands; is there grace that men could wish, or women envy, that grows not in this face; is it not one it self, or rather all the Graces? and therefore kneel.—Thou <stage>They kneel and worship.</stage> art a Virgin <hi>Phillora,</hi> here lay thy hand upon this Virgin turfe, which never crooked Plow deflowred, and by you chaste spring, whose sacred streams with fruitful embraces circles you flowry Meads, never to worship any other of her sex, nor shall any but our selves have leave to sacrifice, lest we pollute her shrine with common vows, which I know will displease her, for she cannot be thus excellent but she must be particular, and constant too; for constancy and particularity shew the minds chastity; every fro|ward Girle taught by custom can keep her body chaste, but the mind is seldom so: vanity, <hi>Phillora,</hi> has a thousand ways to tempt a womans mind, and nothing like love and honour guard it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Should I now be as deaf to your reason as you were to mine, and deny all those truths of Love and Honour; what could <hi>Pollidor</hi> say when he should see me dote upon another face, and forget the Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>I'de say a woman that out-lives her love has out-lived her honour, and is from that minute to be esteemed but as her carcass, and the moving figure of such a perjur'd woman but the shadow of what she was, which some licens'd Demon has usurp'd to dispatch his business here on earth in; and such a looseness stains both the fame and figure, the guilt will cast such a poysonous stench that ages cannot waste it; like treason it taints the blood, the grave cannot hide the deformity; a broken heart will out-last the Mar|ble or the Epitaph.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>From thee I'll learn to love, be thou my guide; while thy great heart leads the way, who follows thee and Love can never stray.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid,</speaker>
                        <p>No <hi>Phillora,</hi> if I dye ere I see the substance of this sha|dow, I conjure thee bury me in this fatal place; and on my Tomb engrave my fate, that the world may know here was enterr'd the betwitch'd Forester; this was he that equall'd Eccho, and rival'd <hi>Narcissus,</hi> unless that goddess (who ere she were) that listned to <hi>Pig|maleons</hi> tears, would now look down on wretched <hi>Pollidor,</hi> and lend a life to this beloved shadow; Love let it be thy act, then find thy eyes, that with one sight of her I might pay thy bounty; but then take heed thy youthful deity do's not become my Rival, as she has done the gods in worship.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="530" facs="266"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leopoldo <hi>in his disguise, and finds</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phillora <hi>upon the place.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>This deliverance had all the favourable gods to friend; my disguise will hide me from the curious eye of all, since 'tis too poor and low to call the search of jealousie or envy upon me; but to think of saving my self till I know what fortune is befallen <hi>Phil|lora</hi> is a thought I cannot let enter my heart, possest with care and fear for her.—Ha! 'tis she; what sight is this? a man in her arms! <stage>
                              <hi>She is lean|ing upon her Brother, and looking upon a picture,</hi> Leopoldo <hi>discovers her.</hi>
                           </stage> they are kind too: see she leans upon his breast; I'll strike the vil|lain to the earth.—Sure 'tis some Phantasme: she refus'd my love when 'twas accompanied with the offers of sacred Hymen; and yet my soul tells me 'tis not possible there should be such a curse de|sign'd me as to love a false heart; they are blinded, sure, with their passion, else they could not chuse but see me; stay, he speaks to her; I'll observe, but fatally, if she be false; which my heart trem|bles to believe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh my <hi>Pollidor,</hi> keep it as the treasure of thy life; 'tis a jewel I would not part with for the world, the gods have sent it, keep it and love it; and now pursue thy fate, and heaven witness how much I love and pity <hi>Pollidor.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! my heart! what do I hear and see?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Keep it? yes, as I would my Reason or my Soul; this shall be my Buckler against all but thy fair self, whose friendship I'll prefer before Empire; and if thou smilest Fortune has no sting: these two lessons I have quickly learn'd, <hi>Phillora,</hi> the unfortunate, and the Lover; and they are two parts, if thou frown, that I must act for ever.—Love, thy Army would be numerous, couldst thou <stage>All the while he looks upon the picture.</stage> to the world shew this Commission; our passion must be happy for the matter and the end is noble, though the subject be yet a mystery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis her picture, she has given it him; my soul is on fire; and though I cannot hope to enjoy my love, my revenge is still in my power.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He goes behind them, and snatches the picture from</hi> Pollidór; Pol|lidor <hi>strikes him with his sword.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain, restore it; restore it upon thy life, and quickly. <stage>Phillora <hi>parts 'em</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>What art thou? why dost thou commit this outrage? who sent thee? why dost thou pursue him, and not regard my words?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Let me kill the villain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>The villain will not be kill'd, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, fond wretch; though that Jewel be by him prized above his life, consider what a vain thing 'tis in thee for a shadow thou knowest not thus to sacrifice thy self, and hazard the beco|ming one amongst the shadows; why dost thou frown upon him, and look'st with rage on one thou know'st not? what, is it for ava|rice thou would'st have it? deliver it, and take a better value then thy poor hopes can promise.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear <hi>Phillora,</hi> cease to sue to the villain, let me come;
<pb n="531" facs="266"/>
Death, dost thou think I shall not win when I play this game; where wilt thou venture my sword if I lose her?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I do not doubt thy success, but 'tis base for both of us to destroy him; and my love for <hi>Phollidor</hi> is such, I will not see him hazard that rich heart against a common sword.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>False and cruel.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Besides, 'tis some poor Souldier of the enemy, whose wants have engaged him, and for a reward he'll restore it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>No, fond Girle; I'll give thee my part of the earth first, and the short span of days the gods have left here I'll waste ere that villain shall boast his victory o're my Master that sent me hither.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Thy Master? who's thy Master? who sent thee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Love and Fortune, blind Guides I fear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>What's thy business hither; for heavens sake unriddle thy anger, speak; what wouldst thou have?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>And speak quickly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>From the Prince <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> who now lyes weeping out his drops of life in red tears on yonder hill; and even with his last breath mourns the loss of thee, if thou be'st <hi>Phillora,</hi> calling on thy name; for love of whom, slowly and unwillingly, he becomes a star, that art giving away thy self into anothers arms.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>The Prince <hi>Leopoldo</hi> dye! oh where! guide my desperate feet to that sad place, and thou shalt see how vain his fears are by the haste this heart will make to meet him; for charities sake, for the Princes sake, upon my knees I beg, restore his Picture, and let us go.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>What should I believe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>What villain gave the Prince his wounds? could he look upon him and strike?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>False and fair have a thousand ways to kill; and there is more danger to <hi>Leopoldo</hi> in those eyes then in his sword; whose frowns nor anger have any terror, 'tis an idle rage; and thy passion only dangerous to thy self.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Death, shall I be injur'd and despis'd too? sure I am not so weak an enemy as to be beat with words?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>They fight and are both wounded, yet she does all she can to part'em; in the mean time</hi> Almanzor <hi>and</hi> Roderigo <hi>come in with their companies, and seize on both</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh my fate, Fortune I defie thee now; dost thou grudge me the mourning for the Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Dog, treacherous dog, this odds made thee so brave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>See, Sir, here are two of those that rescued the Princess <hi>Bellamira,</hi> who in boys habit we surprized, together with <hi>Arcus</hi> the Moor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>And what are these?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>We are nothing, at least not worth telling now, ask thy self what we are; foolish fortune has given thee the power of disposing
<pb n="532" facs="267"/>
fools we are that might have look'd on and would not, and now pay for playing others Cards.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis yet my joy I served the Prince, and sav'd his Sister; and know, Tyrant, if my faithful heart could redeem him, I could know no misery after it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>What is he there?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>A villain, one of thy own train; but had not her fond pity sav'd him, I had paid his score.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>You took one prisoner before from me; but ere you get loose your self you shall pay both scores.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Roderigo,</hi> did'st ever see a more graceful couple; there is something of greatness in their looks I have not seen in persons of their rank. Prithee answer me calmly; what ye are this ha|bit speaks you are no Souldiers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>The unhappy issue of one chaste bed, the children of a poor Forester bred and born in these woods, led to this fatal day by chance, and kindness to this luckless Girle, who till this hour has always been all my care; but love, curious love has found my mind business of its own.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo, </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>Ha! what do I hear, Brother to my Love, and I wretched villain have ruin'd them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Convey them safe to <hi>Capua.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir; we'll see them safe, I warrant you.—Some|thing I must do like an enemy until I can prove a friend, this day's full of fate.—Come Sir, will you march?—Had not my jea|lousie blinded me I might have seen a Brother in his face, and the fatal figure in my Sisters Dream.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Pollidor, Phillora, Leopoldo, <hi>and two</hi> Souldiers</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Manent</hi> Almanzor, Roderigo, <hi>other Officers and Souldiers of his party:</hi> Clytus <hi>and his Officers stand on the other side of the Stage, and</hi> Clytus <hi>looks sullenly.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>At last the cloud's disperst; and now we may see clear, free and round about a full victory, such a sullen game I never plaid, and had they been of one mind, this had proved a black day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>How I abhor the very victory treason brings us!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>If <hi>Bellamira</hi> had not escaped, the whole work had here found an end; but if that scornful fair one fall into my hands she shall see how I can act her part, whom my anger and revenge pur|sues more now then my love did heretofore.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Highness is in passion, else this anger to a Lady of her birth and virtue is so unlike the rest of your character, I am con|fident you would not own it; for to me she stands much greater in esteem for that answer, then if she had shrunk with her fears and <stage>Leopoldo <hi>returns.</hi>
                           </stage> sudden change of fortune, and should have listned to your proposi|tions; for consider her part that was born Daughter to a King, now subject to an invading enemy, the destroyer of her Father, ruiner of her Country, to receive from him in the height of displea|sure and anguish of her mind a proposition seconded by force of arms; it had been strange if she should have sent a better answer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="533" facs="267"/>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>All these Arguments are against her; for she saw my kindness such, as when she was fallen into my power I offer'd from being a Subject to make her a Queen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>Subject? Sir, that's beyond your contract to make any of this Nation your Subjects.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it beyond the sword, <hi>Clytus?</hi> I know no other Law nor Contract.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes; and now in your greatest glory I dare tell you so; And know, there is not a man amongst us, but will fall upon those swords you owe this victory to, ere yield themselves your Subjects; You will find <hi>Naples</hi> scornes to acknowledge any other King then their own: And here, in the name of all those that sent me, whose Loyalty sixteen years banishment and oppression could not weary, no nor the virtue of those most generous Princes <hi>Bellamira,</hi> and <hi>Leo|poldo;</hi> whose miseries though we lament, yet they had not power to seduce our Loyalties; therefore do not hope to fright us into slavery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Clytus,</hi> you are in Passion, and too suddain with the Prince, and your fears most unreasonable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>That. Your answer will clear; Know, in the Name of them whose General I here stand, I again require performance of conditions. In the first place, the delivery of all prisoners into my hands; Then, that this night our young King be produced and crown'd; which Ceremony being past, your Highness will please to Command your Army to retire towards <hi>Calabria;</hi> where, with all conveniency which we shall provide, they may pass for <hi>Si|cily;</hi> and according to conditions leave to us our King and the quiet possession of all those Dominions, that belonged to his Royal Father, the unfortunate <hi>Ortho; Sicily</hi> being by us abandoned to your Highness as 'twas agreed; though I confess my Heart bleeds to think our ills had no other remedy, nor this diseased State could admit of no gentler cure then the hewing off these branches, as <hi>Leopoldo</hi> and <hi>Bellamira,</hi> from the royal stock to save the Tree.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Clytus,</hi> I have stood silent long, and wonder rather then Patience bred that Attention to this new kind of Language from you. Where's the Oppression, Treason, and Tyranny; The wrongs to gods and men; where's the usurper against whom your Flattery and dejected looks and folded Arms? These po|stures and these words were <hi>Clytus</hi> his, when he sought my aid; <hi>Clytus,</hi> there, strove to perswade we were appointed by Heaven the scourge of these mischiefs, and made it appear that Fate had named me in a Dream seven years since to your scornfull Princess; In which I was pointed at, and the whole successe of this warr most Prophetically foreseen; How often has thy Flattery called me that stranger that she saw land in that calm Evening; This, that forreign habit that kick'd up the dust in their faces? And see the King and Prince, all lost in that dust, the disaffected people. And now I know my strength, and see your Hearts, I will not march one foot farther, until the Princes and Castles are deliver'd to me as rewards of
<pb n="534" facs="268"/>
this victory; Nor shall you see your King till I think fit to trust you, lest he find you as false as I have done; which I shall be yet able to punish in your greatest Pride and strength; For the Prison|ers, poor and contemptible as they are, (for I know onely of two Shep-herds) yet since demanded thus unhandsomely, not one hair of their heads shall be deliver'd; nor dares <hi>Clytus</hi> fetch them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>Either produce the King, and perform the Articles you swore to, or we shall find a power will be too strong for perjury.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>Perjury! <stage>They both lay hold on their swords, but are parted by company.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Perjury.—Death, have we refus'd the Bro|ther of our King, to be usurp'd over and govern'd by a stranger? No, <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> if any stranger must be our Fate, thy Starr shall guide us; whose noble Breast, this day, I rob'd of his honour'd Order, and forc'd like a private Souldier to fight for his safety; yet then, had not thy odds rescued thee, or his noble Mind given a protection, thy proud Heart had found a Justice some worse Na|ture must pay; 'Twas he that gave thee thy Life; that Life thou so insultest with over the ruines of his Father, which (slave and Villain as I was, to joyn in laying those sad loads of grief upon his great Heart) I'll redeem, or die in the attempt, if you delay this night to produce the King. Your Answer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis here, double Traytor; here in this sword, and in <stage>Almanzor <hi>and</hi> Clytus <hi>draw.</hi>
                           </stage> the field, I'll make thee read it when 'tis written in thy blood.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>That Traytor, though Truth, shall cost thee dear; Perjur'd Prince.—March.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Clytus <hi>and his party.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven, thy Hand still! <hi>Clytus,</hi> my Soul forgives thee; Honest and gallant; and what I thought crime is but virtue in thee, and loyalty to thy Master; and I'll find a way to tell thee so if thou persist: This quarrel may give us power to strike once more for our Revenge;<hi>—Almanzor</hi>'s full of thoughts; this quarrel must be fa|tal, they have both too much Courage to bear such injuries as these.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>Now, Sir, has your passion had the full swinge are you deep enough in dangers? Have you Enemies enough? If not, we had best seek for more.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis better to know, then doubt of a foe; I saw him false from the first hour he had possession of the Castle; this is but pretence; A few wretched Prisoners, onely a pretence to pick a quarrel now the work's done; It was my curse to trust a Traytor; yet if we had not mist the Princes the Castles had been no losses.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, 'tis now no time to talk of why-nots; this night we must expect some attempt from them, their business is done, the King is slain, the Prince too, for ought we know, his Clothes and order being found upon the ground; the people too are armed in their defence, and expect we should produce their King; which abused hope We cannot expect they should forgive; and we are to believe this party that have defended themselves thus long against the King will never yield to our power by any argument but the Sword: Besides, you may gather from <hi>Clytus</hi> what the rest intend, whose Forces are drawn apart towards <hi>Naples,</hi>
                           <pb n="535" facs="268"/>
and those of <hi>Gaietta</hi> remain still upon the pass; and can if we op|press them, upon occasion, retreat or joyn when 'tis to ruine us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>What's to be done then? I am all rage; The Villain <hi>Clytus</hi> has rob'd me of all my hopes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>You must resolve to fight with one of them this Even|ing, whilst divided, else to morrow 'twill be a double business; if not, march immediately to <hi>Capua,</hi> secure the Harbour, and this night dispatch a Galley for <hi>Sicily</hi> for supplies, and therein send the prisoners; for I believe them of more worth then they appear, by the earnest demand of <hi>Clytus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>Give order then, that we may be ready to march. Fortune, if thou smil'st upon this Action I shall yet have time enough to make ready a Revenge for the Villain <hi>Clytus;</hi> whose falshood in a fatall hour has thrown me from all my hopes of Love and victory. <stage>
                              <hi>As</hi> Leopol|do <hi>goes out, be meets a</hi> Souldier <hi>coming in haste and stops.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldus.</speaker>
                        <p>This <hi>Clytus</hi> shall know.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>How now, the news!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Souldier.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, pursuing the Enemy in the wood I have lodged some persons of quality; who, by their lamentations for the King and Prince <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> I know must be of that party; Two of them are remarkable, a Satyr and a Moor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>Speak softly, tis they. The Princess <hi>Bellamira,</hi> I know by that Moor; <hi>Roderigo</hi> take a choice party and let us fly to this remedy: Fortune, I no sooner called upon thy name, but thy kind Deity has sent a medicine for my Mind, a cure for all my ills; Leade the way, and for this chance thy reward shall exceed thy hopes; Come, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> now we may smile again; <hi>Bellamira</hi> will weigh down the scales, and make our Revenge full.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>A few will do it, the quieter the better, for this wood is full of paths and caves, and there's no hunting of them unless we could do it by the scent like dogs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt all but</hi> Leopoldo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure some sullen star pursues this girl; I'll follow too, and make it sad to some.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Leopoldo.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Nigro, Ravack, Clytus, Cleon, <hi>and</hi> Souldiers.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nigro.</speaker>
                        <p>'TWas done like <hi>Clytus,</hi> and tomorrow we'll second thy words; let the men be well fed to night, and a Dona|tive distributed for this dayes service.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>My Children, <hi>Clytus,</hi> had they many wounds?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>No, nor any dangerous; opprest with multitude we took them, and they are now his Prisoners; But this night, I fear, they will be sent away, and the rather that I was earnest for their delivery; And I believe we are deceived all this while; for I am confident the delivery or discovery of our young King is beyond his power, and onely a pretence to engage the people.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nigro.</speaker>
                        <p>No matter, that pretence has done our work, and now</p>
                     </sp>
                     <gap unit="page" extent="2"/>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="538" facs="269"/>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>Calmly, <hi>Clytus,</hi> and resolved let us proceed: now we have the game in our hands take heed of rashness or security, which may be as dangerous as his despair; let us in, and resolve with the King what we shall do, and to whom, e're ye go, let me present you both; his pardon and blessing will prosper the work. Kings are their Countries Parents, and heaven never blest that people whom a good King curs'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>(A Scene representing a Cave.)</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bellamira, Fidelia, Philemon, Arcus, <hi>and</hi> Satyr.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
                        <p>MAdam, wee'l look out, if you please, and see what we can learn abroad.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Arcus <hi>and</hi> Philemon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Shee's lost, shee's lost, I'll eat no more; a curse on all their heads that fetch'd us from our quiet home.—Let me go, what <stage>Fidelia <hi>holds him.</hi>
                           </stage> are you to me, or I to you, I loathe your hated sights, 'tis your mis|chiefs we mourn, my dear Mistress lived quiet here till your impious visit; Innocence, peace, and Love fill'd every Circle of the Moon till you and mischief came and rob'd us of our peace; Wounded in mind and body, my Love, and her gentle Brother, rage like Dogs, by the Suns poyson stung, and rob'd of Reason, hunt out your dangers, and Death, I fear; and I that have but these poor Rags of Nature, See how I am torn with following you;—Hell on both your causes I have lost my love, and know not where to seek her, but here in my wounded mind; my heart has her still; would she had ne're stay'd beyond this fold; if she die I'll starve my self, I will, and poyson you; I will, by <hi>Pan</hi> I will, you shall not out-live my Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Arcus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Quick and silently into the Cave, for there are some en|tred the Wood; what they are I know not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll not go in, but stay and tell them where you are, un|less you give me my love, or shew me where you have hid her, that I may worship her grave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Shee's not dead, man, shee's in the Woods only, and to morrow we shall find 'em.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>To morrow? why 'tis not night yet; Cramps and Aches find me, and the Murrain eat my Flocks, if I will eat or sleep till I find her; all Night, and not know where my Love is?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Go in then, and defend these people who thou know'st she loves, for shee'll die if they be hurt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Shall we seek her when we have done? I'll not strike a Dog else.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>See they come, defend this pass, and then wee'll seek her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter into the Cave</hi> Bellamira <hi>and</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                     <pb n="539" facs="269"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, Roderigo <hi>and</hi> Souldiers, <hi>and set upon them; while</hi> Arcus <hi>and the</hi> Satyr <hi>are engaged, they force</hi> Philemon, <hi>and get into the Cave; The</hi> Satyr <hi>and the</hi> Souldier <hi>fight, the</hi> Satyr <hi>gets him down.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yield, and let me bind thee, or I'll pash thy Scull.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The</hi> Souldier <hi>thrusts at him while he speaks, and hurts him; he kills the</hi> Souldier, <hi>and takes his Sword.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
                        <p>So, so, follow me, and save the Princess; what, art thou lame?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>The Rogue has hurt me with this foolish thing; a Bee's sting is worse, and yet I am lame.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He lookes upon the Sword, and pricks himself with it, and starts. Exeunt</hi> Arcus <hi>and</hi> Satyr.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bellamira, <hi>and</hi> Fidelia, <hi>prisoners to the</hi> Souldiers <hi>that discovered where they were.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                        <p>NO resistance, but patiently expect what the prince com|mands, or you are dead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>What Prince, Villain? Either be a friend, or enemy; give us our Freedom, or with thy Sword perfect that Treachery thou hast begun with the worst of mischiefs; Kill us, any thing rather then be subject to the impious rage of that insolent Conquerour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leopoldo, <hi>in his disguise.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha, Comrade! where's the Prince? here are two of the birds I promised him, the rest are flown.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(Leopoldo <hi>looks about him.)</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>They are so, Traytor, that thus art armed with success; stare not, but defend thy self; Fly, Madam, to any safety; if this service prove successful, thank me hereafter; if not conceale me, what e're you see me do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Bellamira <hi>and</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam? 'Tis the Princess <hi>Bellamira,</hi> sure.—Villain, thou'lt live to repent this Act.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou shalt not, if I miss not my aim.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>(They fight, and</hi> Leopoldo <hi>kills him.)</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, 'tis enough; my faults are powerful, and Treason alone is weak, I am lost.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(He dies.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>This wretch had given up all our hopes to the Invador, had not my fate been above him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Souldier, which way went <hi>Roderigo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="540" facs="270"/>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>That way in pursuit of the Enemy,—Why not, in this disguise, strike him dead and secure all? why not? because 'tis base, and unworthy of <hi>Leopoldo;</hi> treachery has no Argument strong enough to justifie it, success cannot do it; I'll follow him, defie him, and as <hi>Leopoldo</hi> take a full revenge, or give him a perfect victory, <stage>
                              <hi>As</hi> Alman|zor <hi>goes out he meets the</hi> Souldiers <hi>bringing</hi> Bellamira.</stage>—Nay, then I strive against my Stars; Yield, <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> stoop to Fortune, War no longer against that froward Diety, bent to thy ruine; poor <hi>Bellamira,</hi> something I must do, and by appearing still a violent enemy may gain a power to serve her; Sir, do you not know this Prisoner? 'tis the Princess <hi>Bellamira,</hi> the same that the Shepherds took from us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis not possible, this the modest Princess, fighting in Breeches? sure 'tis one of her Pages.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>What I am is as heaven appoints, who has delivered me over to your barbarous power; what I was this morning is now no argument, since they are pleas'd to withdraw their blessings; yet in all conditions I can despise the insolent <hi>Almanzor,</hi> prince only in power, slave of Fortune, blest by chance, like her undeser|ving children, who claim neither by virtue nor merit what they hold.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>You are angry now, and I laugh; and since you would not be a Queen, try if you can avoid being a Slave; and all those graces of that Magick form which once I loved, all those Flowers of Youth and Beauty my hate shall look on, and see wither in a scorn'd servitude, under an envious and cruel Mistress, who will make my love to thee as great an affliction as thy scorn hath rendred it my heart; for she loves as violently as thou hatest, to whose re|venge I'll give my interest up.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>The same impious barbarous <hi>Almanzor</hi> still, upon whose power I'll look with scorn, it cannot be long liv'd; thou art too wicked to be long our Rod; for thy threats, they move me no more then thy promises; Thou knowest I would not sell my ho|nour for the first, nor be frighted from it by the last; for know, when I will be free, (which yet I will not be) 'tis not all thy guards can keep me; and to heighten thy rage, know, it is no cold frozen Na|ture, no aversion to Loves gentle passion, makes me despise thee; For never Virgins breast had more love in it, that had no more ho|nour then <hi>Bellamira;</hi> and I rejoyce to suffer for thy Rival, and he shall know it, that thy envious soul may gnaw thy heart, which, if thou lovest, 'twill do, when thou shalt see me die for him that's o're|come, and despise thee though a Conquerour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Away with her to the Castle, and upon your lives secure her, I shall have my time too; what success, <hi>Roderigo?</hi>
                           <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Roderigo.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Bellamira, <hi>and the</hi> Souldiers <hi>pulling her.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis in vain to hunt them; that <hi>Satyr</hi> and the Moor are a pair of Devils, stout, and subtle; I'll not undertake such another chase, for their skins; they are all flown, but whither I know not; only one boy, I left him crying and shaking in a bush.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="541" facs="270"/>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>That Boy we have, and with him all our hopes; that in Boys habit was the scornful <hi>Bellamira;</hi> and now <hi>Clytus,</hi> and his in|solent Abettors will stoop again, if my heart can be brought to re|concile it self to her, whose injurious words have again enraged it so that Ambition, Love, nor Interest can scarce make me dissemble my hatred of her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>If you be certain 'tis the Princess, away with her this night, or with the morning Floud, for <hi>Sicily,</hi> together with the rest of your Prisoners; leave me to make good <hi>Capua</hi> untill I hear from you; besides, when you and they are gone, they must treat; for to fight signifies nothing; for if they beat us (which is uncertain too) yet they advance not to their end; for <hi>Leopoldo</hi> being dead, and she next Heir, dissemble, flatter, swear you love, any thing to appease her minde, marry her and confirm your Conquest.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis resolv'd this night privately we'll depart, and in the <hi>interim</hi> order the affairs here to your direction.—Dissimulati|on be thou my Friend while I banish hence this idle passion Love, and make room for the more noble Ambition, thou Guide of Princes, Love, that precious nothing, that dear I know not what, that makes us finde a difference between a Mistress and other wo|men. Farewell for ever blinde unbodied Boy, that's proud to be|come both Poyson and Medicine to the minde, the wounder and the wound, where he can finde a faith; else an indifferent common cheap companion for all (but Death) from King to Beggar;— <stage>Points to his heart.</stage> Here he would have imposed Laws, here threatned Darts, unless I would fondly have worshipp'd him. Fool, that wert made the Slave of Nature! and so thou shalt still be to <hi>Almanzor</hi> when ere thou dar'st appear charm'd by my scorn, and this thy perfect Cha|racter; till thou hast tam'd her minde, and till hers be kinde, in spight of all thy Power or Art, Ambition or Revenge, not Love shall fill my heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>[And the onely one of this Act.]</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leopoldo, <hi>solus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>TOo late I finde my Errour, poyson'd with a dangerous passion, Jealousie, foolishly seeking what it would not finde; the Curse of all the Gods are wrapt in his black thoughts, that yields to that Enemy of man, a Curse both in the Root and Fruit: First he blinded my Reason, against which Reason he made me doubt my Love; Then my eyes, which else must have seen a Brother in his face, and in this cloud made me lose my self; and then to finde a new doubt, another misery. This Picture Picture of my Sister found by him, lost by I know not who, but given by some-body; I would not doubt <hi>Bellamira,</hi> yet I am sure
<pb n="542" facs="271"/>
'tis hers; neither she nor my eyes are disguised; there is some my|stery as well as fate abroad to day; I'll have patience until I speak with her, nor will I be discover'd until I be satisfi'd whose this Pi|cture is. But see how my divided minde forgets her business, and talks away that little time that rests for their safety; for ere I can pursue my Design, and return from <hi>Clytus</hi> his Quarter, (whose faith I now admire and forgive) 'twill be too late to use his friend|ship; for the Prince is resolved with his Prisoners this night to escape for <hi>Sicily;</hi> nor is there a way left to prevent this mischief, unless I take advantage of that trust that this Disguise has given me, and privately arm my friends, so to surprize the Guard and escape to <hi>Clytus</hi> his Quarter: this is our last and desperate hope, and this I must put in execution after the enjoying of some few minutes happiness, thus unknown informing my self of that dear knowledge my heart labours withall, and this benefit my misery will afford me; for being thus levell'd by fortune I may be just to that excellence my better days could neither enjoy nor reward without blushing; such and so cruel are the Laws we our selves are bound to; and though we can give Laws to others, we are yet Slaves to custome and opinion, condemn'd to starve our mindes upon the barren heart of some person onely great in birth, and forbid to taste the full blessings this poor Maid is blest with—Here they are within this place, the darkness will assist my Design, in hearing unseen what they say; and when I will I can by the be|nefit of this light discover my self.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He turns his dark Lanthorn.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The Scene opens and discovers Prison, where</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phil|lora <hi>appear next the Stage chained to a Ring fastned to the ground upon the other side of the Prison, and in a darker part of the Sco●e lies</hi> Palantus <hi>chained behinde them in the dark,</hi> Bellamira <hi>chained, and afar off in prospective other Prisoners and dead Carcases.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Good Heaven, do I lament any thing of Prison? Is not all the World Prison now, and a Prison equal to a Throne when he is gone? O <hi>Pollidor,</hi> he's dead, lost for ever, for ever, that's the great wound Death gives; let that thought excuse my immoderate grief, and awake the guilt that has long slept in thy vengeful minde: Thy Prince is fallen, dead, neglected, and unmourn'd, and thy heart afflicts it self for a Picture, the lost shadow of thou know'st not what, while the best of Princes without a tear from thy eye fills the number, and is by treacherous odds become a shadow: O ye Gods, why should mankinde, wretched mankinde, desire to stay after him, and wither out some few Ages here; why should the World out-last that gallant Prince, whose death has left it but a Carcass?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Your passion onely tells you he is dead, for none saw him fall; 'tis onely in your fears he's lost, and most unjustly you accuse me now of hate; for though I lov'd not the name of <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> yet Heaven witness I now adore the man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="543" facs="271"/>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee peace, and let me love once, and but once; even <hi>Pollidor</hi> can deceive my heart when the Prince is concern'd. Dis|sembler, my fears and thy wishes are built upon the same unlucky ground—See, fond Youth, see the royal distinction of the brave <hi>Leopoldo</hi> from other men, behold his ancient Order, the Chain too <stage>She shews his Order.</stage> I saw him wear this day; but where is the sacred breast, upon which as upon holyest Altars these consecrated Relicks hung? O <hi>Pollidor, Pollidor,</hi> that Shrine Murder and Treason have ruin'd, and with prophane hands thrown down a Temple built by and dedicated to all the Gods,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>All the Gods forbid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Now you and my Father may smile, your hatred has found a malitious power to joyn with your wishes; try if all your Sacrifices or penitent prayers can make such a Prince, but I am certain thou hast lost a Friend; for do not think it possible I can be flatter'd to out-live him? and though I cannot hate thee, I can hardly forgive thy hatred to the Prince, whom I shall make haste to follow; Thou art but gone before to prepare the way; nor will I stay here but to dispatch thy business upon earth, and then <hi>Pollidor</hi> thou shalt see me follow; but I talk too much, untill it be time to justifie to the world how much I lov'd; here I will mourn my loss till I can finde a handsome when, and glorious how to follow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>When that time appears, <hi>Pollidor</hi> will quit himself of this unkinde thought, and thou shalt finde me ambitious to have it said, I fell in <hi>Leopoldo</hi>'s cause.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Such a Monument, (though I love my Brother) I would live to see thee raise thy self and the great <hi>Leopoldo:</hi> And if thou dy'st as handsomely for him as I would have liv'd faithfull to him, who pities thee, or weeps upon thy Grave, are no Friends to ei|ther: but these are words, and he's dead. Ye Gods, who would have lost so glorious an Enemy? 'T was worth thy care to have preserv'd him, though thou didst not love him thou shouldst have kept him for a Pattern, his Virtues were worth thy Love and Envy; though he were bornn to thy Hate; Now thou hast yielded to his fortune; for though <hi>Leopoldo</hi> be dead and fall'n under thy wish, not under thy sword, a gallant man would not have lost such an occasion to have made himself known in his own Revenge: now the world will say, My Brother hated a Prince he could neither love, imitate, nor overcome.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven, can I hear this and not relieve her? I must inter|rupt this grief, 'tis most unjust to let them be miserable for me that am the happiest man that ever Fortune struck at and mist, How I scorn her poor malice! Prouder of these two Friends than all those airy gifts she has call'd back.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Who these should be I cannot imagine; that so confidently avow their love and hate to my Brother; if it be dissembl'd it is done to the life; 'tis some cunning highly wicked, or else the kind|est that our party has this day ruin'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>What Picture's that they rave of? This discourse confounds
<pb n="544" facs="272"/>
my thoughts; a Brother and a Sister; by their discourse she loves the Prince too: I will not yet be known, perhaps they'll be free, and I may know more by chance than by question what that Picture is, the loss of mine makes these Chains heavy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, start not, I beseech you, nor despise the Proposi|tion <stage>Leopoldo <hi>steps to his Sister.</hi>
                           </stage> I shall make for your safety, because you see me poor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure thou art mistaken, dost thou not see thy Errour?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>When 'tis to serve you, Madam, my confidence I hope will finde your pardon, else, miserable as I am, I would die sooner than betray the divine <hi>Bellamira.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Speak softly then what 'tis you design.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>First be pleas'd to know 'twas I redeem'd your Highness, the Souldier that desir'd to be conceal'd, which service I should not remember but to beget your faith. Know the Tyrant boasts your captivity, and vows such miseries as shall make you proud of his embraces ere he'll embrace them; this wak'd my heart; and could my single revenge have serv'd you, upon the place I had struck him to the earth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure I dream, whence comes this gentle sound? and how came so much humanity to get a power in this barbarous place, where Lust, Force, and Treason reigns! How came thy charity to get admittance hither!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Leave to wonder, Madam, and give faith to m●, for our time's short, and 'tis not ev'ry hour I can serve you in: This night you must prepare to follow my directions, and attempt your escape; for you are with the morning tide design'd for <hi>Sicily,</hi> where you must prepare to suffer what the Conquerour shall im|pose.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Wonder not, I prithee, at my want of faith; I have been so little acquainted with civil language since I came into his power that yours amazes me; I have this day received nothing but Injuries from Men and Elements, abandon'd by all, and treated as the scandal and infamy of our Sex, like some Vagabond that had stray'd from Honour and Virtue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Give me leave to remove even the greatest of your griefs; the King and Prince live, I speak a truth as great as your joy; <hi>Palantus</hi> too is safe, and your fellow Prisoner here, and those two you heard discourse even now are Friends to whom your Highness owes much; they are yet but private virtues, but the world shall know them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou art my good Angel sure; May I know who thou art? Certainly I will not betray thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Hereafter, Madam, you shall; let but this night pass, and trust me, and Heaven curse me if I betray you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>He sighs, sure he has been miserable himself he is so sensible of mine, and now some heavy grief hangs upon his heart; I am curious to know what kinde of misery can make this poor Souldier sad.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="545" facs="272"/>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>What kind of misery? alas, Madam, miseries have not one sting I have not felt, and her bitterest roots are now my food.—Nature cannot be disguis'd, though my body be.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He weeps.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>He weeps; what are the miseries that thus wound thy soul? for tears are her blood; didst thou ever love unfor|tunately?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Never, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Canst thou have wit, courage, kind Nature, and a soft soul, and yet not love? 'tis strange that Love and Honour should be strangers; without love all thy vertues are not thine, they're but Lodgers, Inmate excellencies, and may be seduced, if not ally'd to thy heart by Love; therefore leave to hide thy mind and for|tune from me; which I know must have something greater in't then thy words or condition speaks; dare you venture your life rather then your grief?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Take all the secrets of my heart, I love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>How by instinct I found his grief! humanity and ci|vility but guide to Love, whose paths all that have honour tread.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Once, and but once, Madam; and therefore I may say I lov'd; though my eyes have much beauty seen written in her best characters, yet in all my days I was never pleas'd with more then one story of that fair volumn, and my griefs are now the fear I should lose the Book ere I have read it out; for I have but newly begun the History of her face; but I lose time when 'tis most pre|cious, because 'tis yours; for know, Madam, I must retire to the Guard, of which I am one, but 'tis to serve you; as soon as I have contrived your safety I shall give your Highness notice; in the mean time I'll discover, by this light, who are your fellow prisoners; but pray be pleas'd to conceal your self till I give the sign.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Leopoldo <hi>walks from</hi> Bellamira <hi>toward the rest of the prisoners.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure this soul's mistaken; it cannot be such a princely mind should be hid and buried in a Cottage, nor fate let so much honour grow so neer the earth, while a Prince declines beneath the mean'st wretch, and becomes a slave to his passion, and submits to the worst of ills, a barbarous lust, a sin that shame and repentance attend here, and horrour hereafter.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Leopoldo <hi>opens his dark-lanthorn, they all know and gaze upon him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! 'tis he, the same Villain that snatch'd my Picture.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>His hated sight brings back my anger; oh that I were free, to revenge the Prince upon thy sinful head.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Good gods, what do I see, protect me heaven; 'tis the same figure, my heart fails me, the Shepherdess is there too; Oh Fate, Fate, there is no resisting thy decrees.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="546" facs="273"/>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Thanks for this friendly light, now I shall know the Au|thors of that discourse my soul so much listned to; Ha! 'tis the young Shepherdess, I'll speak to her, I'me sure she's a friend. Fellows in misery, and friends to <hi>Leopold,</hi> such I know you are by your discourse, and to such the name of <hi>Palantus</hi> is not unknown; and gentle Maid, by all thy heart loves best I conjure you tell me what Picture 'tis you lament the loss of; for I, wretched I, have this day in battle lost all my soul doted upon; for my royal Master and his noble Family are this day ruin'd, and in this misery I have lost the jewel of my heart; 'twas a Legacy my Master gave me with his dying hands; 'twas a little Picture, but of the greatest vir|tue living, if heaven have spar'd her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Palantus</hi> nor his Master I know not, nor his Picture; but if 'twere that I found to day in the Wood, heaven and earth should meet e're I'de part with it to any hand, but death's; his cold Com|mission should only force it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis rudely answer'd, yet if there were no other difficulty in regaining it then thy barbarous mind can oppose.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>You promise your self too fast the victory o're him that would complain neither of you nor fortune, if he lost it when the sword could win it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee, who art thou that talk'st thus in chains?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>One that neither knows nor fears thee; one that will neither do nor take an injury.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee, who art thou?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>No more nor less then thou art, an honest man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll inform thee what he is; we are two Plants that grew together from the same root in these peaceful Woods; we are two that till this day never saw an enemy; but who can be friends to those that hate the Prince, whose cause drew our swords? and though we be crush'd thus with thy Masters ruine; yet I wish there were no more danger in either of your fortunes then you two will bring upon each other. For know, <hi>Palantus,</hi> thy faith to thy dead Master is admir'd by all; but none values it more then <hi>Phillora,</hi> a name yet a stranger to thee and the world, being sprung this day in blood; know it's the same un|fortunate Girle thou saw'st this day in the Forest; and this whom thou threatnest is my Brother; what he and I have done this day to appear friends to those royal names, <hi>Leopoldo</hi> and <hi>Bella|mira,</hi> is not unknown, though yet never blest with one sight of them but in their miseries, which are but the ashes of his greatness; let not then a shadow divide such friends; though my Brother love the Picture, yet he has justice as well as love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Gentle Maid, forgive the passion my love and misery be|got; and to you, Sir, the ignorance of whom I answer'd will excuse the wildness of my words; pray let us calmly inquire by what ac|cident your Brother came to find and lose that Picture, by which I can easily collect whether it be mine or no.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray describe yours, that will inform us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="547" facs="273"/>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Mine was in a box of gold, enamell'd with Phillamorte and black (the sad colours that are worn by me forlorn) the Cypher two <hi>xx</hi> crost, within a figure of an armed <hi>Pallas;</hi> the hair brown, the forehead calm and full of peace; <hi>Juno</hi>'s eyes, fair and full of mercy; but I want Poetry to express her beauty, to which the gods have give a minde equal to all she bows to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis the same my Brother found in the Wood, and that bar|barous person there snatch'd it from him; and e're we could regain it again the enemy surpriz'd us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Which is he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>That, there he stands; but if ere I get a free|dom I'll make thee repent it at as sad a rate as I lament the loss now.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain, restore my Picture, or thou'lt find my chains too weak to hold me from thy throat; 'tis the same, now I see him I know the Perriwig and clothes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>You wrong me, I never took it from you, nor ever saw you before.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain and Traytor, thou ly'st; and were I loose I'de make thee acknowledge it in thy hearts blood; I would I could look the slave dead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>You are angry, and I must laugh at it; look here's the Picture you have lost; I have it and I will keep it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou dar'st as soon drink poyson; and as safe either of you may do it when I am free.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No more of this rage; cease to injure a man you know not, and despise not a man you have never proved; your loves are nobler far then your hatreds can be; your love has a gal|lant cause, your hatred a meer imagin'd one; for a painted Card the curious thieft of an Artist's eye; besides, we know <hi>Pallantus</hi> dares as much as any man; and therefore he should not talk; and all honest men dare any thing that's just; and he that will more then is just is a bolder man then <hi>Pol|lidor.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Excellent Maid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Forgive me gentle Maid, and I have done; and now I turn to thee, and calmly I conjure thee by a Souldiers honour, give it the person thou took'st it from.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Neither of your two threats nor prayers shall force it from me; yet such a power those eyes have over me, that you shall command it for one kiss of your fair hand; dispose of it as you please; and let me stand the fury of their displeasure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Gentle Souldier, give it to my Brother; thou took'st it from him, and with it all his peace of mind; justice is on his side, for I saw thee snatch it from him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Leopoldo <hi>kisses her hand, and gives her the picture.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>There, dispose of it as you please.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, for an hours freedom, and a sword to dispute this right.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>You shall have both, Sir; and be asham'd of your threats
<pb n="548" facs="274"/>
too ere long; fear not, I have laid up your lye for you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis the same; look <hi>Phillora,</hi> here's our better Angel come again; so, now I defie Fortune and all her falshood; frown on, here's my peace which I'll not give for all thy smiles; how I love my eyes now, better then I did my hands before! they faithfully held their hold, while these like cowards let thee go; 'tis the no|blest sense of any, and informs the knowing soul, makes acquain|tance betwixt us and the great works of heaven, and obliges our hearts more then all the rest; see how it feasts my mind with these thin colours only! how gracefull too the eye is! what it borrows the tongue and heart pays; how just and innocent the eye is! it never wrongs in conversation, nor withers one flower in this Gar|den; she fills her self, and yet leaves no one beauty less for her de|light: Now, <hi>Phillora,</hi> my soul feeds upon this divine object, and yet neither stains nor begets a blush; but, oh my fears! who can this be? that thought lies heavy upon my soul, and when 'tis known how to be won; were she to be fought for, I would not doubt my fate; but this gentle sex must be perswaded and flat|te●'d from their freedom; and for me, a rude Woodman, bred in these Forests, where shall I finde soft words to speak my griefs, and rock her gentle mind a sleep; while her soul listens to the story of my Love and misery; rough as my life I fear she'll think my nature too, and tremble at the thought of our conversation, and fly my embraces.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> these are not thy faults; <hi>Pollidor</hi> was never barbarous, rough and cruel are not <hi>Pollidor</hi>'s crimes; that that stains thy heart was want of love; who else might promise to him|self success in all that honour can be engaged in: be therefore a Lo|ver, and that powerful deity will teach thee how to conquer all those doubts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Be a Lover! how like a young Lover thou speakest! can all that would be Lovers? no <hi>Phillora,</hi> Love puts nothing to the question that God moves in commands; why else do's this shadow bind me? which I can thus throw from me; but how can I remove that that's figur'd in my mind? no, no; I may snarle and be angry, like a Wolf in the toil, but 'tis too late; the Hunter's come, and I am now his prey; yet if I could but know who I love, and see it possible to be believed how much I love, I should not repine at the price I pay for her faith: But alas! I catch at air, and my love is spent on shadows; and when I find it more real I fear my despair must encrease too; for if she be mortal she's some eminent person sure, and where shall I compass proud titles to heap upon her, to raise her name above the people, to please her vanity, when they shall wonder and reverence as she passes by? where's that wealth and jewels whose envied worth and charming beauty may affect and emu|late her bright eyes? had I a Scepter, whose power (like <hi>Leopoldo)</hi> I might throw at her feet, and like him to <hi>Phillora</hi> by such a service speak my love, then I might hope: but alas! all I have to plead is love; and all I can do for her is to love her;
<pb n="549" facs="274"/>
and what is that to her? when I shall urge it, she'll say, who do's not? what then is my love in order to my happiness, till she loves too, but idle air, lost and forgot like the found that breath'd it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>What is love? why, it is sent thy punishment; a re|venge that his Deity has taken for being so cruel to my passion; and see if thou hast not already forgotten my griefs, negligent of the misery I suffer for fear of the Princes danger, only mind|ful of thy own pleasure; and canst thou (unkind) hope I should joyn in thy loy, while thou art so negligent of my sadness? no <hi>Pollidor,</hi> first thou shalt taste my grief; what if she be dead thou lovest?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! what hast thou said?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Dead, as <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> fallen under some wicked hatred. Suppose murther and treason tearing in pieces that noble form, and <hi>Pollidor</hi> looking on, held back by a Sisters envy only; what thinks <hi>Pollidor,</hi> could my reason hold him? could he be perswaded to look on, and not draw his sword to rescue her? thou art silent now, this was thy Sisters case to day, when thou, unkind, re|fused'st to lend a hand, or suffer me to go to serve the Prince; and see how the gods have reveng'd my quarrel; and thou that couldst not be perswaded to love the best of things, <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> now dot'st upon the least of things, a shadow of thou know'st not whom, who perhaps is dead for love of another.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Dead! oh <hi>Phillora,</hi> that doubt has struck me to the soul; pale horrour fills my mind; the tapers of my eyes grow dark; struck with that fear they grow drowsie.—If thou be'st <stage>He looks on the picture when he speaks.</stage> dead may the clouds grow hard, and the seasons be shufled again into Chaos, and destroy the seeds of nature; if thou be'st dead let the spring no more prove a common cradle, but with false concep|tion become their fatal tomb.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Who this should be that thus in shadows walks, and wounds the hearts of men, I cannot guess that know none but my self of all our sex; nor will not doubt my Brothers fortune if she grow not without the reach of honour; but if thy star be placed in a region as high as mine, then we'll sigh, and mourn, and dye, and leave to the world the sad story of our Tragedy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas <hi>Phillora,</hi> death is the only thing that an honest man ought not to fear; nor did I ever apprehend him; but in the per|sons of them I loved their dangers make him dreadful; 'tis not these chains, nor thus to be lost in a croud, or buried in a dungeon, frights me; 'tis fear of this and thy fate that wounds me; for I am certain we cannot dye forgotten, we are not worse then Plants. Shall I believe <hi>Phillora</hi> and <hi>Pollidor</hi> can when they perish be|come lesse then Herbs and Roots? they by dying lose nei|ther kinde nor vertue; nay the ashes of some things my Father says are medicinable; and death sure cannot so quench fame or virtue, but some that have virtuous minds will preserve our story, whose fortune will finde pity, though there be few to imitate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="550" facs="275"/>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet my Soul is sick with thoughts that we must languish and wither here, then die oppress'd in the dark, and go I know not whither; and if not forgotten our selves, yet ig|norant of what Fates our Friends suffer; These, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> are the bitter wounds that strike before death, and wound deeper then death it self.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis he, but how to believe him or Fate I know not; one of the two deceive me; seven years I have loved his shadow, and now no sooner find him but he's lost beyond redemption; his shadow nor his obscure birth are not so impossible to my Fate, <stage>She speaks to her self.</stage> as his Love of another; can it be that I should be so curs'd, to dote upon a man below me, and be despis'd too? Heavens make him worthy of my Love, or me worthy of your care.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Phillora,</hi> all other thoughts have given place to this great one; this deare object of mine Eyes and Heart I cannot part with, nor divide from my Mind; <hi>Phillora</hi> was, but this is now her business; A thousand kisses I'll give each day to this pale shrine, <stage>He kisses the Picture.</stage> while Love and Grief will lend me life.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, as thou hast Honour, hold; and prophane not that picture with thy Lips; all but that I can suffer, till kinder Fate will give me leave to dispute my right.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Not kiss it for fear of thee? Yes, and die upon it. <stage>Kisses it again.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>You will, wretch? I shall make thee live to know that Princess is to be kneel'd to, and not be approach'd but with sa|crifice of thy life; For know, (to thy despair) 'tis the Princess <hi>Bellamira</hi>'s picture that thy lustful Lips have thus prophan'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>aside.</hi> Ha! what sayes he? my Picture!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>Does your Soul shrink at the name of her? Wretch, <stage>Phillora <hi>and</hi> Pollidor <hi>gaze upon the Picture.</hi>
                           </stage> when thou shalt see her Eyes thy Heart will turn to ashes for this Insolence; and thy proud thoughts find an humbler Altar to offer thy sawcy flames at then thy Princess Breast.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>The Princess <hi>Bellamira!</hi> Oh <hi>Pollidor,</hi> our Fates are a|kin still; and 'tis my joy we fell from a height fit for Princes to aspire unto: Great and noble (though unhappy) were our Loves; But if she be that gallant person Fame speaks her, how came you by her Picture? <hi>Palantus</hi> is her Subject as well as <hi>Pollidor,</hi> and all such are set at equal distances in Honour; Any thing that's a Gentleman is as near this hope as <hi>Palantus;</hi> Did she give you this Picture?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>She give it me! no, fond Girl; she has a Soul of ano|ther temper, tis a Jewel of a double value as 'tis hers; the greatest wealth of my Heart that never loved ought but her, though I ne|ver yet durst tell her so: But with care and fear kept diligent watch to hide my passion, as thy fond Brother has done to pub|lish his.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>If she did not give it, by what right can you pretend to it more then my Brother?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>By my Royal Masters Bounty; who this day when he fell in my arms (full of age and wounds) from his Breast he pluck'd that Jewel and gave it me, with his commands to wear it as his
<pb n="551" facs="275"/>
last favour, a present fit for my hopes, that never durst aim at more then her shadow, too well acquainted with her generous Mind; whose royal branches will never bear such low fruit as my Love that was born her slave. Her Brother too, (to whom thou hast avowed hate) my God-like Master; A Prince whose great Soul has still been my pattern, and I must die ere I can imitate; whose kindness still kept me warm in my Royal Masters bosome, and honour'd me with his trusts too; His Mind never stayn'd with jealous thoughts of my greatness with the King, which are the great ties upon my Heart, not to abuse their favour as the un|grateful, ambitious pretentions of a slave; But here my Breast has worn in secret that fire whose grief was known onely to one as unhappy as my self, whom I lament no less then I love the other.— <stage>
                              <hi>He speaks to</hi> Leopoldo <hi>as a Souldier Enemy.</hi>
                           </stage> And now I beg from thee, for that royal families sake, be so just to thy King and Princess, as to redeem from that rude hand those sacred reliques; See how he hath stain'd it with his hot breath! Thy hands are loose; or but release mine, and I'll tear the figure from his Heart too. Good gods, I alwayes kneel'd to it, and had thy Soul been fill'd with Honour thou would'st sooner have kiss'd the Plague then have prophan'd it thus.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis Truth he sayes, my Heart condemns me. Here, <hi>Souldier,</hi> prithee carry it to him, not for fear of thee, but her; <stage>Pollidor <hi>is sad and full of thoughts all this while</hi>
                           </stage> such reverence and such fear as we pay the gods her name has bred here, which is the truest Valour: And here I confess my self a young and ignorant Lover, take it and forgive me; take it and be a friend to him that will dote upon thee for loving that Princess with so much more gallantry then himself; Yet you nor she ought to be angry with me for not finding a way I never trod before; The is the first time I ever saw any thing better my self; we are two, a Brother and a Sister, that have loved each other with as much Innocency and Passion as you can boast; and yet we kiss when we love most. <stage>Leopoldo <hi>gives</hi> Palan|tus <hi>the pi|cture.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>Now can I scarce resolve to take it, his Heart has high sense of Honour; How rude, and how calm, in one minute! would I had some of that power again that I lost this day but to serve thee with, that all the world might wonder at the Friendship of us Rivals in a desperate Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Phillora,</hi> thou sett'st out first, but I shall overtake thee, if not over-run thee; for my Heart is wounded, I hope, to death, with this new kind of grief.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>If we out-live this misfortune thou shalt be my friend; the Brother that lay in the same womb with me shall not be pre|fer'd before thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven! thy hand is working, and as invincibly as fatally.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Pollidor,</hi> dear as my Souls bliss, leave to stab my Heart with these desperate groans; Look up, or else farewel; do not think to go and leave me behind; We are both miserable, the same cause too, and all our joyes were of kin; we are ally'd in our miseries too, and we will die Brother and Sister; I am now
<pb n="552" facs="276"/>
collected, and can chide that passion that accus'd thee even now, and thus kiss those Eyes whose dear light is my Hearts fire; Oh <hi>Pollidor,</hi> thy tears have mortal poyson in them, Farewell; The gods call, and by a thousand wayes becken us to come; and to refuse their summons would look rude in us that have Honour and Peace of Mind gone before to make our way. Oh <hi>Pollidor,</hi> we must part, forc'd by a sullen Fate, and broken heart; Love, and the Prince, give fatal wounds.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[She swoons.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Phillora!</hi> Sister! Oh ye gods, spare this poor Girle, and take a stubborn heart; Oh, she's gone! help, as you have charity, some water, fetch some water.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven, and all good things forbid this early mourning for such virtue in the bud; unkind frost, to nip so soon the fairest Rose that Nature ever boasted. Art, thy Envy has destroy'd her, because thou could'st not imitate her Excellency. She breathes; Oh look up, gentle <hi>Phillora,</hi> and hear thy Prince conjure thy Soul; if Love be her errand, bid her stay; <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> thy <hi>Leopoldo</hi> calls her back; for if thou dyest thou hast lost thy way, and to find <hi>Le|opoldo,</hi> stay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid. Bellam. Palant.</speaker>
                        <p>Leopoldo!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Shep-herd, <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                           <stage>Leopoldo <hi>discovers himself.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Leopoldo!</hi> Sure I heard that name; that voice had a power to call me from my Grave; But why does <hi>Pollidor</hi> abuse his Sister, does he take delight to see her miserable?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Hence all thoughts of low fears, this cloud I thus dis|perse; See, Gentle Maid, behold thy <hi>Leopoldo.—</hi>Oh thou strangely Excellent, above the merit or weak faith of dull men; whose <stage>Leopoldo <hi>puts off his Souldiers clothes.</hi>
                           </stage> story will make past Histories blush, and shrink their narrow fame into nothing, when thy faith and excellency is known; And I blush to think how much I owe thy Virtue, and how little Fortune has left me to pay thee with.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis he, 'tis the Prince; Oh let me kneel to you, Sir; why does your noble heart thus stoop to save a piece of earth, whose infection you ought to shun?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>See, kind Fortune has thrown me down from that greatness that divided us last, onely to make me capable of thy Friendship now; And when I wish my self greater then <hi>Phillora,</hi> may Treason find me; Here is perfect happiness, this is full joy; for what is joy (gentle Maid) but hope strip'd from our fears, that hung like rags upon them and darkened their Beauties?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>My Brother! Then the gods are careful of poor <hi>Bel|lamira.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>If my Love be welcome here, but thy safety I have no wish in store.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Welcome, Sir, as winters sun, or summers shade, wel|come as your own wishes, welcome as your safety to my Heart, that loves and fear'd you were betray'd; Oh give me leave to kneel, and in silence at your feet weep out our joyes which are so surprising I want words to express, and am fain to use these Em|blems of grief (my tears) to utter it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="553" facs="276"/>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>The prince <hi>Leopoldo;</hi> good heaven where was my mind!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>From your Brother I beg forgiveness, for taking his pi|cture; jealous, I confess, he had too much Interest in the Excellent <hi>Phillora;</hi> for finding her in his Arms, the sight blinded me so I could not discern the Brother in his face; Thus love is pleas'd to Triumph still in afflicting our minds with unreasonable hopes, sometimes, and other some with as idle fears. And now, <hi>Pal|lantus,</hi> can you accuse me for having robb'd you of your Pi|cture? but I can reconcile all; for I believe the same Souldiers that took me robb'd you, and in the wood spoil'd me of such Jewels as I had about me, for which they quarrel'd in the divi|sion; The advantage I took hold of, and slew them, and then took one of their habits to save my self, and serve my friends, which you are; who I must now acquaint with the happy news; the King lives, found and known most miraculously by your Fa|ther the old Forester, who knew his Signet upon his finger; the rest <stage>
                              <hi>Points to</hi> Pollidor.</stage> of our friends, I hope, are escaped; for I hear of no other Prisoners but our selves.—And by this my Sister, I hope, believes I am a <stage>Steps to his Sister.</stage> Lover; however I know she is dear <hi>Bellamira.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                        <p>The Princess <hi>Bellamira!</hi> is she a prisoner too?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear <hi>Bellamira,</hi> hide not thy face; let us resolve like our selves, and Act those decrees with honour, and leave the rest to the gods; for we see how little we can command our own, or rule others fortunes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>This was the Shepherd that rescued me, and saved my brother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(Leopoldo <hi>looses his Sister, and brings her towards the Company.)</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis the Princess; then, oh, be dumb, for ever dumb, since thy guilty tongue has betray'd thy heart.—Yes, Madam, 'twas my fortune, and the only grace that she ever shewed me, when she gave me power to save the Prince; and if she will let me die for your Highness, I have all my wishes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>I pray, Sir, quarrel not with Fortune; me-thinks you owe her much, and are still likely to be in her debt for more.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The prince looses all their chains;</hi> Phillora <hi>goes to the princess, and kneels.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, Madam, upon my knees I fall, and beg a pardon for our unreasonable hatred, which our Ignorance was only guilty of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Kneel not to me, gentle <hi>Phillora,</hi> whose friendly heart has Justice to all our kindness; and if I can live to pay my score to this Company, I shall then die endebted only to the gods, whose mercy will take our Faith for further Sums.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Softly, I pray, lest the busie ear of Jealous mischief (watchful to our destruction) catch this dear Secret.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray let me deliver to your Love and Care this Jewel of my life; for know, <hi>Bellamira,</hi> I have vowed, (and 'tis written in
<pb n="554" facs="277"/>
Heaven, and here I again confirm it,) Never to marry any but this Maid; and if fate frown upon that, a strange curse find me if ever I quit my freedom.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh hold, Sir, call back that rash vow, and be still worth the love and envy of all the world.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>If <hi>Phillora</hi> says I am happy my joys are currant; her stamp only can make them so, that's my vow; for I will purchase thee at the rate of all things but my Honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Why do you vow so rashly, Sir? before you have call'd your Reason to counsel? my heart is so much yours it will not consent you wrong your self; and I am so proud of my Innocence, and reall Love to your Highness, that I must not con|sent to that vow; For though I am the private Issue of a poor Forester, yet my heart's too proud to Love every common Vir|tue; nor is it every Prince that I could love, nor do I find my mind so subject to the vanity of our Sex, as to be pleas'd with their loving me; therefore be pleas'd to live my Prince, or I shall die your handmaid, and shew my love was greater then my ambition, which few women arrive at in Story.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>No more of this kind war now, for heavens sake; Put on your disguise, for fear we be all lost in your discovery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall obey, and so must you, <hi>Bellamira;</hi> Do you not find something like your dream, Sister?—Me-thinks there is so much fate in these accidents, that we war with heaven when we dispute them; See thy vision reveal'd; are we not all saved by these Fo|resters? the King lost and found, and these two Cedars of the Forest, whose fate heaven only knows?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Palantus <hi>kneels, and offers</hi> Bellamira <hi>the picture.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>Upon my knees, Madam, I restore this jewel; The grief and distraction my soul was in wounded this day with thousand mise|ries, will plead, I hope, a pardon for the fault my Tongue has made in discovery of a Saucy passion; yet I could wish the whole King|dom were as guilty as <hi>Pallantus,</hi> their love would have been less dangerous then their hate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Pallantus,</hi> if it be dear to thee, keep it; and value that, as I shall do thy Friendship; for I have long known thy heart, and shall trust thee hereafter with the Secrets of mine; my father has found thou art faithful, and grateful; And all the gods so bless me as I love thee for it, with all that thou canst hope, or I can in honour give; and if I have Interest in <hi>Pallantus</hi> he will obey me; What 'tis I command him <hi>Fidelia</hi> shall tell him; till then I am silent, and her love shall speak the rest.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pall.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, I have much pretence to love; but I shall doubt it, and not hope your reward, when I shall refuse a ready obedience to all your Commands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Farewell, <hi>Phillora,</hi> our safety calls me, pray be silent here, when I am gone, for they are jealous of me already; this night if possible wee'll make our escape to <hi>Clytus</hi> his quarter, of whose heart and faith I am fully satisfied; The keys are now in my power; and in the dead of night I'll call ye: The word shall be, <hi>Phillora.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="555" facs="277"/>
                        <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                        <p>All the gods protect the Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Leopoldus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>What do they mean by his figure in a Dream, and point at me, and talk of her Love? sure I dream; when I have seen the worst of Fortunes, 'Twill always be in my power to die; there's none so wretched but she can affoord him a grave; her Eyes are fix'd upon me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Why do's my heart tremble at the sight of him I thus long have desired to see? why should I apprehend this hour as dangerous? Yet I feel a pain without a name, a power not known; 'tis less or more then Love, Yet not arrived at guilt; 'tis neither fear, nor desire; why should I blush then to own the Joy and kind|ness I have for him?</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The Scene shuts, and</hi> Leopoldo <hi>comes in (alone.)</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>HOw vain and Insolent is man, that dares call these the weaker Sex! when we consider the Actions of Virtuous Women, the thousand dangers and difficulties they must pass through e're they arrive at that great name; what pa|tience, what courage, what reservedness, what silence, what mo|desty, how quick of sight, sometimes to apprehend approaching dangers, to shun them, and again not seeming to see such as meet them in the face, their checkings and forbidings of Nature, deny|ing, when she calls loudest, and most pleasing to their sense when she prompts them to be women; Yet we see them many times, in pure sense of their Honour, deaf, and dumb, and lame, even when wealth, dignity, and beauty, becken unto them to come; all these, and thousand difficulties more, almost impossible to our sense (that have taken up a liberty to Act the contrary) they daily perform, with a watchful diligent virtue, whose generous minds have imposed these Laws upon themselves, and now those Laws must be obeyed before they can command a fair name; while vain men assume a Diety, and believe, if they have Courage they can with their Swords build themselves Trophies. In short, from these Excellent sufferers within I may conclude, nature, and all good things ought to be committed by destiny to the care of that soft Sex, who, till they love, and give themselves away to men, can do nothing little.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Leopoldus.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Arcus, Phidelia, Filemon, <hi>and</hi> Satyr <hi>with provisions upon his back.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>SO, so, lay down the provisions here; come, Madam, let us retire into this Rock, until the tide serves, then we shall be called; for we have agreed with an old Fisherman, an acquaintance
<pb n="556" facs="278"/>
of the <hi>Satyrs,</hi> who for his Masters sake will safely convey us to some port that's free from the Conquerours power; but we must lie close till then, for the Enemy are already in the Town, but the height of the Cliffs, when we have the night to friend, will secure us; under whose protection we must make our escape, and leave the rest to Fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll go too, I'll not stay, until I find my gentle Mistress; a curse fall on his head has frighted my love from her home; the plague of Ambition and cross love torment him day and night; may his Eyes ne're shut till I have blest mine with a sight of her; I fear she is hurt, my heart akes so; this busie trouble of my mind was never so unruly as now; it makes me sick, my Spirits grow weary, I faint to death, a cold sweat and sadness is all o're my breast.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>How lively this poor wretch describes my pain! But die <hi>Arcus,</hi> and all the world, e're she knows I have a thought of Love; yet all my resolution cannot keep me from repining at my fortune, made by nature so opposite to what I love, and as if design'd for mi|series her heart is by fate given to a shadow in a Dream; My first cross lost a friend, dear as my Eyes, whose kindness and faith but speak that love which his modest Sister could neither tell nor hide: toge|ther our miseries found us, but to this day I could never know his Fortune, being, by different lots, become the slaves of different Ma|sters, and my heart apprehends his death; our Countrey else would ere this have discover'd him, our colour in this nation, making us as publick as odious; A gallant and a faithful Servant 'twas as ever prince made a Friendship with; and had not our miseries struck us in the spring of our design, something worth story might have be|fallen us; Curious to see the world our youths ventur'd into dan|gers; to which slavery was our first step; but my fate was not to be satisfi'd with one Captivity; not miserable enough she thought, while only my body was in chains, and therefore sent these that gall my mind; Love, blind partial Love will have me his prisoner too, only to shew the variety of his slaves; Why else did he throw away a dart upon me, where there is no possibility of being any thing but his slave? But I am resolved neither my condition nor passion shall be known, but in my Epitaph; and there, by a silent Lover, I'll stand distinguish'd from the croud of Rivals, which my heart only emulates in worship; but see the fate of men, the least deserving is most successful; And barbarous <hi>Almanzor</hi> by an impious conquest has power to revenge himself, and insult over the miseries of that Princess; But I am still a wretch to talk while shee's in chains; Yet if I out-live her, let base and ingrateful be writ upon my name; This night I'll find the proud Conquerour, and print a thousand wounds upon his breast, or fall a Martyr to those great names, <hi>Leo|poldo</hi> and <hi>Bellamira,</hi> which, though they were guests too great for my sad heart to contain, yet their loss is death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, <hi>Arcus,</hi> we have all the same interest in this general grief; This grief and common Calamities (like the infected Air) wounds all, to whose dangers I must add a wound of mine
<pb n="557" facs="278"/>
own, and the cure grows still more desperate; I have lost my friend, the kind and faithful <hi>Pallantus</hi> is fallen; and I must fear, though I cannot know, his misery, the uncertainty of whose ill wounds deeper then any danger that can threaten my self.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No more of this imagin'd danger; but retire, and wisely attend our own safeties, that we may preserve our selves till we know what fortune has befallen our great Master; which we can|not hope, unless this Night we make our escape; within we may resolve what to do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, <hi>with his servants only.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>SEnd for <hi>Roderigo,</hi> put all things in readiness, 'tis resolv'd this morning tyde I'll be gone, and with me bear the scornful cause of my affliction; That blind foolish boy is neither won by reason, Interest, nor flattery, and set without my Swords reach; he is not to be bribed nor won by sacrifice neither, like his friend fortune; some way I must find to reconcile my self to that fond Diety, or all my hopes are lost.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Roderigo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Roderigo,</hi> I am thinking.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Of Love, Sir, I know you were.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Of Love, yes of Love, and sent for—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Me, to inform your Highness of his humour; faith, Sir, I know him as little as you reverence him; his kinsman, and his mother, I have practised, (a Bottle, and a Girle) these kind friends I can serve you in; for the other young Gentleman, he spoils con|versation, and affects corners, either to kiss or cry in; I hope your Highness is not inclin'd to that Idle humour; pray will you let me hear you sigh; upon my Conscience you will make but an ill Lo|ver; I dare assoon undertake to hedge the Eagle in, as you win the Princess; yet they say there are as many and certain ways to win a woman, and as many holes into her heart as there are upon her—Basta.—But believe me, Sir, there's one, if you can hit it, is worth them all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>This is a kind of knowledge, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> that few are igno|rant in; but yet let the god despise me if I fear either of them; and though Poets and Lovers still conspire to beget a terrour in our hearts, yet my reason tells me, even from those lamentable Stories that make love seem so dangerous, that we most unjusty blame Love when 'tis the Lover that's in fault; for Love is not in himself our Enemy; Love is as wholsome and as natural a passion as any that affects the heart; and only corrupted loves are dangerous; Love and Wine may both be poyson'd; should we therefore curse the Vine? No, 'tis Love, wounded with Jealousie and Inconstancy, or Infected with disdain; Love set too high, or too low, by birth or Nature oppos'd, which, thus set out of her reach, or so low in the Earth that Honour cannot stoop to gather her blessings; or
<pb n="558" facs="279"/>
else at such a height that even Hope loses his Leap, and the noble Fruit hangs still to tempt us: or a worse Curse than all these, which is my fate, to love a scornful Maid that loves another: these are the true grounds of Lovers miseries, and their Errours are falsely laid upon Love, and all our stubborness call'd his Crimes, when we, not Love, are blinde, who is indeed the gentle Ty of all Mankinde, though he be made many times the most innocent Root of many mischiefs, and would be all Honey still but that our Rea|son gives him a sting; Reason, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> which Chain the Gods, have thrown upon us; for we no sooner covet and know what would please us, but we finde it still forbidden; and from this Root (this Reason) all the foregoing miseries are deriv'd; kinde Nature else would be obey'd, and all these troubles pass without a thought or grief. But to our business, which I'm sure, Love shall never be with <hi>Almanzor.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet 'twould be fit to be civil, and either send or go your self to the Prison, you have handsome cause enough to yield you an Excuse; dissemble your past anger, being in the heat of battel, incens'd by her scorn, whose sharp language and your wounds smarting made you speak and act beyond your Reason: Come Sir, when you can win two Crowns with a few fair words never refuse to play at any gamc Fortune proposes: besides, I have observ'd it, Women sooner forgive faults done to them, than those they do to others; for their shame is more than their anger can be; and 'tis easier flatt'ring their weakness into pity than ripening their Reason into Justice or Discretion: The left-side is predominant in them still: could I love one Woman better than another, (which I am so far from believing Virtue, that I think I ought to be beaten for't) if I did not with your game win any Woman I'de never com|mand Men again. Death, what Cards would you have to play if these lose? A young handsome General, a Prince, and Conque|rour, that has wit and courage, and yet be strangled in an Apron|string! sigh and let a Smock smother me! They shall bury me un|der the Gallows when I dy of that Disease; No faith, if any of them be too hard for me it shall be in Bed, and there let them use me as they please; I care not whether I win or lose in their arms, and he that desires more of Love than such a kindness is mad: when I embrace her if she smile and do speak like a Lover, let her heart be as busie as she pleases, and make any other happy till I miss her company. I do not remember I ever sigh'd, yet I think I have had my share of Women, but I would not be so miserable as to remember any of their faces for a Kingdom, for then I might be subject to Constancy, a Disease harder to be cur'd than the Pox; Constancy is really a weak-stomack'd Lover: My heart di|gests a Mistress presently, and hungers for another; thirsts and enjoys her without any thought of Constancy and Remembrance; but the last is as dangerous as if my Supper should ly in my belly always, where should my Dinner go? If ever your fine Arguments perswade me to be one of your one Meals men, you shall geld me; give me an appetite every meal in the day, and kinde hearts to
<pb n="559" facs="279"/>
feed on, Wit and Beauty will finde a Cook, and we'll make our Sauce our selves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>This Doctrine I am no Heretick in, <hi>Roderigo;</hi> yet I believe you will allow a man may love one Dish better than another, and so far I am a Lover.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>Fast and get a stomack, Sir; then all that's young and kinde is fair and pleasing; so far I am happy though no Lover.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter to them</hi> Leopoldo, <hi>and another Souldier.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>All things are in readiness for your Highness departure, and we onely stay for your direction.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll wait upon your Highness to the Prison.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>Is all ready?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir, but 'tis somewhat of the darkest to put to Sea, within two hours the Moon will rise; and being not streightn'd in our time, I shall counsel your Highness to stay a little; two hours of the Ebb carries us out of all dangers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>When 'tis time call at my Quarters; Come, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> within we'll resolve of this new business, Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt omnes except</hi> Leopoldo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>This I feared; but how to prevent it, something as speedy as their mischief must be thought of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Leopoldo.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>The Scene of the Prison is discovered, and the Prisoners in it.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>WHy this sadness now when our great griefs and fears are over? Why thus ingratefully in silence do we receive blessings we scarce could hope for? when all our Fates both of Love and Hate were doubtful, none were sad; the great and general calamity past without concern, <hi>Pollidor</hi> and <hi>Palantus</hi> with all their Faith and Loyalty could finde room for Love and Anger; and now when our losses are repair'd they sigh and droop for sha|dows.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>And <hi>Pollidor</hi> that never knew Love, Fear, nor Grief, but mine, till this Figure fill'd his breast, now when he should sacrifice droops and hangs his head like Flowers opprest with showers; now when kinder Fate has unriddl'd all our doubts beyond our hopes, dispersing all those mists we must have wandred in, by the bright eyes of the divine <hi>Bellamira.</hi> Fy <hi>Pollidor,</hi> canst thou be sor|ry for any honour the Gods have heap'd upon thy Mistress? Thy sadness now is self-love, and shews her Excellence is too great a Guest to lodge in thy narrow heart. Fond Man, wouldst thou be happier than to love and be belov'd by such a person; a begging Lover with her alms is richer than those that triumph in the spoils and embraces of another Queen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>I see our passions, <hi>Phillora,</hi> are the innocent thoughts of pure
<pb n="560" facs="280"/>
mindes; we love Honour and Virtue onely; and when they are in safety we know no fears: these men have Designs and farther ends in their desires than their blushings dare declare, else our joys must have found theirs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis too great a truth, Madam, I can prove it in my self; for my condition is equally miserable to theirs; Are not my youth and hopes equal to <hi>Pollidor</hi>'s? Are not my dangers great as yours? Is not my stake as great and rich as any that now distrusts their fortune? Is there not the same distance betwixt me and my happiness that you tremble at? Yet I smile, because I know I desire no unreasonable thing; all my wishes are to see these Princes happy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Can you hear this and not blush to finde two Maids prompt you to finde your resolution? We that are esteem'd the weak Sex, that Shadows have led in Chains, I that have suffer'd under a de|sperate Love without groaning or crying out for help, seven tedi|ous Winters afflicted with a Figure in a Dream, and till this day ne|ver saw the thing I lov'd, yet now 'tis met it shall not make me guilty of a blush for any action, though I know there be a Fate and future Prophecy wrapt in this Cloud (which thou art) and even my own wishes have something in them which I can fear; but <hi>Bellamira</hi> will dy rather than stain her story; and if <hi>Pollidor</hi> and <hi>Palantus</hi> have that honour they pretend they will cease to afflict our mindes with their sadness, and patiently expect that Birth Hea|ven and Nations have thus labour'd to bring forth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>Thus at your feet I fall, struck more by this Virtue now, than by your Beauty heretofore: Oye Gods, the divine <hi>Bellami|ra's</hi> miseries but set her off, and upbraid your justice that could neglect such a minde when they had taken pains to make it. And now be pleas'd to know my silence was no guilty fear of my own misfortunes, but revolving in my minde your fatal Dream, whose every particular is explain'd, which makes me wonder who this Youth can be whom Fate has mark'd out for the Envy of Man|kinde, though Nature have conspir'd against him, and set him as far from the reach of his happiness as there is distance between a Cottage and a Crown; yet see, Madam, if sadness have not seiz'd his heart, destin'd to lodge the greatest Guest that ever yet possest the minde of man, <hi>Bellamira's</hi> love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure <hi>Pollidor</hi> has not so poor a spirit as to be sad for him|self; I should hate him more than I love him now if I believ'd his heart could be so narrow as to wish his own happiness at such a rate as prophaning of this Princess; add for less thou canst not hope to purchase her: Let not this grieve <hi>Pollidor,</hi> but resolve to follow thy Sister still. Remember 'twas she that led thee to this degree of Honour: Remember how, contrary to Nature, Sex, and Custome, inspir'd by the Deity of Love, I laid violent hands upon thy heart, and forc'd thee to receive those glories thou now art proud of, in spight of that low mean hatred of a gallant Prince which would have held thee back: Look upon these wounds, there is a beauty in them, and a grace even in these scars,
<pb n="561" facs="280"/>
such as no Virgin can excel with all the art of dress; and I glory more for having receiv'd them for these Princes, then in any my revenge gave this day upon our enemy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Certainly, when your Highness shall consider my part, 'twill not appear strange that my mind is possess'd with wonder; and then I hope my silence will find your pardon: I would I had lost my Reason with my hopes; that enemy Reason that inform'd my soul, and made me aspire that happiness; the loss of which she now presents with horrour to my mind. Yet, know all the world, <hi>Pollidor</hi> can neither repent, dissemble, nor tame his love, though he can dye when a less cause then your Highness displeasure calls; but will not be hired to live at a less rate then your pardon. And <hi>Phillora</hi> may call to mind something consonant to this fatal Dream; do's she not remember how in our most innocent days, the Dreams our distracted sleeps have had? what honours and what worship has been paid us from crouds of unknown faces? which compar'd with this waking Dream seem to revive, though darkly and afar off, something from those nothings; and these thoughts begot that guilty silence which displeas'd my Sister. But though <hi>Phillora</hi> can chide my silence now, I fear she will short|ly find her heart subject to thoughts too, whose strange kind of fortune is like troubled waters now, and the storm is yet in her streams; but when 'tis setled, honour and quiet of mind will di|vide thy heart; for though she thinks now her heart will desire nothing but leave to love the Prince; know, <hi>Phillora,</hi> those roots that are in the spring contented to send forth a bud, their sollici|tous natures are busie still to nourish them; such is thy heart now Love but buds in it, and it will break to see that after all thy care that flower thou dotest on should hang upon anothers bosome; and all thy sweets and graces wither in that shadow; and while thou dy'st to make a handsome story, some one less excellent, but more fortunate, surfeit on those sweets thou pinest for; then thou wilt find how vain and idle a good pity is, and that fruit (if they love) poor and virtuous <hi>Phillora</hi> may reap; for pity is a good that's still attended with misery, dear bought, being never pur|chas'd at less rates then ruine; and they may be happy that can pity, but the wretched are still their subject; now thou hang'st thy head, blasted with this sad truth; and now thy soul is awakned I defie thy heart to be at peace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, <hi>Phillora,</hi> ignorant of the dangers we were in made us laugh in this storm; and those waves which we were pleased with to see toss our Barque, threaten destruction to us, unpractis'd in that dangerous element, which <hi>Pollidor,</hi> like a Pilot, wisely ap|prehends, and arms against the known ill, whose dangers I dare not now behold: something above Reason must secure our Reason, else sadness and despair must find us all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, I have heard all, and shall conclude, as to play a Game that must be lost, is childish; so to throw up all Cards that agree not with our wishes, shews covetousness and impatience; we do not always play for gain, sometime company and pastime en|gage
<pb n="562" facs="281"/>
us; and I am resolved such fates as are dealt me I'll receive; and shew how much I am above that fortune that opposes me; and if I cannot be happy, yet (against my miseries) I have this remedy, I dare dye; that pale guest needs but little invitation; especially to those that care not to live, nothing is so easie, nor so pleasing <stage>A prisoner within the Cave, cries for help.</stage> as to dye: and we, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> that are but beggars at this feast, may go when we will without taking leave, or being miss'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[A prisoner within the Cave cries for help.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Prisoner within.</speaker>
                        <p>Help, help for charity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Whence came that cry for help?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>As you have charity help the wretched; oh my fate! must I look on and see his dear limbs torn, and not have power to help him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>What strange misery is that that stands in need of our help to relieve him, that are our selves loaden with mis|fortunes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven bless the Prince from use of such a succour; hark, whence came the cry? sure 'twas from above; I fear the Prince may be discovered in his design of our safety; if so, lasie slow death, in spite of thy envy, I'll find a way to meet the Prince, and hasten thy visit hither.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you all deaf to our miseries? have the wretched no sense of others misery? are your hearts hardned to our suffer|ings, who beg nothing but the mercy of a speedy death?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis in the Cave; some other prisoners, sure, I'll take a light and see in what our charity can serve them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, I hear the Prison door open, and that light comes this way; be silent and observe, lest some unlook'd for danger happen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis about the hour the Prince bad us expect him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The door opens, Enter the Prince</hi> Leopoldo <hi>seeming somewhat sad.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Some new calamity, I read it in thy eyes, <hi>Leopoldo;</hi> speak, what fate must we expect?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>The time's too short to execute my design, for now at this instant the Guards are coming to fetch you forth; and this night you must away for <hi>Sicily,</hi> in company of the Tyrant, whose designs my heart dreads to think of, which e're he shall execute I am resolv'd, though I sacrifice my life, I'll strike him to the earth; this must suddenly be done, unless we can surprize the Guards, and thus in the dead of night make an escape; see, here are Weapons for all.—Thus armed and thus unexpected, who knows what success may attend the justice and resolution of this action? <stage>He gives them all weapons.</stage>
                           <hi>Phillora</hi> is the Word; Here then let us embrace, as friends and fel|lows in a great calamity, whose sad estates admits no cure but this desperate attempt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>The gods, and Prince <hi>Leopoldo's</hi> fortunes guide us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh the misery of men, fall'n below the pity even of <stage>They embrace one another.</stage> the wretched themselves!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="563" facs="281"/>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>What voyce was that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis some wretch in the Dungeon; just as your Highness op'ned the door he call'd for help, and your coming put us off from inquiring what it meant.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Leopoldo <hi>takes the Candle and Lanthorn, and his Dagger in his hand, goes to him, discovers in the Scene with his light carcasses of dead men, and other prisoners chain'd upon the ground; and at the appearance of the light some Foxes run away.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, alas! how cruel are men to men! See, if the very beasts do not prey upon the living members of the wetched.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, your habit speaks you a Souldier, and since you are Master of those great blessings, Arms and Freedom, be merci|ful to the wretched, who only beg some charitable wounds to re|lieve them; I hope you will not find your sword the power for such an alms. See, Sir, two of many, two in number, one in blood and misery, the dearer part of my soul, all that the Plague and Fa|mine has left to finish such sad fates as a cruel enemy shall impose, despised and forgotten, neither worth his cruelty nor his care, un|less your sword relieve us; and yet our crimes are onely our Nation.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[They are Moors.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Your colour speaks you strangers; and your miseries have begot a pity, which I have time onely to relieve, but not to inform my self of; what were those that run away? <stage>Here he re|leases the prisoners.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>Foxes, who daily haunt this place, and will scarce ex|pect while we are dead, but grown bold upon our afflictions prey upon the living; yonder lyes my friend opprest with sickness whose words they despise; nor could all our threats nor cries pre|vail; slavery has so defaced the image of the gods in miserable man, that the creatures have lost the respect and reverence due to him; dull captivity has given such strange allay to that rich metal that man was at first coin'd in, that we are not currant among beasts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, we are prisoners too; and now upon forcing our free|doms a sword and liberty I can give; and if you will take your fortune with us you shall be welcome.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>When I have afforded this charity to my friend I shall most readily joyn in any design, to be reveng'd on this barbarous enemy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>One of those keys I believe will open his locks; and while you perform that charity I'll satisfie my self concerning those Foxes.—How should they come hither? surely there is a way out, else how could they come in? I'll see the issue of this chance.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[The prisoner runs to his Sister and releases her.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sister-prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Brother, what new blessing's this that gives thee to my Arms, what means this freedom? will they at last be kind, and let us dye?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Brother-prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>No, gentle Sister, a better star guides us; and far from hence be those sad rites of Funeral, till we have taken
<pb n="564" facs="282"/>
some revenge upon that barbarous power under which we have thus long suffer'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Bellamira <hi>and the rest come to them.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, your goodness I hope will excuse our tardy visit, when you shall know we are under the same slavery, and but this hour releas'd from our chains.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bother-prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>Our gratitude, not our excuse is due; and all my past miseries you have buried in this great blessing, and I shall at last be free, or dye revenging the injuries this poor Girle has suf|fer'd, the only precious part of my soul; whose youth has been persecuted with the worst of ills that Love or Fortune could threaten, and all for loving a gallant man; whose noble heart I know would bleed could he but fear the miseries she suffers for him, though he be her Prince. This ambitious passion has made her taste many a bitter thought: Her colour makes this story strange to your ears, and this black makes it look like a fable, when we say we love; though here be the sad example of that lit|tle god, great in power; whose dart has fir'd her private mind, and the saucy flame aspires her Prince's breast; yet she's nobly born, and what was my blessing proved her misery; for had not I been blest with his friendship she had not ne're been miserable with the sight of him; this as a secret her troubled mind conceal'd till the Prince was lost at the fatal battle of <hi>Carthage;</hi> since which misery I have wasted my days in slavery, and by chance met this poor Girle, hunting through divers miseries a peaceful grave, seduced by a Witch, who ignorant of her sex, being ask'd her fortune, bad her seek her happiness in the hand of a white woman, strange and impossible.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sister-prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>I am very faint, yet my heart divines some bles|sing from the sight of those fair eyes.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[To</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>How my soul shakes to hear this poor Maids misery! and my pity would fain believe, amongst us, she might find that blessing that seems most desperate in her fortunes. <hi>Palantus,</hi> pray give her something to drink.—And be not dejected with thoughts of past ills; you are now amongst a company that dare vie with your most desperate thoughts; and yet will not doubt the rewards due to their innocency.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Her fortune is so like my own I cannot but love her, I grow concern'd too in her miseries.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sister-prisoner.</speaker>
                        <p>My thanks is due to all; but the joy and won|der of this hour has made me neglet the payment, which I shall do in prayers to all the gods, that ye may never know the use of such a kindness, by having tasted those sad calamities that wound my mind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Be quiet and resolved; for I hear some noise at the Pri|son door; which way went the Prince? let us retire, for they are now shutting of the door.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <pb n="565" facs="282"/>
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>The Scene of the Prison shuts.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter as out of a Cave, by the Seaside, frighted, the</hi> Satyr <hi>and</hi> Fidelia, Arcus <hi>and</hi> Philemon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Saty.</speaker>
                        <p>EIther my Eyes deceived me, or they were foxes; I saw them leap.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Foxes, fool? whence should they come?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Why from their burrow among the Rocks, forc'd with hunger to seek their prey; finding us in their way, what's more natural for those beasts then to force through us? Let us return and see if we can find any sign of their passage.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>How easie 'tis to give fire to fear! Our late danger makes us apprehend every noise. Hark, 'tis something scrapes within.—See, see, the furrs hang upon the Rocks still; how con|temptible a thing this fear is!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>They no sooner enter the grot, (which must be made in prospective to present a Cave by the Seaside,) but they hear one knock within.</hi> Arcus <hi>takes the light, and goes towards the hole, and finds the Foxes furrs upon the Rock.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>How long are the hours that sorrow loves! Time passeth like a thought when we are happy; But Oh, how tedious will my <stage>
                              <p>She looks towards the hole where the foxes came out, and spies a light.</p>
                              <p>He layes his ear to the hole, and beckens them to come to him.</p>
                           </stage> grief make the few dayes I have to live! Ha! 'tis fire, some star sure; <hi>Arcus,</hi> do you see that light?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis something strange, but what Heaven knows; A light in the earth! Be not amazed, collect your selves; If our fears be true, what is there in fortune left for fear? Hark, I hear a noise too, listen.—Do you not hear a noyse and strokes? Tis some Witchcraft sure.—'Tis a man, I hear his voice, and his words have reason; I'll speak to it what e're it be.—Ho! within, what art thou? how cam'st thou to this cave? what seek'st thou in this place of misery? <stage>Leopoldo <hi>within, this way they went, and I do see the stars or Moon light, and that mur|mur must be the breach of the Sea.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll answer it.—A wretched Prisoner whom the merci|less Enemy hath expos'd in chains to the rage of wild Beasts; What e're thou art, for charity give some relief to the wretched, by in|forming our miseries where thou art, for thy light has deceived me pursuing of those Beasts that would have devoured us; I hoped to have found a passage this way, which now is desperate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Hark, sure I know that voice.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Le.</speaker>
                        <p>And I that sound, or else my miseries deceive me. <hi>Arcus! Arcus</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Prince <hi>Leopoldo!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>The same; struck with wonder and amaz'd, what are we next to expect from Fate? Are we all Prisoners then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Royal Sir; we are in freedom yet, though their nets are pitch'd about us; Help, help, <hi>Philemon,</hi> to remove these stones, and force a passage here.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[They pluck stone after stone away, till the Prince comes out.</stage>
                     <gap unit="page" extent="2"/>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="568" facs="283"/>
                        <p>things my Heart can wish, glad to find my Love approved by so great a Mistriss in the School of Honour; By whose name I vow to the gentle <hi>Cadesse</hi> an eternal Faith, and <hi>Hymen</hi> shall witness my Vow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                        <p>All the gods say Amen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>We must be gone, but whither, oh whither! Sad Fate! that must be gone, but knows not where to find a safety!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopol.</speaker>
                        <p>Not whither? Yes, to <hi>Gaietta,</hi> where faithful <hi>Clytus</hi> resides; Wonder not that I call him faithful, time will unriddle all; and (I hope) my Sister will not refuse to trust those that I esteem faithful, untill we gain <hi>Gaietta;</hi> Love and <hi>Bellamira</hi>'s Fortune shall guide us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>I submit, and where <hi>Leopoldo</hi> trusts will not ask a why; and if <hi>Clytus</hi> be faithful, and we escape, let us hereafter no more throw the scandal of blind guides on Love and Fortune; but freely deliver our selves to their protectior.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Clytus, Ravack, Cleon, Souldiers <hi>and</hi> Sea-men, <hi>supposed aboard their Galley.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>COmmand them pique their Oars, and let her drive with the Tyde, lest the quietness of the night discover us with the noise; the Moon is risen too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sea-men.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, The boat that came from the Town is put under the Cliff, and there we saw lights.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>Give order to hide ours, lest they betray us as theirs have done them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sea-men.</speaker>
                        <p>Ours are hid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>We have the wind and tyde to friend, she cannot to sea but we must meet her; if she fall into the <hi>Bay,</hi> the other Gallies are ready to oppose her; Come, Sir, let us look out, 'tis a fine Evening.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, and if our honest intentions find their gods, I hope to see a glorious day in <hi>Naples.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, Roderigo, <hi>and</hi> Souldiers.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ROderigo,</hi> if you can think of any thing to be added to your Commission or Instructions, send after me and it shall be confirm'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>At present I can think of nothing; for till your High|ness and the purchase be arrived in <hi>Sicily,</hi> (which is indeed the root of all your business) all other thoughts are idle; and pray, Sir, let me prevail with your passion this night to treat them civilly, and make excuses to the Princess for your past neglects; Confess you know the debts are great you must pay er'e she can believe you a Lover; and if you prevail not with her Heart, consider how
<pb n="569" facs="283"/>
miserable you must be though you should force her to a Marriage, when you must sleep in the bosome of an opprest incens'd princess that looks upon you as the Murtherer of her father, brother, and destroyer of her Countrey; Which, with that soft gentle passionate Sex is a grief above all the rest; her heart must tell her 'twas prince <hi>Almanzor,</hi> that destroyer of the man she loved, to your face, the an|guish of soul threw out that secret knowledge which upon my life the person himself could never win from her; but distracted with her affliction, or anger, to spight your heart, has given you a secret her bosome friend ne're was partaker of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis reason all thou urgest, and I confess my self a beast when my passion rules me; but I will now endeavour to redeem my fault.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, your Civility, If it does not get you a wife, yet it will oblige her, and make her your friend; 'twill be no small advan|tage to your success; and having her in your power, it may divers ways advance your affairs in <hi>Sicily;</hi> Her love and passion for ano|ther, with the right she has to the Crown, and Interest in the people, you may by compounding her freedom secure your Conquest in <hi>Si|eily;</hi> think on't, Sir, and let not passion for a woman seduce you; and Remember Kingdoms, Sir, are scarce, and there are many chapmen, and women are common, and grow every where; let us be wise men, Sir, and when we cannot do what we would, do what we can.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>How now, where's your fellow, that we sent for?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[En.</hi> Sould.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>And please your Highness, we cannot find him; 'tis not a|bove an hour since he went into the prison, whose doors are still lock'd, and the key in the Inward side.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Did you knock?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir, but no body would answer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Death! not answer, Sir, let's force the doors.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>They all go out towards the doors of the prison, which they force open; They all draw their Swords, and with Torches in their hands enter the prison, which is the same Scene where</hi> Bella|mira <hi>and the prisoners lay.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Here's the nest, but the Birds are fled.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Haste to the guard, command no person whatsoever pass without my order, let them seize all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Perhaps, Sir, they're hid; for tis not possible they should be gone, and the door shut.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Search, Villains, 'twill concern you, for your lives are at stake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Highness found us upon our duties, the doors shut, we cannot answer for a prison.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>What Path is this? it is full of the new steps of many feet; let's follow these signs, see whither it leads.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>They follow, and the Scene shuts, and they come all out with their Torches at the hole of the Cave where the princes came out.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="572" facs="284"/>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Here they have escap'd, but 'tis certain this pass was found by chance; and being so lately gone cannot be far from hence; search the Rocks hereabouts, they are but three men, un|arm'd, and two women; let's lose no time, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> but di|vide, and call if you see any body; this Accident has destroy'd all our hopes; fool, fool, too late thou findest the punishment of thy barbarous rage.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leopoldo, Pollidor, Pallantus, Arcus, Cadesse, Bellamira, Phillora, <hi>and the other</hi> Moor.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>IS it far, we must go?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir, the Boat Rides under you Cliff.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter to them the</hi> Satyr <hi>and</hi> Philemon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philem.</speaker>
                        <p>Haste, haste aboard, or we are all lost; a party of arm|ed men pursues us, I saw them and their lights Issue from the Cave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>To the Boat then dear <hi>Bellamira,</hi> and with thee take these our friends, and dearest pledges of our lives; <hi>Philemon,</hi> by all thy past kindness I conjure thee, take it not unkindly that I desire thy age to retire with these to a place of safety.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll not stir unless <hi>Phillora</hi> will be my Guard.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Poll.</speaker>
                        <p>Gentle <hi>Phillora,</hi> let me once prevail, and now wait upon the princess <hi>Bellamira</hi> while I with Faith and Duty follow the brave <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>I obey, and scorn to doubt that fate, that the prince, and <hi>Pollidors</hi> swords strike, to defend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Away, away, I hear their noise; when we are engaged lie off from the Shore; if we be fortunate we'll call you back; The word shall be Victory and <hi>Phillora.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, Roderigo, <hi>and their Company.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>COurage, Sir, it must be they, they fly us; 'tis impossible they should have means to escape.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Let's pursue them close then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <pb n="571" facs="284"/>
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. VI.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Clytus, Ravack, Cleon, <hi>and</hi> Seamen.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>THose lights a shoar must be they; they have now doubled the Point, the Boat too is but a small Fi|sher-man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>I counted them by their lights, they are not above a do|zen in number; let us land a small party upon this Point, and 'tis impossible they should escape us, for we are now betwixt them and their Boat, which I have commanded the Galley to sur|prize.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>I am of <hi>Clytus</hi> his opinion, and that it be executed with diligence.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll command the Boat ashoar then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. VII.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leopoldo, Pollidor, Pallantus, Arcus, <hi>and the</hi> Moor <hi>prisoner.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>STand, and make good this pass, by this, our Friends are secur'd; and let us make them find the danger of pursuing a Lyon to his Den.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter to them three</hi> Souldiers, Almanzor <hi>and</hi> Roderigo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>See <hi>Roderigo,</hi> here they are.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! <hi>Almanzor!</hi> nay, then the Fates are kind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Is there no more of you? Fools, what made you venture up|on even terms? do you think our Innocency, and the Princess <hi>Bella|mira</hi>'s cause, is no odds?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha, how the devil came they Arm'd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Hence this disguise.—Shall stories say <hi>Leopoldo</hi> feared to be known when Fate set him, Man to man, to dispute Fortunes with <hi>Almanzor?</hi> no Tyrant, see <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <hi>Almanzor</hi> and <hi>Roderigo.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Ha! <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Whilst</hi> Leopoldo <hi>throws off his Souldiers Coat, and makes himself known,</hi> Pollidor <hi>speaks.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, <hi>Almanzor;</hi> but see a Saucy Wood-man, that will strike the fairest Deer in the herd, or fall at his foot.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Poll. <hi>and</hi> Alman. <hi>fight.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>And the best is best cheap.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He fights with</hi> Leopoldo, <hi>and the rest man to man;</hi> Pollidor <hi>wounds</hi> Almanzor, <hi>and crys, that for</hi> Bellamira.<hi>—and that. And kills him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="572" facs="285"/>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>O! and this last sigh for <hi>Bellamira.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He dies.</stage>
                     <stage>[Leopoldo <hi>disarms</hi> Roderigo, <hi>and he falls too.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <p>Ly thou there.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>To fall under <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> though it be ill luck, 'tis no shame; your chance is good.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>And so is <hi>Roderigo</hi>'s; and let him thank this Disguise for his Life, under whose protection this day I safely heard him speak like a Man of Honour, which has made me forget he was an Ene|my—Hold, every man hold. Let us not use our Advantage with cruelty, while I embrace the noble <hi>Pollidor,</hi> and congratulate with Princely <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> our strange delivery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pyrrhus.</speaker>
                        <p>Though nothing be welcomer than the Princely em|braces of <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> yet let us remember how dear these pawns are which yet are expos'd to Fortune; and when they are safe let us rejoyce as Winners.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter to them</hi> Ravack, Clytus, Cleon, Bellamira, Fidelia, Phillora, Cadesse, Philemon, <hi>and the Satyr; they being all together,</hi> Ravack <hi>discovers to all the Company who</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phillora <hi>were.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! the Princess taken! this my Soul apprehend|ed: See Sir how busie mischief has been, and prepare to redeem the Princess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Pollidor <hi>offers to fight with</hi> Clytus, <hi>and</hi> Ravack <hi>appears.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> while I to Prince <hi>Leopoldo</hi> discover a Secret which will seem strange and full of wonder; yet wit|ness Heaven, I shall deliver nothing but a happy Truth, a Truth that has already found the wish and faith of the per|sons most concern'd; and to gain the speedier credit with your Highness, be pleas'd to receive this Signet from your Royal Father, who impatiently expects your Highness at <hi>Gaietta;</hi> the Princess and this joyfull Company are already satisfied with my news which I shall begin with throwing at your feet the old <hi>Ravack.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! <hi>Ravack</hi> alive!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>A Name sometimes well known to <hi>Palantus,</hi> who here presents to your embraces our King, and your Kinsman, the young <hi>Genorio,</hi> Son to the unfortunate <hi>Ortho,</hi> whom cross Fate has thus long hid in the person of the gallant <hi>Pollidor.</hi> A Secret not less to him than to your Highness, for which upon my knees I beg his pardon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Is this my Royal Kinsman?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[He runs to</hi> Genorio <hi>and embraces him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="573" facs="285"/>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>What do I hear?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>Be not amaz'd at this new Truth; for it was by the counsel of your Friends we conceal'd your Birth and Quality, which I should have discover'd could I have promis'd my self your safety.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Have I lost the dear <hi>Phillora</hi> by this knowledge, Is not she my Sister still?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Royal Sir, <hi>Phillora</hi> is a Branch from the same great Stock—And what change this knowledge may bring her Fortune we must consult your Highness breast; my heart flatters <stage>
                              <hi>He turns to</hi> Leopoldo.</stage> it self with hopes of happy <hi>Hymens.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Then the Gods have been careful of poor <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> whose heart <hi>Phillora</hi> knows was resolv'd (at the price of all things, but my Honour) to have purchas'd her friendship; and I will not now be so faulty to her as to fear her faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>If sullen Fate had robb'd the noble minde of the great <hi>Leopoldo</hi> of all those Royal Dignities that distinguish'd him from common men (as Fortune threatn'd once this day, acting her worst to destroy him) yet my Soul witness I should have torn from my head all those unlook'd-for Glories she has heap'd upon me, to have repair'd the Prince, from whom I beg that <hi>Hymen</hi> now I refus'd, and defie the World (being <hi>Leopoldo</hi>'s) to make me miserable or faulty.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>To <hi>Gaietta,</hi> and there let the Gods see us possess the blessing they have prepar'd for us; but first let me embrace the faithfull and kinde <hi>Ravack,</hi> who as a Father shall ever be lov'd and reverenc'd by us; and to you, Sir, though once an Enemy, thus I open my arms; no Excuses, <hi>Clytus,</hi> this habit gave a sufficient satisfaction, in which as a private Souldier I heard thy dispute with that unhappy Prince, by whose discourse I can witness <hi>Clytus</hi> his faith to his Prince, which has reconcil'd me to all his Errours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>Your goodness, Sir, has bound my heart for ever; I confess 'twas a blinde zeal I follow'd my Master's interest with; and my faithfull heart has found this great blessing for his reward.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[He runs and kneels to</hi> Genorio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopold.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Bellamira,</hi> thy Hand <hi>Bellamira;</hi> Is there so much of <hi>Pollidor</hi> remaining in <hi>Genorio,</hi> as still to desire to change a Sister? If there be, let <hi>Bellamira</hi> strive to out-vy <hi>Phillora</hi> in Love and Faith, and thus become one Root again, while the different Branches bear the same Fruit, Love and Friend|ship.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[They all four embrace.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure, 'tis not believ'd I should finde words to express my joys; this is a blessing I must thus approach upon my knees, and shall always possess as Servant to <hi>Bellamira.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[He kneels to</hi> Bellamira.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>Your knee, Sir, but teaches me what I owe the King,
<pb n="574" facs="286"/>
nor will I allow you have a greater share in this joy than I: this bless'd discovery has clear'd us of all the guilt that stain'd our Family, while the precious bloud of your self and <hi>Phillora</hi> lay upon our name. This Storm has happily wak'd me from a fatal Dream, and now is setling into Innocence and Peace. Heaven witness how dear the name of <hi>Genorio</hi> was ever to me; and since the kinder Fates have made him and <hi>Pollidor</hi> all one, my heart has nothing left me to wish: Now I can rejoyce when I call to minde the doubtfull hopes <hi>Genorio</hi> (as <hi>Pollidor)</hi> lately pursu'd; and I hope this confession that I believ'd <hi>Pollidor</hi> lov'd will satisfie <hi>Genorio;</hi> he that desires more Arguments of my Love than a Faith of his must dy unsatisfi'd by <hi>Bellamira;</hi> for I can tell it all the World sooner than <hi>Pollidor,</hi> and hide it too from all but him; what is the rest of Fortune that should make <hi>Pollidor</hi> thus sad?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>My silence, Madam, is neither sad nor dulness, but a busie minde, confus'd and surpriz'd with joy of un-imaginable blessings, in which the Crown was the least part. They were the thoughts of the divine <hi>Bellamira</hi> that drew my Reason into my self, that I might with an humble thankfull heart con|template the great Giver and the glorious Gift. Can you be|lieve, Madam, your Friendship is to be possess'd with less than distracting joys? At this time to be deaf and dumb speaks Love best, and my ambitious heart whispers there is a hope in this change that I may out-live my despairs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>No more of Fear, Sir; for know, I do not hide my joys, curious to conceal them or my thoughts from <hi>Pollidor;</hi> but because I fear 'twould look like Dissimulation to tell him how happy this day has made me; and now I beg he will let me con|ceal my joy for my own sake, as I did my grief this day in ten|derness of <hi>Pollidor,</hi> whose griefs were then the afflictions of my heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor,</speaker>
                        <p>Vanity and folly would onely ask more than your great heart freely gives: Know, Madam, when I have wasted my life in gratitude my last breath shall be my last thanks, if I possess such a blessing as to be yours for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Palantus <hi>and</hi> Fidelia <hi>are all this while talking together, and</hi> Leopoldo <hi>and</hi> Phillora; Leopoldo <hi>kisses</hi> Phillora<hi>'s hand.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>By this, and by this <hi>Phillora,</hi> I conjure thee no more of doubt nor fear. Heaven and Earth are reconcil'd, and we shall stand the marks of their blessings here.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>With you, Sir, there is fulness of joy; and I shall be forc'd to use all the virtue Heaven has sent me to receive this bles|sing of <hi>Leopoldo</hi>'s friendship; therefore cease to ask any thing of <hi>Phil|lora</hi> that has nothing left in her heart to give but your self again, and when unkinde you will rob me of that I will dy to make me a
<pb n="575" facs="286"/>
passage through my heart, for nothing but death can force that dear name from thence.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, no more; this kinde strife and emulation in your love will make us waste a happy age together. <stage>Palantus <hi>kneels to</hi> Bellamira.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>From your hands, Madam, with joy I receive and give this faith, and I doubt not but <hi>Fidelia</hi> will approve my faith the better, for having seen it try'd by despair, and approv'd by so great a Judge in Love as the divine <hi>Bellamira.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Nor shall I think my heart less brave for being folded in those arms your Highness refus'd, nor esteem the love and friend|ship of <hi>Palantus</hi> worse for having been worn by so brave a Prin|cess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>This, <hi>Palantus,</hi> is that I had to beg; and now I conjure thee by all that love and gallantry thou hast been so diligent to shew the world, pay here thy vows to friendship, and I shall be happy by be|ing able to make my dear <hi>Fidelia</hi> so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, my love was always obedient, but here is no occa|sion to shew it; and now I lament the virtues of the sad and kinde <hi>Fidelia</hi> which give me no room to express your power. <hi>Fi|delia</hi> has a Beauty and a Virtue to be sought after at the price of Kingdoms, and hazard of all that's most dear to man, and 'tis to injure her to receive her as curtesie from her who knows my soul had always a value and kindness for her; and truth still dwelt in my heart; for since I would not ly to thee that lov'd, but plainly told I lov'd another, be confident I shall never ly hereafter; and now I have said that here before the Gods of Gratitude and Truth, in the presence of this Princess, I vow a faithful friendship to the gentle <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                        <p>Your hand, <hi>Fidelia;</hi> this days misery shall beget to morrows joy and wonder.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>These strange unlook'd-for blessings, like Dreams of troubled mindes, are so far beyond our hopes they can scarce finde our faiths: See, Madam, the first change of Fortune was of this your Servant; you'll laugh, Madam, and scorn, when you shall know <hi>Arcus</hi> was one of your Train, and those eyes made me for|get my Love, till the miseries and kindness of this Maid strangely struck my heart; and I beg the Honour to let our <hi>Hymen's</hi> Torch be lighted at your blessed fire; the black is but the shadow of a beauteous soul, and secures us from Rivals in our Loves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Untill your Highness has seen the King I beg we may de|fer the rest of this story, where there are many Friends that long to pay their duty here; you'll be pleas'd, Sir, to give <hi>Clytus</hi> your Com|mission to publish this joyful news to the Army?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>Why this Ceremony to me? If I be your King, I com|mand you live still like a Father with me; and may Heaven frown upon me when I forget the affection of a Son. O <hi>Phillora!</hi> this day is thine, and (if we out-live it) our peaceful Cell we'll to a Tem|ple turn; but where's our Friend the Satyr?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Fled, with Joy, to bear these tydings to the King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="576" facs="287"/>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Let not our Joys rob us of our Humanity towards these, the Enemies of our peace, since fortune used them as the means to the happy discovery. <hi>Pallantus,</hi> let that unfortunate prince be taken up, and his body embalm'd, and mourn'd, as becomes his birth; his miseries were his own seeking, no fault of ours; To you, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> the body shall be delivered; and to let you taste part of our Joys, in this your misery, you shall have fair leave, and all things fit, to make your retreat; provided you withdraw your Forces out of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and quit all you pretend to there; to this, I hope, Prince <hi>Genorio</hi> will agree.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>This generosity is like the Character the world gives of great <hi>Leopoldo;</hi> and he shall find his humanity has overcome more then his Sword; and from such an Enemy We shall not be ashamed to have received Conditions, nor fail to Magnifie the just <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>This Charity being done, we may safely review our happy|ness, mine has his Centre here. Lead the way, <hi>Clytus,</hi> to the Tem|ple; there let us finish those blessings that the Sword has but begun.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And since such blessings from our Dreams we see;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And that I still may happy be,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let</hi> Bellamira <hi>Dream for me.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         </TEI>

