<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
            <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>325 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 November (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12417588</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing K450.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">61734</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
                  <title type="alt">Works. 1664</title>
                  <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 8 [i.e. 5]-576, 80 p. : port.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Each play has special t.p. and is dated 1663.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="110"/>
THE FIRST PART OF Cicilia &amp; Clorinda, OR, Love in Arms. A TRAGI-COMEDY, The Scene <hi>LOMBARDY.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Written in <hi>TURIN</hi> BY <hi>THOMAS KILLIGREW.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>DEDICATED TO THE Lady <hi>ANNE VILLIERS</hi> COUNTESSE OF <hi>MORTON.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the sign of the <hi>Blew Anchor,</hi> in the lower Walk of the <hi>New-Exchange.</hi> 1663.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="111"/>
                     <head>The Names of the Actors.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Marius,</hi> The Roman Pretor, Lieutenant of <hi>Lombardy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Otho,</hi> His Son, and General under him.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cicilia,</hi> His Daughter.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Calis,</hi> Her Friend.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dyon,</hi> A Gentleman of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Orante,</hi> The Lombard Prince.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Clyandre,</hi> A Lombard.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Turnus,</hi> A banish'd Lombard.</item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Lucius &amp; Manlius</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Brothers</cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">General of the Horse.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Lieutenant-general of the Army.</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Cleon</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Two Romans.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Memnon</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Amadeo,</hi> Prince of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Clorinda,</hi> His Sister.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lysander,</hi> A Lord of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Stella, Cicilia</hi>'s Woman.</item>
                     <item>Two <hi>Hermits.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Banditoes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> Such as the Scene requires.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <pb n="217" facs="111"/>
                  <head>THE FIRST PART OF Cicilia &amp; Clorinda, OR, Love in Arms.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Orante <hi>and</hi> Turnus, Orante <hi>is cloathed in black, with black Feathers, black Perriwig, his person is crooked and ugly, with a Dagger by his side; His habit must be good:</hi> Turnus <hi>disguised like a common Souldier.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Oran.</speaker>
                        <p>HAve you heard the news, <hi>Turnus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Turn.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir, only a buzzing of something from the Army, and that diversly reported, has the Pretor Letters?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Oran.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and <hi>Otho</hi> writes of a Victory gain'd that day against <hi>Amadeo,</hi> and that they are still in chase of those Mountainers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Turn.</speaker>
                        <p>And is <hi>Amadeo</hi> become an enemy worth <hi>Romes</hi> joy when she overcomes him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Oran.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis not the Souldier, but the Hunts-man that is shew'd in this Victory, they have at last catch'd the Boar, his Sister is in the toil too; the Virago that has so long made <hi>Otho</hi> a Souldier, for 'tis certain he loves <hi>Clorinda;</hi> but why, unlesse it be for loving him, I know not; the great reason why most men love their dogs; they say they will treat at <hi>Susa.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Turn.</speaker>
                        <p>Then there is more then we see in it; remember, Sir, <hi>A|madeo</hi> was your Rival, and believed by most that know the Court, the chief cause of <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s aversion to your Highness; therefore I wish he may rather fall by the disease of his Family, (a Roman sword) then come to dispute his Title here, for though he fled the
<pb n="218" facs="112"/>
Court when he was a prisoner upon the death of his Brother, which was slain in the Battle of <hi>Susa;</hi> yet most believe <hi>Cicilia</hi> knew of his departure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Oran.</speaker>
                        <p>Hah, and this may be worth our thoughts; for I am cer|tain <hi>Lucius,</hi> who is now my Rival, is said to have made war against <hi>Amadeo,</hi> not <hi>Savoy.—</hi>(See the Pretor) now we shall know the news, for his vanity cannot conceal it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Marius, Cicilia, Calis, Dyon <hi>and</hi> Cleon; Marius <hi>has a Letter in his hand.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mari.</speaker>
                        <p>Mine are from the place, and mention a victory compleat, and that they are still in chase; the Princess <hi>Clorinda</hi> too is with her Brother; and <hi>Otho</hi> writes that he believes this will be the last stroke they will be able to strike for their Country; 'tis now se|ven years since that handful of men have stopped the Roman for|tune, at the price of five generous Princes, whose blood has been dearly sold to the Roman swords.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Otho</hi> writes, that he never saw more beauty, nor more cou|rage then the excellent <hi>Clorinda</hi> shewed in the Battle, still fighting by her Brothers side; and he hopes to gain them without blood▪ for they are now shut into the streights of <hi>Susa,</hi> and the Cattle possest by the Roman party; and I confess my soul longs to see her whose fame and vertue, though an enemy, has at this distance won my Brothers heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Oran.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Amadeo</hi> will then be fit for a second liberty, Madam; which I believe your Highness will again consent that he may have.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi> will be a Prince in chains, his heart is made of royal metal; and gold will be gold still, what poor mean use soever employed in; and Lead will be Lead though in a Crown.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Oran.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet he brake his word, and ran away (even with <hi>Cicilia</hi> he brake his word) and ran from what he loved; nay, some say, from what loved him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>But he fought afterwards, and by this loss has got more honour then some men win by victories: To the Roman fate a gallant man may lose, and yet keep more honour then some are born to; her Stars have set her so far above the world, that she stamps even vertues; and they bear a price as she bids them be cur|rant; and I doubt not, but Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi> will find that <hi>Rome</hi> ho|nours him more for being a brave enemy, then if he had proved a tame temporizing friend, which hath neither vertue enough to di|spute, nor love enough to revere her power; and I confess, of all the services the Prince did to win esteem from me, I loved him more for running from me when his honour call'd him, then if he had staid, and pin'd at my feet; Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi> went then to make himself fit for any gallant womans love; and Prince <hi>Orante</hi> staid till he was fit for none.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Oran.</speaker>
                        <p>You have reason, Madam; he that will not be reveng'd ought not to be esteem'd; he that will suffer injuries deserves
<pb n="219" facs="112"/>
them; a Doctrine <hi>Orante</hi> may learn in time, could he leave to love; and these remedies may work that miracle.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Orante, <hi>and</hi> Turnus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>You are too harsh; his mind, we know, is full of envy and pride; and when those meet with courage and despis'd love, it may beget a danger your power nor mine cannot resist; let him vent his malice, his words hurt no body.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>'tis my honour and duty that he strikes at, and he has a thou|sand times accused me of contriving the Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi>'s escape; I confess he told me he would go, and would have taken his leave of me; but I thought my self obliged neither to betray a Father, or a Friend; and therefore I would not hinder him, by betraying his trust; nor be so guilty as to countenance the fact by giving him leave to visit me; and for his discourse, I told him it should pass as a thing I neither believed nor counselled (and <hi>Amadeo</hi> had honour enough to know how to chuse with honour) this said, I left him, and he fled; for which I value him, 'twas done like a Prince, whose first business is honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess I ever lov'd him, and though I took it unkind|ly that he went away; yet being a prisoner of war, and no word engaged, we ought to have kept him better; and I believe, now, that if his love had not been more his guard, then his guards were, he had been gone sooner.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dyon.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manlius</hi> gives great honour to the Prince, and he is full of pity and admiration of his Sister; he says, they fought beyond the belief of men, only to avoid the being led in triumph; but his Letter mentions no such certainty of a victory; he rather appre|hends Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi> has some design in his retiring to those streights; for their flight was rather a retreat then a flight; and that he was against the pursuing of them into the streights; and your Highness knows <hi>Manlius</hi> is a Souldier of so much practice that his fears may find faith; he had the Van in the Battle, and lies now next the enemy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>His Letters to me speak doubtfully of this days business, they being desperate men forced beyond a hope of safety; and such as experience has taught us to know, they will sell themselves at as dear a rate as any enemy the Roman yet ever purchased with their swords; and where they now lie, our horse can do no service.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>There is no disputing of this business; but diligently see those provisions sent which <hi>Otho</hi> desires; and lest <hi>Manlius</hi> his fears be true, <hi>Cleon,</hi> command the second and third Legion be this night ready to march; and when they are at the Tower upon the <hi>Poe,</hi> there let them expect Orders from <hi>Otho;</hi> by which means we may secure our friends, if there be any danger; which must be so much the more desperate as it is unlooked for; within we will resolve further.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Mar. Cicil. Cal.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>What strange trouble's this? is not <hi>Manlius</hi> Brother to <hi>Lucius?</hi> am I displeas'd that the world believes him a gallant and a knowing Souldier, young in years, old in experience, and high
<pb n="220" facs="113"/>
in fame; one whom his generous brother dotes upon, one that all the world esteems a person of honour, stain'd only with craft and a little sullen roughness in his nature, having still been bred in Camps, and nurs'd in war; but he is <hi>Lucius</hi> his Brother, and that heals all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>How ill a character has the gentle <hi>Cicilia</hi> received of the best of men, except his Brother! then <hi>Manlius</hi> there is nothing more gallant, nothing softer nor humbler then his nature; famous for war and peace; and though his rough mind want love to polish it, that the world may see how cleer a vertue rules his heart; yet I am confident when your Highness shall see him, <hi>Manlius</hi> will pro|duce some excellencies that will be new and strange, though in the Brother of <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>At last, <hi>Calis,</hi> I have found thy heart, blush not, 'tis <hi>Manli|us</hi> which so often in a third person thou hast accused, praised and lamented; O <hi>Calis,</hi> could'st thou hide from me thy love, that still told thee all the secrets of my heart; have I lived with <hi>Calis</hi> as if I would condemn her for loving <hi>Manlius?</hi> is that a crime in her, and vertue in me to love his Brother? is <hi>Manlius</hi> unworthy? why else do's <hi>Calis</hi> blush to own her friendship?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Madam; neither of these was the cause of my silence, which I shall now no further observe, though a curiosity to know my fate made me conceal it till now; for they are sad stars that wait upon my love, blood and death threatning all the friendships that I make.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Fie, <hi>Calis,</hi> shall dreams fright thee from loving vertue, or fear of ills make thee act ills? <hi>Manlius</hi> is a man my heart is so well acquainted with by publique fame that though yet I never saw him, I could at first sight, methinks, desire all fair and reasona|ble things from him, for he is friend to <hi>Otho,</hi> Brother to <hi>Lucius,</hi> and lov'd by <hi>Calis;</hi> and if I live to see him, I will so chide his fro|zen heart, shame shall make him kind and civil, though not a Lover.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>If your Highness will become concern'd in my fortune, I should no longer doubt my fate; those eyes have ever been suc|cessful; and when your Highness will plead for me, who can deny that has honour? since we see the worst men, and worst natures have stoop'd to your power. See, Madam, where comes a mira|culous <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Oran|te <hi>sullen.</hi>
                           </stage> effect of it in that wretched Prince, <hi>Orante.</hi> See if he be not returned; retire, Madam, and avoid the visit.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>No, I have yet the justice on my side; and let <hi>Orante</hi> do as many unhandsome things as his ill nature can prompt him to, I shall do nothing unworthy my self; 'tis his guilt must make my ill usage justice; else to punish him and use him ill, is not fair; while he is faulty I can with honour despise him; and while I use him like a Prince (which I will do, and not encourage his love neither) if he then fail in what a Prince should return, the world will condemn him, and excuse me. His person is not his crime, he made it not; and if his mind had been good, I could with honour enough have listned to his passion; but his soul is as crooked as his body, and that is an imperfection that honour cannot be reconciled to; I con|fess,
<pb n="221" facs="113"/>
Custom has made his importunities less troublesome then they were before; Especially when I consider, how much more afflicti|on his Love must be to himself, in being the Lover, while despis'd, then to me that am beloved; for while I endure the hearing of it he has the Torment of suffering those pains he would describe, whose cure is desperate; for he knows my heart is vowed to <hi>Lucius,</hi> whose return he dreads; And I am confident he would kill him, if he durst Anger me; for, amongst all his crimes, Coward is none.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Speak softly, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, such is <hi>Orantes</hi> Fate, that even Injuries from your Highness cannot divert his Love, nor all the Harshness in your words, this morning, make me omit the seeing my Enemy, when any pretence can give me the Occasion; There are second Letters arrived, Madam, from the Army; Do's your Highness know the contents? their news has dul'd the Court.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>No, my Lord, not any thing: what is the report?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>They say, the <hi>Pretor</hi> frown'd; and 'tis reported, the Ar|my, and all the Officers, are engaged within the streights of <hi>Susa,</hi> and their condition most desperate; They have writ for present aid; The third and fourth Legion are marched, and the <hi>Pretor</hi> fol|lows with the rest of the Army.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>This <hi>Manlius</hi> fear'd, the gods guide my Brother; <hi>Calis,</hi> we have other deities then Love to sacrifice too, though I hope that God will be propitious.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Cicilia <hi>and</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Amen to that; But Love will still be as blind as For|tune; yet were it not for Love, I could force <hi>Lucius</hi> his fortune, though I cannot flatter my own; for though my Stars have design'd my Person the Scorn of all the world, yet kinder Nature has given me a heart that dares be revenged on all the World; And al|though I cannot be as happy as I design'd, yet I will make others as miserable as I please; and when Love will not let me be a guest in <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s heart, Revenge shall be in <hi>Orantes;</hi> My rest is up, I will either have her Friendship, or her Honour; Who fears not his own may laugh at the Tragedies of others. Divine-form'd <hi>Lucius,</hi> with sounds of Flattery, may pierce her heart, by the Eye and Ear; But if despised and despairing <hi>Orante,</hi> thus branded by Nature, stab not as near her heart with his Dagger, as any smooth Courtier of them all, let me die despis'd in Story too; that, for a little Beau|ty, sold my Honour, and my Peace. When <hi>Lucius</hi> returns, I must dis|semble my hatred to him; which is as hard for me to do, as for him to believe it; yet I do not hate <hi>Lucius;</hi> I could love the man, if <hi>Cicilia</hi> did not; Strange Madness! to hate him because she Loves him; And because she loves him, not dare to strike him; Love, blind love, why hast thou chosen me for a scorn'd subject of thy power? Unreasonably imposing on my Reason a Love for her that hates me, joyning still with fortune, both which have decreed nei|ther Crown nor Love for <hi>Orante;</hi> Depose my soul to some greater power, by taking my reason from it, and then I may be happy a|mongst Beasts, though most miserable amongst men.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Orante.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <pb n="222" facs="114"/>
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>An Alarm within. Then Enter</hi> Souldiers <hi>of both parties, and</hi> Man|lius <hi>wounded, and retires, pursu'd by</hi> Amadeo, <hi>and</hi> Clorinda.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>STand, stand.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Lysander.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lysand.</speaker>
                        <p>Give the word; stand, stand.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[The</hi> Sould. <hi>En. &amp; then stand.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>A little Patience, and then they are all our own.—Why <stage>The Souldiers make a shout.</stage> this shout? Why this cruelty, in chase? Do you fear the Roman? Is a Conquest such a new thing, you are surpriz'd thus with, a victo|ry? have we won, or cheated them of the Day? if not, Why this childish noise? Doth the skilful Artist make fires of Triumph, when he arrives at any thing in his Trade? 'Tis Womanish, 'tis Cow|ardize, 'tis like fearful Girls left in the Dark; you shout and tremble, as if you could fright your own fears; And all this Joy speaks your minds now, as your hopes were before, poor, and low; Nor did you believe me yesterday, when I prevailed with you to retire, having no hope left, unless their Pride could be seduced to pursue us to these streights; Did I not tell you then, 'twas the num|ber, not the name, nor vertue of the Romanes, that beat <hi>Amadeo;</hi> And now, if you will follow me with minds prepar'd for all For|tunes, they shall, at last, find us an Enemy not to be despis'd; and either we will become their Triumph, or they Ours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Manlius <hi>and his Party.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manlius.</speaker>
                        <p>YEt stand, As you are <hi>Romans,</hi> follow <hi>Manlius;</hi> See where Old <hi>Marius</hi> his Silver Eagle lies; Born in se|ven <hi>Consulates</hi> before him; If there be never a <hi>Roman</hi> dares second me to fetch it off, Let <hi>Amadeo</hi> bear it to <hi>Susa,</hi> while you submit your necks under the <hi>Savoyard</hi> yoke; Are you all dead, all stabb'd with one Calamity? Why did you shake your spears in the morning, and call for a Signal to the Battle? Now you see, how low and foolish it is at any time to despise an Enemy; Yester|day you were all noise, and full of revilings; Now a Pannick fear possesses you: If you had Conquer'd yesterday, you had rob'd your selves of Triumph, for your vanity left nothing fit to be re|warded; and now you are overcome, how your wounds will blush with shame; What dishonour must your General sustain, when he sees himself a Prisoner to the enemy! he despis'd—See the General of the Horse too, shall he see you deliver the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagles <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Lucius.</stage> to a handful of beaten Enemies?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, <hi>Manlius;</hi> I see a <hi>Roman</hi> anger in their looks, and this Affront has given an Edge to their Swords; Let us go, and make good this pass, and we may regain the day; for <hi>Otho,</hi> and the second Legion are drawn to the mouth of the Streights to meet with <hi>Cleon</hi> and the fourth Legion; The <hi>Pretor</hi> too is upon the March himself.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="223" facs="114"/>
                        <speaker>Manlius.</speaker>
                        <p>I can bear any thing but this dejection upon a Loss; yet I know not why we should at any time despise this E|nemy; Remember my Opinion yesterday, when you were all bent to pursue them to this place; Let us call to mind what they have done with a handful of men; how, in <hi>Ten pitch'd Battle,</hi> they have stop'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagle in heighth of Conquest, and check'd her power more then whole Nations; Five Gallant Princes have defen|ded their Freedom with their blood; and this, the last of that Great Race, whose vertue we have proved in Peace and War; And I confess, but in kindness to <hi>Lucius,</hi> whose Rival I know he is, nothing should have engaged me to have drawn my sword against such vertue which even accuses the Gods for arming a|gainst him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear <hi>Manlius,</hi> Brother in my mind as well as Nature, how I admire thee for this honest plainness? But we are now en|gag'd, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Honour is at stake; 'tis <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Battles, we bleed in; and who draws a sword against her must be Our Ene|my; Else, by my Honour, though it be my Rival, I would hazard my life to save him, the Princess has given so noble a Character of him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manlius.</speaker>
                        <p>Let us find the General, and joyn with me in proposing a Treaty, while there are some to shew mercy to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Yesterday your words would have come as well-come as Victory to him, for I know his heart loves <hi>Clorinda;</hi> But now, 'tis neither Honourable nor safe to propose it; you know they are a Resolute Enemy, and must not be sought for till they are beaten; if we treat, They will believe we feared they might overcome us; And <hi>Otho</hi> must not treat with the <hi>Roman</hi> Enemies in Arms; When they acknowledge her Power, then 'tis time to shew a <hi>Ro|man</hi> clemency; till then, all Acts of War are <hi>Roman</hi> too.—See <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Otho.</stage> the General; I would your Highness had been here a witness to our Discourse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>All Discourse is tedious, and unseasonable now.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, We were proposing of a Treaty.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis out of time; We must not give Our Honours for <stage>He whispers.</stage> Our Safety. Your Ear, <hi>Lucius.—</hi>The Legions will not be here, as we expected; 'twill be night ere they can arrive, and We must be resolved, with such Cards as fate has dealt us, to play this Game; <hi>Manlius,</hi> you must give the Charge, if they advance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall obey your Order, Sir; for my kindness as well as duty obliges me to your opinion; yet 'tis strange, that nice Ceremonies should make Prince <hi>Otho</hi> thus design how to punish that Courage in an Enemy which all the gods have so often reward|ed in himself. This generous Prince has no crime but valour that pleades against him; and shall Courage be a sin in him, and virtue in a <hi>Roman?</hi> Come, Sir, I know you have too much Honour to dispute this with me; witness all the wounds that I have felt; I look upon them as the copy of our first <hi>Rome; Rome</hi> in her cradle, such a despicable handfull of Men were we, such a contemned virtue was <hi>Aeneas,</hi> so despis'd, so prest by an insolent Monarch, such
<pb n="224" facs="115"/>
proud Neighbours found <hi>Rome</hi> in her Infancy, and what had we then but this virtue to defend us, what right to <hi>Rome?</hi> What force to defend or redeem us but such a Courage? Nay, by what Title now do we hold an Empire over the world? But by these swords, and minds resolved, such an Imperious Enemy wakned then our sleeping virtues, and by forcing us often to dispute for her, at last won Fortune to our side; with our swords we overcame the greatest difficulties; And from a Colony of a few sea-beaten Fugitives, we are become Lords of the Earth; and who knowes the Fates of these Men? We have try'd their virtues in ten years Warr, to which now is added their despaires; Nor has our supplies and numerous Armies, during this War, been oftner recruited then they have renewed their virtue, still shewing equal Courage to our best of Fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>When I shall speak in favour of a Treaty, sure none that know my Interest will doubt the Reason of it; And your High|ness knows with what zeal I have pursued this Warr; Yet I con|fess, <hi>Manlius</hi> his words have made me ashamed of that cause that bred my hatred to him, whose Gallantry I shall alwayes love next to Honour: And I know the generous <hi>Otho</hi> could not be deaf to the reasons he hath given, but that he is angry with the affront which they have this morning thrown upon his Fortune. I know his Heart is too noble else, to hate this little great Enemy, amongst whom <hi>Clorinda</hi> fights; 'Tis true, 'twould vex a winner to find one, and the last stake stoop his fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, Sir, win this Prince any way; his virtues in friend|ship will do more Honour to <hi>Otho</hi> then a Conquest; Were I the General, I should be prouder to fold such an Enemy in mine Arms, then to have led <hi>Syphax</hi> in chains.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Now after a day won and lost, in which they have shew'd both Active and Passive Valour, not dejected by the loss of yesterday, nor blown up with the success of this day; They fell under our wounds, yet no groanes fil'd our Ears; at our feet their wounded truncks lay, and frowning breath'd their great Souls out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>We call them barbarous; but what will the next age say, when they shall read this story, but that the <hi>Romans</hi> feared <hi>Ama|deo,</hi> and destroyed that eminent virtue, because he might have become their Rivall? But this is but discourse, let us consider the place and our condition; If they know and take the advantage, it may be our turns ere the Sun sets, to fill the Graves we talk of; The place will serve for a Moral; have we not this day stumbled at the bodies we slew yesterday, making those Triumphs then our dangers now? Your silence, Sir, confesses the Reason we speak.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Lucius; Manlius.</hi> Friends, dear as my Eyes; why should you two; whom my Soul loves, thus gall your friend? and now when he is beaten and dishonour'd, tell him what a Conquer|our should have done? Yesterday who mention'd a Peace? was not victory then in all mens mouthes? And now, when we are expos'd to their swords, and no way left to shew we are <hi>Romans</hi> but by dying bravely, you would have me treat; 'Tis poor and low
<pb n="225" facs="115"/>
for <hi>Otho,</hi> a grave is handsomer far; and they will understand it Fear, not Clemency, should we propose it; Let us redeem this fatal day, and then command me; but till we can give Laws, I am resolv'd to try Fate to the last sword, and here. Let us part and em|brace; whether we meet again or no, we are <hi>Romans</hi> still; <hi>Manlius,</hi> our Honour and our Lives lie in thy hands; And I am pleas'd to think the <hi>Roman Eagle</hi> has such a Protectour; If they force the pass, <hi>Lucius</hi> and my self will be ready to receive them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, Sir, he is a gallant Enemy, and to lose to such is no dishonour; 'Tis their turn to day, 'twas ours yesterday, and may be again to morrow; Gamesters that play fair must expect to lose sometimes, especially those that will adventure at a Game so full of Fortune as a Souldiers trade; Be therefore, Sir, resolved to make a safe retreat, and save our Honours; so to play this after|game will shew a Souldier no less then a victory have would done.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter a</hi> Souldier.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, the Enemy advance apace, they have gained the the Hills; and <hi>Tullius</hi> sayes, unless he be supply'd he must quit the pass; Nor do's the Enemy move disorderly, as upon a success, but whole and in Bodies, as to execute something long since design'd. <stage>The Alarm increases.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Let your Forces second mine; for if we lose this pass, you must not think of a retreat to <hi>Susa.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Away then, each Man to his charge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[A charge soundes.</stage>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lysander, <hi>and after him,</hi> Amadeo <hi>and</hi> Clorinda. Souldiers <hi>bring in</hi> Manlius <hi>bound.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo.</speaker>
                        <p>AWay, <hi>Lysander;</hi> follow where Fortune and Victory leades thee, and let these <hi>Romans</hi> see we can be an|gry though not revenged; this is more then ever the <hi>Romans</hi> could boast from us; 'Tis true, your swords have digg'd our Princes Graves, yet they could never shew one of <hi>Amadeos</hi> line or Family led in chaines; see, <hi>Clorinda,</hi> a <hi>Roman Generall</hi> in chains.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis a noble sence of Honour, and <hi>Amadeo</hi> chides me handsomely; but if I had any scruple in my Heart that tells me, <hi>Manlius,</hi> for fear of death, or want of Courage became thy Priso|ner, I would now beg thy sword to fall upon me, to let thee see, how a <hi>Roman</hi> ought to free himself from such calamity; But I will live and tell the world how much I honour that greatness of Mind, though in an Enemy. For <hi>Manlius</hi> is a name, thy Father, Brothers, and thy self have often proved in Battle; and I am sad to think, how fatall my sword has been to thy Noble Family.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="226" facs="116"/>
                        <speaker>Clorin.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manlius</hi> is Brother to <hi>Lucius,</hi> Friend to <hi>Otho:</hi> O <hi>Amadeo,</hi> that I durst speak my thoughts now, or that my Brother had but kindness enough to hear me speak, before he chides my Passion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
                        <p>What wouldst thou say? speak any thing but in praise of bloody <hi>Otho.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorin.</speaker>
                        <p>Bloody <hi>Otho?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, bloody <hi>Otho;</hi> so bloody that his Love cannot tame his Heart; what else can he hope from us? Why should <hi>Rome,</hi> which is the Mistress of all the world, hunt poor <hi>Amadeo,</hi> and warr against him, to make his people more miserable then Nature has design'd them; Here we live contented with our own, though the place be so poor that curious Travellers are scarce tempted to pass through it, to enjoy the fruitfull vales of <hi>Lombardy;</hi> What can ye hope by making us your slaves? Rich Mines we have none, Odours, Spices, and the Silk-worm are strangers here. These streams no shels with Orient Pearl afford, our sands breed no strife-full Gold; These Rocks have veins, but far from the blew Saphyr; The Ruby, Emrauld, nor the Diamond, grow not here. Innocence and Peace of Mind is all the wealth we boast of: And our Freedom the only Jewel we defend, which we will keep to the last Man; and the <hi>Romans</hi> shall alwaies find us strong enough to kill our selves, though we cannot destroy our Enemies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorin.</speaker>
                        <p>If my Love or Faith has any Credit with my Brother, let him take my Councel; Let a Virgins divining Soul prevail once, though my words seem now most unreasonable to common sence. Now when he has power to kill, now when Conquest is in his hand, when flight, dishonour, and certain death hangs over his Enemy, 'tis, like <hi>Amadeo,</hi> now to sound a retreat; Now offer Peace, offer all but our Honours and Freedom for it; This my Soul prompts me to say. <stage>Amadeo <hi>after a litle thought.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
                        <p>Call <hi>Lysander</hi> back, sound a Retreat, let <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s Fate guide <hi>Amadeo,</hi> my gentle Sister has refused no Fortune to follow me; and Heaven forbid I should refuse to venture upon thy hand this last stake; onely swear upon this sword, by thy Fathers Soul, and by the chaste ashes of thy honoured Mother, never to be led in Triumph; swear this, and let what Fate displeased Heaven has de|creed <stage>She swears and he em|braces her, she kisses the sword.</stage> come, I scorn to fear it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorin.</speaker>
                        <p>I swear, and Heaven curse me if I break my vow. Sir, by the Power my Brother has given me I release you; give him his sword, and conduct him through the Army safe; Let all Prison|ers be armed and releas'd, and give command, that no Man strike a blow more, nor hinder any <hi>Roman</hi> in his Retreat. Sir, you are a Friend to <hi>Otho,</hi> and may find Faith when you speak; Pray tell him, a Virgin that loves as much as he can hate, sent you to him, one that loves him next to her Honour, equal to her Brother, and far above her self, would fain speak with him; to try, if it be pos|sible, to save one Root of a Royal Family, and die without Infamy; that is all we ask, and here we shall expect your Answer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="227" facs="116"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lysander.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>I accept the benefit, Madam, with a heart as pleas'd as if Fortune had given me power to have plaid your part to day; And if I live, I'll serve you; or being deny'd here I promose to return my self your prisoner; till when, live most excellent among men, and noblest among women.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo, </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>'Tis high Reason that she speaks; for if we over|come them, 'tis but exasperating an enemy we cannot conquer; and this little victory can but prolong our misery; we might if we pursu'd this advantage have kill'd some few enemies; but in spar|ing of them we have gained many friends; for they are a generous Nation, and have often been won, but were never conquer'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>To have kill'd them all would have tir'd us, though they had sat still; and when we had done we had but shew'd our teeth <stage>[Aside.]</stage> to them, and have taught them to imitate us, by destroying all that fall into their power; for why, after such an action, should we expect ought but the fortune of the war? hitherto we have de|fended our selves with honour, and enough disputed, as enemies, to make them value us, if we become their friends.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lysand.</speaker>
                        <p>If Fate have design'd the Romans masters of the world, we in vain dispute what the earth hath granted; and 'twill be ho|nour enough for us to have it said we thus long durst be their enemies; and if your Highness can thus compass a peace with ho|nour, 'tis my opinion, to embrace this opportunity 'twill give us some reputation with them, to see we have taken this handsome way to offer a friendship when we not only can defend our selves, but destroy them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>Let us stand upon our defence only, till I give the word.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lysand.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Highness Order shall be obey'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>So shall my ever dear Sister, the vertuous <hi>Clorinda.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>And when I am swayed by any interest, to propose ought against my Brothers honour, let him and heaven scorn me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, when I was prisoner to the Romans, I found civility from <hi>Manlius;</hi> and though he be Brother to my Rival, he has too much honour to hate an enemy; <hi>Clorinda</hi> says you are free, and she commands here; and now I owe the noble <hi>Marius</hi> nothing, for young <hi>Amadeo</hi> was not worth a limb of gallant <hi>Manlius,</hi> great in arms; and 'tis the greatest joy my life has seen, to be able this day to pay that debt; and when you shall bless your eyes with a sight of the divine <hi>Cicilia,</hi> throw at her feet the life and service of the unfortunate <hi>Amadeo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lucius</hi> is Brother to <hi>Manlius;</hi> and you cannot be ignorant that love more then hate, or Empire, has made him thus long an enemy to his Rival; the General <hi>Lucius</hi> had odds enough in being <hi>Lucius,</hi> and needs not the advantage of an Army, to dispute his fortune; the gentle <hi>Cicilia</hi> is a perfect Judge of Love and honour; and would not be seduced to chuse the least noble, and where
<pb n="228" facs="117"/>
                           <hi>Orante</hi> is only Rival, 'tis no honour to overcome; therefore, for <hi>Lucius</hi> his honour make a peace, and give <hi>Amadeo</hi> leave to try his fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall not only deliver this, but find some other Argu|ments, which <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s modesty will not let her name; and thus much I dare say, <hi>Lucius</hi> his hate, if he be so poor as to hate a Ri|val, will not hinder this peace so much as Prince <hi>Otho</hi>'s love will advance it; and although my sullen nature was never yet a Lover, yet he that can hate may love; and I that can see others love, though I cannot love like them, yet I can tell what disease reigns; and I shall either find the Prince of my mind, or return <hi>Manlius</hi> a prisoner, bound by the Reason and Gallantry of <hi>Clorinda.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>All kind fates wait on <hi>Manlius;</hi> here we shall expect our dooms, with minds prepar'd for all that peace or war can threaten.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Otho, Lucius <hi>and Souldiers.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>WHat means the enemy, they make a stand; and have sounded a retreat; haste <hi>Lucius</hi> to the Pass, perhaps they see not their advantage; if we can gain the Valley, we may defend our selves this night, and joyn with those Legions which now are upon the march; poor <hi>Manlius,</hi> thy fate is sadder then all the rest.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Sir, give me leave to charge again; if it be possi|ble; let me fetch off my Brother, his faith ought not to be aban|doned, shall we see a Roman General thus; forsaken in the hands of a barbarous Mountainer, and his body, for ought we know, want his funeral Rites?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter divers of the Roman Souldiers Arm'd, and that had been Prisoners, releas'd by</hi> Clorinda.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>How now, whence comes this rudeness? where are your Officers, under whose command are you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manlius</hi>'s, and thus set free by warlike <hi>Clorinda,</hi> unspoil'd either of Arms or Ensigns.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Manlius.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Is <hi>Manlius</hi> safe too, what means this? my soul is full of wonder; see, Sir, my dear Brother is return'd. <stage>They both run to him and embrace him.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>The ever noble, always welcome <hi>Manlius;</hi> but how thus arm'd and safe, with freedom inform us, dear <hi>Manlius.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, here I stand, the bounty of <hi>Clorinda;</hi> not only my self, but all of us owe to that generous Maid our present safety; be pleas'd to know, we fell not into their power by chance; 'twas long design'd; nor are they ignorant of the least advantage, and had pur|su'd it but for the divine <hi>Clorinda,</hi> who prevail'd with Prince <hi>Ama|deo,</hi> and stop'd his fury in the heat of chace, and conjur'd him ere he took the advantage of this day, to hear her speak; Now is
<pb n="229" facs="117"/>
a time, saith she, for <hi>Amadeo</hi> to shew his vertue; now 'tis time to treat with honour; now when you cannot only defend your self, but destroy the Foe; if ever you hope to make a peace with this great enemy, neither rob nor disarm them; if they fight for ho|nour, and to command the world, they will not forgive a disho|nour, nor forget a benefit; what we have done this day, and all the wounds we have given to this place, was for our honour and safety; but what we shall act further, if you pursue them, will look like a desire of revenge or hatred; and make the world believe if we could have conquer'd we would never have treated; then she turn'd to me, and having received absolute power from her Bro|ther; <hi>Manlius,</hi> says she, is Brother to the noble <hi>Lucius,</hi> and friend to the most excellent of men, Princely <hi>Otho;</hi> and <hi>Manlius</hi> has ver|tues which will weigh down the scale of <hi>Amadeo.</hi> Thus when she had made me blush with praise of my self; with our Arms and Honour she commanded we should in safety pass to pay the debt her Brother owes Prince <hi>Otho;</hi> and when you see the General of|fer our friendship to him, offer these few lives and swords we have left to serve him and the Roman Eagles; offer all, but our ho|nours, for a peace; and let it be such a one as we may not blush to receive, nor the Romans despise us for accepting; and if we can|not gain his friendship upon these terms, here you shall find us rea|dy to defend, with our antient vertue, both our Fame and Coun|try, with minds resolved for what fates soever the Gods ap|point us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Did I not tell you 'twas a gallant enemy? what is there to consider? why should not your heart fly into the arms of this gallant Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear <hi>Lucius,</hi> draw up the Army, and stand upon your Guard, till we return; and during the cessation be only ready to defend your selves; Come, <hi>Manlius,</hi> we will find this gallant ene|my; and if we can with honour grant what he desires, thou shalt find how welcome <hi>Manlius</hi> and his opinion is to his friend; send <hi>Cleon</hi> with a Guard to attend us, during the Treaty.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Amadeo, Clorinda <hi>and</hi> Lysander; Clorinda <hi>was wounded, and her Arm in a Scarfe.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>THe Officer says, <hi>Manlius</hi> was received with much joy; and upon the arrival of the Souldiers the General gave immediately Orders for a Cessation of Arms; and 'tis <hi>Manli|us</hi> desire that we expect him here, where <hi>Clorinda</hi> shall, at last, see this fate of <hi>Savoy;</hi> how do's her Arm, <hi>Lysander?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lysand.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, the wound had taken cold before 'twas drest.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clon.</speaker>
                        <p>This wound will heal, as we succeed; if I can cure them of my Country, these are but sleight; but if it must be war still, sadness will add one more to my heart, that foresees I must part with my dear Brother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="231" facs="118"/>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>I hope, <hi>Clorinda,</hi> we are not now to set up our Rests; they have been long at stake, we were born Princes, we have lived so, and must resolve to dye so; we must all dye once, and Princes have no sepulchre more noble then a Battle, nor Epitaph so ho|norable as a wound when 'tis received in his Countries cause. There is no disease so Princely as to fall by the sword when he must dye; sickness and old age take away from that Majesty that Reverence men pay us: who can adore us as Gods on earth, when they see the Gout Cramp us, or a saucy ague shake a Princes soul out? No, <hi>Clo|rinda,</hi> when Fate will call me to my Doom, let me meet it in a pitch'd Battle, against a gallant enemy; then we fall like our selves, and our Funerals are waited on with thousands of loyal Souldiers; those that live to wither here till old age waste their souls, dye common deaths; and go to heaven like private men, and pass unregarded like some melancholy Ghost.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lysand.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, the Roman General appears.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Otho, Manlius, <hi>and some of his Guard.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>How they gaze on each other?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lysand.</speaker>
                        <p>There is greatness and gallantry in his looks. Good Gods, why should these men be enemies!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis proper for me to break this silence, and to shew <hi>Clo|rinda</hi> my heart is not ungrateful for the benefit I received; the General is here ready to receive your propositions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>What excellencies, what vertues must fill the minds of these Princes, when their very looks speak great things? I never saw her steadily before, but passing and charging; she robs her gallant Brother of my wonder, she lessens his glory, which should be my admiration (were she away) she is chaste and stout, courage of both sexes flows there; such a fellow in Arms who durst war against? her eyes have gain'd a perfect victory over my heart; my youth and fortunes first kindness shines in those divine lights.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, by <hi>Manlius</hi> we sent a message to great <hi>Otho; Clo|rinda</hi>'s Prophetick soul proposed it, our desires were few and short, being the sence of those minds which never yet were false; we on|ly ask to be used like friends to the Romans; that we once dared to be enemies ought not to prejudice us, but rather shew us wor|thy the honour of a peace, which, with honour, is all we ask, and then command us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>Why should the Roman General be twice moved to ac|cept us for friends? <hi>Rome</hi> has enemies enough besides; she has ma|ny Tributaries, and many Slaves; Nations of poor minds, worth no better fates; such as <hi>Rome</hi> got no honour amongst, for they had none to lose, scarce worth a Triumph; methinks they should for variety desire one friend, my Brother begs the place; you may love him too, and not be jealous of his greatness; and well he may become their friend, and other mens envy, whilst <hi>Rome</hi> takes a pride to make him so. Alas, Sir, we are no <hi>Carthage;</hi> no <hi>Antio|chus,</hi> no <hi>Philip</hi> treats now, that may be emulous with the Roman
<pb n="231" facs="118"/>
Greatness. We onely beg to possess, with honour, the Sepulchres of our Fathers, in this little Province, and to hold, as friends to <hi>Rome,</hi> what is even lost in the Map; and for your Friendship, take Our Faith, and Love; Other tribute <hi>Amadeo</hi> cannot give you, he receives no other from his Subjects; 'Tis all his wealth, that we love him, and he asks no more of us, and that We will pay to you, Leave us our Honour, that We may be worth your Friendship, and then our Swords are yours; But if you dishonour us you will de|spise us too, and we shall hate you; This is all we have to say.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manli.</speaker>
                        <p>Why are you silent, Sir? Is there room for thoughts in your great mind? Can you be in doubt, whether you should re|ceive those for friends, or no? They are so few, 'tis a shame for us to War against them; they are so few, they are onely fit to be Friends; But when you consider their Gallantry, and Numerous Excellencies their Courage too, how Infinite, 'twill be wisdom to gather this rich seed into your Bosome; <hi>Romes</hi> Dominions are large, and lie fallow for want of such virtues; Plant these brave minds amongst them, and bless the Empire. There is a Virgin too, worth your highest thoughts; try to conquer her with Love, and softness; such a <hi>Pallas</hi> in your lawful Bed would Steel your soul a|gainst the world; and under her virtue, and your fortune, what Souldiers could miscarry?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee peace, and learn to love, and then thou wilt cease to wonder at my silence; Dost thou think the first sight of the objects we love can so little possess our souls, that there should be room for words; what has <hi>Manlius</hi> seen in <hi>Otho,</hi> till this Minute, that could call him dull or vain; if not, sure <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s Eyes and Reason must beget both Amazement and wonder, and let not the Excellent <hi>Clorinda,</hi> because I am silent, doubt her Power; for know, my bus●e soul was full of surprizing Joyes, and unexpressible won|der; and my narrow heart blushes still to think, how short my love and Fancy fell; when they thought by Imagination to present the divine form and great mind of the Excellent <hi>Clorinda;</hi> to express whose Excellence where shall we find Epithetes, when a Lovers fancy could not comprehend it? O my Fate! can ye wonder, Ma|dam, at this dumbness and amazement in me, when I see my bar|barous heart upbraided by that scarf? that wound has shame be|longing to it, which will stain my soul for ever; and I could curse this prophane and Sacrilegious hand for violating that Temple where Honour, Love, and Beauty, with a perfect vertue, were en|shrin'd in those chaste Veins; till the prophane <hi>Otho</hi> warred against Heaven and <hi>Clorinda;</hi> at whose Feet behold the guilty ready to <stage>He kneels to her.</stage> weep out his last blood a Sacrifice, to appease the incensed <hi>Clorinda.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Do not despise me, Sir; for though <hi>Clorinda</hi> may lose her hopes, yet she will keep her Honour; and then, though she be not worth your Friendship, yet she ought to be above your scorn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Frown heaven, if I despise, or dissemble with the best of Women; and some Curse, new and beyond Example, as his sin, strike <hi>Otho</hi> at your Feet, if my soul have not a cleer faith and Ado|ration for <hi>Clorinda;</hi> nor will I rise from this place, till she believes
<pb n="232" facs="119"/>
and pardons me this crime, which thus, in shame and Repentance, I have confest.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, Sir; 'Twas the first favour I ever received from Prince <hi>Otho;</hi> 'tis an honour I shall ever be proud of; from this wound I gathered Courage, and began to hope your Highness had some value for me; Whilst Prince <hi>Otho</hi> turn'd away in Battle, whilst he received my Blows, and would not deign to strike again; he call'd me Woman, and despised <hi>Clorinda,</hi> which made me both with Love and danger hunt him till I had gained this Wound; then I began to hope, since he thought me worthy of his Sword, when we were Enemies, if we live to see a Peace, I might be worthy of his Friendship too; and if this Wound can make Prince <hi>Otho</hi> kind, I am happy to have bled for the health and safety of my Countrey; and if your Highness have kindness enough to wish it whole, Em|brace my Brother; Then you shall see, with what Pride I will kiss and wear this Scar.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(Otho <hi>runs to</hi> Amadeo.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>I embrace him, as I would my peace of mind, or <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s Friendship, and at her Feet throw my self and power; Here, Sir, ends all Acts of War betwixt us; And if We dispute again, it shall be to o'recome in kindness; Sir, I am here my Fathers Lieutenant; Till he and <hi>Rome</hi> Sign and Confirm my Acts, They are onely kind in|tentions, which have a readiness to shew how much my heart is vowed <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s; Though I believe the Senate will not dispute my Act; However, Sir, your are safe from this War; <hi>Manlius,</hi> let all the Garrisons be drawn off, while this Prince and People be re|ceived as Friends to the Senate; and see there be no injury shewn to the meanest person; but let all be treated like part of those whom thy friend Loves and Honours; at <hi>Millain</hi> we shall expect you, whither if your Highness please, we will repair, to stay my Fathers march; whose kindness is, now, upon the way, to pre|vent that Danger our Alarm gave him last Night.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall wait upon you, Sir, and not despair, by your in|tercession, to obtain the <hi>Pretors</hi> pardon for my uncivil depar|ture last.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Marius</hi> is too much a <hi>Roman</hi> to be displeased with a ge|nerous Act, though his Enemy perform it to his prejudice; Your Highness needs not fear your well-come where <hi>Marius</hi> commands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorin.</speaker>
                        <p>May your wishes find the Gods as propitious to you as you have been to us, while we love and Sacrifice to <hi>Otho,</hi> the No|blest of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Otho</hi> is, in all things, <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s Servant, and Prince <hi>Ama|deo's</hi> Friend; <hi>Manlius,</hi> you are sad.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorin.</speaker>
                        <p>Not displeas'd with our happiness, I hope.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven forbid; No, Gentle <hi>Clorinda,</hi> though I have been bred in Arms, unacquainted with the Peace and softness of the Court, nor ever tasted this Love you so greedily drink down, ha|ving never known nor sought other Honour then the Sword gave; yet I find, 'tis not impossible for <hi>Manlius</hi> to learn to love, if he had such a Lesson as <hi>Clorinda</hi> before him to imitate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>War, Sir, has been your Mistris, and your Business still;
<pb n="233" facs="119"/>
and 'tis a Trade that Princes learn with Honour; Swords are the Instruments, and with His the Noble <hi>Manlius</hi> has Writ high things; There is no Beauty like an Army, in a Souldiers Eyes; Victory is his Mistris; And passionately gallant <hi>Manlius</hi> has, all his life, pursued her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorin.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manlius</hi> has not yet seen any thing he thought beautiful, perhaps; but love will have a share in his heart: Honour and Cou|rage are but Fore-runners of that god, to prepare the Heart, when it shall bid Beauty and Vertue Well-come, which makes me pro|phesie, I shall live to see <hi>Manlius,</hi> for all his roughness, a passionate and a handsome lover.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manli.</speaker>
                        <p>She is a Witch, by this light; 'Tis the Divel, or love, vexes me already.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>If your Highness please We will retire, and give <hi>Manlius</hi> Opportunity to see the Army march.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>We are here to receive and obey your Highness Orders.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt. Manet Manlius solus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manli.</speaker>
                        <p>The Noblest of <hi>Romans!</hi> I am not envious, nor proud, yet the Noblest, me-thinks, is a Title should be bought at a higher rate then <hi>Otho</hi> has paid for it. Ambition is a Souldiers Beauty, Honour his Mistris; and I will not give place to any man when that is in dispute; What, a Pox, makes me thus Quarrelsome; Thus on the sudden concern'd in her Opinion; There is some|thing seems new and strange to my mind; 'tis troublesome, and yet 'tis pleasing, 'tis a vexation I never felt before; Her words raise a storm, and her Eyes allay it again; I never was concern'd in a Wo|mans thoughts before; Me-thinks I could now be strangely plea|sed to act something, that might please her; If this should be love What would become of me? A peace and Love both together, You must get a dark house for <hi>Manlius;</hi> They will make me fit for <hi>Hellebore;</hi> I will find <hi>Calis,</hi> and tell her my pain, she has talk'd of Love, and loving me; I will find by her, whether I am bewitched or no; My heart will not be idle, I perceive; We no sooner are proposing of peace, but he is busying himself with Love. All brave men I loved before; But never saw a Woman that could possess my thoughts; But this has so much of the Souldier in her, I begin to fear; I would I could see her spin; This storm has so disordered my mind, all things lie on heapes in my heart; Love and Hate, Reason and Honour, lie shuffled together; 'twill cost an Age, in thoughts, to Collect them, and place them as they were before this fatall day, so full of care. O! That I could see what fruit this bit|ter root can bear.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lucius, <hi>in a Disguise, with</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O Calis,</hi> all my fears are ripe, and the doubts my soul labour'd with are now delivered to the world, thou
<pb n="234" facs="120"/>
know'st my heart has try'd Love, in all his Passions, but never felt a Torment like a jealous mind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Whence this disorder? Why this fear? Is the Army De|feated?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, Victory and Peace attends it; And with that Peace, All my miseries flow in'; In short, <hi>Otho</hi> loves <hi>Clorinda</hi>'s beau|ty, and <hi>Amadeos</hi> Gallantry; all these several virtues make but a poi|son for <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Be plain; Or else Expect no help in my Counsel.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Know then, 'twas all our opinions, That <hi>Otho</hi> should make a Peace with <hi>Amadeo;</hi> which being done he now avowes his Love to <hi>Clorinda,</hi> whose heart has alwayes admired Prince <hi>Otho,</hi> and hither they are coming with speedy Marches, to renew the Ancient kindness betwixt <hi>Cicilia</hi> and <hi>Amadeo;</hi> which sprung first, when he was a Prisoner, more to <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s Eyes then <hi>Marius</hi> his Guards; you know the story: O <hi>Calis!</hi> had the Princess less ver|tue, or Beauty; Were fame silent in her praise, or had the noble <hi>Amadeo</hi> been onely born great, like wretched <hi>Orante;</hi> had not hea|ven given him Honour equal to his Birth, I could then have slept with a secure mind, seeing him love while she had despis'd; But his vertues, <hi>Calis,</hi> make me fear a second spring will grow, whose Harvest cannot but be fatall to <hi>Lucius.</hi> I conjure thee therefore, let my passion prevail above thy Reason, that I may receive the Ho|nour of speaking with the Princess, this Evening, that my trou|bled soul may find some peace from her, to calm my Jealous heart, whose doubts, and fears of my own worth, make me still Jealous I may lose the Jewel of my Heart; Dear <hi>Calis</hi> knows, I never pre|tended to purchase <hi>Cicilia;</hi> No such guilty vanity has stayn'd my Love; but, like an humble Beggar, still offer'd all my Heart for Love; And if her gentle mind can forgive this fear, which I can never lose, till she be mine, though a smile from her may allay <stage>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>She discovers her self first.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Enter</hi> Cicilia</p>
                           </stage> the Tempest that now distracts my mind.—Ha! The princess. Madam, if you have heard me, Behold, at your feet, the blushing and the guilty <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Rise, Sir, <hi>Lucius</hi> is welcome as mine own wishes; <hi>Lucius,</hi> to me, in his faults, even in this fear is well-come; and though I will not chide him, because his Fear is Love, yet I will counsel his Jealousie, which, to this hour, I confess, is not onely pardonable, but ought to be rewarded; Which thus I do. Know <hi>Lucius,</hi> Though <hi>Amadeo</hi> has Excellencies enough if 'twere possible to justifie a broken Faith; Yet it must not be where my friend is his Rival, Who has all that is required to make a happy Friendship, if not stain'd with Jealousie. Be therefore con|fident that I have Honour; And here must cease all the un|handsome fears that tell your heart ought, but <hi>Lucius</hi> shall en|joy my Love; And now I have said this, if <hi>Lucius</hi> shall again stain me with his Jealousie, I fear my heart will not bear such an Injury; For none but a faulty heart can doubt the Honour of his Mistris, when she has given her faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Madam, would you have me hate Jealousie,
<pb n="235" facs="120"/>
whilst you Excuse it, and reward it thus? 'twere Ingratitude; I ought rather to Sacrifice to that weakness, since it has been so fortunate as to make me happier then all the endeavours of my life be|sides.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Justice, Sir, shall ever prevail, and that makes me confess your jealousie to this hour was Innocent; for it tells me, <hi>Lucius</hi> was afraid to lose me; But if, after this declaration, he shall doubt a|gain, that doubt calls me false, and tells all the world I am not worth his Friendship; Therefore, if you love me, here you must begin to hate jealousie or I shall find as severe a Revenge to punish that Injury, as I did a kindness, to reward this Alarm which Love gave to <hi>Lucius</hi> his heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Madam, spin this Thread no finer, lest it break.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>I have done, the <hi>Pretor</hi> expects you, whither now I am going, and long to hear the truth of this Business, which has so much surpriz'd the Court.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Marius, Otho, Orante, <hi>and</hi> Dyon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>WHen we have paid our sacrifices to the Gods for this deliverance, not onely from a danger but from a warr too, 'twill then become <hi>Otho</hi> to provide for the entertain|ment of these Princes, like Friends and Allies to the people of <hi>Rome;</hi> whose Honour is no less at stake now when they are Friends, then when they declared themselves Enemies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall most gladly, Sir, receive this Commission; and I am so partial to mine own Heart, that I am apt to believe <hi>Rome</hi> never got more Honour from the Triumph over any Prince, then she will in the Friendship of those whose Virtues and Persons call the gallant part of Mankind to protect them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Amadeo</hi> has more years in his face, else the same Man he was when he fled unkindly from us; I confess, I never saw any stran|ger I had so much kind value for before. There is something too so <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Cici|lia <hi>and</hi> Calis</stage> new in the Princess <hi>Clorinda,</hi> which I cannot but admire and pity; and I would not, for my old Honours, this war had ended in the sword; 'twould have upbraided the <hi>Roman</hi> clemency; <hi>Cicilia,</hi> I observed, you were disordered at the sight of them; you see Beauty nor Virtue are not confin'd to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Far from me be the vanity or guilt, to wish the Gods should confine their Blessings; 'tis well if the <hi>Romans</hi> can preserve their own Honours, and nobler far then to seek the ruine or destru|ction of it in others; I confess, I never saw nor read of any persons more to be admired then these two Princes: And <hi>Rome</hi> joynes with me in their praise, since in all her pride of Empire she has thought these worthy both of Warr and Peace; and now, after seven years dispute she embraces them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="263" facs="121"/>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>Did your Highness never see them before? has there never been any League betwixt your selves or Nations?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Not any, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>Alwayes Enemies! What esteem had you of them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Nor Friends nor Enemies; unthought of, they lived by us. Good Heards-men, sullen, stout, hardy fellows, such as this his race have alwayes been; who because they know no better, seem to despise the valleyes wealth, bravery and luxury they are unac|quainted with; For what should they be drunk with? Milk? How exercise their gluttony? upon black bread and scorch'd flesh? For Cloathes, you see, they have as little variety as invention; a Sun-tan'd skin, with the Fur inwards turn'd, with the season, is the Wardrobe of their great Shepherd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>I find <hi>Orante</hi> has no great kindness for the Prince nor People; yet he cannot deny the Princess <hi>Clorinda</hi> is a strange ex|ample of Virtue and Courage; she fears no wounds not dangers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>She will play at foot-ball, thresh, and hew woods, as well as her Brother; Alass, Sir, 'tis not there as in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Eastern World, where the Women are soft, bred nice, and full of tender thoughts; Here is no difference betwixt the Sexes, but that they esteem them less then Men: Their Cowes plow too, and their Mares bear burthens, and their Women fight. No beast of that Country has any priviledge; and I wonder at nothing so much as the <hi>Roman</hi> Curiosity, that has made Warr thus long against this waspes nest in a Rock. By all our Gods, we never thought their Country worth asking for, we onely banish'd Malefactors thi|ther; and they have chosen rather to return and die here, then live and wither out their daies in that nest of Winter. Cold, Pover|ty, and Ignorance, are the onely commodities, I know, their Country affords.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, they have something else; they have a breed of stout and handsome Princes; Their Nation too have Loyalty, and <hi>Amadeo</hi> lookes like a Prince among his People, his Mind too is Princely; and though he live in a Cottage himself, yet his Soul resides in a Palace; which is nobler far then to see Fortune blindly give a Crown to a wretched Prince, who fills a Palace himself, while his Soul lies in straw.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>You are <hi>Otho</hi> that say this, else you should know <hi>Orante</hi> understands it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>And 'tis to <hi>Orante</hi> I say it; who, I am certain, has guilt enough to know I mean him; whose Envy cannot suffer the Virtues of a gallant Prince, and faithful People, should be praised; Be|cause he knowes 'tis upbraiding of him, who has neither Merit to win, nor Power to keep a Crown. Where were the Battles fought that wonn those fruitful Valleyes? What have we to triumph over in <hi>Orante?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, I say; the Prince is in our protection.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Let him talk on, Sir; he has Reason on his side; For <hi>Orante</hi> is both in Person and Fortune fit for <hi>Otho</hi>'s scorn: But if <hi>Ci|cilia</hi>'s eyes had not more Magick in them then his sword, I should
<pb n="237" facs="121"/>
ere this have found a way to be revenged.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Orante.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Otho</hi> raises stormes, and I must allay them; All this will fall upon my head; and, in serious earnest 'tis not well done to upbraid him with his Person or Fortune; you will rub that tender part till he grow desperate; A thousand times I have heard him say, 'tis yet in his power to kill a Prince, though he cannot restore one; which dark saying he will never explain with other answer, then, Am not I a Prince, may I not kill my self?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Let him be just to others, I will be just to him; Why should his ill Nature find excuse, and my truth be trouble|some? Why should he lessen my Honour in this Warr, by despising my Enemy, undervaluing, and detracting from the nobleness of those Minds with whom we have made a Friendship?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess you have reason to be angry, if the subject were worthy of it; but being branded with the marks of a Malici|ous Nature and an ill Tongue, you ought to despise his words; for how can you be handsomely angry with one you have overcome already? To whom you may give Honour, but can hope none; And I know <hi>Otho</hi> scorns such an easie secure Warr.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet I am then like my Sister, who, whilst she con|demns it, fights that battle, and has again overcome a Brother, whose Heart and Reason has by a thousand victories confess'd her Power, and still shall remain the loving, though the conquer'd <hi>Otho.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>When you see <hi>Lucius,</hi> let him know I would speak with him, and let us have no more of this dispute; You know, he is a thing we cannot fear, let him pass by; and since he has not Ho|nour enough to kill himself, let him live.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>How now, <hi>Calis!</hi> sad!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>So will <hi>Cicilia</hi> be, when she knows what I see.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee what can there be of new that should make me sad?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Did you observe <hi>Lucius,</hi> when <hi>Amadeo</hi> spake to you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Not particularly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>I have so much Friendship for <hi>Lucius,</hi> as to fear there may be some trouble in his Mind; some fears worth the remedy of his friends to cure betimes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>His fears? 'tis not possible, sure, that <hi>Lucius</hi> should have fears now; if he has, they will be more dangerous then any thing he apprehends; for if he fears me after this mornings satisfaction, he has lost my Heart; for I shall despise him that call me false. Love has but one path, but one safe way; he that would walk in two may lose himself; and I have told <hi>Lucius</hi> he is that way; and no|thing but his Jealousie and Injustice can make <hi>Cicilia</hi> stray.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter to them</hi> Orante.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>See, Madam, a visit not to be avoided; would <hi>Amadeo</hi> were no more to be suspected for <hi>Lucius</hi> sake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>While <hi>Orante</hi> is civil, I must bear his visit; and his Love
<pb n="238" facs="122"/>
is less injurious then <hi>Lucius</hi> his fears will be.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>If my return be troublesome, as my fears still tell me, unfortunate <hi>Orante</hi> is even in his Love to <hi>Cicilia,</hi> who has no guilt but what she and Love are to answer for; Behold I am come once again to offer, with humble thoughts, all the service of my life at <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s feet; Dot no despise me because your Brother throws his Injuries upon me; 'tis your Highness protects him from <hi>Orante,</hi> who fears nor loves any thing but <hi>Cicilia;</hi> for whose dear sake I have still born the burthen of my Miseries.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I am not now to tell you why your Propositions come too late; <hi>Orante</hi> is not ignorant of that Obligation <hi>Lucius</hi> has upon me; and to pursue me after that knowledge is such an Injury, as if <hi>Orante</hi> doth not repent and desist from, I shall be bound in Honour to punish.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>To punish you have reason, Madam; your Brother teaches all the world how to treat tame <hi>Orante.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Highness is onely sensible of those Injuries which are done to you, and never consider how you force Men into Passion; would you have heard a third person despise the Princes? I am con|fident you would not; why then should your Highness in a full Court speak disdainfully and sleightly of <hi>Clorinda,</hi> knowing what Passion the Prince and she have for each other?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>I despise her not, nor ever consider her or her Brother so much as to beget my Envy; I cannot admire them for lying in snow, and eating of black bread; they live and eat as they were bred; better food would set their teeth on edge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet 'tis great Virtue to bear those difficulties, and suffer them rather then lose their Honour; and will be admired by all generous Minds that shall read their story.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Not at all; no more then we admire our Horses for eat|ing grass, 'tis their Nature; nor is there more wonder nor pity due to what <hi>Clorinda</hi> acts or suffers, then to a Tree for standing in the rain; and I would call one as soon into my house as the other; they are all bred to't, 'tis their Countries Nature and Custom; their Fathers did it before them, and their Children must do it after them; 'tis Nature not Virtue you admire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>If this be not Virtue, what will plead for an Admira|tion in your sence? What do you believe worth Honour and Admiration?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Their contrary; to have been born great, heir to the pride of Nature, Prince of a Country the envious world, nay <hi>Rome</hi> her self, hath looked upon with covetous eyes to have pos|sess'd; That without trouble, fear, or danger, to have had all the blessings that the Gods could send a Man; To give these, nay be robb'd of these, and not feel the theft, but willingly suffer to be thus deposed from all his joyes for <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s sake. This if it be not worth her admiration, it deserves her pity at least, since she is the cause of all this misery; For her Beauty is the chain that binds me from taking Revenge for this theft, for whose dear sake I have di|gested all these scorns and injuries; Nay, I have brooked a Ri|val,
<pb n="239" facs="122"/>
a happy Rival too, because she loves him; but be not too ob|stinate in this cruelty, urge not a heart too far that is full of love and duty; your scorn may bow him till he breaks all bounds of Love and Honour, as you have done of Charity; My form, I know, is despicable; but Love is beauty still; Love can make me lovely, and scorn, gentle Maid, is as deformed as I am; and such a poyson it will even infect <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s heart, and make her ugly, even in <hi>Orante</hi>'s eyes; Scorn will do more then Reason, Love, or Ho|nour; 'twill beget anger, in whose darke shades, in whose storms Love and Beauty will be blasted; and then what succeeds, hate, dangerous hate, whose effect will be as full of misery to <hi>Cicilia,</hi> as Love has been to me; who cannot hope will be angry, and re|venge still waits a despairing Lover; and who ever he be that is despised, till he despise himself for loving so unfortunately, may when he will be revenged, though not pleased; your Father con|quered my Country, betray'd by those I trusted; all, but <hi>Orante,</hi> Treason gave you; but I was reserved to give a victory to <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s eyes; but if she still delight to frown, know, I can and will be free; but I have yet so much love, as to fear, for your Highness, what issue your scorn and my revenge may have. When I have the honour to see you next, and your Highness has considered what I have said, I shall hope my love may beget an answer to bind me ever to your feet; your pardon, Madam, I will retire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Orante.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>What do you study, Madam? is there any thing in this to be considered? haste to the Pretor, let him and your Brother be acquainted with the dangers that he threatens; he is no more to be trusted loose, my heart prophesies he will act some desperate vil|lany, if you permit him to walk and converse among us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>I have my fears too, but not for my self; <hi>Lucius</hi> and <hi>Otho</hi> are the objects of his hate and envy, which makes me apprehend, for them; else for what concerns me I despise him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Amadeo, Otho <hi>and</hi> Clorinda.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>WE will dispute this no more, Sir; pray give me leave that my faith and love to the fair <hi>Clorinda</hi> take all ways it can to express it self; I held it a duty in friendship, when I knew your noble heart had still retain'd his love to my Sister, not to expect your sollicitation to express my readiness to serve you; and since we have gain'd my Fathers consent, doubt not the rest; for I know she is too much a Daughter, and Sister, to refuse to meet our desires in Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi>'s love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>'T was the opinion of many when my Brother was prisoner here, the Princess was not displeased with his addresses; but ab|sence and such a diligent Rival as noble <hi>Lucius</hi> makes us fear a greater opposition then your kindness will apprehend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>That <hi>Lucius</hi> loves I doubt not, for <hi>Cicilia</hi> has beauty and
<pb n="240" facs="123"/>
vertue enough to win an esteem from the severest minds; but cer|tainly I am so much a friend to both, they will take no resolution without my consent.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, how blind is kindness; and how unlike to a Lovers passion is that which Nature owes, and pays betwixt Bro|ther and Sister; had your Highness my heart and my eyes, how visible would those Lovers appear? how many kind jealous doubts would their looks, this day, have raised in your heart? know, Sir, I am certain he pursued this late war more as my Rival, then your General; and how much against his heart this peace was made, time will shew; but when I consider his fears told him the Princes <hi>Cicilia</hi> was at stake, I love and forgive him for that hate; for she is cause enough to put the world in Arms, and worth the trial of their fortune, till she declare whose she is; and then 'tis equal sin and treason to oppose her desires, as 'tis now vertue and true honour to aspire her friendship.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>And if <hi>Amadeo</hi> be the man design'd for this blessing, The gods have largely paid all our sufferings, in the friendship of two such Princes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess, my fears make me wish the Princess had first been moved on my behalf; then the Pretors consent had com|pleated all my wishes; the honour I have had heretofore to practise her excellent mind makes me fear she should believe me faulty in this Proposition; for though it be kindnesse in your Highnesse, as a Brother, to move it to her Father; yet I that am a Lover know the first sacrifice of Duty and Prayer are to be paid to the Mistrisse; else she may believe I desire her friendship, but am loath to take the pains to win her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, Sir, no more fears; shall we in peace know that pain we felt not in war? or doubt a conquest over a Sister when honour pleads against her, will she deny to follow this president; and by the example of <hi>Clorinda</hi> that has blest me with her friend|ship, refuse to make <hi>Amadeo</hi> happy? she cannot sure, unless she re|sove to make me blush to death when I shall find how much I have loved, and how little reason I had to value her kindness.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clor.</speaker>
                        <p>If your Highness then will discover to her how far you are advanced (as unknown to us) 'twill be a way to inform your self, and prepare her for the love and service my Brother is ready to present.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>This morning I have design'd to speak with her, that she may not have any ground for her displeasure; I will only acquaint her with it, as my desire, which before I would proceed in it, I took my Fathers opinion; according to her answer, we will resolve; till when, your Highuess pardon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <pb n="241" facs="123"/>
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cicilia, <hi>and</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>YOur Highness is sad.—Pray heaven <hi>Lucius</hi>'s fears be vain.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Aside.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess, my mind never had more business then at this hour; then now my heart had never more use, nor ever was less capable, of counsel; divers interests plead within me, but honour shall still be my guide, and <hi>Lucius</hi> may (if he be wise) still keep his power over this heart; yet his second fear has made me so angry, that I begin my self to fear <hi>Amadeo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>And what do's that fear prompt you to?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>To believe that <hi>Lucius</hi> and my self had kind stars that re|moved him hence, lest such a gallant Rival might have disturbed our peace; for 'tis not easie, without partiality, to decide such a dispute as their love must have bred in a mind of honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>I do not wonder at <hi>Lucius</hi> his fears, since I find you doubt your own strength.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>I do not say this from any guilty thoughts of mine, which should give <hi>Lucius</hi> reason to be jealous; but as I apprehend the world may condemn me of my injustice to <hi>Amadeo;</hi> for certainly, with|out partiality to himself, <hi>Lucius</hi> could not pretend to that injustice which my kindness gave him; for my love to <hi>Lucius</hi> cannot blind me so but that I shall always confess I ow <hi>Amadeo</hi> what I can ne|ver pay; and though he nor the world shall ever know how much this debt troubles me; yet he shall have all the satisfaction I can in honour give him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess, Madam, the character that <hi>Manlius</hi> gives this Prince is enough to inflame the world.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manlius</hi> has his clouds too; and methinks, <hi>Calis</hi> should have remembred his praise of <hi>Clorinda;</hi> had I been she, 'twould have concern'd me more, <hi>Manlius</hi> is one I never saw before; and though my mind were too busie, then, to make an exact observati|on of him; yet, methought, there appeared none of that gayness in his humour, none of that voluble tongue men speak of; By this sight of him, <hi>Manlius</hi> is changed, or else the character I have heard of him was made by a very ill observation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall hide my fears no longer from your Highness, but confess his coldness since he returned; and that strict friendship he has made with Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi> makes me believe he has some de|sign on the fair <hi>Clorinda,</hi> which vain hope; when I consider, her mind and his Rival, I cannot fear he should be master of his wishes; yet the attempt will be enough to let me see I am past hopes of mine; for I know him of a nature most violent in his passion, ei|ther of love or hate, bred always a Souldier, and taught by success to know no opposition but what a Souldier ought to remove; yet when your Highness sees him you may, by some Questions, as by chance, inform your self of what I dare not mention.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="242" facs="124"/>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>He is Brother to <hi>Lucius,</hi> and friend to <hi>Calis,</hi> which are obligations enough to make me concern'd in his fortune, and to justifie such a curiosity; and if I can deserve from him, <hi>Calis</hi> shall find a diligent friend; and he shall be very crafty if he hide his passion from me; and if I perceive any name but <hi>Calis</hi> in his heart, I will so chide him, so shame him to himself, he shall not dare to pur|sue so injurious an act.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>But how will he brook this freedom, Madam, being so newly acquainted; I would not for the world he should believe I set you on; for we have still made it our business to hide our friendship, so much, that 'tis yet a secret to <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>That shews <hi>Manlius</hi> has not so open a nature as his Bro|ther; for I am confident <hi>Lucius</hi> has not a secret but <hi>Manlius</hi> knows it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Stella.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Stella.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, the General and the Lord <hi>Cleon</hi> are within to wait on your Highness.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>We will follow you; come <hi>Calis,</hi> a little patience will re|concile all; and remember these thornes will grow where there are Roses; 'tis as natural as his beauty, or his sweetness; and kind nature that gave us the Elixar of the Bee, gave him a sting to de|fend his Hive against Drones, but not to wound thee or me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, Madam, I am so perfect a Lover; I find little things make me fear, and less reason hope; yet 'tis as pleasant as strange, to observe in Loves war how many fear, and how few despair.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Orante, <hi>and his Banditoe.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bandit.</speaker>
                        <p>'TIs most certain, Sir, I heard your <hi>Bando</hi> proclaim'd; the people said 'twas published upon a complaint the Princess made of a violence that you threatned; three days you are limited to present your self.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Then there is three days to be revenged in.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Band.</speaker>
                        <p>I was told too, from a good hand, that Prince <hi>Otho</hi> had gain'd the Pretors consent for <hi>Amadeo</hi> to marry the Princess <hi>Cicilia,</hi> so to tye by a cross match an alliance betwixt the two Families.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>And all this stir only to compleat a curse for <hi>Orante;</hi> yet I have three days, and this Dagger left; and if this hand hold his humour, and this Dagger keep his point, I may spoil the Plot; my Lord, we must keep our friends and our selves still in readiness, and in this disguise walk amongst them, for a day or two; but this cursed person of mine that will lye hid in no disguise: how in the Devils name shall we contrive to obscure it? this hill upon my back calls all eyes to my vexation and my scorn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Band.</speaker>
                        <p>Like an old woman, stooping upon your staff, you may creep amongst them; and in that disguise frequent the temples, where you are sure to find an opportunity; and in these woods here you may abide amongst the old Hermits, and mingle with
<pb n="243" facs="124"/>
those beggars that haunt <hi>Juno</hi>'s Temple, while I prepare our design in the City; and when 'tis time then be resolute; and let us strike home, better dye at one blow then wither thus.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>How comes it they defer thus long the hunting of the Boar? <hi>Otho</hi> and <hi>Amadeo</hi> were wont to delight in that chase; me-thinks <hi>Otho</hi> should long to see his Virago, that cloven knight, come pricking over the Plains, clad in mighty Petti-coats, <hi>Clo|rinda</hi> hight; that hateful issue of a fruitful enemy, how comes she to change her savage mind for love?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Band.</speaker>
                        <p>Love has made her change her tragick Buskin, and now she delights in the soft steps of Comick love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure all the world changes its nature only to vex me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Band.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, Sir, we must now leave to wonder or talk; and resolve speedily to take our revenge upon them; your disguise shall this morning be with you; and if I can learn any news you shall immediately have it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Banditoe.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Orante.</speaker>
                        <p>To what a streight am I forced by Love and Fortune! how have I armed all the world against me! but Nature, unkind Nature was my original enemy, who has not only set the world, but my self against my self; mine own eyes despise this object, what wonder then if <hi>Cicilia</hi> hates it; yet I love <hi>Cicilia,</hi> and her mercy is as due to my love as her scorn is to my person; but 'tis not my deformity makes me despair, but <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s love of another; that is it makes my blots so visible, and my despair so high, that of all the passions mans heart is capable to feel, revenge is only in my power; and that, if fate deny not, <hi>Orante</hi> will command.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Orante.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Otho <hi>and</hi> Cicilia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>YOur anger, Sister, is more unreasonable then your de|sires; and the worst way you can take to satisfie a friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>When my heart tells me I have injur'd you, like a Sister that honours and loves her Brother I shall humbly beg your par|don; but you must give me leave to say, I am injured now, which I will not dispute with <hi>Otho;</hi> whose heart is so busie about his own love, he has no leisure to consider his Sister; else I am confident he would have spoken to me before he had engaged himself, or my Father; and 'tis not the least of my troubles to find a Brother that I have loved, so sleightly to part with me to please another, with|out a thought of <hi>Cicilia,</hi> or her future happiness; I must there|fore tell you, Sir, I am engaged to <hi>Lucius,</hi> who has honour and love for me; and humbly he has vow'd it, and I have kindness enough to see it. This I know is no secret to <hi>Otho.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Engaged! how can you engage, or how dares <hi>Lucius</hi> re|ceive it? have not you a Father and a Brother? have they no share in <hi>Cicilia?</hi> sure you will make but an unhandsome present,
<pb n="244" facs="125"/>
if you give their part without the consent of such friends.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>At least my own part is free for me to give, and that is <hi>Lucius</hi> his, the rest you may give to <hi>Amadeo;</hi> and if <hi>Lucius</hi> keep his value, all the interest I have in <hi>Cicilia</hi> is his, and nothing but <hi>Luci|us</hi> shall make me forsake him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>You are now in passion, yet that shall not make me lose my kindness, nor my respect; nor can you wonder to find me sur|priz'd with this answer, since 'tis the first time I heard <hi>Lucius</hi> his pretence had gain'd your heart; and what I did in moving for Prince <hi>Amadeo,</hi> was in kindness; believing his love would be wel|come to you, without making you blush at the saying so; nor was this my single opinion. But I have done; and since <hi>Lucius</hi> has for|got the respect he owes to me and my Father, I shall find other ways to resent his injuries; he is no Brother, yet, though <hi>Cicilia</hi> be a Sister.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Nor <hi>Otho</hi> a Brother longer then he is just to <hi>Lucius;</hi> 'tis not threats nor anger can prevail with me; I have too much of <hi>Otho</hi>'s nature in me to be beaten into any mans opinion; if your kindness and Reason cannot overcome me, your anger shall not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                        <p>Something I shall do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Otho.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>This rash act of <hi>Otho</hi> has forced me to discover our Resolutions, which I meant should have lain hid till <hi>Lucius</hi> could have made his way to my Fathers consent, who has long since been acquainted with our frindship; and knows how much I have been concern'd in the honour and fortune of <hi>Lucius;</hi> I cannot there|fore but wonder he should give his consent to <hi>Amadeo,</hi> without speaking with me; 'tis not of yesterday that we have been friends, and he has known it; nay, I know he has not been displeas'd with <hi>Lucius</hi> his pretence; I will be better satisfied, for I believe 'twill prove only the importunity of <hi>Otho;</hi> but I must mind the present business; passionate men when they do injuries they are loath to see them; and <hi>Otho</hi> is as much displeas'd as <hi>Lucius</hi> ought to be, and his threats are fit for my fears; for I know <hi>Lucius</hi> will no more endure a threat then <hi>Otho</hi> will fear to give it; something I must do in time to prevent what the pursuit of such a passion may breed betwixt 'em: They are too much Lovers, for Reason or Friendship to se|cure them; <hi>Clorinda</hi> is at stake in <hi>Otho</hi>'s anger, concern'd in her Brothers love, equal with her own; and I am at stake with <hi>Luci|us,</hi> who I am vain enough to believe will not, for fear of any mans anger, quit his pretention. These thoughts distract me.—See <hi>Calis,</hi> she is come as if sent from heaven; she shall know all, <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Calis.</stage> and acquaint my Father with it, as her own observation; so to se|cure them from deciding by the sword what <hi>Otho</hi> pretends to; and she shall intimate to my Father how unkindly I took <hi>Otho</hi>'s motion; and how to the heart it struck me; that after all the love and duty I had shewn him, a Father could part so sleightly with me; and consent to rob <hi>Lucius</hi> of the reward of all his faithful service, and give his friend to a stranger, unask'd.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Calis,</hi> there is an accident hapned this morning,
<pb n="245" facs="125"/>
which will require both thy kindness, friendship, and discretion, to manage our part of it; within my friend shall know all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lucius.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius,</speaker>
                        <p>I met the Prince, and he would not speak with me:—There is the Princess too, I will speak my griefs to her before my fears take root, and try if her friendship hath kindness enough to weed them out. Hah! gon without speaking to me!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Cicilia <hi>and</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Stella.</speaker>
                        <p>See, Madam, there he is,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Stella, Cicilia, <hi>and</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis enough, away <hi>Calis;</hi> make haste, I will entertain him here while you return.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Leave the rest to me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Otho</hi>'s Injuries have made me forget those of <hi>Lucius;</hi> and my kindness has now spent that stock of anger I had for him, that should have armed my Justice against him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>She is troubled too; I fear, Madam, my visits are un|seasonable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>If there were nothing more unseasonable in <hi>Lucius</hi> his Heart then this visit, he would not think so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Love, Madam, is a fruit alwayes in season in a Lovers Heart; and other fruit then Love <hi>Lucius</hi> his Heart never bare for the fair <hi>Cicilia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Why then, after all my kindness, do's he fear his Harvest?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>That storms, Thieves, or the wild Boar may destroy it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>But he is a Mad-man that will for fear of these possible ills afflict himself as if they were come; or cut his Corn green to prevent the Lightning that might blast it when 'tis ripe; And a jealous man is this Mad-man, and Jealousie will be that storm, that Boar, that Thief you speak of; And if <hi>Lucius</hi> will not leave con|versing with that Enemy to Honour, which will break all bands and Laws of Friendship, he will find too late the danger of such an Injury as pursues with doubts and fears a Heart that loves him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>This Remedy, Madam, will not cure the wounds that afflict my Mind, they are too near of kin to my fears. Your anger was the greatest danger I apprehended; and since that is fallen upon me for loving, what would not my Heart doubt hereafter? Why should <hi>Cicilia</hi> be angry with <hi>Lucius</hi> for loving, if it did not hinder her from receiving the Love of another?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet I have kindness enough, notwithstanding this An|swer, to tell <hi>Lucius</hi> when ever I shall dare to be false, I shall not fear his displeasure; and a few hours will shew him, though Jealou|sie be at all times as unreasonable as the fears of Cowards, (which makes them ridiculous when there is no danger, and disarmes them when there is;) Yet, at this time 'tis most injurious; and if <hi>Lucius</hi> be a Lover, he has no way but that to destroy his <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Calis <hi>and whispers to</hi> Cicilia,</stage> hopes.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(Speaks softly.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="246" facs="126"/>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis done, the <hi>Pretor</hi> was much troubled at the accident, he has sent to command them both to their Chambers. The Prince was seiz'd while I was there; and <hi>Dyon</hi> is now coming with a Guard for <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Dyon <hi>and a Guard.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Hah! <hi>Dyon</hi> and a Guard, what will this be?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dyon.</speaker>
                        <p>This Ring, Madam, will make my excuse; By virtue of which, and the <hi>Pretors</hi> command, I beg your Highness leave to deliver his pleasure to the General.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>There is nothing, Sir, but Duty in this place.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dyon.</speaker>
                        <p>My Lord, 'tis the <hi>Pretors</hi> pleasure you retire to your Chamber; where I shall wait upon you till I receive further Orders.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>To my Chamber!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>If I have any power, I shall beg of <hi>Lucius</hi> to submit to this command.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis enough, Madam; when your Highness saies die, though I do notlove enough to please, yet I shall obey you, though it be to become a sacrifice to my Rival; Sir, you may execute your command, I am ready to obey.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dyon.</speaker>
                        <p>The <hi>Pretor</hi> commanded me, in his name, to prohibit your Lordship from sending a Challenge to, or receiving any from, the Prince or any Man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>What Riddle's this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>In the evening, at your Chamber, I will inform you of all: till when, let no troubles afflict you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, I can obey; and that's the true obedience, when we do it onely to shew what power they have who command; without requiring any reason for them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Lucius <hi>and</hi> Dyon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Why did you not tell him the cause of the imprisonment?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Because I am loath to declare so absolutely against a Brother, as to joyn with his Enemy against him; Therefore, dear <hi>Calis,</hi> go from me to <hi>Lucius,</hi> whom thou wilt find fuller of di|straction then ever; tell him all that is past betwixt my Father, <hi>Otho,</hi> and my self, concerning <hi>Amadeo,</hi> and his desires; Tell him of the consent they have gained; but withall assure him, 'tis in the power of nothing but <hi>Lucius</hi> to alter my Resolution; Tell him, I have confessed our Loves to <hi>Otho,</hi> which bred his Anger, whose threats begot this Imprisonment; But then conjure him to remember, <hi>Otho</hi> is my Brother, and not to think of a Revenge upon him, if he loves <hi>Cicilia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall not fail to observe your directions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Love is so short-liv'd, and subject to so many diseases, that few Lovers live long enough to know their names or reme|dies; Nay, some die with Receipts by them ere they know which to use; I am now to cure <hi>Lucius</hi> of his fears, and yet observe the duty and kindness due to a Father and a Brother, though <hi>Otho</hi>
                           <pb n="247" facs="126"/>
(unkind) to shew his Love to <hi>Amadeo,</hi> forget a Friend in <hi>Lucius,</hi> and a sister in <hi>Cicilia;</hi> And now how shall we remedy these ills? though We know how to cure them, yet we are to seek the Ingre|dience; for though the Receipt be common, yet where are the Drugs? Justice will cure all, but partial Love, in <hi>Otho,</hi> conceals the remedy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Cicilia.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lucius <hi>(in Prison)</hi> Memnon, <hi>Cleon, and</hi> Souldiers.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>PRince <hi>Otho,</hi> Sir, is a Prisoner too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you know the Reason?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>Not certain, there are divers Reports.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>Some say, that the Prince and <hi>Amadeo</hi> have from the <hi>Pretor</hi> obtain'd the princess <hi>Cicilia,</hi> which bred a dispute betwixt him and the Princess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! Prince <hi>Amadeo?</hi> has the <hi>Pretor</hi> given him his con|sent? <hi>Otho</hi> would not speak to me this morning; foul! foul! that I am dull, cold, negligent <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>Prince <hi>Orante</hi> too is fled to <hi>Rome,</hi> disguis'd, as they say, with the news, and some Injurious words that <hi>Otho</hi> gave him late|ly; In short, the <hi>Pretor</hi> and prince are full of disorder, your Bro|ther too is missing; observed to be dull and melancholly of late, and do's look much upon <hi>Clorinda.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Orante</hi> is this day banished, at the Complaint of the Prin|cess, to whom he threatned violence, and has but three days to ap|pear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis <hi>Amadeo,</hi> and <hi>Lucius</hi> must dispute this; and if thy fate give thee <hi>Cicilia,</hi> I will wish thee all Honour and happiness; But know, neither her Father nor Brother shall make me quit my Interest, though <hi>Cicilia</hi> her self joyn; the Sword onely shall decide our doubts. 'Tis visible now why she made me stay till <hi>Calis</hi> re|turn'd, with whom she whisper'd when <hi>Dyon</hi> ent'red with the Guards; The plot is visible, 'twas contrived betwixt her and <hi>Otho,</hi> this morning; to bind my hands till they had past the Ceremonies of a wicked and a perjur'd Hymen; She conjured me too I should remember <hi>Otho</hi> was her Brother, whose Interest has prevail'd; and, to please <hi>Clorinda, Lucius</hi> is to be sold, and condemn'd to misery for ever; her stay too confirms my fear; for her promise was, her self to come and clear my doubts; and <hi>Otho</hi> is made a Prisoner too, for fear of my Revenge; 'tis clear as the Heavens she is fore|sworn by.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>He is strangely netled with this news; it makes me be|lieve, there are some grounds for these discourses concerning him and the Princess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Amadeo</hi> is yet at Liberty; I will find him before he has <stage>Aside.</stage> time to triumph over my misery; This Window is not high, When they are gone, I will leap it; But how to be rid of the Importunity of these people! I will forbid them to let any body speak with me,
<pb n="248" facs="127"/>
and, under a pretence of a privacy when I write this Evening, make my escape; <hi>Cleon</hi> pray give Order for a Pen, Inke and paper, I will write to the <hi>Pretor.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit a</hi> Souldier.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>You are sad, Sir; which the Noble <hi>Lucius</hi> cannot be, but all that love him must be curious to know the cause; you wrong us too, if you conceal it; He is not born, Sir, shall injure you; Pray tell us onely the publique part of the cause; and if We can serve you, command us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>I thank thee, <hi>Memnon;</hi> and if I thought both the Court and Camp had not been full of it, I should my self have told you. Know then, <hi>Amadeo</hi> has broke my Friendship with <hi>Otho,</hi> and his Sister; We have long been Rivals in Love and Honour; But <hi>Ama|deo</hi> has the odds; <hi>Clorinda</hi> is a powerfuller Argument, then all my Services; she pleads with <hi>Otho;</hi> to please whom <hi>Lucius</hi> must be sa|crificed to <hi>Amadeos</hi> Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>I am glad to hear 'tis no worse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>No worse? dost thou understand what I have said?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi> is your Rival. Will you kill all that love the Princess? 'twill be a great task, though <hi>Lucius</hi> undertake it; and when he has done, he must fall upon his own sword too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>What has he said?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>By my faith, Sir, much reason me-thinks; and if you hate the Prince for loving your Mistriss, what would you do to him that should hate her?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Kill him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>So you would do this that loves her, if you had your will; how ridiculous would this be, in one of us, that should di|spute the rewarding Love and hate alike? Well, Sir, I am glad you have no other cause of trouble; By this light, I thought the Prince had rais'd some scandal upon her, struck her, or ravish'd her; these Injuries, I confess, had been fit for your rage and our Revenge; But to be angry with a prince, and sad, because he loves an Excellent, virtuous, beautiful maid!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>This is thy sence, <hi>Memnon;</hi> But love has his own reason; and though he gives Laws, he will take none; and Love has said, he cannot Love his Rival; and if Love be against you, what will your Reason avail?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>But the General had wont to give Reason place; even in his Anger, and his wounds, he would not be averse to Reason; else I should not venture thus rudely to give him my opinion. Pray, Sir, tell me, is it a Crime to love, or a sin to be loved? for in one of these two lies the guilt; if it be a sin in either, why are you so partial to believe your self Innocent for doing that which is a Crime in the prince? whose Love is Honour, rather then prejudice to you, and but justifies to the world that you have placed your Affection upon a deserving person; and this Injurious jealousie of yours, but shakes her Resolution; and, by disgusting of her heart, gives more ground to your Rival then ever his Addresses could have won. Were I the General, who would should love my Mistris better then I, so she loved me better then him; And then my Rival should break my
<pb n="249" facs="127"/>
neck assoon as my sleep, upon that score. Rivals are so many Wit|nesses and Arguments, so many Affidavites, that she has honour, so many Bucklers to defend her against the Envy and malice of the world; and when you fold her in your Arms, they become so many Trophies of your Victory; Rivals are, in Loves war, as Pri|soners, Colours, and the Cannon; Win the Battel, and lead them all in Triumph.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess, this is wild reason, yet such as I cannot deny; but what can you say to hinder me from hating and seeking to be Revenged on both, when you shall know the Prince tempted her, and she has broke her faith? and as I loved the vertuous <hi>Ci|cilia,</hi> so I hate this; for she is false, though she prove true to <hi>Amadeo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith, Sir, if this be so, (which few will believe) my Counsel is, that you should be silent; for she has such a stock of Reputation in the world, as no single Opinion, nor any one Action, can waste; and 'twill not be for your Honour, while the world esteems her, to say, I am that <hi>Lucius</hi> that the Princess <hi>Cicilia</hi> loved once, but she is now unconstant; 'tis the same thing, as to say, you had like have couzen'd her, but she found her Errour: Hide this misfortune, rather, as some imperfection; 'tis a story better forgot; for either, you were deceiv'd in her, or she in you; 'tis clear, one of you wanted your value; Come, Sir, let no man think to get any advantage over his Mistriss, or, to add to his own Esteem, by saying she is false; for no worthy man ever let a Gallant Woman be false; 'tis not possible to destroy a perfect Friendship, you may destroy nature as soon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>This plain speech has posed him; and if not cur'd his jea|lousie, yet he has so vexed him, I hope the Nobler Passion, anger, will possess him; This damn'd jealous sickness is as ill in a lover, as a Coward in a Souldier.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cleon,</hi> you have heard all this, and your silence makes me curious to know your sense of my suffering; you have studied and travel'd in your time, and are now a Souldier; how would you have born my part in these three several Conditions; When you were a Courtier, how would you have born it, had you found your Mistriss false?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith, Sir, in those youthful days I dwelt in the Garden where they grew; and when I found my self injured, as a wither|ed Flower I forgot her, and still gather'd some new Rose unblown with the praise or flattery of any; in whom I fancied still more pleasing Graces far then the former had.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>This was, when you were a young Courtier, <hi>Cleon;</hi> But now you are a Souldier, whose Passions, both of Love and Anger, are not onely Excusable, but laudable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, I would have given her love the lie, and in her new lovers face spit the vows and faith she gave me, and, to vex her, Cut his throat.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! 'tis but just a Souldiers anger should be revenged, not reasoned, nor argued into Peace; no Quarter to his Rival, nor
<pb n="250" facs="128"/>
violence to his Mistriss; I love thee, <hi>Cleon,</hi> and thou and I will talk further on this business.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Memn.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Sir, ask him how his Philosophy would have born it; hear all, and then chuse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>I would, as neer as I could, have imitated History, which delivers many stories to us, by which are preserved the honoured memories of chaste and vertuous Lovers, of both Sexes, whose Friendship stands high in Story; Many too are the blots that stain even the sheets they are writ in, whose black Actions and names are left as Terrours and whips, to deter mankind from becoming like them, the hated subjects of succeeding ages; Yet nothing has met my wonder more, nor bred my amazement so often, as to finde that excellentest of Creatures, Women, whose body and Nature, when virtuous, are so tender that we pity them if the wind blow sharp upon them; Yet when lust has prevail'd, and arm'd them, you would start to read where they have taken the sullen Mur|derer by the hand, and undaunted led him through difficulties even those men shrink at; Nay the murtherers heart has become soft; Poison has lost her force, and the Dagger his point, to save what they have doom'd to death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>No more <hi>Cleon;</hi> heaven keep <hi>Cicilia</hi> from breaking with the gods, if she should be false to men.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>Your patience, Sir, that I may Vindicate History, and my own memory, in being Just to that Sex whose very Nature is soft|ness, and these but the Monsters and depraved part of that Excel|lent Creature, lest the world believe I onely such the Poison out of History; Where I find more Excellency in that Sex then you once fancy'd in the divine <hi>Cicilia;</hi> where the Crimes of the wicked have not arrived to the sufferings of the good. Their constancy in Love, their often and patient becoming Martyrs to Friendship and Honour, as far beyond the merits, as faith of men, scarce one of them trusting that has not been betrayed by our perjur'd Sex; Mercy being their Nature, and oftentimes their Enemy, having rendred them miserable; For could they see us sad, they might laugh; But their pity of false men makes many of their Scenes set in tears and blood; and 'tis as rare to find a Constant man, as a faulty Woman; Yet I find History condemns revenge in either, Mercy in the last Act being as becoming a gallant Lover, as Love in the First, so to strive to win from the world a handsome Cha|racter, by forgetting and forgiving each others crimes; and those who seek by Revenge to vindicate themselves; The guilty has from that found pity, and their Rage stood condemned by gods and men; Yet, in this latter Age, we have deliver'd our selves up to a mistake of Honour; and Custome has made it so binding, that 'tis not to be disputed against, 'tis by Duel; which vain &amp; Cholerick men embrace with Joy, as a quick way for the one to be known to the World, and the other to be revenged of the World; Nay, wise men submit to it now, as a necessity; and though, in your case, some would fight, Yet there are divers would not; Much is to be said for them both, and against them, and the wilde Justice
<pb n="251" facs="128"/>
of a Duel; but he that disputes it must be some one that is known to plead against his own practice; for whoever will be heard to declaim against Duels must fight many first; and when his va|lour is undoubted, his Reason may prevail; but where to find such an Orator as will use his Rhetorique to perswade the people to <stage>Lucius <hi>frowns, gives no answer, but walks out.</hi>
                           </stage> pull down the fame he built at such a rate, I know not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mem.</speaker>
                        <p>I am glad to find there is so much of the old <hi>Lucius</hi> left, as will give over rather then be beaten.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>Have not I fitted him for a grave speech?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mem.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, I dare say, if he had thought thou could'st have re|membred so much of Books, he would have broke thy head ra|ther then open'd thy memory with a Question; he looked for a Sa|tyre, or some Ralliry.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>I guest as much, but thought this the shorter way; A pox on it, they know we are Souldiers, and have other business then to observe him while he besieges one woman, and defends another all his days; if he had staid, I was coming into mine own ele|ment; he knows we are Souldiers and Travellers; fit people to de|cide Questions in Platonick Love, that have been bred in the li|berty of other Nations, whose kindness has engaged me to defend that sweet sin he speaks against; if he had asked me what I would have ventured to enjoy another mans Mistress, 'tis a case I have been versed in, and he might have been resolved; but for the re|vengeful part, By my troth, I am to seek; for I never had any Mi|stress of mine own yet, upon which I ever cared to shut the door when I went out; that and Marrying I defie; my experience has taught me 'tis so much cheaper and easier to get another mans Wo|man, then keep mine own; and now he is gone, prithee be free; dost thou think the Princess a Rogue, Sirrah? By this light, if she be.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mem.</speaker>
                        <p>And what if she be?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>If she be, I am sure I am one; and I cannot chuse but hope; and if she be one of us, let <hi>Cleon</hi> alone to tell his tale; come, come, let us away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mem.</speaker>
                        <p>And if <hi>Cleon</hi> do's not, let me alone to tell it to the Princess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, well: when you dare tell, it will be a jest for <hi>Cleon</hi> to laugh at as well as <hi>Memnon.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Manlius, <hi>alone.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>SUre, Love makes me his scorn; and I that could not love any now dote upon all; <hi>Clorinda</hi> wiped <hi>Calis</hi> from my mind; the one sighs too much, and the other has too much anger in her eyes; and now all her graces fall too, since I saw <hi>Cicilia;</hi> in whom there is not more vertues, then difficulties; 'tis hard to say whether my Lover despair be greatest; why did my Brother and
<pb n="252" facs="129"/>
                           <hi>Amadeo</hi> praise her so to me or having praised her not hid her from mine eyes? either vanity or madness made them send me to her, for my destruction; my way was prepared too, by a friendly character; That I heard nothing but praises of <hi>Manlius</hi> from her, even then admiring <hi>Manlius</hi> for friendship and honour when his heart was busie how to destroy a Brother and a Friend: yes, those are the ties, those are the impossibilities that I must labour against; yet their Love, Birth nor Merit, I fear not; for though they star|ted before me, they shall not make more haste then I to gain the prize, could I reconcile the action to my self; but 'tis a breach of trust and faith to both, both have told me their several passions, and sent me as an indifferent friend to sollicite their hopes; <hi>Lucius,</hi> though he believed I loved <hi>Clorinda,</hi> yet that knowledge could not make him doubt an unjust action from me; and <hi>Amadeo,</hi> though I was his Rivals Brother, such a stock I had amongst them that the ties of Nature, nor interest of affection, could not make these men fear <hi>Manlius,</hi> who till he saw <hi>Cicilia</hi> was as honest as they were just; and could till then have defied the world to ac|cuse me of one wry step, or one stumble in the whole practice of my life, where honour was concern'd; but now by what curse I know not, friendship, honour and vertue seem sleight; her smiles are prefer'd before gods or men; yet how many crimes must both of us act ere I can enjoy her friendship: I love my Brother, his nature and sweetness of humour, so stout and kind it wins even upon his enemies; <hi>Amadeo</hi> too, how shall I look him in the face when I have betray'd his trust? their angers will be too just for the boldest man to meet; but that danger is the least, there is but sword to sword, and fortune may be as well on my side, as justice on theirs; and could I answer it to honour and friendship, I should not then make this dispute; but 'tis the friend, not the enemy threatens, and that will wound my soul ere I can be an enemy too; for my anger though it has been as fatal as any mans, yet 'tis most unreasonable here; and therefore I must take some quiet secure way to gain my ends; how unwilling I am to be a villain! ye gods that see excuse, or divert the crime; but what if she will not receive my love, what rests for me? 'twill be too late to put back when I have discover'd the villain; she will hate, and they despise me; and I shall sell all my past honours for a shadow; what rests then? Force. Ha! good gods! what may not man be if he will once break the bounds of honour? see if I have not already swallowed the great difficulties of Friend and Brother, and given up that honour I have preserved through a thousand hazards; and lust, finding it self master, would not only reign, but bring in murder too; sure I was never honest, never stout, all my fighting was but cowardize, nothing but fear to dye made me defend my self; If I had either honour or courage in my heart, they would now defend me against my self, and make me ashamed to yield my sword to lust and treachery; sure if it were ever lawful to kill, 'tis now; for a greater villain then my self no man can strike.—See this Dagger prompts me to it; the act will be no|ble, <stage>He draws his Dagger.</stage>
                           <pb n="253" facs="129"/>
having first in two short li●es writ the cause; then to stab and dye, she could not chuse but love me when she shall know I fell in this strife, her martyr; I will do it; since I cannot live worthy her love, 'tis resolved I will dye to find her pity.—Ha! see, see, ye gods, she comes, her eyes shake my resolution. <stage>
                              <hi>Ent.</hi> Cicilia.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Calis</hi> stays long, <hi>Lucius</hi> will be impatient to know the cause of his imprisonment; see his Brother, he is sad; I will take this opportunity to try if I can find who it is he loves; and while <hi>Calis</hi> is busie to serve my friend, I will try if I can advance her de|sires, though my mind a● this time be not bent to mirth.—What makes the gallant <hi>Manlius</hi> so sad? thoughts are such strangers to his humour, that 'tis a civil curiosity to inquire the cause; sure something new and excellent must be hapned that's able to disor|der his mind whose happy Stars have made him all he can, in ho|nour, wish; is it your Brothers imprisonment, Sir, that troubles you? if it be, let me assure you, there is neither dishonour nor danger in't.—Ha! he minds me not, or at least will not trust me <stage>He stands lost in his thoughts.</stage> with his secret; yet <hi>Manlius</hi> knows that I at first sight gave him all the secrets my heart ever swell'd with; and if he refuse me his friend|ship, I shall belleve he thinks me not worthy of his Brothers love, or else grudges me his kindnesse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven and earth witness; and I guilty? who knows his fate till he proves it? how beautiful, even in her hatred, will the <stage>Aside.</stage> fair <hi>Cicilia</hi> appear; but thus adorn'd with friendship, and her words thus cloath'd in kindness, how divine, how charming every grace! there is Magick in every sound, her words whisper my soul to be happy, and something bids me be a villain; if the loves, I shall be happy enough, in her embraces, to weigh down the opinion of the whole world besides.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>What strange accident is befallen him that can make him thus silent; there is distraction, fear and wonder in his looks, and all I say passes without regard.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manlius, </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>I will speak to her, she is alone.—Do's not your Highness find a new kind of character here? is not <hi>Manlius</hi> his mi|sery visible in his forehead?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and 'twas my wonder.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>My distracted heart and troubled mind, are they not writ so plain in my face that your fair eyes may find and read my for|tune there?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis true, and one whose eyes are less concern'd then mine may find a new kind of humour in every look; every moti|on tells something strange is hapned in <hi>Manlius</hi> his fortune; and my heart has so much gratitude and kindness for him, that if it lay in my power, I would serve him faithfully; but finding him un wil|ling to impart them to so idle a subject as <hi>Cicilia,</hi> I shall leave you; lest my company be as troublesome as my Question.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manlius, </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>Why this, if not more? why should she tempt me thus, if her heart had not love she never shew'd, nor I durst hope before? I will tell her I love her, she is a woman; and what if she once had honour, so had I; yet she had power to blow that
<pb n="254" facs="130"/>
bubble hence, and who knows but that I am design'd her fate, as she was mine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He sighs and weeps.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! he sighs and weeps; why these tears, <hi>Manlius?</hi> why these sighs? what can thy heart wish or desire within the bounds of honour that <hi>Manlius</hi> should despair of? pray tell me your griefs, I may be a friend where you least believe it; for I know something; and, perhaps, have seen what you would fain have hid.—Sure he loves <hi>Clorinda,</hi> and is asham'd to think of his faults to <hi>Calis.</hi>
                           <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>Know, Madam, your kindness has ripp'd ope my heart; and now take a secret, the first and last of my life; too great for my heart, though too little for her I would present it to; a fatal one, I fear, and yet 'tis love; doubting, humble, and faithful love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Then the gods have heard the wishes of his friends, if <hi>Manlius</hi> be a Lover.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! what do's my surpriz'd heart hear? do's your High|ness rejoyce to find <hi>Manlius</hi> a Lover? that glad sound has struck confus'd joy to my heart; nor do I know how to understand that joy of yours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Manlius,</hi> thy noble Brother and my self have often wished thee a Lover, to refine thy mind, and weed some harshness, and those wild thoughts from it, which like weeds infest the noble flowers that nature had planted, and honour watred in thy Soul|diers heart; love in <hi>Manlius</hi> is all he ought to wish for, or his friends rejoyce in; love will make him envy'd by those that hate him, and ador'd by those that love him; of which number none is a more real admirer then <hi>Cicilia;</hi> and happy she, who ever she be, that is born to reign in thy heart; for <hi>Manlius</hi> has courage, and all that is required to make a happy friendship; and now I beg to know who it is, that after a curious and a long search <hi>Manlius</hi> has found worthy of his faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>O Madam, when you know that you will hate me, and say I have reason to be sad, and curse those Stars that have cursed you and me; can the noble <hi>Cicilia</hi> see a Lover in my eyes, and not find who it is by my actions? is <hi>Manlius</hi> so general a Lover that his passion cannot be discerned? Is he such a dumb distracted thing in all companies, that his disorder cannot speak her name he bows to? must my trembling tongue tell her name ere your High|ness discern it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, my busie heart has been so intent upon her own business, I never observed it diligently till now; but rather then be troublesome to <hi>Manlius,</hi> I shall wait his leisure, and not rudely press into his secret thoughts, unless I can serve him; and then he wrongs me if he conceal his love, who will to the world avow the friendship and value my heart has for him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manlius, </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>Why shall I be silent longer? I will tell her I love the gentle <hi>Cicilia.—</hi>Stay, Madam, and take the secret of my soul,—'Twill not out; I have yet so much honour as to guard the door <stage>She is going out.</stage> against that guilt that would fain tell you, I love; and the divine <hi>Cicilia</hi> is the object; and if you be curious to know how much; to death, by all.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="255" facs="130"/>
                        <speaker>Cicil.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, no more; my busie innocence, and folly, you have in two words sufficiently punished; yet you will find we are both deceived; I in a vain false opinion that <hi>Manlius</hi> had honour, and was worth my friendship; I should not else thus have betrayed my self within his power, where he shall find his part too, for having so low a thought as durst doubt my honour; but since I have found him false, I shall live to repent my errour, as he will do this mean opinion of me; Go hide thy self, false man, till thou can'st repent the injury thou hast done thy Brother; and if there be any spark of that honour left in thy heart which the world took fire at, let shame kindle that flame again; Go repent, sleep, and forget this treacherous act, and wake again worthy of thy Brother and thy friend; I have yet so much kindness as to be sorry for thee; and if thy fault dyes here, for thy Brothers sake, it passeth as a dream, and we will awake, to morrow, friends again, else thy love shall not exceed my hate and scorn; No reply; I have an Ar|gument in mine own heart pleads for thee, more then all thy words can do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Cicilia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manl.</speaker>
                        <p>What a fool was I to put my self into the power of for|tune, whose blind partial hands have still opposed me? vain deity, by me no more valued when thou fawnest, then when thou frown|est; but more despis'd for thy false flattery when thou smiledst in the beginning of our discourse, then thou art hated now, when thou hast declared thy self and her mine enemy; thou found'st me, this morning, relying upon honour and vertue, whose faithful pro|tection had I not abandoned to lean upon thy rouling-wheel, I had still kept the honour of <hi>Manlius;</hi> who striving to become one of thy Minions is now left fit for Chains and Greaves; which of thy hated great ones attain to honour, but they are at last hurried to fates more violent then their fortunes? I am now embarqued, and engaged beyond my own knowledge; and dare not find safety from the counsel of my friends; now the blackness of this act ap|pears when I dare not tell my friends how miserable I am; this shame is only left me for a sting to my soul; and all the Reason and Honour I have left is only to make me ashamed of what I have done; <hi>Calis</hi> too, my last counsel; her kindness is barr'd at this time; yet something I must do to lose the old <hi>Manlius,</hi> or to find the new.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Amadeo, <hi>and</hi> Lucius <hi>in a Disguise, following him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>THough I am not guilty of <hi>Otho</hi>'s fault to the Princess, yet I am afraid to appear before her; and methinks, there is a kind of guilt in being unlucky where we love; and <hi>Otho</hi>'s kindness too hastily imploy'd, has, I fear, gain'd me her dis|pleasure yet her justice makes me hope when my innocency shall appear, 'twill find her pardon; for if I find her heart given to my Rival, Heaven forbid I should oppose her desires, but rather with
<pb n="256" facs="131"/>
sacrifice of my own give her back the promise and engagement of a Father and a Brother; for <hi>Amadeo</hi> shall never receive his Mistress but from her own hands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, this paper is directd to your Highness; do's it re|quire no answer? <stage>Amadeo <hi>re|ceives the pa|per, and walks away.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amad.</speaker>
                        <p>Follow me to the Princess <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s lodging, and you shall have your answer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Amadeo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>He is grown vain and insolent already; Death! is the Princesses Chamber become your place of audience already? Hell upon him, he will date it from their bed, if I prevent not their speedy Hymens, I am mad with rage; <hi>Cicilia</hi> came not neither, nor <hi>Calis,</hi> as she promised; <hi>Manlius</hi> is sullen too, and out of the way when I should use his counsel; the whole frame of friendship is fallen in pieces, as if the world conspir'd to make <hi>Lucius</hi> miserable, without the remedy or protection of one friend to advise him; yet kind fate has left this to protect me.—But while I talk, and forget my <stage>Lays hold on his sword.</stage> self, I may be miss'd and prevented; and to live without <hi>Cicilia,</hi> or a revenge for her, were to exceed all sick men, or chain'd slaves in scorn and misery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Lucius.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Calis, <hi>and the Guard, as from</hi> Lucius <hi>Chamber.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>SPeak with no body!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas his command.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, I will make your excuse, for disobeying him this time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Madam, pardon us; till he calls we dare not open the door.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cal.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you fear I should bring him a challenge? well, Sir, I will retire; and when you see him, pray, tell him that I was here to have spoken with him from the Princess <hi>Cicilia;</hi> and I believe he will not thank you for refusing me the door.—This passionate man will suck poyson out of every flower; and I know his jealous <stage>Aside.</stage> humour and cholerick heart is now gnawing it self; and con|cludes all the world false to him, and has not patience to imagine one truth of his business; 'tis the greatest misery in the world to have a friendship with such a jealous nature to whom all things ap|pear as his fears present them; and what is meant with most kind|ness, their jealous nature corrupts into injuries, so that 'tis impossi|ble but friendship wanting the nourishment of faith must wither and dye; and were I so miserable as to love such an humorist, I would set my heart before him, and let him carve himself; for 'tis impossible to please him, give him what bit he will: Now in the evening when he shall hear I was at the door, how he will storm that I came not in! and if he had not been obey'd, his rage would have been as great; there could be no reconciliation with a jealous man; but that we know, jealousie commits and punishes her own crimes; for none of those doubts but has his own sting, which car|ries
<pb n="257" facs="131"/>
Revenge as well as Injury for the Lover. I am now to find the Princess, and when she shall know he refus'd to speak with me, 'tis ten to one but she grows as angry as he is jealous. They have indeed both their diseases, though from different causes; which I fear will never be cured till they are bound in a pair of sheets to|gether; Hymen and a Bed some Physitians hold a certain cure for Love; would <hi>Manlius</hi> and I had honestly tryed the Receipt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Calis.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. VI.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Amadeo <hi>alone.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo.</speaker>
                        <p>SHe is all a perfect Myne of Virtue; no one thought but has a guard, such as Modesty and perfect Honour set over the Hearts of Princes; Her words werefull of Justice, and though she conceived her self injur'd and neglected in her Brothers Treaty, yet her Answers were calm and full of civil sence; still mentioning me and my passion with respect and sadness, which has so divided my thoughts I know not how to proceed; If I pursue her against her will, there is nothing but hatred to be ex|pected. I will observe her, and make <hi>Clorinda</hi> break my way either to her Love or Friendship; and if my Fortune will not make me hers, yet I will have the pleasure of contributing my own peace to the making her as happy as she desires.—This paper I had forgot: Ha! from <hi>Lucius!</hi>
                        </p>
                        <floatingText type="letter">
                           <body>
                              <head>
                                 <hi>Lucius</hi> his Challenge to <hi>Amadeo.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <opener>
                                 <salute>SIR,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>I Have this Evening broke Prison, and so I shall all Laws and Civility too, rather then out-live the Injury your Highness has done me. The Princess</hi> Cicilia <hi>is a Jewel nothing but your Sword can win from me; though her Ambition has made her break her Faith. And since I can promise my self no longer the being beloved, I am resolved to be re|venged, or fall in the attempt. This Morning I shall expect your Highness under the wood side by</hi> Juno<hi>'s Temple, where I shall attend you alone with my Sword only. The Honour I have had to know your High|ness makes me not doubt the receiving this satisfaction, that I may at least preserve my Honour, though the rash</hi> Cicilia <hi>has falsely prophan'd hers.—</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Lucius.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                        <p>Fond <hi>Lucius,</hi> dost thou need more Enemies then thy self? Thy wild injurious Heart has wrong'd a Princess, whose least thoughts thou art unworthy of; and, for her sake I will meet thee; and if my Innocence be any guard, I shall punish thy low thoughts of the most excellent of Women. <hi>Cicilia</hi> break her Faith? Vain and
<pb n="258" facs="132"/>
and false? He would have me believe she has given it him. Fool! She knows too well the value of that Jewel to give it thy savage Heart. Rash <hi>Cicilia!</hi> Rash <hi>Lucius</hi> rather, whose madness has now made room for my hopes, and given an occasion I could not have hoped for; And I shall take it, to shew how much I loved the Princess, and how little thou deservest to be preferr'd before me. Sure no Man of Honour could ever have thought he should have occasion to draw his Sword in the defence of the Princess <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s Honour against one that knew her. And who knows but For|tune has appointed this Injury to give me the advantage of the Sword against <hi>Lucius,</hi> who thus long took <hi>Romes</hi> Sword, not to fight his Countries quarrel, but his private interest; and pursued me as his Rival, not <hi>Romes</hi> Enemy. I will instantly find him.—Hah, <hi>Clorinda?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Clorinda.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Brother, saw you the Prince since his confinement?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and he is as much to seek for the cause as they will be for satisfaction that caused it; We hear <hi>Lucius</hi> is a Pri|soner too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>I believe the cause is easily guess'd; you know the Prince and his Sister have this Morning disputed with some heat and Choler concerning our affairs; <hi>Lucius</hi> too is inform'd that the <hi>Pretor</hi> has given his consent at the desire of <hi>Otho;</hi> and the displeasure the Princess shewed her Brother is but a spark of that Fire you are to expect from <hi>Lucius,</hi> whose nature can never endure, nor dissemble his troubles; whence came you now?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo.</speaker>
                        <p>From making my excuse to the Princess, where I re|ceived so civil a resentment of my proceedings, that her dislike was but one degree of less Obligation then the acceptance of my Love would have been. For I must confess, my Reason Honours the Princess when she acts great things; and to be faithfull is most Princely. 'Tis like her self, to avow her Friendship; yet her words were full of civility, and, in all her expressions as just to me, as kind to <hi>Lucius;</hi> And that Civil Justice shall bind me as much as her Love can my Rival. And though his pretence may be more fortunate then mine, yet who ever shall give a true Character hereafter of <hi>Amadeo</hi>'s Love, the world shall say, he owes nothing to Honour nor <hi>Cicilia</hi>'s Friendship.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Be yet so kind to me as to visit the Prince, who is now our Prisoner; to whom pray say all that a Maid is fit to justifie, all that <hi>Amadeo</hi>'s Sister should say when such a Lover wooes, and such a Brother counsels, while I find the Princess, and take the first oc|casion I can handsomely to present your Resolutions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo.</speaker>
                        <p>Farewel, dear <hi>Clorinda;</hi> I shall not fail to visit the Prince as soon as I have dispatch'd a business which concerns me to give audience in this Morning. Live and Love, thy Brother, dear <hi>Clorinda.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Love my Brother!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[He lets fall the paper</hi> Lucius <hi>gave him, unseen of either.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <pb n="259" facs="132"/>
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lucius <hi>alone.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lucius.</speaker>
                        <p>THis is the place, within this wood I will expect him; I wonder he is thus late; guilt has his sting, though in the Courage of <hi>Amadeo;</hi> when he is to justifie an ill action he is even slow in coming.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Manlius <hi>in his Retreat.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manlius.</speaker>
                        <p>Reveng'd? upon whom? foul Revenge is due to thee, not from thee; Thou hast injur'd a Friend, a Brother, and a Mistriss; and thou talkst of being reveng'd, of which of these? good Heaven! whither am I fallen? Reason and Honour are dead within my Heart, and the Coward is crept into this breast, else I could save all yet; Thus: this Sword bent against the Tray|tor here would do it yet; But Honour has lost his power, Lust and Revenge reign Tyrants over my Heart, Revenge: whose plea|sure is of so short a reign, it scarce out-lasts a thought longer then the storms that Injuries and Anger raise; and who enjoyes it most is most Beast, and shews more wicked nature then all the several vices that Man was born subject to; Nay, 'tis hard to say, who repents a revengefull Mind most, the Revenger or the sad subject of his Revenge; That I, who this Morning was a Lover, should be|fore night degenerate into such contraries as Hate, and desire to de|stroy the thing I lov'd, it starts my Soul. I that would have dy|ed this Morning to have serv'd or pleas'd <hi>Cicilia,</hi> am now bent at the rate of all that is precious to Man, Honour, Health, and Peace of Mind, to seek her despight, and, with hazard of mine own life, strike <hi>Lucius,</hi> though a Brother, which she nor Nature can long|er protect; For though my Heart tells me he is my Brother, yet she has said he is my Rival; which very thought has more mysterie in it; then I shall live to understand. That I should have reason to know this, and not have power to master that impious Passion! They have too much reason who affirm there is a Fate in all things, which commands above our Reason; and 'tis vanity in Man to think or resolve he will be virtuous: His Stars laugh at him; and what is writ in Heaven we must act, for we but play our parts here; how would the world wonder else, when they shall read this part of my story? <hi>Manlius,</hi> that in his youth did something like Hon|our, and aspir'd at nothing but a fair Fame, proud of the worlds esteem; Now, when he has found the highest Object Honour and Virtue can work upon, which is to Love handsomely, without any design or hope of Reward more then such a virtuous action brings; To know this, and to despise all the rewards that the Gods and <hi>Cicilia</hi> must owe to such an action, and sacrifice to Revenge all that a Brother, a Friend, and a Mistriss claim, must beget mise|ries which already beget my despair. Love, if thou bee'st a God,
<pb n="260" facs="133"/>
as thy blindness has led me to this precipice, thou hast wings though no Eyes; and 'twill be Justice to lend me them to save me; else this new kind of madness will find too late a pity. My Hate levels at all, Brother and Friend are not out of distance. What she loves I must hate, my Rival cannot be my friend; nor can I with patience think she should be any others, though I know she will never be mine; But woe to the happy Lover who ever he be, 'tis not Brother nor Friend shall protect him. <hi>Calis</hi> too, though I never said I lov'd, yet I have listned to what she has said of modest and kind; so that this crime of mine cannot stab less then four; for each base act that I commit, she will bleed though innocent.—Ha, what noise is that? 'tis Horse-men; sure I am pursu'd, I will take the covert of <stage>A noise with|ut.</stage> this wood to observe the motion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Manlius.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Amadeo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amadeo.</speaker>
                        <p>This by the description should be the place, yonder are the Hermits Houses, and there is the Temple.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Ama.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. VI.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Clorinda, Cicilia, <hi>and</hi> Stella.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>I Come not, Madam, to justifie the mistaken kindness of Prince <hi>Otho,</hi> whose Friendship to me out-ran the respect was due to your Highness; when I desired him to speak for my Brother, his Love mistook the Object, and without either of our knowledge moved it to the <hi>Pretor.</hi> This we both started at when he told us the success, and fear'd what your just disdain would do, when you should find we had not paid the duty and civility a Lo|ver owes to such a Mind, whom we first ought to have prepared, being the chief concern'd in Love and Hymen. This Truth, Madam, has faults enough, and therefore we may hope to find belief; and this Errour which a Brother committed, we hope for a Brothers sake may be pardoned.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Highness had need make no more excuse; though, I confess I was something troubled at the first; But since I received a visit from the Prince, I am so far from accusing him when I per|ceived his Innocence; I think he will confess, I said more to let him see I was not angry, then I should have done to have pleased another; For give me leave to tell you, <hi>Clorinda,</hi> in all her kindness, has not more value for Prince <hi>Amadeo,</hi> then I have. But love him I must not. <hi>Cicilia</hi> is not worth her esteem when she is false to her vows, which (I confess,) I have given <hi>Lucius;</hi> and nothing but <hi>Lucius</hi> can absolve that vow. Death, or <hi>Lucius</hi> his faults, can onely set <hi>Cicilia</hi> free; This I would have told the Prince, but that I was loath to add to his griefs a knowledge that might make him hate my friend or me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>I know my Brothers Heart so well, I am confident he will worship this Virtue in your Highness, equal to all the
<pb n="261" facs="133"/>
blessings of the world beside; and when he shall know your Heart has pity for him, Honour will change his Love to Friendship and Adoration; and he will still worship the fair <hi>Cicilia,</hi> without <stage>
                              <p>Stella <hi>finds the paper</hi> Amadeo <hi>let fall.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>She gives</hi> Ci|cilia <hi>the paper.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>She offers the paper to</hi> Clorinda.</p>
                           </stage> one earthly wish or stain of mortal thoughts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>What paper is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Stella.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis directed to Prince <hi>Amadeo.</hi> I shall not be so curious to know the secret.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Not I, Madam, till you read it; I am certain my Brother has no secrets he would hide from <hi>Cicilia,</hi> since she knows he loves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>I should know this hand, 'tis <hi>Lucius</hi> his Character, my Heart fails me; This paper bodes some mischief.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>She is troubled, pray, Madam, read it without any scruple.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess, I would fain be satisfied, for I have as much Interest in the Character as <hi>Clorinda</hi> has in the direction, 'tis <hi>Lucius</hi> his hand.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven forbid my fears, pray give it me,—'tis a challenge from <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                           <stage>
                              <hi>She reads till she comes to</hi> Lucius <hi>injurious words, and then stops.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>This I feared; <hi>Calis,</hi> a word; Your Pardon, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Cicilia <hi>and</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Something I must do to prevent this mischief; who that had read this paper would hereafter trust the Love of any, since <hi>Lucius</hi> can be thus faulty to such a person; My Heart begins to doubt, <hi>Otho</hi> may have his faults too, but this is no time to talk.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Marius, Dyon, Lysander, <hi>and a Guard.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>Gone?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dyon.</speaker>
                        <p>Gone Sir; he leap'd his window that look'd into the Garden.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lysander.</speaker>
                        <p>Prince <hi>Amadeo</hi> is from his Lodging too, and was seen to ride out alone this Morning.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>Take the Guards and follow them with all dilgence; disperse your selves, and if it be possible prevent them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Stay, my Lord; Sir, if you please to read this paper, 'twill direct you where you may certainly find them; I found it in the Gallery this Morning. <stage>He ●eads the challenge to himself.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>Insolent and false, thou shalt find what 'tis to despise my Orders, and violate the <hi>Roman Protection</hi> given a Prince; be|side what my Justice shall inflict upon thee, that durst without my leave, treat this sawcy Friendship with my Daughter; and not onely rob me of the Duty of a Child, but dishonourably seek to take her fair Name from her. <hi>Lysander,</hi> and <hi>Dyon,</hi> haste to the Grove, where <hi>Juno</hi>'s Temple stands, there is the place of ap|pointment; Alive or dead bring him to our Justice. <hi>Dyon,</hi> you know me, look I be not disobeyed; Some of you call <hi>Cicilia</hi> hither, and set a strong Guard upon <hi>Otho.</hi> Your pardon, Madam; this trouble has made me thus long forget my respect to you; This In|solence
<pb n="262" facs="134"/>
shewed to the Prince, and despising of the <hi>Roman Disci|pline,</hi> has robbed me of my patience; But I shall give his Highness full satisfaction, and with his blood make him an example.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clorinda.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven forbid, Sir; I know <hi>Amadeo</hi> will sooner die for him, then bring any such sad Calamity to his friends, and there is much to be said on both sides. You have high Reason, and ought to have the first place, as his and <hi>Romes General,</hi> doubly injur'd in your blood and power; Yet Love and heat of youth have their Friends that plead for <hi>Lucius.</hi> And we cannot expect, Sir, a Souldier and a Lover enraged should find place for Reason. Honour and Opinion slave the world too much; <hi>Lucius</hi> is a <hi>Ro|man;</hi> and from <hi>Romes</hi> example where he findes difficulties he draws his Sword to remove them; See the Princess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cicilia <hi>and</hi> Calis.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Calis.</speaker>
                        <p>His displeasure is high, for his Orders were to kill him if he resisted, or else to bring him alive to Justice; You know how strict the <hi>Roman Discipline</hi> is, upon such a breach as this, to which is added Personal Injuries; and if your Highness do not in|terpose, 'twill be sad; there is no safety for him if you shew a dis|pleasure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Though he has injur'd me, I will not be so unjust to condemn him, before I hear him speak; fear not, <hi>Calis,</hi> 'tis not the anger of others shall make me forget what I owe to <hi>Lucius;</hi> and though he has done a rash act in disobeying my Father and my self, yet I will look upon that disobedience as Love to me; and Heaven forbid I should joyn to punish him for faults committed upon that score.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>I sent to speak with you; did you know any thing of this business?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Nothing but what my fears prompted me to, and that I gave you an Accompt of by <hi>Calis.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>If he hold his appointment, I shall at last have my Re|venge upon him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>I am sorry to find your Highness thus bent against a Per|son whose Friendship to me has been thus long known to my Father; 'Tis true, this act is not to be defended, but I am consi|dent I need neither blush the becoming his Mediator, nor my Father be ashamed to let my importunity prevail against the se|verity of that Law that condemns my Friend.—Which thus I do upon my knees, interposing my Tears to save from your displeasure <stage>She kneels.</stage> a forfeit Friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>Rise; you must not plead for such an insolent offender; Innocence comes in question when it appears so partial in the in|tercession for the Guilty. <stage>She 〈◊〉.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, my Interest in all his sufferings plead for him, <hi>Lucius</hi> his guilt is my pride; <hi>Lucius</hi> his crimes is love of me, and here again I profess him my Friend; I love the Man, and if you punish him you make his crimes mine in the Affliction; and though I had no
<pb n="263" facs="134"/>
hand in his guilt, yet I shall feele all his punishment, such is the mysterie of Friendship; You cannot execute him a|lone, and I am as innocent as the Law you would revenge; and your Justice upon <hi>Lucius</hi> is unjust upon me; so that to satisfie an Injury, you will murther a Daughter. This be|loved Guilt, this affected Malefactor has won my Heart; even this Crime is an Obligation. My Friendship shar'd in all his good, and shall I abandon him in his misery? Heaven forbid. You know, Sir, in his healthy hours, in his dayes of Triumph, <hi>Lucius</hi> left not me out. Can I then with Honour share with him in his glories, and abandon him in this sad afflicted Fortune, where I am the cause too? It cannot, it must not be. You may deny me his life, but know then, you cannot perswade me to out-live him. Nothing shall say, <hi>Lucius</hi> was so much gallanter then <hi>Cicilia,</hi> as to die for her that would not in his Funeral bear him company.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>While <hi>Lucius</hi> knew how to be a Souldier, I loved and preferr'd him; But grown Insolent, and perverted in his Nature; as his virtues found my Friendship, so his crime shall feel my Justice, till he stands in story an example of both.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>When <hi>Lucius</hi> was in health he needed none of your Physick; and now he is sick, you will not afford him a remedy; Innocent <hi>Lucius</hi> fear'd not your power, even that power which his sword has confirm'd, though now you threaten his noble life with it. Nor will the world wonder why I plead for him: Is guilty <hi>Lucius</hi> such a common Theam? Were he not guilty, why should I bow my knees? A Daughter to one, and a Friend to the other? Are her tears no tie? Are her knees bowed, and her hands held up, of no force with a Father for a Friend? Is there nothing due to these? Common Miseries find common Remedies; And my Father may by a thousand wayes shew his Justice, though how for my sake he shew <hi>Lucius</hi> Mercy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>Fond Girl, Thy kindness but heaps coals upon his head, and speaks him a black Villain to injure a person so far above him both in Love and Honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cicilia.</speaker>
                        <p>My Reason, Sir, loved him once, and my Love makes me pity him now; his Virtues overcame me then, and I but imitated the world in loving him. Thousands were <hi>Lu|cius</hi> his Virtues, thousands were his glories, and ten thousand were the ties he has lay'd upon the world; Single is this ha|tred, Sir, single his Crime, single your Justice too, and in that, Cruel. <hi>Lucius</hi> was ever glorious, and but once guilty. Ye Gods! who would through such narrow wayes and crooked pathes, with difficulties, hunt for flying Honour, if her wealth prove such a burthen unto Men, that even with Friends an Age of Virtue cannot weigh down one rash Act? <hi>Lucius</hi> for one Crime dies, for whom a thousand generous actions past could not prevail; and <hi>Cicilia,</hi> from a cruell parent must return deny'd. But I have
<pb n="264" facs="135"/>
yet anger enough left to laugh at those that believe this Cuelty can make way for any low design.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Marius.</speaker>
                        <p>See fond Wretch, blush and hate thy Folly. Read <stage>She offers to go out.</stage> this, and be▪ thy own Judge. Behold what a Friendship thou hast built thy Peace upon, scorn'd and suspected; In that read thy <hi>Lucius,</hi> and see to what a miserable Fate thou art arrived, after thy having given thy Honour, Duty, and Brothers kindness to purchase a Friendship with a Jealous, Cholerick, Insolent Youth. Go, haste to the Temple, make him your Lord, that he may chuse some other Beauty to pay his broken vows to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He gives her</hi> Lucius <hi>Challenge to read; she reads the paper, strikes her breast, and throws it a|way, and goes in. [Exeunt omnes.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>Partis primae Finis:</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         </TEI>

