<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
            <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>325 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 November (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12417588</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing K450.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">61734</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
                  <title type="alt">Works. 1664</title>
                  <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 8 [i.e. 5]-576, 80 p. : port.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Each play has special t.p. and is dated 1663.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="234"/>
THE FIRST PART OF Bellamira her Dream: OR, THE Love of Shadows. A TRAGI-COMEDY, The Scene <hi>NAPLES</hi> and <hi>SICILY.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Written in <hi>VENICE,</hi> BY <hi>THOMAS KILLIGREW.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>DEDICATED TO THE Lady <hi>MARY VILLIERS DUCHESSE</hi> OF <hi>RICHMOND</hi> and <hi>LENOX.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the sign of the <hi>Blew Anchor,</hi> in the lower Walk of the <hi>New-Exchange.</hi> 1663.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="235"/>
                     <head>The Names of the Actors:</head>
                     <item>The King of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ortho,</hi> Brother of the King, slain in a Battel.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> Prince of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Naples.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Almanzor,</hi> Prince of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roderigo,</hi> His Lieutenant General.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bellamira,</hi> Sister to <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fidelia,</hi> A Lady of the Court.</item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Pollidor,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Two Foresters.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Phillora</hi> his Sister,</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ravack,</hi> A banished Lord, of dead <hi>Ortho</hi>'s party.</item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Nigro,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">Three Lords of <hi>Ortho</hi>'s party, in Arms in <hi>Gaietta.</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Clytus,</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Cleon,</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Palantus,</hi> General of the Horse to the King of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Naples.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philemon,</hi> An old Lord at Court.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Satyr,</hi> In Love with <hi>Phillora.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Areus,</hi> A Moor, Slave to <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Juba,</hi> A Moor, Friend to <hi>Arcus,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Both Prisoners.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Cadess,</hi> his Sister.</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> such as the Scene Requires.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Bellamira<hi>'s habit, when disguis'd, some Antick handsome Property.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pollidor, Phillora, <hi>and</hi> Ravack, <hi>must be habited like Fo|resters, part Hunters, part Shepherds habit; neither Rich nor Plain, but proper all, of different Colours; For the two young ones, gray and blue, hair Colour, white and some silver;</hi> Phil|lora <hi>must have a piece of the Lyons Skin in her habit;</hi> Ra|vack <hi>must have a very white Curl'd head and Beard of Hair.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Satyr <hi>must have a Call of Silk and Silver, and the Wooll of</hi> Phelice <hi>made into a kind of scrip on one side, and the Horns of</hi> Phelice <hi>gilt tyed to the ends of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Arcus <hi>must be in a Noble habit, Rich, and his Person black, being a Moor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <pb n="467" facs="235"/>
                  <head>THE FIRST PART OF Bellamira her Dream: OR, THE Love of Shadows.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Nigro, Ravack, Cleon, <hi>and Attendants.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nigro.</speaker>
                        <p>'TIs for certain, the people at last have found a head, to whom <hi>Clytus</hi> is joyned; and I fear will follow the Revenge with as little mercy as the King shew'd his brother, our dead Ma|ster, the Royal <hi>Ortho;</hi> whose invasion though we neither counsell'd, nor assisted, yet such is the fate of Courts, when the People Arm against their Princes; which we have sadly proved, who now suffer that punishment which was meant to the Authors of that unnatural War.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Is the Spanish Prince arriv'd at <hi>Naples?</hi> is there a ground for that report?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nig.</speaker>
                        <p>Most certain; led on by <hi>Clytus,</hi> Their descent in <hi>Sicily</hi> found no resistance; the people were so generally disaffected with the pre|sent Government they willingly consented to put themselves under the prince's protection; This news has awaked the King, till then lost in security; and now too late he finds the fire he despis'd has taken hold of his Palace. The prince <hi>Leopoldo</hi> is absent too; A person of that Piety and Virtue, but that he is the cloud that shadows our young King, and unjustly possesses his right, I could joyn with the world in worship of him; and it was indeed his Interest, ioyned with his noble Sisters, which these late years has kept the people quiet;
<pb n="468" facs="236"/>
But the prince and <hi>Palantus</hi> being absent in these late disorders, our Friends have taken hold of the occasion, and prevailed so far, that the people are now Armed in the Name of our long lost prince; which hope, joyned with their hatred of the present Government, has begot a danger. The King cannot resist, but 'tis thought he will be forc'd to leave <hi>Naples,</hi> and seek a safety in <hi>Capua,</hi> that place in my Opinion being fittest to make his general Rendevouz. This news was the cause of my sending for you, that you might avoy'd the present danger which the prince <hi>Leopoldo</hi> and <hi>Palantus</hi> his Army may bring, who are now upon their march towards <hi>Naples,</hi> and must pass through your Forest, where your abode, during these troubles, will be most unsafe; and to prevent a mischief, pray let me counsel your self, and the Children, to retire hither this Even|ing. Where did you leave them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>A hunting, in which they both delight; Books, and that, are their great diversion; and I am glad to find their Affections so Innocent, and minds so ready still to take fire at any great Ex|ample they meet in Story: I left them this morning in chase of a wild Bore; nor is <hi>Phillora</hi> less masculine in her Spirit then <hi>P●llidor,</hi> but far from cruell, or Barbarous; I have wondred to see her give such wounds, and then lament them; she has indeed overcome all the Niceties of her Sex, and yet retains the softness of her Na|ture; and though she loves to be one still in all our Sports, yet a modest, innocent, and most gentle assuredness attends all her Actions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nig.</speaker>
                        <p>Nature and Sex are but materials that custome works upon; and both Sexes are Effeminate, or Warlike, as they are bred;—but no more of this: time is too precious; Now or Never we must regain our Countrey, Prince and Liberty; <hi>Clytus,</hi> our Friend, is already joyned with the Spanish Prince, and Com|mands in <hi>Naples;</hi> The Castles are in his hands, declared for the survying heirs of the dead <hi>Ortho,</hi> and with his our Forces shall this day joyn; and if the gods have enough reveng'd that rash Act of our unfortunate Master, We, the remnant of his friends, that this sixteen years have suffered all kinds of Calamities for his fault, may yet hope to return to our Countrey. In the mean time, <hi>Cleon,</hi> let some diligent spy follow the Princes Army, and learn (if it be possible) his intentions, and observe his motions, numbers, and Affections of his Souldiers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>That my tame Satyr shall do; he is crafty, and seems simple, armed with his Club he shall mingle with them; hee's ac|quainted too with all the Fasts of the Forest, secret paths and Caves, and can, in spight of their swiftest horses, make a retreat; the poor wretch dotes upon my Girl; and if shee'll but promise to sing, or play to him, there is no danger, for her sake, he will not at|tempt; but I must return e're they miss me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nig.</speaker>
                        <p>Farewel, the Gods guide our honest intents; 'tis not for Re|venge, but justice, that we strike.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <pb n="469" facs="236"/>
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the King,</hi> Phillemon, <hi>and Attendants.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>PHillemon,</hi> are those returned we sent to mingle themselves with the multitude, to try, if 'twere possible to learn the cause of their taking Arms so suddenly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phill.</speaker>
                        <p>Some, Sir, are return'd, all report the same substance in different language, great oppression, no Justice done upon com|plaint; But the great cause is, the pretended pity they ought to have upon their Countrymen, whose long miseries they publickly lament, whil'st others proclaim the joyful news, that their young prince <hi>Ge|norio</hi> lives, who long since was mourned, as part of his Fathers ruine, whose Injuries to your Majestie, though they were of the highest nature, yet being a Brother, I could have wish'd they had not found so severe a Justice.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>He fell not by any Act of Cruelty that we ought to blush for.—War, that War which he most unjustly waged, as 'twas his crime, proved his punishment too. <hi>Sicily</hi> was the Conquest of our Father; In which I served him, and with my Blood entituled my self to that Crown which, at his death, was by my Fathers will conferred upon me; <hi>Naples</hi> was my Brothers birth-right; yet the gods witness with me, neither my wishes nor commands were guilty of his or his Childrens death, which to this hour my soul laments; And if the kinder fates have preserved them, as they pretend; May all miseries find me, and pursue me to my Posterity, if I shall not with joy carry these gray hairs to <hi>Sicily,</hi> and deliver <hi>Naples</hi> into their hands, being the undoubted right of their Father.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phill.</speaker>
                        <p>This Piety, Sir, I am confident had long since produ|ced a happy Peace, could their Party have given faith to it; but their guilt, and doubt of such a goodness has now bred this Civil War; which the desperate condition of their banish'd Nobility I fear will make use of. <hi>Clytus</hi> is certainly with them, and now Commands the Castles where he hath declared the young King <hi>Genorio,</hi> and his Sister, the Princess, <hi>Phidamira</hi> living, with which Joy the people are possest; and your Majesty must look upon that Joy as your Enemy; For I cannot believe the re|port true, though I confess I wish it; 'tis but a pretence, to set the people against your Majestie, and gain a power to work your ruine; to prevent which, my Counsel is, that your Majestie immediately proclaim <hi>Genorio</hi> King, and pardon to all if they can produce him, and require a cessation of Arms till the people be satisfied, whether your Majestie or their In|tentions be most Ingenuous, in restoring the young King to his Right.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="470" facs="237"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Arcus <hi>with a Paper which he gives the King.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Arcus,</hi> what news? Thy looks are full of trouble; How dost thou find the people inclin'd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>To the ruine, Sir, of your self and Family; they call the Prince and Princess Dissemblers, and Betrayers of their Trust, your Majesty Usurper, Tyrant, and Murderer of your Brother and his Children. Pardon, Sir, this blunt relation; my gratitude for the freedom I have found makes me unwilling to flatter your Ma|jesty into a Ruine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>How does this agree with <hi>Clytus</hi> his proclaiming their Prince <hi>Genorio</hi> King?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, Reason, Justice, nor Honour, you must not look for in this Beast the Multitude; 'tis all Back and Belly, no Breast, no room for a Heart; All Slave when commanded; All Lust when they have power; they are full of Rage and Wine; Treason and Novelty are the things they worwip: A Slave of the same Gally where I was Prisoner gave me this Paper; 'tis a Decla|ration the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and Confederates have dispers'd, where|in the Cause and Resolution of this War is most maliciously set down, and I fear findes too much faith among the people; they have intelligence too abroad; some (when I was there) came from <hi>Capua,</hi> that assured them they had no time to lose, for the Prince <hi>Leopoldo</hi> was upon his March, and would within two days be in sight of the City, upon which they purpos'd immediately to attempt the Palace; In short, my fear for your Majesty appre|hends the worst that Malice and Treason can act upon your self and royal Family.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Therefore consider, Sir, whether your strength either in the place or number of your Friends, be able to resist this Torrent till the Prince can come to give you aid; and if not, take counsel with your safety, and make retreat to <hi>Aversa,</hi> 'tis in the way to <hi>Capua,</hi> whither your friends shall have private order to repair; 'tis in the Princes way too, whose coming is much sooner than they feared.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Majesties safety has no time to spare; this night you must prepare for Flight or Defence; I have those in readiness shall deliver your Orders for either as it shall be re|solved.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>What to resolve I know not; My heart scorns to appre|hend these Villains; yet when I consider what Stakes they throw for, how little they can lose, and what they may win, who knows how Fortune may assist the daring of such Villains? My dear <hi>Bel|lamira,</hi> and <hi>Leopoldo</hi> too, their Fates are woven in this Thred of mine, else they should finde, old as I am I have not lost one grain of that courage that gave me conquest in my youth. Prithee finde my <hi>Bellamira,</hi> she must this night prepare to depart with me. I dare not venture to leave her here; All her Guards of Beauty, Greatness, or Virtue, are but idle nothings when they meet the bar|barous
<pb n="471" facs="237"/>
force of Treason in a raging Multitude: Have you seen her lately, <hi>Philemon?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes Sit, but so afflicted since the Invasion of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and Revolt of <hi>Sicily,</hi> she hath scarce eat or slept, and with pain endures the conversation of her Friends; her minde and fears are still bent upon her Dream, the thought of which she now trem|bles at, and apprehends it as a prophetick Vision sent by the Gods to us to denounce these miseries.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas odd, but my innocency makes me secure; and yet I dare neither believe nor despise it; for though Dreams be the common Issue of Sleep, and are in relation to the thoughts we have been most affected with the day before, or take their Births from the Humours that are most predominant in our Constituti|ons, yet men may reasonably and piously believe the Gods both do and have by those strange ways sometimes darkly foretold their Designs; which makes me neither believe nor contemn all Dreams.—But no more of this, the night and <hi>Bellamira,</hi> if habited like her sex, will be unsafe and incommode; therefore desire her to make use of a Disguise, and for my sake chearfully to endure this first difficulty of our adverse fortune; her Jewels may be use|ful too, if she can convey them with her: this and my blessing, good <hi>Philemon.</hi> Come <hi>Arcus,</hi> you must to my Son this night, and acquaint him with our Resolutions, and that the Rendezvouz will be at <hi>Aversa;</hi> whose strength and provisions I dare rely upon as well as the faith of him that commands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bellamira, <hi>and</hi> Fidelia <hi>in her Chamber.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>WHat thinks <hi>Fidelia,</hi> were my fears vain or no? Is it not visible the Gods in their care foretold our ills? Is not the Stranger landed, and doth not the Dust fly in our faces? 'Twas too true an Exposition the good Hermit made of my Dream, who told us, that kicking the Sand at us would prove a dangerous Rebellion in the People. O <hi>Fidelia,</hi> my soul is full of horrour, yet all mine own miseries do not at all deject me; but for my Father, his loss, I must confess, brings a weight of sadness I can|not bear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>To deny your cause of grief will but make your anger joyn, and give new wounds to your minde; that fatal Dream I have not dar'd to read, my nature is too superstitious; yet my curiosity would fain know what Stars rule your Highness fortune, to which mine is ty'd, and by a nearer interest, Madam, than your goodness yet imagines.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> though (I confess) thy modest hiding of a Passion has been very discreet, yet all the shadows thou couldst in|terpose have not obscur'd it so, but my grief and kindness have both seen it; and though I cannot be happy my self, yet tis my joy in the
<pb n="472" facs="238"/>
midst of these afflictions I have a power left to give thee some peace of minde; turn not away, I will not put thee to blush the rest; onely thus much, live assur'd, if I can serve thee, thou shalt be happy in the wish'd friendship of thy <hi>Palantus;</hi> and that thou maist give faith to what I say, at thy leasure read this Paper—'Tis <stage>Bellamira <hi>gives her a Paper.</hi>
                           </stage> my Dream expounded; in that thou wilt finde my Fate; and I confess with a clear soul, and as much innocency as the sleeps of Children, I love that fatal figure, that something without a name, that kinde nothing is all the business of my minde; In my sleep he rescu'd me, me thoughts he sav'd my honour in a time of dan|ger when my heart was desperate; and though a Dream the fear has still dwelt here, and a kindness for him, which makes me pre|fer him before all but honour; cease to wonder, for that shadow is all my conversation, all my joy, and all my misery; Is it not a strange Passion that the Gods have sent me for one I never saw but in my Dream, the similitude of nothing? yet this advantage we have of others, we are secured from jealousie; for as Fate has hid him from my eye, so a kinde power has set me free from the envy or fear his love may bring; by night he makes his visits still; like the <hi>Egyptian Apis</hi> in a Dream he comes; the soft-foot'd God of Sleep is onely Witness to our Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Since your Highness has been pleas'd to break this silence, giving thousand joys I never hop'd for, take the secret of my heart; 'tis Love, Madam, so much more than I can master, 'tis more than I can tell, and that makes me fear such a Present as <hi>Pa|lantus</hi> his Love, when he shall finde onely a Shadow for his Rival, may gain an easier Victory than your Highness fears; nor do I blame <hi>Palantus</hi> for loving your Highness, 'tis his greatest virtue to do it; and my crime to tell you so; because I know though 'tis an ho|nour to have you there, yet 'tis the business of his heart to hide it; and ere I can have his friendship, his faith must be blasted; for Inconstancy is the first step to any possibility of my being happy; yet he has ever paid me a Civility; and though I cannot boast his love, yet he has made me believe he was not displeas'd that I love him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, dry thy eyes, and calm thy breast; for though he should prove unkinde I'll be faithful still; and if <hi>Palantus</hi> will hope to act any thing pleasing in my eye, he must pursue his friendship to <hi>Fidelia;</hi> for I believe, with the most excellent <hi>Bellessa,</hi> that Faith and Constancy are so much lovelier in both Sexes, than any other Beauty that I should expect from a gallant Woman; she should sooner spoil her face, than break her faith; and this I shall tell him; who if he be the gallant <hi>Palantus:</hi> the world esteems him, he knows all that Beauty can hope for; nay, all it aspires to is but to create a faith, and binde the heart it loves; and when Beauty and Love have done their best they make but one constant Friendship. Nay, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> how many fair faces do stories mention that could not make one constant Love, though it has been still the business of Youth and Beauty?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Those Ages, Madam, wanted the divine <hi>Bellamira's</hi> minde
<pb n="473" facs="238"/>
to finish that great work, whose Friendship will be the envy of the whole world, and may it never want the pity you have shew'd me; &amp; as your Scholar I shall pursue <hi>Palantus</hi> with a modest heart, &amp; teach him the virtue of a faithful Lover, a mystery known but to few men.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith is such a strange good, 'tis neither valuable nor communicable beyond two; I mean the Faith of Love; a galiant man cannot be twice faithful; who would be twice, was never once a Lover.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Why are so many Women pleased, then, to gain a servant that was anothers?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Such women are fit for the Friendship of such of men, and knows not what a nothing they have won; for instead of a Friendship she onely gaines a dead carkass of one that might have been a Lover; And such women, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> are guiltier then the men, who must be either foolish or wicked; For Honour is deaf to their prayers, and blind to their tears; who can say nothing that ought to prevail where there is Virtue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Unless it be to plead the power of her Beauty that has made him break his faith to another; quitting Empire there for chains else where.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>I tell thee, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> such a wretch that durst hope a reward from me for such a crime, I should look upon him as one that threw dirt upon my Fame, and my scorn should tell him so; for he who has impudence enough to plead that guilt for me|rit, I shall believe, will never care to be innocent.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, Madam, let me kneel to you; And though I cannot accuse <hi>Palantus</hi> of broken Faith, yet his dissembled pity makes me beg when he bows before this shrine, and pleads rewards from your Breast, for scarrs received in others service: O let your Ju|stice revenge me upon him and in the afflictions of your frowns, teach him to feel those pains he inflicts upon others.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Rise, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and believe <hi>Palantus</hi> can never deserve this; he knows me too well to venture his Passions beyond his thoughts; and I will rather be unjust to him, then prove unkind to thee; and when thy griefs have let thee collect thy thoughts, this secret I gave thee even now, must remove all thy feats; for know, I have a guest here lodged by Fate, and so proud he will dwell alone and reign sole Monarch of this Breast; And trust me, gentle <hi>Fidelia,</hi> I am proud too, and scorn a part or corner of a Heart; and he, who ere he be that will be mine, must bring an entire Friendship no divided brest, a Province will not satisfie me; 'Tis a solitary Heart that affects crowds of Lovers; In love alone is best com|pany, absolute or nothing in a Heart, if I be one.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Those that err having such a guide must fall unpitied; O Madam, did I hope this sad day such joy as this? No, no, this change of my condition confirmes me in the uncertainty they build upon that trust to Fortune, who afraid to be thought she loves any one thing long, made me fear she had now designd my Ruine; whom she so long indulged with the Friendship of two such persons as your Highnesse and <hi>Palantus,</hi> to shew 'twas she,
<pb n="474" facs="239"/>
not Virtue raised me; I cannot yet pretend to the least of your Highness favours, being but the youngest child of Love and Fortune; and can plead but from your pity no interest, nor no inheritance in eithers blessings.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Fortune nor Love shall make me forsake thee; and for Love, though I find his venome in my Mind, yet this truth I dare proclaim, that god hath no partial customes to difference his Children by. Love has not elder Rights, all are his Heirs that Love with Faith and Honour: This strange madness that afflicts my Mind, call it what you will, Love or madness, to dote upon a shadow, though it hath depth and stream enough to bear me with it; Yet all this Tempest in my Mind has raised no Billowes there; no faulty desires, nor dangerous vanity waits upon my Love: This shadow of one, is all men to me; like wealth con|tracted into Jewels, so I bear the precious load here.—See who <stage>
                              <hi>One knocks. Enter</hi> Phile|mon.</stage> knocks.—What news, my Lord, from my Brother? His ab|sence at this time was most unfortunate; He hath interest with the people; But Fate rules all; are the people in a Body still?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Madam, and I can give little hope of better dayes, till the sword decide the difference; The Prince and <hi>Palantus</hi> are upon their March this way, but the dissorders are such we dare not attend his coming; for the King is inform'd that the people will this night force the Palace, how easie it will be to do it I will not counsell the King to make a tryall especially when we consider the consequence; His guards, though faith|full, are too few to conquer, and too many to sacrifice; There|fore the King has resolved with them to make his retreat this Evening to <hi>Aversa,</hi> whose strength and affections he dares rely upon, 'tis in the way the Prince must march; to whom notice is already gone, and private instructions to those that are faithful in this Calamity, to make that their Rendezvouz.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>The Gods are still with us; and to dispute their Actions; were to incense them, our obedience prevailes more then complaints. What are his Majesties Commands to me? How shall I dispose of my self in these disorders?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>The King, whose chief fear and trouble is your Highness safety, desires your Company this night with him in some disguise, to prevent any accident; to which your Person (as your self) may be subject; habited like a boy, he thinks will be best he knows; it will seem strange to your Highness to change your Sex; but his command and necessity will be excuse for both.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>My obedience shall in all things possible serve his will; A mans habit! I have none, you must provide it, who shall go with me? Has the King appointed any?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>In this, and all difficulties, my Life and Fortune shall be proud to bear a part; And though I know I shall blush to see my self in that habit; yet to bear a share in your Highnesses For|tune is an Honour I shall alwayes covet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Welcome, Dear <hi>Fidelia;</hi> may thy kindness to me be as succesful, as I prophesie thy Love will be; We now begin to tread
<pb n="475" facs="239"/>
that path, which though it be full of thorns and horrour, yet it leads <hi>Fidelia</hi> to Love and Honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Pollidor <hi>from hunting, and some part of the Quarry in his hand; The Scene must be a fine Land-skip, and a</hi> Cave <hi>must be in the Scene.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>THe Woods are full of armed men; Troops of gallant youths pass by me without regard; Me-thoughts a scorn flew from every generous Heart and sparkling Eye, to see such sloth and degenerate youth lie hid in this peaceful shape of mine, when all the world is in Arms; And my Heart tells me, it were as easie to circumvent them, as a Lyon; and as little danger to kill their Tyrant Prince, as to strike a Boar with this trusty spear; <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> he is their Generall; They say his Father kill'd our king, murther'd our Princes, and banish'd my Father, who has often bid me hate him; And now 'twere easie with a well aimed Arrow to lay his Pride upon the earth in the height of all his glories; such a quarry would make a Hunts-man proud, and find matter fit for story; But down, down all thoughts of my Revenge till he bids strike who knows why and when 'tis fit; till then, be quiet, all the troubles of my Heart be gone; and here let <hi>Pollidor</hi> rest contented in this Cave, where thou wert bred and born; Here we live unknown, un-envied, and as free from danger as the glory of this world; This Cave none will fight for sure; 'twas the Habitation of a Satyre, and he has given us leave to possess it; 'tis the Charity of a kind of Beast, whose Love to my Sister is beyond the faith of men, and strange as any accident in our Fortune; She sent him home from hunting with the Venison we kill'd; and under the notion of serving her the poor Beast is to all of us a Servant.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He goes into the</hi> Cave <hi>to seek his Sister, and Father, and Satyre, finds none, and returns presently.</hi> [The Scene must represent a Cave] <hi>Enters as from the Cave.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <p>There's no body within, yet all things are in order, and all absent; I cannot but wonder where they should be thus late.—Oh, here <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Satyre</stage> comes one can resolve me. How now, where is my Sister, and your Master?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyre.</speaker>
                        <p>For the bright Maid, she is gazing, like one that were planet-struck, upon those new kind of men that fill the Woods; I never saw a Mind so soon reconcil'd to her fears; at first sight she shrunk, and lean'd to me till she blush'd, and then bent her brows and bow too, and then gaz'd again; They laugh'd to see her in this disorder, but she pursues them still, without regard to my cries or prayers; and walks as if her Mind were grown greater from the sight: And though my business calls me hither, I was loath to leave her, for fear they should hurt her; Prithee, good Master, seek
<pb n="476" facs="240"/>
her, and chide her home, you will find her by the great plaines side; where the sacred Oak with the Trophies stands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, I'll seek her; and if my Father returns and ask for me, tell him whither I am gone</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Pollidor.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyre.</speaker>
                        <p>I love them not, yet I dare not hurt them; for my Love sayes, she shall die if they be hurt, else I would poyson them, I know a root will do it; But I love the Maid, so sweet a Flower never deck'd <hi>Pan</hi>'s Garland; her Voice charmes the wildest Breast, and her touch cures all wounds but those of the Mind. This Cave was mine, by Birth mine, Ages we have lived in it; 'Twas <hi>Pan</hi>'s gift of old, yet I gave it to my Love but to smile upon me; My Sire was worshipped in these woods, and lies buried un|der yon <hi>Altar;</hi> I cry sometimes when I miss him; seven tedious <stage>
                              <hi>That</hi> Altar <hi>must be ex|press'd in the Scene.</hi>
                           </stage> winters have I waited, in hope they would give me the Maid; so long though a child she has seduced my Mind: There is a hidden power in her Eyes, that makes me fear and love to see her; I can|not live out of her sight; and yet Famine is not so insupportable as to see and not enjoy her. This bottle they drink of, 'tis a pre|cious liquor; and when I converse with it it makes me bold, and therefore 'tis forbidden me; I'll taste it though, and fill it up at the Brook; I can sleep too in spight of Love, when my Mind is charm'd with this.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, Roderigo, Clytus, <hi>and</hi> Souldiers <hi>to fill the Scene.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almonzor.</speaker>
                        <p>FRom <hi>Gaietta</hi> we are assured of a considerable force to Joyn with us to morrow; And 'tis believd we shall find the King about the Forest; for the Prince and he are met; and what number, <hi>Clytus,</hi> do you judge their Army to be now they are united?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>The Scouts speak of many thousands more then the King expected, or I believ'd would follow his Fortune; but all makes not two thirds of our present Army, besides those of <hi>Gaietta,</hi> which will this night lodge in the Forest.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Almanzor.</speaker>
                        <p>Was it for certain, the Princess <hi>Bellamira</hi> fled in Boyes Habit, as was reported?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>For certain; and I confess I cannot but lament her part in this Calamity; for she hath ever born a Mind full of Honour, and upon all occasions been ready to assist them that misfortunes made fit for her Charity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>But she gave an unhandsome answer to my Prince, whose Love in a profer'd Marriage (mention'd by chance by a friend, as a means to compose the present troubles, in Policy as well well as Civility) might have found a handsomer denial then the upbraids of Traytor and Usurper.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="477" facs="240"/>
                        <speaker>Almanzor </speaker>
                        <stage>speaks aside.</stage>
                        <p>Observe him, <hi>Roderigo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! does your mind run that way? is that the fair pre|tence of restoring our lost Princes? this I doubted before, but it was too late to prevent it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Her pride may fall into my power, and then I shall give an answer like her message; till then let us intend our business, which a woman shall never be with <hi>Almanzor.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Aside to Roderigo.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Roderigo,</hi> a word.—Now you find the Decla|ration was well design'd, and before they shall find a power to dis|prove the truth whether their Prince be in our power or no, I will make these Traytors cut themselves. This <hi>Clytus</hi> is a villain, and begins to grow cold, he likes not the marriage with the Princess; therefore strike that string no more.<hi>—Clytus,</hi> how do the people take the news of their young Kings safety?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>With joy, Sir; and with impatient longing they expect the sight; and 'tis my opinion 'twill be the best way to produce him this day, and present him to the Army; if we should delay their expectations, perhaps we may lose their affections and their faith too; and then we have only arm'd and drawn together a multitude that may, for their revenge, joyn with the enemy; who when he shall hear of their discontents will not neglect to play the best of his Game; 'tis therefore again my counsel to lose no time, but produce the King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>It is his own desire not to be discover'd till things be set|led, at least till the Castles and strong places be surrendred, for the better security of his person.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Besides, 'tis now most dangerous to produce him; his enemies and Fathers murtherers being in arms, and ready to di|spute his title by a day of Battle; in which if he miscarry he is not only lost in this, but in all future hopes of a revenge: but if <hi>Gaietta</hi> will receive him, and a Garison for his safety, or you <hi>Clytus</hi> give up the Castles in <hi>Naples</hi> for his use; then the Prince shall upon his word and honour produce your King; else, till the Battle be over, without breach of faith, he cannot expose his friend to such a visible ruine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                        <p>If the people will be satisfi'd with this, I am; Sir, you know by the contract, <hi>Naples</hi> was to be in my command, which I pos|sess'd in right of my Master; <hi>Sicily</hi> (as 'twas agreed) was resign'd to you; and if I refuse, now, to deliver the Castles of <hi>Naples,</hi> 'tis not to keep out my King that makes me do it, but to be sure who shall be my King when I have done it; for 'tis no question, Sir, when you have the strength of the Kingdom in your hands, and an Army master of the Field, 'tis most easie to shew who shall be King of the Countrey; but if you are a Prince in soul as well as fortune, you will scorn to deceive our trust; and if there be foul play in your heart, small and despicable as our Force are, we shall yet with that venture to call you Enemy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="478" facs="241"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter a</hi> Souldier.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>How now? what's the news?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>The party that pursu'd the King last night are beaten in, and the commanded men that were sent to the Pass at <hi>Capua</hi> are cut off by a party of the Kings, who now appears upon the hills, where he possesses the places to his most advantage; and the Officers ex|pect your Highness Orders.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Come <hi>Clytus,</hi> let no jealousie nor fear afflict thee; but take the word of a Prince, I shall be fair and real in all things. Eve|ry man to his command; and (if it be possible) joyn with those of <hi>Gaietta;</hi> I confess I did not expect to be call'd to the Battle, 'twas my fear they would fly us; and, but that I believe their de|spair rather then courage makes them seek us, 'twould startle me; but here let us part like fellows in arms, and men of one interest, faithfully act our parts. <hi>(Genorio</hi> King) that's the word; and if a misfortune find us, let <hi>Mola</hi> be the R●ndevouz, from whence we may retreat to <hi>Gaietta.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Almanzor.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>I never fear'd an enemy before, nor till now doubted a day of Battle: these traytors that are joyn'd to us, methinks I see a curse even in their looks; how can the gods fight for treason? would they were all sunk.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>This I fear'd; but to prevent it was not possible; that the young King lives may be truth, but that he is either in his power or knowledge, I fear is as false as he is; but I am now too far engag'd; else he should find <hi>Clytus</hi> drew his sword upon another account then to make <hi>Almanzor</hi> King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Phillora <hi>alone, she looks upon the ground, and then starts into speech.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>AN Army!—I never saw so glorious a sight before.—There is a beauteous horrour in't, Their very looks command fate; where dares there be any thing so bold, as to declare it self an enemy to such a body, if the soul be answerable to the limbs? sure, Armies are the pride of nature, and her enemies too. There is a strange sweetness in their Musick; yet their Trumpets curdles my blood, and my heart's grown too great for my breast; this Cottage grows too narrow for my mind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Ravack <hi>and</hi> Pollidor.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>See where she is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Father, I have seen the Army; 'tis the most bewitch|ing sight the Sun e're shew'd my eyes; there is at once a beauty
<pb n="479" facs="241"/>
and a terrour in't, and makes me love and envy those that com|mand such things; how came you to leave being a Souldier? me-thinks death only should have made a separation 'twixt you and such a body; it moves with such a Majesty I was afraid at first; but now the awe is not unpleasing, my fear is turn'd into wonder and admiration; did <hi>Pollidor</hi> imagine it such a thing? this is the first my Brother ever saw.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, <hi>Phillora;</hi> but I have read of many.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>So have I, dully and coldly described; of their Battles too ill fought and worse painted in story, presented still by their fears, or partiality of some weak Historian, who delivers them still in their crimes and miseries, like love known onely by the scars, while the crafty happy ones (as they say) jealous of their wealth and envyed blessings, conceal their coveted happiness; and methinks we might do something worth story in this ap|proaching day, that foretells so much honour to them that dare meet this storm; and I know not what 'tis that prompts me, but my heart longs to see what fate attends this Army; will my Brother go?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>When thou shalt know, gentle <hi>Phillora,</hi> who commands this Army; what Tyranny, Oppression, Usurpation it protects; and that no hand there but wars against the gods, thou wilt then hate and loathe them which thou now admirest, who guard that great ill man that destroy'd his Brother, kill'd his Children, and now usurps his throne, to revenge which the people are arm'd, and now has forc'd him to defend his ill-got greatness; to side with whom is no less then to war with heaven: but these as too distant and ge|neral ills I will not oppose. But when thou shalt call to mind thy Fathers banishment, withering here under his oppression; thy self and <hi>Pollidor</hi> buried in these obscure Woods, that owe to the world a better account of their days then this sollitude can pay, you will then find other thoughts; yet I am pleas'd to see this impatiency in thy mind; but the time is not yet ripe, in which upon a just and honest cause, your swords and minds will have use of your best resolutions to bear your parts. The business is laid, and in <hi>Gaietta</hi> our Scene lyes; but till these troops are past pray, let us retire and lye close till our friends, which are their ene|mies, appear; and then we'll joyn, to their destruction. The Prince <hi>Leopold</hi> I hear commands the Army.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it not our King, and the Prince, you speak of, Sir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, but Murther and Usurpation hath made him so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>And may we fight against him? sure 'tis a strange justice you would seem to put in execution; sure such crimes were not appointed to punish crimes; do you believe it such a fault in him to defend himself against a Brother, then turn'd enemy? and no sin in us to arm against our King, whose succession is undoubted now his Brother is dead, faln under a ruine he made himself; for I have heard you say, he was slain in Battle; why did you then de|fend him no better? 'tis vain to think what heaven thought not
<pb n="480" facs="242"/>
just then in the person of the King (who you would have me be|lieve thus wicked) should punish their own act in the person of the innocent Prince: but suppose the King as guilty as you would make him; what has the Prince done, then a Child? why do you war with him? whose virtue neither your rage nor hatred can deny; for to my self you have often given him divine honour; Oh, Sir, your silence is more noble then your hate; and lest I may be seduced to lose my loyalty, or my duty, in this dispute, I'll retire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>This is a language I cannot but wonder at, from <hi>Phillora;</hi> have the injuries of a Father no greater place? is all my care and love paid with this unjust sence of my misery?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, those grounds you laid of truth and piety in my heart when I was young, that seed bears this fruit; would you have me to obey your passion, hate my King, and prefer your anger before all the gods you made me bow too? and not only wish, but joyn in the ruine of the Prince, who your soul knows has no guilty share in the least of our misfortunes? you know, Sir, there can be no interest but honour that moves me to say this, for the Prince is one I never saw.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>What crimes must he act ere you believe him guilty? go, court with your youth and beauty those armed troops which you thus dote upon, follow till your dishonour hath made you a quar|rel; there are those will not ask twice the pleasures they can force.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>This from <hi>Pollidor,</hi> for desiring to be worth his love! I rather expected to have found that fire which age hath quench'd in our father, should have inflam'd thy generous breast to have joyn'd with me in the search of honour; methinks thou shouldst be ashamed to look on, and see these Armies bleed, and with a revenge thou darest not take.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>You are angry, <hi>Phillora;</hi> you would not thus mistake my kindness else.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>My anger is to see <hi>Pollidor</hi> can consent, with shame, to lye hid in this glorious day of danger, and endure this private life, and thus sleep away thy days, when honour is upon the wing, and Armies striving to catch her; who hovers over the world, search|ing only some glorious front to light upon; do's fear or pale envy hold thee back? if thou think'st thy self a gallanter man then the Prince, prove thy fate upon him; 'tis womanish to shoot at him with wishes, or hope to blast his youth with curses; if my words wrong thee lead the way, give me the lye in that motion; or blush|ing follow me; while a Girle leads <hi>Pollidor</hi> to arms and honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Needs <hi>Phillora</hi> more Arguments that I love her! if she do's, let her read this patience.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>What means this fury? will you expose your self to dan|gers, only to be talk'd of? what honour can you hope in this at|tempt? come <hi>Phillora,</hi> let us retreat, and upon our knees make our war; an old man and a maid must finde their ends in prayer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I find other thoughts fire my mind; Fortune thy coy Deity I will worship; and if thou smilest I'll build thee Altars; if not, when I am old, and my mind grown heavy, then I'll listen to
<pb n="481" facs="242"/>
those dull Customs that our thoughtless Sex obey, which perhaps will lead me to the quiet privacy of this place; but I have yet too much fire, Sir, to be inclosed by Custome, or Pale fears. Woman, and all those nice follies, and shaking heart, that use to possess our soft Sex, as things unknown and unpractised, I put off with my Coats; and thus, as I was wont to search the Game, so will I hunt my fortune; The spoilers of thy herds I have often made my prey: A Bore or a Lyon I start not at, you have taught me know they were created my Inferiours; and with these spears we have not only made them our sport, but our food too; That I am a woman is no fault of mine, which Custom (a second and better Nature) has, (I thank you) redeemed, by giving me great thoughts, and weeding out, by your philosophy, all the little low affections that would choak our minds, and learn'd me to despise all the fond false Doctrine that cunning men would insinuate into us, designing all our Sex their Slaves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Your anger, <hi>Phillora,</hi> comes in still, to justifie all your errours; yet give me leave to say your Anger's more naked then any other passion; for angry women, like drunken men, are neither to be va|lued, nor punish'd; which priviledge e're I would plead, I'll suffer the penalty of any crime both those faults are subject to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> 'tis not anger, but my reason that speaks this; my eyes and heart are open, and the things I see those I speak; In|terest nor hope of any flattery shall bind my tongue; Tell not me our Sex cannot modestly be angry, and that a maid enraged is an uncomely sight; that wounds add not to her beauty either given or received, We must onely frown, forsooth, or lament our Injuries. Hence with all those Impostures, and such whose folly or faint souls will be subject to this Doctrine; while the several passions of your Rage or Lust impose upon us, who like your chained slaves must not only submit our selves and honours, but our Reason too, refer|ring all our griefs and Injuries to the justice of the gods; which when <hi>Pollidor</hi> sees <hi>Phillora</hi> suffer, let him and all mankind despise me, and stamp slave upon my forehead.—Honour, thou Diety of both Sexes, Thou male and female virtue, let thy power look friendly on my youth; Guide my feet this day to follow my heart in the paths thou leadest, and I will have—A glorious life, or else a handsome grave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you leave us then, and thus throw behind you all the kindness of a Father and a Brother? has the place no tie upon your grateful Nature? has my love and conversation (besides a Brothers Interest in your blood) gained no place in <hi>Phillora</hi>'s heart?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, yes, ever dear <hi>Pollidor,</hi> they have, they have; and know, I leave not this place, because my fond will arrects a change, nor am I ungrateful to this place in which thou taught'st me those rules of Love and Honour, whose great Examples (though yet no Lover) I now begin to imitate; and <hi>Pollidor</hi> shall find me ready to pay all those debts when Love and Honour calls; and for this dear Cave, this beloved Cell, thus I take a sad and kind Farewell; with tears I part from thee; and for the blest protection we have found in thy</p>
                     </sp>
                     <gap unit="page" extent="2"/>
                     <sp>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="484" facs="243"/>
our retreat to this hill, from whence we fled yesterday, must breed some doubt of the cause; for it must seem strange to finde themselves sought by those men to day which fled them last night; Besides, your Highness knows, Their Army is compos'd of divers Interests, which will make them jealous of each other; and rea|sonably enough apprehend we have some intelligence in their Army, which time can onely satisfie, and may joyn to them the doubtful part, which expect but the fortune of a day, to declare for the Conqueror; We can hope no more then we are; every day will increase them, both in number and repute; therefore my counsel is, to offer them Battle, while we are in lust, and hope of victory; delay will but abate the Souldiers hearts, and then 'tis easie to master the Limbs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess, you have reason; and <hi>Arcus</hi> shall return my sence of it to the King, and desire him to send my Sister, and the Baggage to <hi>Capua,</hi> there to attend our success.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>What says your Letters?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>They mention some disorders among the Rebels in <hi>Na|ples;</hi> But this fatall Paper makes their Army dangerous; 'tis my Sisters dream expounded by the old Hermit, 'tis sent me by <hi>Fide|lia;</hi> there read her letter, thou wilt find something that concerns thee, whilst I rest me here.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(Palantus <hi>reads the Dream, the prince lies down.)</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>The Dream.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Your Highness walk by the Sea-side in a quiet Evening.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Signifies, the peace and security drawing to an end will be</l>
                        <l>Interrupted by the unconstancy of the People; For the Evening</l>
                        <l>Signifies the conclusion of a happiness.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And the cloud that landed a Knight in Forreign habit, who</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Kick'd up the sand in your Faces, in a dangerous proportion;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Signifies a forreign Invasion, which discontents will</l>
                        <l>Countenance; for <hi>Raising the dust</hi> is raising the people, whose</l>
                        <l>Hieroglyphique Sand and dust are, <hi>Flying in your Faces,</hi> is</l>
                        <l>Rebellion, which knows no bound, nor respect;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Your being angry, and not able to revenge the injuries,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Foretells this Rebellion will be powerful.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The flying from the Dust, and loss of the King, in it;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>My fears apprehend his loss in this Rebellion;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Your succour in a wood, where shepherds beat down the dust, with boughes.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Signifies a happy relief in the faith and loyalty of the Countrey</l>
                        <l>People. <hi>Trees,</hi> being the Hieroglyphique of Loyalty.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And the extravagant desires of the Shepherds, who importune the</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Prince and your Highness to the marrying of two Trees, affirming</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Else that the dust and danger would return again,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Signifies, that by some Miraculous manner your Highness</l>
                        <l>Must fix the peoples hearts.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="485" facs="243"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the</hi> Satyr <hi>wounded, an Arrow sticking in his Arm, he is amazed when he sees them, and looks with fear upon</hi> Arcus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>How now! what dost thou seek! who gave thee this wound? why this fear and wonder?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He kneels and holds the prince.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Seed of gods, or the god of War himself, what e're thou bee'st, Thus I adore thee, thus I implore thy aid; tell me but where thy Altars stand, I'll haste and fetch a Lamb, and sacrifice him to thee, my great deliverer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Rise poor wretch, and cease to fear, or worship; there's neither due here; We are mortal as thou art; yet if any In|jury threaten thee, we will protect thee; how the poor wretch trembles! prithee, <hi>Palantus,</hi> help to draw the Arrow; how came you by this Shot?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>From a fair and cruel Foe, Divinest, A maid of heavenly Form, brighter then the Evening Star, lovely as the <hi>Syrinx</hi> our great gods Paramour, straight as young hazel wands, or the Cornel Darts by <hi>Diana</hi> thrown; and far the Nymph out-shines all her train.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, and what of her? The poor thing loves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Love? yes, yes, love, so they call my pain; 'tis a grief grows here—Beloved of—gods, here, I suck'd the Venom at my Eyes; and my old Master says 'twill never be cured.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>And is it troublesome, your pain?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Troublesome? The Plague or Famine, or the wilde Wolfs tooth, wounds not like it; My mind is all afire.—Great, and blest, did thy happy soul never feel the thirst that beauty breeds?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Never; and I wonder how thou comest thus miserable; by my life, <hi>Palantus,</hi> he tells me more of Love and his power then some Poets feign.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Never Love? Why what do you do all day? how do you spend your thoughts? My very Dreams are Love, my Sinews shrink when she frowns; sure shee's a Witch, there's such Magick in her Eyes; My flock I'll pawn against a Dog, you will like and love her too, 'tis such a Divine form; 'tis not thy Army, nor thy Arms can guard thee from her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Dost thou know her? what is she?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sat.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, yes, in this wood she lives, and hath done from her mothers breast; her father and her brother are my masters (but I serve none but her,) My Sire gave them his Cave to live in, we were bred to|gether, and yet unkind she seeks to destroy me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Who are her Father and her brother?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Strange men, and hold strange Opinions, of Names and Places, of pains for ever, Divinest, and talk of Gods, and their rods, above <hi>Pan</hi> and his punishments; which wilde things too they threaten, of being nothing, Master, and yet last ever, and call all that I desire, by nature taught, a fault.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="486" facs="244"/>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>What urged her to wound you thus?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>I found her sleeping in yonder Grove, and would have stollen a kiss; seven Summers here have I worn this wastful fire in my suffring breast without a hope of rest, and yet she threw me from her, call'd me Beast, and bent her Bowe; yet I have seen her kiss her Brother's Dog a thousand times.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>I swear she's very unreasonable to despise thee, and be so kinde to a Dog.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>But I hang'd him for't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>'T was wisely done to remove your Rival; but you forget your wound, does it not smart?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>The unkindness does, and she's ungrateful too; for would I have sought a Maid amongst our own kinde, she that has the curledst Horns and crooked'st Thighs would have been proud of me; for, despised as I am, there is no subject of our Master <hi>Pan</hi> can hunt, climb, or out-run me, none surer with his Bowe or Dart, none feller with his Club, or bolder in his heart, ally'd to <hi>Pan;</hi> my breast too is broad, smoother hoofs, nor wealthier fleece clothes no Satyr's things; these unshorn Curls from my birth I wear, they cut theirs (Master) that are poor; these gilded Horns were hers too, the first fruits of her brow, an earlier Musen none casts than she, and thousands wait upon her smile; but she'll have none but me, that pine for this cruel scorn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Has she a Father and a Brother, say you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, great Master, and here they live, converse with none; sure some sad misfortune or great guilt hangs upon them, for they are always sad.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>How do they spend their time?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>They read and hunt, I taught them: we have this day slain a Bore and a Lion, divine <hi>Phillora</hi> wears the Spoil: Their Fa|ther too is old, and gray as Winter, but stout as young Lions, wise as Oracles, pious too as <hi>Pan</hi>'s Priest; he has been injur'd, he says, by a King of men; I hear him talk of mighty things—But hark, I hear her Horn, with that she calls her Brother; I dare not see her <stage>A Horn ●indes.</stage> eyes, I can charm all rage but hers: Fool that I was, I taught her to resist my Philtres; and now if you protect not I am lost, her heart threatens destruction.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Step behinde, let me meet your danger.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Phillora <hi>with her Bowe bent pursuing the Satyr.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>This way I'm sure he took, he cannot fly far, my Arrow found him; for by his lustful bloud I have track'd him to this place—I see the Villain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>She levels her Bowe at the Satyr, but spying</hi> Leopoldo <hi>gazes up|on him, and stands in the posture, and all the Company seems amazed, the Satyr creeps out from behinde</hi> Leopoldo, <hi>and looks in the face of one, and then of the other.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="487" facs="244"/>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>How they gaze upon each other! thus did I look, thus wonder, and then grew sick in my mi●●●● her eyes are fix'd, she mindes me not; I'll seek my safety first▪ and then dispute my Crime.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He cuts her Bowe-string, which makes her collect her self.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! do you glory in this wile? but know, 'tis onely de|ferring of thy doom.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Gentle Maid, may we know the reason of this War?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Nought, great Master, but my loving her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>If that be a Crime, where have you seen that dull thing that either could or would be innocent? By all the divers troubles of my minde, one sight of that divine form has surpriz'd a strength here that never fear'd a womans power till now—Here <stage>Points to his heart.</stage> fair one, where never power of beauty dwelt before.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! Why do I gaze thus?—What have I seen?—Is it a God or a Man?—Such a Figure my eyes never saw before—How far he out-shines my Brother!—The Pride and Opinion of my self too, those wither'd Leaves I feel fall from my heart—There's no such Glass as perfect Excellency in others for Pride to see and hate her self in—O that I had been born blinde, or could tear these Traitors out that thus have robb'd me of my content and peace of minde, to both which Farewell for ever—What is it that stops me? Something calls me back, my fond heart would <stage>She offers to go out and stops at the Door, and then pro|ceeds.</stage> gaze again. Do, do, and be fit for pity, drink deep of that delici|ous Poyson, so are you past remedy; yet if you bet ler me fly and inflame the world; Love and Desire, your winged fire here I feel, yet glory not in my ruine; for 'tis but a poor Shepherdess breast, and no wonder if a God oppress it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>She is gone, and all joys go with her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>And all my fears; yet I love even that anger in her eyes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas a strange accident, who can this Maid be? 'tis some delusion sure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>The Prince is troubled; pray Sir, leave your wonder, and strive to divert your thoughts: This figure calls to minde the Shepherd in the Princesses Dream, the Sex onely differs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>There's more than ordinary accident in this; See how his eyes are fix'd. I'll speak to him; Sir, Sir, your Highnesses minde is so intent upon this Girl you do not hear the Trumpet, Sir, whose call tells us, Something like Danger threatens; something worthy your presence, and your thought calls away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Didst thou see her <hi>Palantus?</hi> The <hi>Arcadian</hi> Nymphs that boast their sable eyes, white-wristed <hi>Juno, Venus,</hi> or the Goddess that Woods affects, no nor the Virgin-Deity, she that bears both Shield and Spear, and has eyes that farther wound, yet all their united Graces (though we bow to them) out-shine not this Flower of the Wood; And thou God of hearts stop this Fate, either call back or bless thy flying Dart; cure mine, or touch her heart.—Come hither, dost thou know this Maid, and the place of her abode?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, yes, I know thy pain too, fear'd of men; there's a Feaver in thy breast, a fire that all the Herbs in the Wood
<pb n="488" facs="245"/>
cannot cure, nor Streames of these Meadows quench.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>I must finde this Maid though thousand Difficulties op|pose; 'tis the very Figure in my Sisters Dream.—O <hi>Bellamira,</hi> thy prophetick soul has foreseen all our Troubles both of minde and body.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Sir, forget not the business that now stays for us, two Armies in <hi>Battalia,</hi> two Kingdoms in dispute, your Fathers safety, your Life and Honour, all at stake; will you throw all these by to follow a phantasie, the shadow of a shadow, one like to no|thing, seen in anothers Dream? Me thinks these Dangers and Du|tie which are at hand should remove all those light thoughts from your heart; Pardon this freedom, Sir, 'tis my affection speaks.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee Peace, Father and Sister are empty names, Virtue and Honour, and all the Gods must fly <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> or make my way fit to the enjoying this lovely Maid: My soul is sick, I know not of what Disease, but sudden and deadly as the Plague; The Infecti|on struck me, Honour and Virtue be still <hi>Leopoldo</hi>'s Guides, and cease to take pleasure in opposing his happiness with your difficul|ties; 'tis not the distance else between a Crown and a Shepherd shall divide us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Art thou a Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and one, if thou canst serve in my love, will make thee happy; my soul longs to enjoy the friendship of this lovely Maid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Enjoy her? She will not be touch'd, Heavens, Fire, and Time, will be touch'd and stay'd as soon as she, if she thought you imagin'd such a hope.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou mistak'st me, I dare as soon attempt my Fathers life as stain her chaste bosome with any faulty desires.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Away Dissembler, I see thy aim; thou a Prince? 'Tis false; Where's the virtue that set thee above a world of men? Thou art the Satyre, sure; though thou hast cast thy Horns and Hoofs thou art more a Beast than I. Fool that I was, did I kneel to thee, Abuser of the Gods; Most ingrate, did they give thee this form and power to betray men, and pollute Virgins? Defend me! thou Wretch, wouldst thou make me accessary to the abusing of the thing I love better than my soul, or thou lov'st thy self?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, fond Beast, hold, and be gone; your honest igno|rance, Sirra, defends you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>And so it shall do still against such impious Greatness; if I durst but see my Love I'd home, and tell her what a Villain a Prince may be. <stage>
                              <p>Arcus <hi>stops him as he de|parts.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>The Satyr looks upon</hi> Arcus <hi>the Moor as a|mazed at him, and gives him no answer.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Why in such haste? I'll ease you of your Club; Have you found a remedy for your arm yet?—This strange Accident a|mazes all my thoughts; This Wretch too, to finde such a noble anger upon a thought of force being offer'd to his Love: There's nothing in this day but miracle; something, sure, great and high as the persons design'd in this Tragedy, the Gods are busie to deliver to the world; for 'tis no common birth that Nature and Nations thus labours with, which makes me with patience bear those throws
<pb n="489" facs="245"/>
that afflict my heart, whose desperate love, though a lo ser of all those hopes I had at stake, makes me resolved silently to look on, and see this Game plaid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee, <hi>Arcus,</hi> let our Rival go; and when thou seest the maid tell her, if I out-live this day I'll find her, and doubt not my love shall be less commanded then I would my self be obeyed; here, bind his arm in this Scarfe, <hi>Arcus;</hi> and then haste to my Si|ster, tell her she must instantly for <hi>Capua;</hi> and assure the King I <stage>
                              <hi>He gives him a scarf to bind upon the</hi> Satyr<hi>'s arms.</hi>
                           </stage> will not fail to make good this hill.—Love and arms that have so often met, smile on your Priest that has seen what my soul can ne're forget.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Leopoldo <hi>and</hi> Arcus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>If my heart can judge she loves this Gay Man, then she'l be glad of this Scarfe, I'll give it her and she shall forgive me; when I can please her my heart rejoyces; but she ne're thinks of poor little me but to grieve my heart. <stage>As he speaks and goes out he licks his arms.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bellamira <hi>alone.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>THis strange chance that <hi>Arcus</hi> relates makes me fear some sudden issue of my Dream; he describes a Maid, whose beauty took my Brother in an hour when his heart was most opposite to love; and by the habit and the place only her sex differs; for his description most lively paints that shadow which my Dream has thus long enjoy'd; ye gods, if it be your will in Riddles still to wrap your secrets, we mortals can only say Amen. But why do I let this lesser thought fill my breast; when Countries ruine and the death of my dear Father (the great part of my fear, or ought to be) past by unmourn'd? sure there is a reason for this fault; this weakness has its cause; something that my mind does yield to, prevails; yet I find not my Reason overcome, though there's something in this gentle fear I know not what to call it: I never yet felt love by what I observe of him in others; yet I begin to fear he's knocking at my breast, and would fain get in; sure 'tis he, for I was never till now so neer being a Lover as the fear of it. But I must still these noises in my thoughts; for a Virgins innocency is so coy, so jealous, and so gentle too, she need not take the pains to beat it from her heart; she may think that and her peace away. Therefore, <hi>Bellamira,</hi> wisely in time correct thy thoughts, and suffer them not to play with this dangerous god, lest the sport prove ear|nest, lest the child thou play'st with grows too strong for Rea|son; and from innocent thoughts becomes unruly passions. <hi>Fidelia,</hi> though she knows all but my fears, yet I now begin to blush, because there is something like my Love, whil'st 'twas <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Fide|lia.</stage> in shadowes onely; I was confident, there being nothing in Nature to accuse me but this, though a Virgin like my
<pb n="490" facs="246"/>
self, yet 'tis something now that my passion builds upon; and that newness, though no fault, is yet unconquer'd in my mind; and I cannot yet tell her this new stranger thought, though she know all the other secrets of my heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Arcus</hi> says, since he left the Prince he saw a Shepherd in age and clothes so like the Maid, that he believes it must be her Brother; and from this sight concludes your safeties neer; for why should we find the evil part, and not the good prove true, of that fa|tal Dream?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! what coldness is this?—What trembling?—What paleness? this confusion of mind, what means it?—This joy and fear, this mingled nameless passion, of all passions com|posed.—What art thou, or what would'st thou be?—Why this violence on a Maids heart?—Be but honour, and wear what danger, what form, thou wilt command, and I'll obey thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>She's strangely troubled; I never saw her thus before: Madam, has my news displeased you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira,</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, <hi>Fidelia;</hi> my heart has troubles which thy joys to find some ease for me has overseen, whilst the greatest and saddest part of that fatal Dream; the King, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> the good, the kind, the valiant old King, my friend and Father, must in this dust be lost; remember that; what joy then can a safety bring when we cannot hope our victory at a less rate then his precious life?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Your pardon, Madam; the Princes love, and strange pas|sage of the Satyr, your interest, and hope of future good, made me forget that piety and pity was due to the King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> love, but do not pity us; for my part, though their ruine threaten, yet I despise a pity; nor is it due to my fortune; for I am not miserable so ordinary a way, as to be relieved with so cheap a remedy; and were the King safe thou shouldst find me resolved, though not contented; and other joy then that resolution I cannot promise to my self; yet if I could be satisfi'd with such joys as affect others, I might esteem my self blest; But my mind, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> is too severe to be taken with such shallow happiness as I see most women pursue, who affect the noise and vanity of the world, whose bubbles deceive and slave the most of women.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Arcus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>See, Madam, here's <hi>Arcus;</hi> let him now describe the Maid, whose beauty he said was equal to all that ever his eye saw.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Pardon me, Madam; my heart and reason make one exception.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Arcus</hi> is kind to beauty, and where ere he meets ad|mires it; but what do's the noble <hi>Arcus</hi> think is beauty? if his eyes chuse what is valued in his Country, there's nothing amongst us he can approve of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas our curse to be born in that Countrey, Ma|dam; and that slavery which at first I lamented, I now rejoyce
<pb n="491" facs="246"/>
in as the means to make me able to distinguish between good and bad; for beauty, 'tis my contrary, what is not like me is beauti|ful; this is the shame and brand of nature; the curse of an incens'd deity lives in our black.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>Y'are cruel to the colour; and I rather think, like divine <hi>Bellessa,</hi> beauty, afraid of injuries, or in revenge of that inconstan|cy she has found in men, hath thrown off red and white; and to live safe from the vanity and perjury of both sexes hath made this re|treat into black for her security.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, the story of our change is common; and the Poet tells whose curse we bear in our faces; no such reason as your Highness in your goodness imagines, whose charity would perswade us we might yet find acceptance when we lov'd; but 'tis too sad a truth, that for the sin of one coy <hi>Daphne</hi> all our Nation mourns; that froward Girle incensed <hi>Apollo</hi>'s rage, and in re|venge of her scorn thus he brands us all, lest our Coun|trey should again boast a face, that he might love; yet this good I finde from my black; all people boldly praise me; and 'tis such an impossibility to believe any body can love it, that even your Highness will venture to defend it, and safely may; for 'twill beget no mans jealousie nor womans envy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>But if <hi>Arcus</hi> will find the Prince, and tell him how fain his Sister would see him before the Battle, and certainly in|form himself whether these two Shepherds are really in nature, or only walking Dreams.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Bellamira</hi> will owe him more then praise, or thanks can pay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas his Highness Order I should expect him here, yet I shall not fail to obey your command, though betwixt this and the Prince the enemy has placed a Guard which I must pass through; for to go about I fear will be too long for your Highness to expect my return.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellamira.</speaker>
                        <p>No, 'tis enough, we'l expect his coming; I did not know there was a danger in the Pass; nor will we venture <hi>Ar-Arcus,</hi> whose faith shall be reserv'd for greater trusts then to be thrown away upon this common one; if I doubted his heart or love to my Brother, he should go; and I'de prefer my curiosity be|fore him; but to let <hi>Arcus</hi> see I value his faith, I shall still preserve him as he has done it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, now I beg upon my knees your commands; and either you doubt my heart or faith, whose readiness to serve you you shall find as constant as my colour; my life and free|dom I value only as the gift of your generous Brother; and your goodness has made me such a continued happiness, and so far above my merit, I am fain to trust to the report of others ere I can believe I was ever miserable; my birth in my Country I am not asham'd of, though I am of my fortune; to redeem which, if your Highness shall fear to command or expose me, I shall rather think you doubt, me then that you have any fears for me. For know, Madam, I cannot be satisfi'd, nor
<pb n="492" facs="247"/>
count my self a grateful receiver of this freedom, but when I ex|pose that and my self to serve you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>When I have a danger worthy of him he shall be sure to find the trust, and my prayers with it: but since my Brother de|sires it, whose love has sent him about me, pray expect him here; for this Letter says, you and old <hi>Philemon</hi> must accompany us to <hi>Capua;</hi> and should you miscarry, our sex and ignorance of the place may throw us into many dangers.—Sure there is more in this man then his humble heart yet shews: such guests as honour, faith and courage would not lodge in so mean a Cottage as a private slave, unless benighted, or to avoid storms. Good heaven, what fortune do we see dealt to some men, as if justice had no power nor voice in heaven!—Well, <hi>Arcus,</hi> if we live to see this storm blown over, I shall very unwillingly be denyed a better knowledge of your for|tune; for 'tis not this cloud, nor this night that hangs upon thy forehead; nor those chains thou lately putt'st off can hide thy mind; it still shews something too great for those misfortunes to pretend to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven hide his mercies when I hide a thought from the divine <hi>Bellamira;</hi> my story, Madam, when your Highness has leisure to wonder at the averseness of fortune, and would allay your own joys, then you shall know it: for that is a story has tasted of all kind of changes; and my miseries shall serve for your diversi|on, Madam; in which nothing lies heavier upon my heart then the loss of a friend; which since my being a slave in <hi>Cyprus</hi> I could never hear of; and by me you may learn what custom can; do for my heart has of late been so beaten with afflictions they are grown natural to me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Leopoldo <hi>and</hi> Palantus <hi>to them.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>See, see; <hi>Arcus,</hi> who is come to decide the difference? Oh, my Brother! what new strange misery is this! <hi>Arcus</hi> has fill'd my heart with fear and wonder; the truth of my dream makes me tremble too, with the apprehension of the Kings danger.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Bellamira,</hi> my distracted soul is grown weary of this habitation; the new and many strokes that fortune has given of late makes me even turn coward, and yield to her malice; me|thinks all she can do, or vertue hope for, is not worth the dispute; I would I had lost all she aims at so I were dead, or in some place forgotten and unknown to any but the gods.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>I will not compare my griefs with my Brother's; but sure if I did you'ld pity me, and not add your troubles to them; I hear you have seen a Maid in the Woods, and such a beauty as the Court never shew'd you; and I have got a Lover too, I was sending now to acquaint you with the person, and his propositions. I can conclude this war without a stroke, at least the Spanish Prince tells me so: 'tis only marrying him, and quitting my Father; and dear <hi>Leopoldo;</hi> this is all I am to do, and I shall prove how much he loves me even in this my desperate estate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>This from the false usurper? what answer sent you back?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bellam.</speaker>
                        <p>I bad the Messenger return him, I never saw that man I would marry, nor any one whose company I prefer'd before my
<pb n="493" facs="247"/>
Brothers; but if there were a necessity, and my choice free, the meanest Gentleman in all his Army that wore a sword, and had not lost his honour, my soul would prefer before him, even in this height of all his pride and power, that could believe my heart so degenerate to let it self be embraced by the destroyer of my Country, and murtherer of my Family.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Spoke like my Sister, I never hated an enemy before; had love or ambition fairly arm'd his men, or desire to have got fame upon us, such a choice honour would have pleaded for; and I could have fought with him, and lov'd him too: but this treacherous pride and covetousness are too low things and too mean instruments for the gods to use, even when they have de|creed a Monarchs ruine. Thunder, Famine, Sword or Pesti|lence, are nobler far; sure we shall blush at our fall from this mean hand.—See, <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s engaged, let us leave her; I have something to tell thee ere I part; 'tis a new secret, <hi>Bellamira;</hi> but the richest of my heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Leopoldo <hi>and</hi> Bellamira.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>You'll finde nothing but truth in what I have said; that she loves, or at least fears so, is as certain as that she can|not love you, which Love and Fortune both has sent to afflict you in revenge of that scorn you have paid my friendship.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>The figure of something seen in a Dream! the shadow of a shadow! this is a fate as aiery as mine own, as hopeless, No|body, or a Shepherd! as impossible are her desires as mine; this being as much below her merit, as she's above mine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia,</speaker>
                        <stage> aside.</stage>
                        <p>Who knows their fate? their desperate passions make mine possible; I know 'tis not common nor scarce ho|nourable in Maids to wooe; yet, methinks, I may tell him that I love, if there be no more ill in the word then my desires or thoughts aim at; I am sure I may with innocency enough, and when I have told him so, if I lose a grain, or grow less in any one good, if I pluck one beauty from a Virgins mind, let how|lings find me, and may my crimes in sad repentance unpitied fall in showers upon my cheeks; therefore arm'd with my innocence I am resolv'd to prove fate further; for to the vertuous and the fairly daring Fortune still holds out unlook'd for success; and if mine be like my love, it must prove better then my hopes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>You are sad, <hi>Fidelia;</hi> is the Prince ready to depart?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you not go in and resolve your self? I know there is one from whom you will take a most unwilling leave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> there needs no circumvention to know all the secrets of my heart; ask and take them, for the gentle <hi>Fi|delia</hi> mistakes her friend, if she thinks I have any wish that has a blush attending it; nor did I ever hide my desires from her, but in kindnesse, being loth to let her see a sight might trouble her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He turns about.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel.</speaker>
                        <p>I cannot speak to him, my heart's too big to beg for love.—Farewel, <hi>Palantus;</hi> live and love all, but—('twill not out.) <stage>She offers to go away, he calls her back.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Stay, gentle maid; 'tis true I love, I will not lye to thee, nor dare I tell her whom I love; that truth, yet my wishes
<pb n="494" facs="248"/>
as no less innocent, then my hopes desperate; and I wear the fire here, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> without a fault, and shall do till I am earth; Yet my own despaires wound me not so much as <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s, when I con|sider her and Fate; and if thou wilt have patience thou shalt see me revenge thee on my self, decreed to such a misery as will not let me take the pleasure of making thee happy, nor my self; Yet I conjure thee, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> strive with thy Passion; and now thou knowest my Heart, let us smile some time when we meet each other; a sullen sad Love looks as if it mourn'd some past sin, or struggl'd yet to con|quer some ill design.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Malice and jealous Lovers make more serious search then death; and what I told you even now was my fears rather then my wishes in thy Fortune; for know, my Heart is too full of Friendship for <hi>Palantus</hi> to wish against him: And farther, though I know all his desires are designed rewards for another, and thou wouldst see thy wishes enjoy'd by one thou canst not question, (being Rival'd by a shadow,) yet I cannot blame thy Love; For <hi>Bellamira</hi> is an Excellence fit for Heaven to co|vet: Nor doe's <hi>Palantus</hi> rejoyce in those Excellencies more then I, though her graces are to me as so many Enemies. Thus <hi>Fide|lia,</hi> though despis'd, will preserve her self fit for better Fortunes, by bearing this with Honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure there cannot be such a punishment in store for loving <hi>Bellamira</hi> as thy kind fears apprehend; And since we have touch'd this string, whose harsh sound I have long avoided for thy sake; Yet give me leave to say, Heaven and my Friend can witness, I never made any vows to <hi>Fidelia;</hi> what I have done for her, let the gods prove propitious to them and make us happy yet. And therefore, in Justice, you cannot call me unconstant, or abuser of your Love. Gratitude (if it were not too like vanity to say so) is all I ever could pay to thee; Not that I would not have given more, but 'twas all I had left; This fatal fire sent for my punishment, I fear, is either Child or Parent of that little god; for till then, I never knew or scarce believed there was such a power; nor did your own Heart desire a return of Love more then I have longed to give it you; For I know, Honour in all the heights of excellency produces nothing more glorious then a handsome Friendship: Other Virtues have him in pieces, but intire Honour is in the perfect Love of two; which since we cannot enjoy as we wish, yet you cannot accuse me of a crime which you have confess'd your self; Gentle <hi>Fidelia,</hi> though not at the same Altar, yet I bow to the same power that leads thee in chains; nor will I be so bar|barous as to imploy thy Love to advance my wishes with <hi>Bella|mira,</hi> nor fear from thee such injustice as to do ill Offices: Let our Friendship pity each other, and while we love with Honour leave the rest to Fate; and thou shalt find, though Love be binld, since he has brought us to this precipice, (I prophecy) he will lend us his wings to save us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>See, see, my Friend, how pleasing Truth is; when thou
<pb n="495" facs="248"/>
dissemblest even now, and hid'st thy Love; Thy words came out unwillingly, and their harsh sounds were forc'd through thy teeth, as if thy Tongue had hal'd them to suffer for some crime they had commited: But now there's Musick in them; and though the Tune be sad, yet 'tis well set; and our Souls sometimes af|fects the serious and the grave, as well as the jolly triumphant noyse of victory; And since <hi>Palantus</hi> values my Friendship, and looks with pity upon my sufferings, my Soul is at peace; for can he do this and not love? What is that but Love? Give me this, and take all the world besides: My Soul has not another wish in store, but that my Friend may find his, and I a pardon for a fault he shall not know until I have redeemed it; The Princess <hi>Bellamira</hi> too shall beg it for me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>What fault can you be guilty of to me that needs a Mediator? Is there a power beyond our Faith with each other? Come, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> though our parts be hard, yet we have a fair field to act in, and if friends looking on● and I miss my part, prompt me Love, and <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s Heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Pollidor, Ravack, <hi>and the</hi> Satyr <hi>wounded;</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Ravack <hi>seem to be full of troubles, the</hi> Satyr <hi>fawnes upon the old man and speaks.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>I'Ll drink no more of this poyson'd Juice; 'tis full of mad|ness, Rage, and Lust; I lost my Reason and my leggs too, and but darkly; yet remember what I did; good Master, calm her Mind, and make my peace, I dare not see her else.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas the Prince <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> sure; he sayes they call'd him Prince, the accident is full of mystery; The gods laugh still at the wisest actions men design without them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, yes, <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> and Prince, so they call'd him; I thought he would have wrong'd my Love; if he had, lame as I am, my club should have pash'd his skull.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>The Prince, men say, is gallant; My Father that hates them all for's Masters sake, yet calls him the just <hi>Leopoldo:</hi> And valiant all the world delivers him; sure he cannot then do a base Action; Yet his suddain passion may want reason to counsel him; and listning to his blood and power, who knows how that may prompt him to seek his end upon a Shep-herds Daughter? I'll find <hi>Phillora,</hi> and from her know all the Truth; Her wonder and silence makes me fear she loves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>She gaz'd, he sayes, and stood dumb; then changed co|lour, and with fixt eyes lost her self in thoughts, till he cut her bow-string undiscern'd. Come let us find her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Polidlor.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, my thoughts upon this accident have been work|ing long, but what to wish or fear, I know not; They have both
<pb n="496" facs="249"/>
Honour, and that secures me from the apprehension of a great misfortune; though my Reason cannot hope the least happiness from their passion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>Let's lose no time in finding her, nor take notice, when she comes, that we have heard of this accident; get her things made up, and we will away to <hi>Gaietta;</hi> she's too modest to say she loves him; and we must be so discreet as not to see she's troubled, when she's once in <hi>Gaietta,</hi> the object being removed; she will not forget him; 'tis the first gay sight she has seen, and that works upon her phansie: But she has youth enough to out|grow greater blows then this; Yet I confess, my Heart, since my Master dyed, never felt such divided thoughts as this passage has begot; let us haste and find them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>I'll stand the forked lightning sooner then meet her now she's displeas'd; my flesh trembles to remember she was an|gry; either let her forgive me, or I'll be gone; I'll serve you no more if she frowns; 'Tis for her sake I am a slave, my Soul has pleasure in obeying her.—See where she comes, hide me, earth, from that anger that fills her Mind; I'll not let you go till she for|gives me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora sad.</speaker>
                        <p>They bowed to him and call'd him Prince; Ye gods, what need has he of such Additions? But Fortune will be Fortune still, lavish to some, and niggard to others, disposing her blessings like her blind self; What need had that Person (his moderation and his parts) of Titles, as if those vertues were not enough to give him rule over the world.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravak.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Phillora,</hi> come, dispatch; we have staid here till it is late; for you know we have a long walk to <hi>Gaietta.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>How came you so incens'd against your poor Lover? Fie, <hi>Phillora,</hi> could you be so displeas'd with a poor creature who knows no better then to be happy when he can? One not born subject to the Laws of Honour as we are. Nature was his Parent and his Mistriss, she teaches no other Lessons; and yet, for your sake, he has bound in strict chains his blood and desires, and a thousand times hazarded his Life to meet your dangers; And could you be so cruel to intend his death for one fault? Orecome with wine too? Come, pray let me make his peace.—Come hither. <stage>He calls him.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>I dare not till she forgives me, and calls me hers again.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Forgive thee? yes, with all my Soul I forgive thee, and beg thy pardon, poor thing; How full of fear he is of me that had forgot him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>I pray dress his arm.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall, Dear <hi>Pollidor,</hi> and then I have other wounds to cure; First, let me see this, so.—Go fetch me some of the pot of Balsam thy Father taught us to make; Here, prithee take this Bow and Quiver; I'll give them thee for being so ready to exe|cute <stage>She looks upon his Arm</stage> my Anger upon my poor Lover, and burn them if thou wilt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="497" facs="249"/>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Do, and I'le give thee this Scarf, the Prince gave it me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>The Princes Scarf? did he give it thee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Divinest. But what care I for him, or it, but to please <stage>Gives her the Scarf.</stage> thee? take it, and forgive me—All the gods bless thee, fair and gentle; may all that wrong thee bleed like me, In heart too, and find my wounded mind; Shall we go, this night, for <hi>Gaietta,</hi> Master, I'll put up the Pyes we made; But I'll destroy the bag that holds my enemy, that baneful Liquor; I'll spend all my Arrows on that damn'd skin, and let his blood out as fast as he did mine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>And when you have done haste to yonder hill, and dili|gently observe which way those Troops bend their march that pass the wood; assoon as you return wee'll be gone; come <hi>Phillora;</hi> you are sad, he is not dangerously hurt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I am glad I mist my aim; And I would there were no more danger in my wounds, then I wish, or fear, in his.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Your wounds, Sister, where are you wounded?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Come nearer, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> thou art my brother, my dear brother, <stage>She sighs and weeps. Aside.</stage> until this hour, the only sharer with this good old man, in all the wishes and joys of my heart; this morning I had no wish, no hope, no joy, beyond us three; Your good was all I pray'd for then. But—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>But? What dear <hi>Phillora?—</hi>Ye gods! 'tis too true, I fear what the poor <hi>Satyr</hi> said, he knew by himself She was in Love, and having felt the sickness confidently describes the disease; how Nature and Honour strive in her wounded Breast! but I must not seem to indulge her passion, there being no possibi|lity she should be happy; Nor can I, if I would be angry with her; My Counsel I'll give her gently, and use a Brothers Interest to prevail.—Let not <hi>Phillora</hi> wonder at my silence when she weeps; Tears and Sighs, in thy Fortune, cannot pass by me, but with pain and amazement, what ayles my Sister, why do's she hide her Eyes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh that I had been blind this day, then I had not seen that god walking amongst mortal men; his Eyes, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> wound like the Pestilence; here, here it struck me, I cannot bear the pain, nor would not willingly be cured.—'Tis either Love, or death, or both; For both bear darts, and sometimes death has (they say) used loves Bowe; if ever, now he has borrowed it; for I find a strange sadness here, sadness even to death, <hi>Pollidor.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh poor <hi>Phillora,</hi> this news flew before thee, but we hop'd thy wounds were not so dangerous, nor their pains so great, as to make thee cry out for help; dost thou know, who 'tis whose eyes have poyson'd all thy peace?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>The man I know not, But excellent, sure, above the rest; his looks appear'd as if he had some great place in General Fame; Prince they call'd him too, and like <hi>Mars</hi> he mov'd.—In his looks you might have read him a King of men.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>But when <hi>Phillora</hi> knows this is that Prince <hi>Leopoldo</hi> she has heard my Father so often mention, she will then remember what hatred is due to him, and not heap sorrow upon her Fathers head by loving his Enemy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="984" facs="250"/>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Leopoldo?</hi> was it the Prince <hi>Leopoldo?</hi> then I am mi|serable not that he deserves our hate, for my soul tells me; he has no guilty share in our misfortunes; Did my Father know him when he revil'd him? could <hi>Pollidor</hi> know and curse <hi>Leopoldo?</hi> sure you never saw him, did you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Never I, nor wish not, but to take my Revenge upon him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>That's not kindly answer'd, and I dare swear now thou never saw'st him, else his looks would have reconcil'd thee; 'tis not possible such a Noble Countenance should have an Enemy in thy breast; 'tis it self too generous; If this be the Prince <hi>Leopoldo</hi> believe the choice my heart has made; 'tis my first Election, find him out, make acquaintance with him; if then thou canst find in thy soul to hate him I'll never see him more, But rather die then not comply with my Brothers wishes. Oh <hi>Pollidor,</hi> see and know him, and thou wilt find a prodigal Star reigned at his birth; prince and power are Crutches fit for wicked men to lean upon, whse lame souls will fall without such helps; his very looks Command; Thou wilt find great things writ in his Eyes, and hee must bee a Prince wheresoever hee will but deign to Reign.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I find your weakness has yielded too far for me to have a power over your passion: yet if you do love him, you ought not to hate me, nor expose my Honour rashly; But no more now, 'tis late, and we must haste to <hi>Gaietta.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>To <hi>Gaietta?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, to <hi>Gaietta,</hi> our safety and our business calls us thither, change of Faces too, may make you forget him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> I have no such waxen heart; I confess I am wounded, the Venom of a Lovers Eye has stung my heart; I know too, 'tis the common remedy, to decline the Object; but I scorn to be heal'd that Common way; let the Scorpion cure the Scorpions poison; had I never seen the Prince, Not to see him were good counsel; but having seen him, who can behold any other object? my mind carries his figure here; I must blind my reason too, e're I can lose the sight of that bright Star of Honour who now beckens us to come.—Hark, now he calls, now flie to him and Honour, they have but one habitation; Follow me, dear <hi>Pollidor,</hi>
                           <stage>The Trumpet sounds.</stage> Follow, and learn by him how to conquer with perfect honour, and from me to be overcome by <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> with no less glory. To stay here, and have our Virtues chain'd up in Solitude, shews but a passive virtue, onely the Courage of Slaves and Beasts; and they will exceed us too in such a tame Courage that glo|ries onely in what they can endure. The great tryal of great hearts is seen in both Fortunes; who stoops to either Fate of Prince or Slave is not perfect; come, and see the Prince la|bouring himself like the god of War through these dangers; op|posing their Treason with surprizing glories; see every look speaks; whose every motion has more grace and Beauty, and binds me more then his Face; Yet his words were ful of Love; and though I will not say I deserve it, Yet I am confident I have all
<pb n="499" facs="250"/>
that honour could give, in so short a warning; and I will not doubt but my Love has credit with his Heart, for greater sums then <hi>Phillora</hi> desires of Fate, to make her happy. Follow, and be witness of this Truth; see him only, if you then condemn me, I'll yield.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Stay Sister, <hi>Phillora,</hi> I am past my reason; whither <stage>She offers to go out.</stage> will you go? will you thrust your youth into the dangers of the licentious Souldiers? retire, only for this day, into our peaceful Cave, where we will, with my Fathers Counsel, resolve what is to be done in this Extremity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Have I not been buried all my life here, and beg but one day to live? give me but this day, and here interr me again.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Phillora,</hi> I have with grief and amazement heard thee, and now shall cease to wonder that our counsell cannot prevail, since you have thus thrown off the modesty of your Sex; For this confident avowing of your Love is so immodest, that I fear your <hi>Phillora</hi> will give sooner then he asks; That I love thee Heaven witness; and that I am not deaf to Love Thy Mother (whose Ghost will scorn thee,) witness for me; nor do's thy youth know that God. 'Tis true Love, of it self, is innocent, and the gods have given it for a tye a|mongst men, and 'tis the greatest Blessing, even to the happy'st Fortunes; A Beauty in the best minds, if not corrupted. Else That, as all good things in Excess, are ill. Consider then what 'tis you attempt. A Prince, and your Fathers Enemy; One By the Stars set out of your reach; If Honour then be your guide, what can you expect to be (but what I ab|hor to name?) Are you not born private issue? A Shepherds Daughter? can that condition hope any thing but to become some vile thing, despis'd by him, before enjoy'd, and by all, af|ter? Have you a reason to urge against this? if not, let my truth find place.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Scorn me? The Gods we both bow to will revenge me then. A Shepherds daughter? A Herds-mans Childe? the banish'd Issue of a poor Forester? What if this be so? yet we bow to the same Altars, Worship the same gods, and draw the same free Air; do's he scorn all his Subjects? if not, why me? I ask him nothing; is it a fault to love my Prince? If it be, it is no general Crime; Witness the sad Cause of these Wars; and if my Father did not lend a more Parti|all ear to his Anger then to my Love he would not now Command me to hate my Prince, nor longer cherish that only crime that stains his Story; That low passion makes us miser|able; or can you doubt me so fall'n from virtue, so aban|don'd by all the gods, as to forsake all their Sacred Rules, to become a prostitute, or such a Child as to give up all their rights to the first Temptations of my heart? Oh, Sir, re|serve your censure till I have play'd my Part in this unfinish'd Story, and you shall find I build not my happiness on any other grounds but those of honour; And if the Prince prove Master
<pb n="500" facs="251"/>
of all those Excellencies I believe in him, they shall be no Argu|ment to make me wicked; but if he prove short of those vir|tues, you shall finde me scorn him, and pity my self; and if his virtues have no power to tempt me, I am certain his vices shall not; 'Tis the Diety in the Prince, not the Man, <hi>Phillora</hi> stoops to; and when my Father, or dear <hi>Pollidor,</hi> can bring such an Argument against my Love, as to shew me Prince <hi>Leo|poldo</hi> acting one thought less then his part, less then a Prince, you shall see <hi>Phillora</hi> prompt him, and Act something more then woman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>Could I be confirmed he loves, my fears, I con|fess, would vanish for there's no such guard to honour; as per|fect Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I am sure I love, and that shall save me; and I hope he loves; for why should he flatter me? By your own ill rule, if his heart were as wicked, as you would have me believe him, sure he had power enough, he needed no such darkness, as a pretended Love to act a mischief in.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Poor girl, If all that had said, or swore it, had been Lovers, or the half of those that have seal'd it with their Oathes, tears, or bloods, our Stories, <hi>Phillora,</hi> would not have been so full of the mischiefs of that God whose barbarous fires have thrown ruine and destruction into that peace that inhabits amongst the gods them|selves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, of all the herd, The talking Lover, Sir, should find least Faith; the angry and the jealous Lover are to be prefer'd be|fore him; and 'twas a great truth of him that said, 'tis with Lovers as with those that work in Tapestry; they see not the piece until it be done; so he that can describe his pussion, and tell how much, the why, the where, and the when he loved, and what throws and pains his heart felt, is awak'd from his Dream, he could not else make a description of a way he never travell'd; and he that has trod loves paths once exactly, may be a good guide to anothers Passion, but never good Lover himself; after such a Journey.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>When I shall love, give me a Maid with a Virgin passion, and ignorance in Love; that sets out at the Eye, and rests in the heart; Your talking Lover, that strives to gain Love by the Ear, aims at low pleasures, impatient of deser|ving great ones, and loses his Arrows; Where there is Ho|nour, Love needs no such guide as the tongue, to find out Love; nor company, to tell his story to; Love and a Lover are to each other all the world; they cannot be alone, their thoughts are able to people the world.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, gentle <hi>Pollidor,</hi> talk on, chide me thus, and I'll be silent; how came you to know this great mystery of Love?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollidor.</speaker>
                        <p>For thee, <hi>Phillora,</hi> I have felt a passion, equall to all that Poets feign, and yet never felt one uneasie thought till this hour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="501" facs="251"/>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>O my Brother! dearer yet than my self; this kindness has ty'd thee to my soul, preferr'd before all but the Prince, second to none but <hi>Leopoldo</hi> O turn not away from me, but hear the truth I speak: If what I utter be not Reason, yet 'tis Love: a Vir|gins first and chaste passion for a most excellent object now in dan|ger, pursu'd by treason, and bleeding for the faults of others: O let me do something to help him. I see that smile, now your heart laughs at me; 'tis true, I draw a weak Bowe, but Love will guide the Arrow: I know I hunt all this while impossible things, yet for my peace of minde let me beg, <hi>Pollidor</hi> will be so kinde as to fol|low me this day; what though I lose my self in some hand|som high Attempts, should thy Sister dy, there would be Fame, though no Victory; and if I live there will be time enough to return hither, and in this private life lament my ambitious passi|on, and here learn to level my thoughts at something low as my fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis then too late to counsel; Reason I see has lost his force; All I have to say is, Have you any kindness left, by which I conjure thee, for my sake, defer this business but this day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, for Charity no more; I grant you have reason, but I am mad; Alas, you sue to me as if I had power over my self; Finde the Reason I have lost, and restore it, and <hi>Pollidor</hi> shall finde me the same governable tame <hi>Phillora</hi> I was yesterday. But as it is, you may as soon expect I should sleep when I am bidden, or leave to remember <hi>Pollidor.</hi> I know I am mad, and must plead that Madness, which now must instead of Reason prevail with thee: In desperate Diseases, and with mortal wounds, where no|thing can do good, nothing can do hurt: I am that person, so sick, so wounded. Thy Sister hath at her eyes drank mortal Poyson: Here in my heart I bear the wounds <hi>Apollo</hi> himself complain'd he could not cure; since then in Art and Nature there rests no hope, I conjure thee in kindness let me again drink the pleasing Venome in, and refuse not to thy unfortunate Sister (since she can|not live happily) the satisfaction onely of choosing this way to dy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He embraces him.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>Dry thy eyes, and far, far away be that sad hour; Look up <hi>Phillora,</hi> thou hast overcome me; Reason, Safety, and Revenge, all but Honour, I freely give to thy Passion, and with a Brothers tender heart I'll serve thee. Ye Gods, what Fruit this fatal bitter Root will bring I know not; I'm sure 'tis planted in our richest ground. Come, lead the way, and since Love thus lays violent hands upon our hearts, and will force us in this publick day to play our parts, let us obey his Messengers, and thou shalt finde how dear <hi>Phillora</hi> is to me, whose Peace I'll hunt through the world with faith and truth to Fame or Death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>And if thou find'st thy Sister made like the common frame of women, in whom a sickly weak honour inhabits, such as want the counsel of Friends, or the poor remedy of Spies, to preserve fit for thy love, let my Brother despise me for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                        <p>I am confirm'd, and thus will seek our fortunes in this day
<pb n="502" facs="252"/>
with mindes prepared for all kinde of chances. And you Monarchs of the World, Fame and Honour, what though we bring no Troops of armed men to court you, yet look down with justice upon our actions, and ye shall finde we have not lost one grain of that virtue the Gods were pleas'd to give us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>My soul takes fire at thy words; and though <hi>Pollidor</hi> be no Prince, but a kinde of Plant bred and nourish'd in the Woods, yet I have seen him act what the best of Princes need not blush to imitate; and I prophesie, though he now begins to build without materials, Fortune will supply him; and Princes looking on shall wonder why <hi>Pollidor</hi> was a Shepherd, and their People wish him a Prince seeing him act such things as we sacrifice to in others; then shall the story of kinde <hi>Pollidor</hi> out-last his Marble, and dy onely with the world.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis in vain to resist this Passion; yet if the Prince's love prove noble, greater and weightier interest than they imagine may yet hang upon this day; but the time is so distracted, and so short, I cannot listen to the call of those things that concern us most; for they are gone, and I must follow; Love and Innocency protect them.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Nigro, Cleon, <hi>and their Company of Souldiers in</hi> Gaietta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nigro.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>RAvack</hi>'s stay makes me apprehend some danger, the Ar|mies are both in the Woods, and my fears are more for him and those dear Pledges of Fortune; should they miscarry, all our faith would finde but a sad conclusion; <hi>Clytus</hi> too confirms my jealousies of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Prince, that he means some foul play, by his desiring to marry with the Princess <hi>Bellamira;</hi> his first con|fidence to promise the People to produce their long lost and sup|posed dead Prince begot my fears; but 'twas no time then to dis|cover the falshood of that Promise, because it did our business; for it armed the People,, and shall finish our work too; for before they can be undeceived, or question the truth of that Promise, we'll have play'd our Game; for if we overcome <hi>Leopoldo</hi> their anger's nothing; if <hi>Leopoldo</hi> overcome us, that nor all the world shall win me to survive that day. <hi>Cleon,</hi> we must keep a strong Guard this night; and leave order, if <hi>Ravack</hi> comes, though it be late, that he be let into the Ports, let the Gallies ly loose; and feed your men well, that we may be ready upon all occasions that are presented; I fear the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> but we must not seem to mistrrst him; yet let all the Officers know <hi>Clytus</hi> is the person they are to follow, if he and the Prince of <hi>Spain</hi> dispute; give this intelligence your self, it is not safe to trust it to a common Messenger, lest our fears wrong the Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cleon.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall obey, our Forces are this Evening joyn'd with <hi>Clytus,</hi> 'tis a brave Body; and trust me, the King's looks with a minde not less daring; 'tis true, their number is not so great as
<pb n="503" facs="252"/>
ours, yet their virtues may be equal; for the Gentry fills his Troops, and such whose Fortunes depend upon the Court; in that lies their odds; and 'twas in my opinion no policy to to take away their Retreat to <hi>Capua,</hi> 'twill but beget a desperate Charge; for now their flight can promise no safety; many will do more in such a necessity than Honour would have prompted them to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nigro.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis too late to give that Counsel now, but let us be rea|dy to do our parts when Fortune calls; our Rests are up too, and to Justice I yield my part who knows my heart is honest.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, <hi>and</hi> Roderigo, Clytus <hi>meets them at the other Door.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>CLytus</hi> welcome; Are your Troops joyn'd with those of <hi>Gaietta?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir, and we have already receiv'd a Visit from the Enemy, we have taken some Prisoners that assure us that the King, Prince, and Princess, are all in the Army.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>Why then we shall do all our work at once; I hate delays, let Fortune give me my Answer quickly, whether a Monarch or a Slave;—If my Stars have in this Fate this Crown, This day 'tis <stage>Aside.</stage> mine; if not, there's a hope lost.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>If you could produce the person of our King, my pro|phetick soul tells me the day were ours; such a signal Victory would make all their hearts turn Coward; the justice and venge|ance they must expect from his injuries would wound farther and deeper than either Sword or Spear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>Make it safe by Conquest for him, and my life to gage I'll bring him to you; but if his Friends will not give one blow for his safety, I fear he will not be perswaded to trust their jealousie; but this is wide of our business<hi>—Roderigo!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He whispers.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, do, whisper, the Gods hear you, still I have ac|quainted <hi>Nigro</hi> with my fears, and he, I'm certain, will not be cir|cumvented; 'tis for our own interest we fight as well as yours, ere we see the King, else you should stand alone for <hi>Clytus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>This though it be policy, Sir, is neither honest nor gallant; besides, I cannot be such a Fool as to believe <hi>Clytus</hi> durst say these things, but that he is sure of his Army, who you see has possest yon Hill, and stand in a manner divided from us: Take heed how you anger him lest you tempt him to be wise and honest; 'tis ea|sily done; but standing still, or joyning with the King, or if he will look on, he's secure in the advantage of the place, and may laugh at us that must labour for him; and when we have destroyed each other, how easie 'twill be for him to give Laws to both we shall quickly finde. 'Tis my counsel to dissemble still; 'tis true, one blow with this Dagger does it; but what good can you derive from that mischief? when the Battel's over; if you can strike him securely it may signifie something, but till then let us
<pb n="504" facs="253"/>
bear him fairly: 'tis late, and the King's men are advanc'd alrea|dy, and we must not let them take such courage as 'twill give them to finde us unwilling to fight.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, <hi>Clytus,</hi> every one to his charge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clytus.</speaker>
                        <p>I fear no Enemies; if my Friends be true, I'll look to my Enemy my self; and I'll have a care of false Friends too; <hi>Rode|rigo,</hi> I shall, and yet I'll fight well to day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Clytus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>See, Sir, my fears are true, upon my life he's jealous; something and quickly must be thought upon, and wisely too, ei|ther to confirm him, or remove him hence; but Fortune, if that Trumpet sounds what I believe, it will perhaps take the work in|to her own hands, and we may see the Traitor fall in his own snare—Hark, Sir, 'tis a Charge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[The Trumpet sounds.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                        <p>Away then, Give the Word round, Command all to march.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leopoldo, Palantus, <hi>and</hi> Arcus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>FArewell <hi>Palantus:</hi> this day is set to decide our hopes or fears; Love be thou propitious, and I shall not fear the rest; the King has his ancient virtue still, his courage, and will command the Battel himself; my Charge lies this way, let us embrace and part, and this day strike, to be always free from such a danger as this false pretence which now hath arm'd these Traitors.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray Sir, let <hi>Arcus</hi> attend the Princess in her journey to <hi>Capua, Philemon</hi> is old; and though his courage be great 'tis but ill guarded; if I might attend that service he should not have that envied Office.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Aside.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Nor wouldst thou grant it me, if thou knew'st my minde,—I shall not fail to wait upon her Highness; but I believe till <stage>Asids.</stage> those Troops of <hi>Clytus</hi> be forc'd from yonder Hill, it will not be safe for us to pass, for we are still subject to his parties; and we must expect he will not let us pass free unspoke with; and if once we be taken 'tis a great blow to your Highness affairs, as appears by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Propositions of Mariage; for though he promise to give a King, his business is to get a Queen, and by that Interest of Bloud ally his success unto the Crown; which Curse Heaven with thy Fires forbid, or give <hi>Arcus</hi> leave with his Dagger to re|move.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Hark, they receive the Charge; Away, our Place and In|terest is first this day, and Honour tells us it ought to be so in dan|ger too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <pb n="505" facs="253"/>
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Almanzor, <hi>and</hi> Roderigo, <hi>both wounded, and their Swords drawn.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>URge them: how <hi>Roderigo?</hi> the aged King acts won|ders above man; how the stubborn rock broke our charge; he has many wounds, and in revenge of them his men fight, such resolution I never saw among so few men.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>How I abhor that traytor <hi>Clytus,</hi> that could so barba|rously charge his King!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>He is a villain, but his hand's useful in this work; haste to him and second him in his charge; I'll once more prove the Princes temper; he has a name in Arms, and I long to grapple with him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the old King wounded, leaning upon</hi> Palantus, <hi>with their Swords drawn.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>NO, no more, <hi>Palantus,</hi> 'tis enough, Fate has run his cir|cle; here my greatness begun, and here it ends; in a Bat|tle, I set out King, and in a Battle end; the sword gave me my honour, and to the sword I have again surrendred it: and I pri|thee tell my Son, if he survive the day, and fortune smile, which yet I despair not, (for his virtue must meet greater dangers then these) command him to search out the truth of the Spaniards de|clarations; and if he can find my Nephew, let him restore the Crown; it had been my voluntary act, had not that traytor <hi>Clytus</hi> crush'd all our intentions; the rest were beaten, I saw them stag|ger; their Officers and Prince retreated, till <hi>Clytus</hi> false and stout with wicked troops of our own Countrymen charged us, fools and wicked that could not in such an act believe how great a sin their valour was.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, Sir, do not take such hasty leave from your poor and miserable friends; what shall we do when you are gone?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <p>Thy faith, <hi>Palantus,</hi> will redeem to story the long lost gratitude of Favorites; and 'tis one joy to me I never was decei|ved where I trusted; I find a blindness that foretels the way I am to go: farewell, be happy for thy kindness to thy old Master, who without trouble dyes, embraced by the arms of him whom he loved; thy faith was always welcome, but in death most pretious; and I prithee fail not to give my blessing to my dear <hi>Bellamira,</hi> whose dream is made good in this my fall; and to let thee see all thy care did not hide from my eyes thy modest passion for <hi>Bellami|ra,</hi> here from my dying hands take this Legacy; I have worn it as a relick many a day, love it as well as I did, and death can only part ye; could I have loved her less, or consented to see her acting of a
<pb n="506" facs="254"/>
deed I could not justifie, long since thou hadst had my consent to have been happy; but she was ever my dear <hi>Bellamira;</hi> and I know <hi>Palantus</hi> though he loved, yet his mind had honour too, and would not see her go less to satisfie his passion. But it grows late, and I find my blood waste apace.—Hark, we are pursu'd; save thy self, leave me, faithful <hi>Palantus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[A noise of follow, follow.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, Sir! do not bid me believe you love me, and com|mand me this, at least not wish I should obey you: this treasure of <stage>The King faints and lyes down.</stage> my life I keep as my soul, and but this shadow have no friend: could you refuse to drink of this fatal cup that treason and murther have prepared, at the rate of my life I'de buy your place. But see, while I talk, death is making his pale unwelcome visit in my Masters noble heart, the seat of a thousand vertues.—Oh! he <stage>The King swoons.</stage> is gone, set for ever in this cloud; this object and this loneness how dismal 'tis! none but death and I at a Kings Tragedy; but 'tis just, I had his trust alone, alone his love, his favour, without a Rival, but not without a Nations envy; here I'll stay, here the Conqueror shall find his victory had not power to make me fly to save a short loath'd life, and lose my place in story.—Ye gods, <stage>He lyes down and weeps upon the King, and embraces him.</stage> that see these wounds, arm all your vengeful hands, and strike the traytors quick into the earth that thus have brought his sacred head with violence to the grave; may their torn Carcasses never find a grave; see, see this reverend head that you have spared; the double tye of King, and old, found no reverence, nor his gray hairs protection; no friends had they here that had in hea|ven no enemies; such was his piety that treason and murther were fain to arm against him, to second time, that great enemy of man and nature, who could not alone destroy this sacred Pile, whose ruines I shall not have power to mourn, unless I can save these reliques from the malice of those traytors that pursue us; I'll take off his robe and mine own too; and if I can pass for some pri|vate Souldier I'll scape with my load.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He strips off the Kings and his own upper garments and throws them into the Wood, and covers the body with Souldiers coats, and is pursued by the enemy; he bestrides the dead body of the King, untill</hi> Almanzor <hi>and</hi> Roderigo <hi>come in and take him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Who are you? disarm, and bind him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>We must ask that of you; the day has given you power to appoint us fates.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>What is he you defended?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>One that an hour since would have fought with thee, or any man alive; 'twas my Father; may thine again never bless his <stage>Lyes down by the King.</stage> eyes with a sight of thee, whose ambition has set his in blood.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Thy faith shall plead for thee, though thy curses has struck me more then any danger I ere saw. <hi>Roderigo,</hi> behold a great example of faith and fortune; how pious that young
<pb n="507" facs="254"/>
man looks in his wounds, and how lovely in his sorrow!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>And how black we look that caus'd them! my soul ab|hors my part of this conquest, I never pitied an enemy before: in|deed we never met a gallant one till now; and had not their own swords fought against them, we had not stood here now to mourn their sufferings; how I hate that traytor <hi>Clytus!</hi> he call'd me in the Battle, and bad me witness what he did for his young King. Vil|lain, some old curse will find thee for't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, what's next to be done? the Prince stands still, and <hi>Palantus</hi>'s Troops are rallied.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas a gallant fellow their Chief; I saw him charge to second the King, when <hi>Clytus</hi> broke him, but since he was not seen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter a</hi> Souldier.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, the Officers expect you; <hi>Clytus</hi> is press'd by the Prince, and calls for horse to second him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Away with him to my Quarter, let him receive no in|jury. <stage>
                              <hi>Points to</hi> Pa|lantus.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Almanzor <hi>and</hi> Roderigo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, friend, shall we be jogging? you have a kind enemy you see.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>His humanity has won me strangely; if I live to see the Princess she shall know how handsomely he gave his character, both of the King and Prince. His general too is a brave fellow; with what scorn and hatred he mention'd that traytor <hi>Clytus,</hi> the cause of all these miseries; that villain laid this Scene of war and death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Come dispatch, dispatch.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>Witness heaven, how unwillingly I part from this dear load; and friend, if thou wilt return and give this old man a grave, and but tell me where you lay his body, poor as I am in fortune, I shall find something to reward such piety.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>When you are safe we'll talk of that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2.</speaker>
                        <p>Let's go through the wood upon the left hand, and there we shall have time to examine his Pockets.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Phillora, Pollidor, Ravack, <hi>and</hi> Satyr, <hi>all wounded.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>This way, this way, <hi>Pollidor,</hi> I see the storm bonds; all their wicked force is bent to destroy the best of men. <stage>She offers to go out.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, <hi>Phillora.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you yet retreat, and not with idle passion fondly pursue a lost man? you see the day is lost, you see the gods the ju|ster side have taken, the enemy has all in chase; and if we stay we must expect the same fate that follows their impiety; 'tis ridicu|lous, this love, that thus with madness you pursue; can you ima|gine it possible that these swords can redeem the day? you see in kindness to your grief we have given up our Reason, and our re|venge; and, for your sake, struck even against our hearts, and all that kindness begets but a wilfulness in you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="508" facs="255"/>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I find my Brother has but dissembled then, and <hi>Pollidor</hi> has no sense of the pain he never felt, nor kindness for <hi>Phillora;</hi> he could not else thus harshly rub her wounded mind: but take heed this despised power thou now contemnest, do's not in vengeance arm some unequal dart against thee; this mornings Sun found my breast as free as thine, proud too as my Brother, both of my form and liberty, and at as high a rate I prize my freedom; yet one sight of his eyes has burnt them all to ashes; and I prophesie those several virtues that now lye idle in your breast, shall but make love a triumph when those torches of thy eyes shall take fire from that star, to whose beauty fate and love have decreed thy pain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, <hi>Phillora,</hi> here's none that chides thy passion; counsel we may; we only tell thee, Love and Honour were born twins, and will endure neither separation nor competitors; you must not divide those friends, together they act great and glori|ous things; the mind that possesseth them is scarce mortal, but if you separate that cordial, you'll find too late, Love is but the poy|son; excellent in medicine when prepared and allayed with ho|nour, and but prepares the way; 'tis good, <hi>Phillora,</hi> at opening the door to let the Treacle in; so much of the venom Love is good as serves to fire the mind with great thoughts; but honour (child) must direct his feet; he will neither find else, nor know his home.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, be not thus cruel, Sir, to wound me with your reason; my sick eyes cannot see the light; have mercy upon me, and let me go.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>You must not go; 'tis kindness to be cruel: your passi|on grows to madness; and 'tis folly, not friendship, to listen to your prayers; you must not pass.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall force my way either through thine, or my own heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, pass here; make thy way through my heart, or and it made by grief, ungrateful and unkind <hi>Phillora,</hi> to see all my love and care thrown behind thee, like the despised things of the world; go, <hi>Phillora,</hi> follow thy passion, give to a stranger, of|fer to the pride of one that perhaps will not accept thy present, that love, for nothing which thou wouldst not pay unto a Bro|ther: but when thou returnest here thou shalt find me dead; for know I will not out-live thy honour: go wretched Maid, give that innocence which thou shalt never find again; that innocency for which, this day, thou stood'st the envy of thy time, and wilt hereafter fall below a common pity, cruel, blind, ungrateful and unkind <hi>Phillora.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Pollidor, Pollidor,</hi> thou hast struck me to the soul; un|grateful, and unkind! any thing but that, that was cruelly urg'd, witness my broken heart, to which thy unkind kindness has given its mortal wounds: farewel, <hi>Pollidor;</hi> be thou happy though I might not.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[She swoons and falls down: the Satyr seems much troubled.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>She is not well, she looks pale; <hi>Phillora,</hi> dear <hi>Phillora,</hi> look up; see thy Brother in tears, beg thy pardon; 'tis the heavens
<pb n="509" facs="255"/>
fights in this passion, and their wills must not be disputed; speak kindly to her and heal her mind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pollid.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, how easie 'tis for me to speak kindly, heaven knows that sees my heart; <hi>Phillora,</hi> Sister, unlucky Maid, once more pardon the harsh expressions of a Brothers grief, whose love and kindness mistook the way to express it self; all my design was to have recommended reason as a companion for thy love, for love alone is but a passion, and a blind one; Dear <hi>Phillora,</hi> much care and pains goes to make him a virtue, and then honour must be his parent, and his issue too; this is all I had to say, and this I would fain should have been reason; but thy love shall prevail hereafter; and dear <hi>Phillora</hi> cease now to be sad, and angry with thy Brother, or to believe me so barbarous as to dispute against that god of passion, but as I fear him thy enemy:—Or think me such a stranger to thy heart as to doubt <hi>Phillora</hi>'s honour; what I have said was only to prompt thy mind, which I found this day so busie obeying of thy love, I was afraid, during this civil war in thy mind, some watchful enemy passion might surprize that strength which I am confident no assault, or siege can win.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Ever lov'd, but never dearer to my heart then now! Oh, let me rest upon thy brest, and hide my blushes there! yet my soul covets no faulty thing; 'tis no whisphers, nr midnights darkness that I seek; no corner to tell my story in; no guilt hangs upon my heart, my mind and desires are as bright as the days guide, as pub|lick as <hi>Leopoldo</hi>'s name, I dare avow my love of him; shall we be|cause the gods frown add misery to those which they afflict, who, we know, suffer for others crimes? and joyn with treason to wound the man my soul admires? no Brother, he is my Prince; and let heaven speak to him in thunder, while I obey and follow him to his Grave, or throne; whiles my heart weeps over the one, but never envy him the least glory of the other.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the</hi> Satyr.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>There are armed men entred the Wood; haste, dear Mi|stress, and follow me, or we are lost. The Princes party flies in every place; the enemy pursues us close.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillora.</speaker>
                        <p>The gods protect the Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Pollidor <hi>and</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Ravack, <hi>with a Helmet full of water.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Here I left her, there's the <hi>Satyr;</hi> where's my Daughter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Now gone into the Woods.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>What makes you stay behind, what is't you gaze on?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>A man lyes a dying here in the bush, he groans and stirs still.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>A man, where?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Ravack <hi>looks upon him very earnestly.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, leave him, prithee Master, he's but ill company now, and going a worse journey; and if we stay, perhaps, we may be sent upon the same errand.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="510" facs="256"/>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Is there any life? help, hold up his head, he breathes and stirs; 'tis long since I saw this face, yet there are lines in it my me|mory <stage>He looks up|on his hand, and finds his signet.</stage> retains, 'tis he.—This confirms me, Heaven I accept this of|fer; sure some great work is design'd in this chance; I'll bear him to our Cave, but first I'll take off his Ring for fear the enemy meet us; come, help to take him up.—Little hast thou deserv'd this charity from me; but I'll not upbraid thy ashes; if I can recover him of his wounds we'l find a way to make him useful to us, at least secure him for hindring our designs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Satyr.</speaker>
                        <p>Carry him to the Cave; and if he be a friend let me alone to cure him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Palantus <hi>bound in the Wood, with two Souldiers whispering together.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palan.</speaker>
                        <p>I Do not like these villains whispering, they have made me leave the road; sure they design some mischief in this wood; should I seem to fear, that might encourage them in their villany.—How now, What whisp'ring's this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>What we have done already is more than we can an|swer; let us search his pockets, and deliver him to the guard at the foot of the Hill. <stage>They lay hold upon him and pull out his purse.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>Villaines, this violence shall cost you dear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Ha! This is no small bird, such feathers few of your kind wear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Search farther; Here's a Jewel too, and papers, those we shall not use.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>If they find my picture too I'me lost, my Soul cannot indure that separation; What would you have more, have you not taken all already?—Hell take your loathed Souls.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Oh, this is it; A picture, what have we here? Golden Houses for shadows? <stage>He resists, and they throw him down.—They search his breast and find the picture, he kicks and bites all the while.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, a picture onely, after all the rest of your Injuries, restore but that and I'll freely forgive you; take the case too, onely the picture again; if you have any humanity you will not deny it; 'tis to you of no use, but to me the dearest jew|el of my life; 'Tis of a friend, whose Memory I adore; set any rate upon it and I'll purchase it; it is your own Interest I propose.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Keep our counsel and you shall have it, upon our words we'll restore it; But if you tell any Tales, or complain to the General of this visitation of your pockets, then down goes <hi>Dagon,</hi> nothing saves your Saint; here she shall lie safe till we find you a man of your word; till then, take a civil leave of her, and let's be gone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>Without you will restore it I'll not stir one step.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Come, come; if you consent to go in all together, we'll afford you the cutting into quarters, and do it at four.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="511" facs="256"/>
                        <speaker>Palantus.</speaker>
                        <p>Villaines, you'll dearly repent this Insolence.—Pray, (and heartily) I get not my hands loose; 'twill be sad to some of you ever if I be free.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Come, fret and curse at home, till we repent.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. VI.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Leopold, <hi>and</hi> Arcus, <hi>wounded.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>OH <hi>Arcus,</hi> 'twas she, there's nothing like her; She is an original, I saw her and the poor <hi>Satyr</hi> too; la|bouring in our cause, she acts above a mortal power; My Hearts a fire till I know her Fortune; she had the scarf on I gave the <hi>Satyr;</hi> My Father and <hi>Palantus</hi> are both wounded, and both missing; Haste and try, if possible, in this general mischief, to save some remnant of our family: Find my Sister, conjure her to haste to <hi>Capua,</hi> and there ship for <hi>Rome;</hi> whither (if I can reach my ends) I'll with diligence repair.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Alass, Sir, I fear she's lost, and so will you be too if you thus pursue your passion; Consider, Sir, how many thousand lives and fortunes hang upon your precious dayes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Lost! Heaven sleeps not sure, nor will so negligently part with such a Jewel; And Nature, kind Nature, that has care even of Plants, and waits so diligently upon every Season, think'st thou, <hi>Arcus,</hi> she would mind a Bird or Tree and neglect these? No, no, she'd sooner spare the Sun, the Pride of her workmanship, then suffer such a blow; 'twould wound her deeper then her opposites of Sword, Plague, and Famine, though waited on by death; Hark, we are pursu'd; some brave Enemy that would bring a gallant Revenge, or a handsome death, would make me smile upon my Fortune; But I talk, and thou art here still, my Sister will be lost; Flie, <hi>Arcus,</hi> fly, ere it be too late to counsel her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Alass, Sir, what sullen Starr rules you? Why would you have me leave you? Why do you choose to fall alone? Do you think I am of so low a spirit, or so base as to leave my Prince in danger, and seek my own safety? Go, and I'll follow you throughout all the world; but if I leave you, Heaven curse me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>We are all lost then; for I am resolved to find this Maid ere I think of safety; I saw her enter this wood. Oh, <hi>Arcus,</hi> 'tis a strange wonder of her Sex; 'Tis a gallant Mind dwells in that private Breast, and blest is he shall find a Friendship there, yet my Love shall cut-vie his; For he that is her equal, is mercenary, and proposes to himself her for his reward, which I cannot without injuring her or <hi>Leopoldo;</hi> which ere I will do, thou shalt see me fly where my despaires will carry me, and converse with Beasts or Trees, envying the life of Plants, whil'st I despise my own.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="512" facs="257"/>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Sir, let me beg once in my dayes to be believed; and lest my fears prove fatal, by her whose fair eyes you love best I beg you'll at lest quit this habit and your order, and for a time strike sail to fortune in this storm; you'll sink a brave vessel else, and lose a noble fraught.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>How? And fall a private man? Pluck from my self my Honour? No, <hi>Arcus,</hi> thou shalt see me frown, and meet the worst of Fortunes; For I dare die, as well as live a Prince; And here, with all the <hi>Triurnio,</hi> and glorious distinctions of a Prince, thou shalt see me fall a crowned sacrifice to Love and Fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, Wisedom as well as Courage is allowed us in all our accidents of this life; and to be wilful in our miseries upbraids the gods, and looks as if we would glorifie our selves: Besides, if you desire to be capable of enjoying her own wishes in this habit, and like your self, it is impossible. <hi>Leopoldo,</hi> This day was your happiness; But <hi>Leopoldo</hi> now can promise nothing but misfortunes; your misery is the desire of all men. The busie Ambition of the Enemy hunts nothing but the greatness of the Prince; In which time a private man may escape; Besides, the the Maid will sooner listen to your words when you stand in a level with her, then when she sees such a desperate height as is be|twixt her and her Princes Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! What hast thou said? 'Tis Truth he urges, and I submit to thy Reason in hopes to find it succesfull;—Thus I consent to a disguise, which this publick Character cannot wear.— <stage>Pulls off his Order.</stage> Here, <hi>Arcus,</hi> take this envied Character from my afflicted Breast; This shewes how dangerous these distinctions of Honour are, and how vain men are that seek them.—Poor and safe; could great|ness believe that truth! how happy might we be whose sad expe|rience I now must prove? Would I could lose my self to all the world, but thee <hi>Bellamira,</hi> and this Maid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, Sir; who knows but this stooping a little to For|tune may make her kind, and take it for satisfaction for all the scornes your Virtue has thrown upon her; trusting still to Ju|stice, and aspiring to that title rather then the fortunate <hi>Leopoldo:</hi> Hark, Sir, the noise draws this way; in this woods thickness we may hide our selves, and let the danger pass.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Lead the way, but with how ill a will I yield to Fortune, the gods witness; Love, 'tis thy power more then any argument of fear or hope prevails with me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. VII.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Ravack <hi>and</hi> Phillora.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ravack.</speaker>
                        <p>'TIs sure a party of the Enemy that pursues us, but these woods are thick, and we are now near home.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas the Prince, I know his clothes; His royal slave was with him too, a mark not to be mistaken.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="513" facs="257"/>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>If the <hi>Satyr</hi> overtook him he is then retir'd to our Cave, to enjoy the welcome news of the Kings safety, which if his age de|nies not, I can promise.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>How fain I would believe the Prince safe too in this time of penurious hope! that he lived, were all I would ask: Alas, I saw him fall amongst his enemies; and since that sad hour can give my heart no news of his safety; I would fain speak with him, and tell him only how innocent and faithful a passion my heart labours with. Could he then be so barbarous as to scorn me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter from the Wood</hi> Arcus <hi>and</hi> Leopoldo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, gentle Maid; Heaven (if thy rage have a curse yet left in store) throw it upon me if I scorn thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis the Prince; and thus upon my knees I fall to him, in vertue, courage and all that's excellent, a Prince; all but these miseries are his own: Oh Sir, that you are safe is all my joy; and let not the Prince be angry to find a fond Girle hunt his greatness, who begins to fear her self his evil Angel; you were never happy since I saw you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Fair and dear; what interest in this days chance engaged your virgin hand? why dost thou not fly before our misfortunes crush thee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Sir; gods and men will fight your cause, and all that have heard of <hi>Leopoldo</hi> (but this band of wicked ones) would dye for you; and if my life could save a hair of that generous head, I'de dye as quietly as little birds in their Nests; for I shall never find a joy but in serving you; and 'tis one great blessing we have saved the King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>The King!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>By the appointment of the gods, I hope, he fell into my hands, faint and full of wounds, known by this signet upon his fin|ger; for 'tis long since my age left wandring in the splendid paths of Courts; he is now in our Cave, where he is safe and private; and I hope a blessing in his cure; and if your Highness will vouch|safe to put your royal head under that humble roof till this storm be over, we shall think our selves blest in the occasion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, no more; my life and all that ever was preci|ous I value less then this news; in spight of mischief I grow happy, since I have found a faith here; for I heard your discourse even now, the joy it gave me may your soul never wish in vain; may I not know your name?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Phillora,</hi> Sir, I am called; Daughter to this good old man; here in these woods I had my birth and abode; I have a Brother too, dear as mine eyes; he's now bleeding in your Highness cause, ambitious to be in wounds, ally'd to your miseries; heaven bless him when he fights your Battles, and curse them that fight against you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis the prettiest and the gallantest innocence that ever
<pb n="514" facs="258"/>
my eyes saw; ye gods, such another excellency but my bright Mistress sure the earth shews not; how my heart pities the dispa|rity of her birth, that forbids them to equal the gods in happiness!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Gentle <hi>Phillora,</hi> is there no hope to find your love has cha|rity for my passion, as well as value for some other object?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Find the means, Sir, to satisfie that question; let the Prince and honour search it, and if I deny, at the rate of my life, to pur|chase it, let no mercy find me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Phillora,</hi> name not those tyrants, honour and opini|on, that still persecutes mankind, and impose their severe laws up|on our hearts; what have Lovers to do with them, or they with us? we will love beyond their Rules, and suffer beyond their ex|amples, till there be nothing left for us to imitate; and then we will our selves become examples; and to love like us shall be the next ages rule; and <hi>Phillora,</hi> all ages wonder.—Yet, methinks, in midst of my despairs honour holds out a light, which though it be afar off, it guides me to something that I may hope.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Hope, Sir! why not? all that is honourable; and your vertue will overcome the rest of fate; there's nothing lays such vi|olent hands upon generous minds as to see a Lover despair of being happy: and this doubtful looking upon your wishes, whatever they be, shall make me give sooner then the greatest Argument your va|nity can propose; there is a kind of Magick in the eye of a lan|guishing despair, that good nature cannot see without pity, and yields sooner to it then presumptuous confidence, or force.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet force has been successful, and many have out-liv'd it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>None, where there was honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you then deny the fame of those maids that lust and force have injur'd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>If they out-live it unmindful of a just revenge, I shall.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Would you be so cruel to kill the man should thus speak his passion, when this Idol, honour, you adore, has stop'd all other possible ways to his desire?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! 'twas not well urg'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Aside.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>If this be serious, I have yet a power to save her honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you doubt it, Sir? would I live fam'd here, or dye to <stage>Aside.</stage> become a star in heaven? so sure I would kill all that's mortal, if this spear could reach him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, 'tis not for fear of the gods then that you are ho|nest? for, sure, murther is worse then rape, and in this you declare there is something you prefer to them. Suppose I should now by the advantage I could find abuse this opportunity, would you kill me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>The gods forbid; no, Sir, when I find the Prince start back from virtue, and so far quit his own Rules of goodness, that have gain'd him the sirname of Just, and for my sake become a Ravisher, I shall quickly let him see how I hate such a tempter; for when I find my innocence too weak to defend my honour I shall at least find honour enough to defend my innocence; and I will al|ways dye worthy your love, Sir, when you shall refuse to let me live
<pb n="515" facs="258"/>
so; nor is death faulty then, but like a friend to vertue, finding op|prest arms in her defence; and strikes, not to destroy <hi>Phillora,</hi> but to rescue her honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Upon my soul thou wouldst, thou excellent and single in thy goodness; come neer old man, and record my vows, that if thy Daughter be but gently born, here I'l fix my heart; either hers or never womans, so heaven and earth assist me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh hold, Sir, call back that vow; be still my Prince, while I follow and admire you as far as fame finds faith, or passage; but to be yours will make me blush for ever, and the guilt will al|ways deject me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>By my love, by beauty, innocency, and all that's fair, by truth it self, or <hi>Phillora</hi> (which is all these) I swear, thy honour and my vow I'll most religiously preserve; and if my life be blest by thy embraces, thou shalt command more in that day then I would beg now; do not doubt my faith nor your power, which nothing but your fears can lessen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>The gods say, Amen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Rather all the gods forbid such Hymens should attend your blessed day; let me first sink forgotten into my little grave, ere I become the subject of such a curse.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Is this <hi>Phillora</hi>'s friendship?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Do I refuse this for want of love? no, Sir, when that comes in question my life is ready to clear the doubt; I know I have nor birth, nor parts to pretend a fellowship to Crowns; the sin and guilt of such an act would sink me lower then your passion has done you; let me be still your subject with my innocence; let your Reason love me as well as your passion, lest I lose your love and your value both; for in unequal Hymens beauty will find but a short reign. For Princes grow asham'd of their faults; and the gods protect me from such misery as your depos'd love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>Will <hi>Phillora</hi> thus cruelly punish my love? thus, for fear of a possible ill, to make me certainly miserable?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir; my love in all its kindness speaks to you; and when you forget your self you ought to be punish'd for that act more then for your crimes to others. I am sure I shall be severer far when you offend so then when you injure me; for witness hea|ven, <hi>Leopoldo</hi> is still most precious in my eyes. Oh, Sir; rather haste to repair the ruines of this day; you were never overcome, till now, and sink faster amongst your friends then in the Battle; and I that would dye to serve you, in this command you would make me the destroyer of my Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis resolv'd, I will be thine, or else a single life fate shall not deny me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Ye gods, what do I hear and see? my glad heart is big with joy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Arcus.</speaker>
                        <p>I hear a noise of weapons.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[A noise in the Wood.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, we have talk'd away our safety; I fear new dan|gers, or separation, worse then death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rav.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet if we can regain the wood, I'll guide you to my Cave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="516" facs="259"/>
                        <speaker>Leopoldo.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Phillora,</hi> 'tis in vain, they are upon us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter three or four Souldiers, and set upon them, and, after the Souldiers the Spanish Prince: the Spanish party drives the rest off the Stage.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Yield thee, wretch, or this bold attempt shall cost <stage>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Enter</hi> Al|manzor.</p>
                              <p>Leopoldo <hi>looks about.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>They fight,</hi> Almanzor <hi>is wounded.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Leopoldo <hi>wounds him, and in the close disarms and throws him.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </stage> thee dear; thy safety is in yielding.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis he, and we are alone; heaven, thou art kind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>The villain has wounded me again; such a courage in a wretch, and of a beaten party, I never found.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>There, take your length on that earth your ambition thought to enslave; see how one handful of it has check'd that in all thy glory; my heart has not malice nor baseness enough to strike thee upon thee ground, nor leisure to consider thy fate, until I have found my dear <hi>Phillora;</hi> sure these woods have paid his debt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Leopoldo.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Roderigo, <hi>and</hi> Souldiers.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>These woods are so thick, and the Rogues fly like deer in them; 'tis in vain to pursue 'em, where left you the Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I saw him not, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Nor I.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Nor you? ye dogs, where did you leave him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>We saw him not, Sir, since we left the party.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Roderigo,</hi> here, thy hand, prithee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! wounded, and upon the ground!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>My hurts are sleight, by chance of war only; and it was a gallant fellow, who ere he be, that gave them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
                        <p>Beat all the woods and plains, he cannot escape; what was he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>Seek him, but upon your lives wrong him not; 'tis but a private person; but I dare say, a bolder soul tri'd not his fate this day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Souldiers, <hi>bringing the Prince</hi> Leopoldo <hi>bound.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>This is he, Sir; we knew him by your Highness sword.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alman.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, use him kindly, and carry him to my quarters. If thy Prince had fought thus well this day he had not been mis|sing now in Battle.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leop.</speaker>
                        <p>My Prince fought better then the proudest of you; my Prince stood the last danger of the field, and scorns to fly; he's either dead, or worse, in chains; nor can you boast your victory, which you ow to our own swords; 'twas <hi>Clytus,</hi> not <hi>Almanzor,</hi> beat <hi>Leopoldo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Away with him to the Quarters.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>We'll through the woods again, and try what ballast he bears in his breeches.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Roder.</speaker>
                        <p>Make haste, and meet us at the hill by the wood side.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>Partis primae Finis.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         </TEI>

