<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
            <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>325 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 November (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12417588</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing K450.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">61734</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Thomas Killigrew ...</title>
                  <title type="alt">Works. 1664</title>
                  <author>Killigrew, Thomas, 1612-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 8 [i.e. 5]-576, 80 p. : port.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Each play has special t.p. and is dated 1663.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="80"/>
The Pilgrim. A TRAGEDY, The Scene <hi>MILLAIN.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Written in <hi>PARIS,</hi> BY <hi>THOMAS KILLIGREW.</hi> 1651.</p>
                  <p>DEDICATED TO THE COUNTESSE OF <hi>CARNARVAN.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the sign of the <hi>Blew Anchor,</hi> in the lower Walk of the <hi>New-Exchange.</hi> 1663.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="81"/>
                     <head>The Names of the Actors.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alphonso,</hi> Duke of <hi>Millain.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sforza,</hi> His Son in Love with <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Julia,</hi> Widow to the deceased Duke of <hi>Pavia,</hi> now Dutchess of <hi>Millain.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Victoria,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Alphonso,</hi> in Love with <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cosmo,</hi> Son to <hi>Julia,</hi> in Love with <hi>Victoria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fidelia, Julia</hi>'s Daughter, in Love with <hi>Sforza.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Matthias,</hi> The deceased Duke of <hi>Pavia</hi> only mentioned.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Martino,</hi> A Lord of <hi>Pavia,</hi> Favorite to the deceas'd Duke and Dutchess, and now Favorite of <hi>Alphonso.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carlo,</hi> Governour of the Castle of <hi>Millain,</hi> a Creature of <hi>Julia</hi>'s, and Secretary.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Baptista,</hi> A Lord of <hi>Pavia,</hi> banished both States, in Love with <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Antonio,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Friends to <hi>Cosmo</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="4" cols="1">All four Honest Men.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Giovanni,</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Richardo,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Friends to <hi>Sforza</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Ferdinando,</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Phillipine,</hi> Page to <hi>Victoria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pietro, Nicolett,</hi> Banditoes.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Hermit.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Trivallin,</hi> A Ferry-man over the <hi>Poe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bertolin,</hi> His Man.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Argentin,</hi> His Wife.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Moretta,</hi> His Maid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Attendants,</hi> Such as the Scene requires.</item>
                     <item>
                        <table>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Angelica,</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Servants to the Princess.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row role="data">
                              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                                 <hi>Maria,</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <pb n="157" facs="81"/>
                  <head>The Pilgrim.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Giovanni, Ferdinando, <hi>and two Officers of the Army.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giovanni.</speaker>
                        <p>WEre I worthy to counsell the Duke, he should know this removing of Gene|rals breeds ill blood, and disaffects the Souldiers; whose kindness at this time is of more importance then his security will give faith to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>That <hi>Cosmo</hi> was made General, though it seemed strange at first; yet those that know <hi>Julia</hi>'s power with the old Duke, he be|ing her Son, wonder not at it. But how he comes now to be dis|graced, and yet she and <hi>Martino</hi> hold their Interest in Court, makes me suspect some foul play, some further, designes then their Craft will let us discover.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>He has won strangely upon the Souldiers by his Courage and Affability; for those that are his Enemies will yet allow Prince <hi>Cosmo</hi> a gallant and stout Souldier, else he would have found the hatred they bear his Mother would have clouded all his parts; his first Reception was so cold, we thought he looked dejected, as if he were asham'd to own his Mother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee talk no more of her; she is an evil the Nation ought to arm against; The sword (and that speedily bent against her) can onely prevent the ruine she and <hi>Martino</hi> threaten this State with. Prayers find too slow Remedies for such mischiefs as their power daily contrives.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven had many Crimes to punish in <hi>Millain,</hi> when she and <hi>Martino</hi> were sent our scourges; Her own Subjects despis'd and scorn'd her, and deriding her victory, say, we fought for their diseases onely.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>I wonder how Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> brooks this Familiarity of hers with <hi>Martino;</hi> for 'tis said, he passionately affects the Princess <hi>Fidelia,</hi> a Virgin of unquestion'd Virtue, and yet her Daughter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>She has indeed an unspotted Fame; and when I consider it, Iam amazed to think Nature should send such Sovereign Fruit from so poysonous a Root; yet they say Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> but ill di|gested
<pb n="158" facs="82"/>
his Fathers Marriage with the Mother, for all his Passion for the Daughter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>Can you blame him? Is it not a hard Condition to find his Enemy and his Captive become his Mother? Supplanting him in all the power and trust of his Father? yet his Piety makes him obedient, even to her weakness; and civil, even to his Fathers faults.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>O 'tis a matchless Gallantry inhabits in him; his Princely breast is all compos'd of Honour; whether Enemy or Friend, he conquers still; so faithfull in his Promise, mild in Command, and gentle in Dispute, Constant and Resolute in dangers, never absent to himself, never transported when he overcomes, nor losing himself in disorder, nor amazed when he is worsted; I have seen him win and lose a battle, but with that evenness of Soul, as fair Game|sters use to meet their fortunes with.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>Yet I heard him say, he thought it had been better for <hi>Millain</hi> to have lost the battle, then wonne <hi>Pavia;</hi> since his Fathers weakness had so far betray'd him as to marry <hi>Julia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>See if we were not fallen into the discourse of her again, that Curse; and our miseries are so large a Theam we cannot shun it, though we warn each other.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>To divert you from that discourse, pray let me know your intention; are you for <hi>Millain,</hi> with the Generall, or will you stay here? I mean to wait upon him, and, by that Title, till I see some worthier then himself receive his Command, which they will scarce find in <hi>Millain.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee, <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> think better of me, then to believe I will serve under any Man that Clouds Prince <hi>Cosmo;</hi> let us go find him at his Lodging.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>He is gone abroad, I saw him and <hi>Antonio</hi> upon the workes; This way we shall meet them, see where they come.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo, Antonio, <hi>and</hi> Carlo; Cosmo <hi>has a Letter open in his hand, which he reads with a troubled look.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>They need not be so hasty in repeating their Injuries from <hi>Millain; Cosmo</hi> has not so ill a Memory to forget the first, that they need not prompt him with a second;<hi>—These are to Command you to quit the Army, and to attend us at</hi> Millain, <hi>to know our further</hi>
                           <stage>He reades.</stage>
                           <hi>pleasure. Alphonso</hi> the Duke may command, and 'tis just that I obey; And 'tis as great a truth, his Command ought to be just. What if I will not quit the Army? 'tis not this paper can force me, <hi>Carlo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>Force! who dares think they can force hence the <hi>Lom|bard</hi> General, or, atleast, publish that thought? Death! do not go, Sir; say to us, you are wrong'd, and you will have justice ere you stir; we will send a Messenger shall make <hi>Millain</hi> know she has her power from hence.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>I thank you for your hearty affection; but I must not let you be faulty to serve me; my Lord, you may return, and say, I
<pb n="159" facs="82"/>
shall obey; My innocence dares go and meet the author of this in|jury, and then play <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s part.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carl.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I am sorry 'twas my misfortune to bring this unwel|come news; and 'twas one part of their design that wrought this mischief, to have me employed; that it might wither my hopes in your Highness favour; but this Letter, Sir, I hope, will acquit me; 'tis from your Princely Mother. <stage>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>He delivers him a Letter, which he opens.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Cosmo <hi>tears his Mothers Letter.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Giovanni,</hi> that is one of <hi>Julia</hi>'s familiars; would thou or I had the opening of his heart; what a nest of Villains we should discover!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Womens counsels are like their actions; let her practise her patience still; though she can digest affronts and scorns, they shall find <hi>Cosmo</hi> will not; I must be patient and suffer an affront, because Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> is to succeed in my Command.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>So it was reported, Sir; but 'twas the wonder of all, why he of late should so labour your remove; nor could we learn who were the means he wrought by, till the Dutchess suspecting your Si|ster <hi>Fidelia</hi> intercepted some of her Letters, by which she found the Prince and your Sister hold intelligence; and 'twas her com|mand, and Count <hi>Martino</hi> counsell'd, that your Highness should not build too much upon the seeming friendship of the Prince; who but ill brooks the love and trust your Highness has in <hi>Millain;</hi> and those that will strike at your honour thus, she says, would strike at Prince <hi>Cosmo,</hi> if they durst attempt him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>Did not I tell you, that is a Villain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>I find him, and her practice too, fond Girle.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! 'tis Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> then that succeeds our General.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>What if it be Prince <hi>Sforza?</hi> what is that to me; who has heard me question his merits? or wish one glory from his grow|ing greatness? why then should he look with envious eyes on mine? are honours so scarce in the Court of <hi>Millain,</hi> that they must rob a stranger, ere they can pay their Debts to their Prince? let them build him Trophees of their Love, till his envied fame grows great as his mind; I shall not repine at it, so I be not injur'd; who ever heard <hi>Cosmo</hi> repeat the ruine he suffer'd in the war be|twixt <hi>Millain</hi> and <hi>Pavia,</hi> because I was then their enemy? and though I lost my Country, I kept my honour. But when they will call me friend, and injure me; smile in my face, and stab me; wish health to <hi>Cosmo,</hi> and put poyson in his cup; the world must par|don me, if then my passion grows untame; when I see they aim to make me the basis to build anothers greatness on; which ere I will suffer, I'll raise a storm shall shake the proudest in their proudest thoughts. <hi>Antonio,</hi> follow me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Cosmo <hi>and</hi> Antonio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>This I look'd not for; I must find him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>This mischief I foresaw; 'tis easie to read <hi>Julia</hi>'s craft; the malice of a bloody and an ambitious woman is clearly to be disco|vered. Oh, <hi>Giovanni,</hi> the ruine that threatens this State must have sudden, honest, and bold remedies; and we must wear our swords ready for all occasions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis apparent her design is to break the friendship between the
<pb n="160" facs="83"/>
two Princes; and I am confident, <hi>Sforza</hi> has no hand in this inju|ry done to our General; therefore let us haste to <hi>Pavia,</hi> and ac|quaint Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> with what has past, whither I believe <hi>Cosmo</hi> is gone; his nature is too fiery to sleep upon such a conceived injury.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>Agreed: But let us pass by <hi>Millain,</hi> and observe what face the Court wears towards the Souldiers; that will instruct us how to proceed; for my fears apprehend some sudden mischief.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. I. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Martino <hi>and a Servant.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>The Duke speechless, no sign of life, but warmth?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                        <p>The Physitian bad me tell you, that he apprehends this relapse will be mortal.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[aside.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>If he should die, 'twould cross all our designs; <hi>Carlo</hi> is ab|sent too: this chance distracts me; saw you the Dutchess?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir, but one was dispatch'd to call her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Serv.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Haste to the Physitian, and the Guards; command them strictly to admit no visits, till I come.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Julia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Martino,</hi> we are lost, for ever lost, if suddenly we attempt not some brave rescue; and the plot we have so gloried in (our breaking the friendship betwixt my Son and <hi>Sforza)</hi> as 'twas then the way to compass our ends, if the Duke dies, it will be our utter ruine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>What says your Messenger, how did he leave him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>The Impostume brake, and he was almost strangled ere they found it; and he left him speechless, and void of reason; and he must find sudden ease, or death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>But why this distraction, Madam? think you I have not thought of all the remedies that either our power or craft can propose? thinks your Highness that <hi>Martino</hi> is so dull, as to sleep in this storm where you and <hi>Cosmo</hi> are threatn'd? No, Madam, I am too proud and kind to quit the Helm, which thus long your fa|vour hath put in my hands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>What then do's thy soul prompt thee to? is there a hope left we may gain <hi>Sforza</hi> to our party?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no; that thought is vain and desperate; <hi>Sforza</hi> is not to be wrought upon; were he a coward I would fright him from the Throne; or were he a fool, I would flatter him till his heart were tame, and then rock him asleep, and insensibly rob him of a Crown. But these charms have no power upon him, his sullen nature's proof against them and lust: yet if <hi>Fidelia</hi> would joyn, that bait might engage his soul,; for I know he loves her; and if she would be wise enough to listen to her own good, I would not doubt our success. Did you move it to her?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, yes; But hell upon her, she's too cold, she was chang|ed, sure, in the Cradle; No child of mine could be so unseasona|bly
<pb n="161" facs="83"/>
vertuous; when I urged it to her with all the kindness and in|terest of a Mother; Shewed her that all her past glories, present honours and safety depended upon her consent; she urged consci|ence and the Gods, and a thousand strange examples of their judge|ments upon such actions. In short, I fear she is honest; and there|fore neither to be trusted, nor tempted longer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Hell take her and her froward conscience; let her live and dye a fool, and slave to <hi>Sforza,</hi> since she prefers a Maiden|head before a Crown. Secret is honesty enough for any woman; and since there is no other remedy, they both must dye; I have or|dered to admit no visits; and if he dye, we must conceal it till <hi>Sforza</hi> be dead, which is the only counsel our extremity admits. <stage>She leans upon him.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>That was spoke like a friend to <hi>Julia;</hi> now I find my youth did not erre in her choice; nor do I grudge that bounty or love that purchas'd <hi>Martino</hi>'s friendship,<hi>—Sforza</hi> must dye, was it not so thou said'st?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Madam, he must dye, 'tis the only remedy; if he get the Crown, we are short lived.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sforza</hi> get the Crown? has <hi>Jul.</hi> quitted all her peace, all her honour, and her God, to make her <hi>Cosmo</hi> great; and after that, shall she see him stoop to <hi>Sforza;</hi> I had rather those limbs were torn by a Hang-man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Put off your fears, and calm this passion; 'tis resolv'd, <hi>Sforza</hi> shall dye, and your Highness laugh at his Tragedy, whose thoughts are big with hopes of our misery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>These words have given life to my dying hopes; and could I hear thee say <hi>Sforza</hi> was dead, <hi>Julia</hi> were then Mistriss of all her wishes; and till I do hear that musick in thy voice, the fear that he should live master of <hi>Cosmo</hi> and thee, makes my joy faint; for know, I have set up my rest; and we will stand the greatest, or fall the wicked'st in <hi>Millain.</hi> O <hi>Martino,</hi> canst thou call to thy mind that sad day, when I kneel'd a petitioner at great <hi>Matthia</hi>'s feet (thy dead Lord and mine) the private estate I then mourn'd, ga|ther'd from his first looks ambitious hopes, which with such art I managed, that ere I had my story told with tears and youth, so cunningly I pleaded, that he left to be <hi>Caesar,</hi> and rather obeyed, then granted what I sought; but Love was my aid then, Love mo|ved in these eyes; and so powerful were those tears, his heart was struck with the sad object; but these eyes had fire in them then, <hi>Martino,</hi> Fire, such as that misery could not cloud, such as those tears could not quench; But to his bed they lighted <hi>Julia, Pavia</hi>'s Duke I ruled, and upon a cruell Brother took a deep Revenge; High was the Fame of <hi>Julia</hi>'s Beauty then, when all bowed to <hi>Julia,</hi> and observ'd her rising, as if the day had broke from these Eyes to whose power all stoop'd; Yet then, <hi>Martino,</hi> my <hi>Martino,</hi> in midst of all these glories commanded <hi>Julia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Why do you repeat this, Madam? Do you believe your Servant wants spurs? Are not our Interests equal? Is there any thing can attempt me to be ungrateful?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Martino,</hi> not that I fear thy gratitude, but to call to
<pb n="162" facs="84"/>
thy Memory thy dead friends; That I was handsome is but a weak Argument; and if thou shouldst prove forgetful, <hi>Julia</hi> would not frown upon thee, because she knowes 'tis vain and idle; frownes <stage>She poynts to her face.</stage> and anger from decayed Beauty beget no terrour in Men; 'tis like <hi>Caesar</hi> in his Marble, which to none terrour beares.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Take heed how you encourage me to be false; Men, when they fear no punishment, are seldome faithful for Honours sake; and if I should be false, what would you do? <stage>He embraces her.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Mourn, and conjure thee to thy faith again, by all those past pleasures, by all those joyes which I have brought thee, by our stolne sweetes, and those envy'd embraces which we so often have expired in, and beg of thee not to add to the miseries of time; <stage>They embrace</stage> Then would I shew thee that Heaven thou hast so often sworn by; These stars too, which furnish'd thee with new matter for thy vowes; And at last, sighing, name <hi>Julia,</hi> as thou wast wont to do; when thou would'st swear by what in Heaven and Earth thou lovd'st and feard'st most, <hi>Julia</hi> would then fall from thy Tongue, and tears from thy Eyes; And, if in those dayes my kindness obliged a gallant man, thou wouldst again return to thy friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, Fate and <hi>Martino</hi> shall change together; I am still your Highnesses; command me and prove my faith, though it be to fix this Ponyard in <hi>Sforza's</hi> heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, <hi>Martino,</hi> I will bear a part in all; I require no single danger from you, but onely to joyn with me: For thou art one my thoughts labour to preserve rather then to hazard; and when we can gain our ends safely, then I again conjure you to joyn with me to make our <hi>Cosmo</hi> great; for to me he is dearer then all that the Earth shews, or the Sea hides; Because he is the fruit <hi>of our Love;</hi> 'tis for my dear <hi>Cosmo,</hi> thy <hi>Cosmo,</hi> 'tis for him I plead; And by thy part of that pleasing sin, by that beloved fault which <hi>Cosmo</hi> is; By that dear crime, which I cannot, nay will not repent, because 'twas thine, let us resolve to pursue our design: That we may leave our <hi>Cosmo</hi> great as our Loves, lest envious lookers on, in these dayes, should scorn our past greatness, and laughing say, <hi>Julia</hi> and <hi>Marti|no</hi>'s glory was as mortal as her beauty, which is the common Fate of Women.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, <hi>Julia,</hi> By this—and this, my <hi>Julia</hi> is to me still all Pleasure, all Beauty, all sweetness; O thou excellently <stage>They kiss.</stage> faithfull to a broken Faith, and diligent maintainer of thine own Laws.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Love and Ambition know no Laws; a Mistress and a Crown have no certain way; Election, Birth, Sword, all are good. Nothing was ever call'd Treason, when the Traytors stood; Laws are fit to bind the people, Princes are above them, and the wisest make them their servants; The sacrifice was the peoples expiation, and so sacred, they might not touch what they offered, yet what they offered was to the Priest but food.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou hast fired my Soul, and I long to see <hi>Sforza</hi> Earth. <hi>Baptista</hi> shall suddenly put in execution the plot we resolved on; he'll this Evening be at my Lodging, and all things agree to make
<pb n="163" facs="84"/>
it hit; For <hi>Sforza</hi> is this day to set out from <hi>Pavia,</hi> which will give an occasion fit for our design; our doubt was, where to at|tempt him; 'twas my opinion in the wood, when he is past the Ri|ver; But <hi>Count Baptista</hi> believes 'twill be safer, when he passes the Ferry; I have whetted him on with repeating of his Injuries; and <hi>Carlo</hi> hath so confirmed him, that his banishment was procured by <hi>Sforza</hi> (who is now his Rival in <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s Love) that he is ready for any mischief, so she may be his reward, which we assured him, with a Restitution to all his Possessions when <hi>Cosmo</hi> reigned, which must be performed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, if there be no way to remove him when the work is done; for he is of too bold a Nature to be trusted with such a secret.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>That is a danger not ill foreseen; for such men, if not re|warded as they desire, still cry, They gave the Crown, and think they are never paid till they have the gift again.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure I am greater then I was; this Faith in my Friend has renewed my years; if not in me, yet it has in thee, faithfull, kind <hi>Martino,</hi> who now appear'st lovely, as <hi>Bacchus</hi> in his Wine; when the well-natur'd God look'd kindly on the faults of the false <hi>Theseus;</hi> and I could wish all the forsaken Beauty of <hi>Ariadne,</hi> to add to what time has wither'd here, and thou that Gods desire, blown by his own fire, that <hi>Julia</hi> might meet thee again, and again overflow thy heart with Joy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>What news begets this haste? where's <hi>Cosmo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>He left the Camp enraged at the Letters, and threatens a Revenge against <hi>Sforza;</hi> and if not prevented, I fear, in his own Person he will attempt it; there is no body but <hi>Antonio</hi> with him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Watch his coming to Court, and give me notice, that I may lay my command upon him, not to venture himself in such a danger.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>That thought is vain; Pray take no notice of his intenti|on, nor seem to intend his prevention, lest he suspect it and steal privately away; Leave the care to me, I will have the guard rea|dy; and as soon as he enters the Court, we will seize him in the Dukes name, and make him a Prisoner at my Chamber, till <hi>Sforza</hi> be gone his long Journey.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>You must lose no time in that design neither; for 'tis certain, <hi>Sforza</hi> sets out this day; have you resolved where we shall set upon him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Either in the Wood, or as he passes the <hi>Poe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>You know, 'twas the <hi>Count Baptista</hi>'s opinion, the River was best; for the Act once done, 'twas but sinking the Boat, and the waters being high, they may have time to escape to <hi>Pavia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee call him, he is now at my Chamber, and we will resolve.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir, Pray let him not be seen in this publick place; his disguise is not proper for you to hold discourse with, it may beget
<pb n="164" facs="85"/>
suspition; within he shall attend you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>I will to the Duke, to keep all visits from him but death, who could never have come unwelcome till now; had he waited on <hi>Sforza</hi> first, we might then have lighted at his Funeral my <hi>Martino</hi>'s Hymeneal Torch.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Spoke like my great Mistress; and 'tis my glory that I serve such a Soul: But lose no time; let <hi>Baptista</hi> be instructed, that is the hinge on which all this glorious work must move, and Crown Prince <hi>Cosmo;</hi> which will make Divine-formed <hi>Julia</hi> great in Story.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Away <hi>Carlo,</hi> call <hi>Baptista</hi> to the Dutchess Cabinet, where we will expect you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Baptista <hi>alone, habited like a Beggar.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>HAteful Habit! loathed form! scorn'd fortune! wretched <hi>Baptista,</hi> disgraced, banished, and despised by her I Love! O Heaven! Is there no way to conquest but through the miseries of the Innocent? My crime to this State was my faith to my dead prince and kinsman; which too well <hi>Martino</hi> and false <hi>Julia</hi> know; if they had any gratitude for his memory, they might long since have dispersed this cloud, having absolute power in <hi>Millain;</hi> But they are false as Cowards bred in blood and Lust together; Yet now their dangers begin to approach they fawn upon <hi>Baptista;</hi> and to gain their ends, promise more then Passengers in storms, or a prodigal to his Whore, when Beauty and high rough Seas plead in their Lusts and fears. And now I will dissemble too; and be as blind as the Scene requires; neither see nor hear ought but what they shew or tell; Not that I will believe thee <hi>Martino;</hi> but I have my ends too in <hi>Sforza</hi>'s death; 'Twas that proud Boy eclipsed all my glories, and left me thus a naked shrub; 'twas he that like untimely frosts kil'd all my forward hopes in dear <hi>Fide|lia;</hi> for whose sake, Fate spins no thread so fine but I dare cut it; and for her sake he shall die.—See where she comes; This is all the joy I have, this sight makes me endure my misery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Fidelia <hi>and her</hi> Maid.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>This disgrace of <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s amazes me; Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> too, is called home; and the Duke fallen into a relapse; When I con|sider these accidents, I am able to give my self so little satisfaction, that I cannot but fear there is some foul play intended; for I know <hi>Martino</hi> cannot but apprehend the Prince in both, Oh! this thought has fears which Heaven protect the Prince from.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>All blessings of mind and Fortune fall upon the Excellent <hi>Fidelia,</hi> till the abundance equal that Excess of beauty that strikes the world, for being so charitable to her daily Beads-man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="165" facs="85"/>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>I am not uncharitable—yet my heart affects not that fellow; Heaven pardon me, if I judge amiss; But me-thinks he de|serves his Curse; nor did I ever yet give him a willing Alms; Yet <hi>Maria,</hi> give him something. What said he? <stage>She speaks aside.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Baptista.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mariae.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Victoria.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>O sister, send off thy <hi>Maid,</hi> till I relate my fears; <hi>Martino</hi> is a Villain, a bloody and a subtle Traytor; and if not ptevented, will ruine all that is vertuous in this Court.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh my divining soul! whence spring thy fears, Gentle <hi>Victoria?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Passing through the Privy Gallery to my Fathers Cham|ber, which you know joyns upon your Mothers Cabinet, I heard some laugh, which made me curious to listen; where I heard such light airy things as suit not with these times, nor our distracted for|tunes; and one (I will not name) with wicked mirth made men|tion of those dangers that now besiege my fathers life; At which my anger made me look, to see who they were; more amazed at the sight, then at the sound of those words: For the old beggar (we use to give our Alms to) was with them; He stood upright, no age nor wrinkles in his Face, nor silver hair on head or beard; he whisper'd something to the Dutchess, at which she laugh'd; and I could hear the Villain say, by to morrow Sun-set she should see no air of <hi>Sforza;</hi> and to his horrid wish bloody <hi>Martino</hi> said, Amen. But that which most cuts my soul, was, to find the Dutchess of this Councel.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh! Madam: That Villain I have long trembled at, fearing his counsel would at last tend to some horrid mischief; she is my mother, I shall therefore neither Judge nor revile her; though my heart weeps for her; let heaven speak to her, and tell her what Duty she owes to them, and give me piety enough to pay mine to her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She weeps.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear sister, do not weep; I came not to afflict you, but to Counsel, with you, how I might save the Innocent.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Madam! to what misery was I reserved? when your noble Brother saved us, and gave his Charity to those that arm'd a|gainst him; would I had died with my Father, with that peace and Innocence I then enjoyed; I shall live now till none will pity me; None will mourn when I die, nor shed a tear for poor <hi>Fidelia;</hi> In that day <hi>Millain</hi> will burn fires of joy; no Funeral-torch shall light the sad mourners from my Obsequies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Your griefs are now unseasonable, pray defer them, and consider what is to be done to save my brother from their Malice; Your commands are more powerful far then mine, I will not doubt a sisters Interest; Let us write our fears, and assure him that there is a Plot laid for his life, and acquaint him with the relapse, and suddain danger that my father is fallen into; he will then know how necessary his presence must be here; but counsel him to come pri|vately in some disguise, and we will expect him at your Chamber; while you write this, I will call <hi>Phillipine,</hi> to whose care we will give it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="166" facs="86"/>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall; and 'tis one joy, I am not so lost in your Opinion but that your highness dares trust me with your fears, though my Mother be part of them; If I keep that value with the Prince too, I shall not be so miserable as my fears would perswade me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo, <hi>muffled in his Servants Cloak, observing his Sister, and the Princess as they go out.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>'TWas she, and the Princess <hi>Victoria;</hi> I will observe till she goes to her own Chamber. I dare not see the Princess; my love has too much folly and softness; When I be|hold her she calls to my mind, 'tis her brother that has injur'd me; and that thought distracts me; Yet I must not tamely bear this Injury, nor rudely dispute it with her I love; But for <hi>Fide|lia,</hi> a Sister that I have loved above my Eyes; that she should joyn in my disgrace, is a Return I could not have feared from any thing that I have valued like <hi>Fidelia—</hi>She comes, I will not be seen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Fidelia <hi>and</hi> Victoria.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Till night, Madam, I will take my leave, lest our being together beget suspition.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fidelia,</hi> Sister. <stage>
                              <hi>As she goes out,</hi> Cosmo <hi>pulls</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Brother? well-come, What Accident calls you to <hi>Millain?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>My Injuries, which I hear you are no stranger to, <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>What was it you said, Sir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I am told you are no stranger to the affront that brings me hither; for 'tis said, you love Prince <hi>Sforza,</hi> sister.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>I heard you, Sir, at first; But was loath to understand you; and 'tis said, you hate Prince <hi>Sforza,</hi> brother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Hate him? Nay I scorn to hate him; When I am angry I dare be reveng'd; Nor will <hi>Cosmo</hi> think this anger away; That I hate him is false.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>And why may not I be scandal'd too?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>If 'twere false, why do you hold Correspondence with him has wrong'd your brother?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>I know he has not Injur'd you, and therefore I hold correspondence with him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I know, he has: poorly, and by Whispers, wrought my disgrace in my absence; and by detraction robbed me of that Faith his Father gave me; 'Tis <hi>Sforza</hi> has made me suspected: But I shall prove my self honester then he dares be.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Honester then he? I would thou couldst.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, then he, or any that dares avow this disgrace done to <hi>Cosmo,</hi> and to their teeth tell them so; and they dare assoon beard a Lyon, naked, as maintain their Injury.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>He is the gallanter man; Dare you maintain an Injury?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I dare, as much as he.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>And more; for he dares not use a Sister thus; Go tell
<pb n="167" facs="86"/>
him what you dare do; you will find him your equall in Honour, and in Arms.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>He is not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, he is. Remember <hi>Pavia,</hi> and the life he gave you; Remember me, and my honour, which he saved, When neither your sword nor passion could protect it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>You are angry, Sister.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir; I never yet met that man so rude, nor Injury so wild, could raise my Anger; Yet I confess, I have so much share in <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s faults, that they wound me; Thou art abused, and when 'tis too late thou wilt find it; and if my words had faith with <hi>Cosmo,</hi> I would tell thee thy Courage and all that is Gallant and Honourable in thee (Those strengths given to defend thee) are by the malice and Craft of those Traytors whom thou trustest, arm'd against thee; And because they durst not attempt thee, they have raised <hi>Cosmo</hi> against himself, and this Civil-war will ruine thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I understand not this complement; are you with me, or against me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>In the Princes cause against the world; for I know he is Innocent; and if you were your self, I could clear all these doubts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosm.</speaker>
                        <p>My self? what disorders are there in my words or actions, that makes your partial eyes find the Mad-man in a Brother?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Unmanly ones, such as in Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> I should hate, but in <hi>Cosmo</hi> I pity them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>You are my Sister that sayes this.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Dost thou not blush to say so, with that cloudy brow? would any gallant man look upon a Sister so, with such a storm in his Fore-head, and Eyes full of Anger? Would any man shew this Rage to a Sister, whose Sex can scarce modestly be angry? But that, and all the Injuries thou canst do me, I can pardon; because I know there is a Tempest in thy Heart, craftily raised by those that hate thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh <hi>Fidelia!</hi> I am wronged, disgraced, my Country lost, and all the Credit I had with the Duke blasted; my Com|mand is taken from me by Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> and his Party.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou art deceived, <hi>Cosmo:</hi> Yet I know you are wrong|ed, and my Heart has bled for it; But why you should punish me <stage>S●e weepes.</stage> for it, why accuse wretched <hi>Fidelia,</hi> that had no Joy left but in her Innocence, and <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s Love; Why pursue me, that never in thought wronged you or any man; Me, a Virgin and a Sister, oppressed with miseries, and rudely thus throw your wild words at me; And your self (a Brother) become the Author of a scandal that thy Hon|our should have engaged thee to tear from a strangers Heart! But now since you have defamed me, who shall fear to blot <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s Name, when <hi>Cosmo</hi> a Brother shall be known to revile her? <hi>They say, you are in Love with Prince</hi> Sforza. Oh <hi>Cosmo!</hi> when thou said'st it, thy Eyes were red, and thy Heart call'd me Whore; And had not you expressed a want of value for your Sister, who durst have ventur'd the defaming of <hi>Fidelia</hi> so: The man was ne|ver born durst venture to tell me <hi>Cosmo</hi> was a Coward; And had
<pb n="168" facs="87"/>
mine honour been as pretious to thee, thou wouldst have kill'd that poysoner of my fame; yet, I here declare, the only glory of my heart, is, the friendship she has gained from Prince <hi>Sforza.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, <hi>Fidelia, Fidelia!</hi> pardon thy unfortunate Brother, and let my distracted mind plead my peace with thee; though the injuries I have received would force an Anchorite from his Cell, and with broken vows break all Laws of Gods or Men, rather then not find a revenge: Read that Letter, and be your self the Judge. <stage>He walks, and she reads.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>If this Letter find your faith, We are lost; 'tis <hi>Martino</hi>'s falshood. Oh, that Serpent, which but now begins to throw his venom out! the Prince sue for your Command? (did you desire the Government of <hi>Pavia?)</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fidelia,</hi> I ask your counsel; I am not now fit for your mirth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you know this hand? pray read it. <stage>
                              <hi>She gives him Prince</hi> Sforza<hi>'s Let|ter, and walks.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>I work underhand, to gain the Government of <hi>Pavia,</hi> as I did the Army of <hi>Millain?</hi> 'tis false, false as Hell, both; and through the earth I will hunt him with my sword, till I have taken revenge of him that dares accuse me of one treacherous thought.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you now perceive the mischief they aim at, that have made this remove in your Commands? <hi>Martino</hi> and <hi>Carlo</hi> cannot gain their ends, while the Prince and you are friends. You have both too much honour, while you love each other, to listen to their mischiefs: but being once blinded with anger, their false pretences may find a faith, which you and all may live to repent. The Prince is as great a stranger to his being General, as you are to the Government of <hi>Pavia;</hi> yet when 'twas labour'd to make him believe you were the cause of his remove; his friend|ship would neither believe, nor suffer such a scandal to be laid on <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Is this truth, <hi>Fidelia?</hi> or feigned, only to keep me from ta|king my revenge where you have a friendship?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>No, <hi>Cosmo;</hi> I will call no man friend that dares do a trea|cherous act, or fears to justifie his own innocence; and if you think otherwise, Go to <hi>Pavia,</hi> find the Prince, and satisfie your doubts; only thus much I beg; for my sake be not hasty, nor injurious in your words, but clearly tell your griefs; Courage and Reason should tread the same pathes; else you may lose your way, though justice guide you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall obey your counsel; for I know him valiant, and full of honour; and though we both love him, if he wrong me, I must not bear it, <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, I am none of that fond kind of women, that would save a Brother ingloriously; nor have I said this, to bid thee not fight with any man that wrongs thee. For I know my Brother fortunate in fight; nor do I fear, or doubt his sword against any sin|gle enemy; and though I would bet upon his arm against the world; yet I would counsel him to let honour guide him, and ne|ver to detract from any enemy: For it lessens thy triumph when thou art victor; but if overcome, then a scorn follows the loss.—See who comes here; can that softness calm your heart, or will it
<pb n="169" facs="87"/>
swell against her too?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Victoria.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>She staggers all my resolution; I must not stay: I hope your Highness does not believe me guilty of the injuries I stand accused of to Prince <hi>Sforza.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>I am so far, Sir, from believing, I am to blush for those my Brother is taxed for; but I hope you see from whence that malice takes its root; <hi>Martino</hi> is a villain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis visible I am injur'd; and when I thought Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> did it, my anger then was just. But <hi>Fidelia</hi> has made me lay by that anger, till I have spoken with his Highness: And I know the Prince is so gallant, he will not love me the less for seeing me sen|sible of an affront; For nothing can confirme him better that I will do no injuries, then to see that I will take none; for to ap|pear worthy of such a friendship, is, to let him know I am not afraid to be his enemy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Why was he so harsh to me?—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[aside.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, this is but civil anger; and I must not go till you pro|mise me, not to be an enemy to my Brother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>By your self, I swear (to <hi>Cosmo</hi> of all Oaths that binds most powerful) never to be an enemy to Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> till he injures me; and then to be patient is neither the way to honour nor safety.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>I am satisfied, so you will let some other, and not your own passion, be judge of those injuries.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Be your Highness always judge of them and me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Trevallin.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>I Fear <hi>Argentin</hi> is not so full of honour as my wife should be: A drunken <hi>Thedes-key,</hi> one of those wandring <hi>Tra|montanes,</hi> whose business in the world is Wine Whores and Horse|flesh; one of these, at first sight, called her by her name, and talk|ed of old stories, such as would make a jealous man smell of the horn; if she be one of those that cannot say no, what a Trade shall I drive, that have the carrying over mine own horns, by Boat|loads; but if I find her trading, By St. <hi>John,</hi> I'll spade her;</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter to him</hi> Bertolin <hi>and</hi> Argentin.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <p>That's a sly Rogue too; I durst not go to gather boughs for my <stage>Bert. <hi>and she play together while he talks.</hi>
                           </stage> Boats, for fear he should be plucking her forbidden fruit at home.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argen.</speaker>
                        <p>I, now you cog; but I have not forgot that you gave <hi>Moretta</hi> the shirt the Dutch-man left behind him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Will this jealous humour never wear out? Come, and if you be true steel, Mistress, let us in, and strike fire; and I <stage>
                              <hi>They fool to|gether, and</hi> Trevallin <hi>sees them.</hi>
                           </stage> will promise you a bundle of Dutch-mens shirts, the next that passe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>So, so; this will come to somewhat, shortly; I shall pre|fer you, <hi>Bertolin,</hi> the French-way; I shall; which is, fleay you, and
<pb n="170" facs="88"/>
send you to serve the Grand Duke, Sirrah; I shall, if I catch you in this saucy fit again, of playing with my wife.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, we were but talking of the Dutch-men, that knew my Mistress when she was a brave Girle; he that dranke a pound of Candles to her health.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>And whither is she gone now? to find that fine Dutch|man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir, she's gone to the wood,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>I know her mind now; and if I would consent to her Roguery, I might gain my own ends the better; 'twere but giving her an occasion, and taking an opportunity my self, for <hi>Moretta</hi> is as willing as I am, and see where she comes,—Dispatch, and get the boughs ready.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall, Sir, and it shall go hard but I will make a Rod for your Tail, out of them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>My Mistress is so jealous of her Bauble, and so covetous of anothers, that poor <hi>Moretta</hi> starves for a little of either; yet the Master or the Man are willing to relieve my hunger; she is a wo|man would fain change, and keep her own too. Yonder is my Master, how handsome he appears, now there is none but he! (thus brown bread is good when one has a stomack) she is va|nished, and <hi>Bertolin</hi> gone; now for a charm to try him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Moretta.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Quickly, and softly, a kiss, Wench.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>O dear, Master, take ten, and ask them afterwards, eve|ry word would make a dozen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Let us look where the old spy is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>She is gone to gather boughs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Come Wench, a kiss, and in, lest we lose this minute.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt both.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bertolin.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>WE are the strangest unlucky, every body is willing, and yet none can meet; we know each others minds too well; now for a minute, I have a jobbe of work here, a minute would do it, and a design in my pate to cure all their jealousies, by giving them full satisfaction of their doubts. Here comes my Mi|stress, I must be kind to her; and she comes on as easie as my old slippers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Argentin.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argen.</speaker>
                        <p>There he stands, and we are alone; if he should offer, how shall I do for a where withall to deny him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>Mistress, there is an old suit depending; I am poor <hi>Berto|lin</hi> still, but a most sufficient able Lover, that has—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argen.</speaker>
                        <p>You staid for me here now.—I, I, dissemble, 'dissemble; where is your Master? <stage>He plays the Rogue with her.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>He is gone home.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="171" facs="88"/>
                        <speaker>Argen.</speaker>
                        <p>And what do you hanker for? I saw the boughs at the door; Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> will be past before you have trimmed or made clean the Boat.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>I would that you would but step in with me, and help to set up the boughs; I have a trick, if you would but joyn, Mistress, would tickle you till you laugh again. <stage>He kisses her.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argen.</speaker>
                        <p>I thought 'twas such trick; why so, is this a time to fool away in tricks and kissing?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>Say you so? I would we were but on t'other side the wa|ter; if you will go, we will put the Boat a drift; and when the work is done we'l call for help.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argen.</speaker>
                        <p>I am willing to do thee a kindness, but I dare not be long absent; for I fear my husband should come home in the mean time, and fall aboard <hi>Moretta.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>That is a Whore in her heart; let me alone to watch her; we will be back before them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. II. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Trevallin <hi>and</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>THere is no safety here, 'tis my Mistress that watches us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Whither shall we go then, to be private?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Send my Mistress to the wood, for boughs; and when <hi>Bertolin</hi> comes home, make him stay for his break-fast; step you to the Boat, and lie privately, I will come to you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou wilt not fail.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>This in earnest. Farewel, make haste, and send home <hi>Bertolin;</hi> see where he comes with his boughs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bertolin <hi>with his boughs at his back.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Whither are you going?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>To the Boat with these boughs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Where is your Mistress?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>In the wood, gathering more boughs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>More boughs, what to do? unless you were certain the Prince would come.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>A Gallant told me so, that knew my Mistress before you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>A pox of his knowledge, and memory too; there is neither of them honest.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, let me go; and if you were as well loaden as I am, you'de have little lust to talk under such a burthen; I have more upon my back then you are aware of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Lay them down, and go break your fast, and then call home your Mistress; there is boughs enough, one would think.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Boughs enough? why, 'tis none of your pains, to ga|ther them; can't you let one make the Boat handsome when the Prince is to pass?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="172" facs="89"/>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>You are alwayes thus troublesome.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Let me carry these aboard, and then I will call home my Mistress.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>Leave your prating, and lay down your Boughes, and go now and call her home; for if I lace your Coat 'twill be less easier then your plain one.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>I will not go alone, where she is; you will be in your old jealous humour, and mistrust something, as you did t'other night.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>Away, you are a fool; give me the Boughes, and make haste.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>I will not quit my Boughes; you do things so by halfes still.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Break-fast is ready; why do you dispute thus with him, you know 'tis a wilfull fool, let him go, you lose time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, Sirrah, make haste, and come down to Breakfast.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt</hi> Trevallin <hi>and</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Mistress, Mistress, don't you stink for fear? I assure you I do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Bertolin,</hi> dear <hi>Bertolin,</hi> quick, quick, quick, unbind, unbind, dispatch that I may run home, I would not endure such another fright for all the wealth in <hi>Pavia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and then you will be gone and laugh at <hi>Bertolin;</hi> no faith, you must even be patient, Mistress; I will not lose my labour and my longing too; 'tis an opportunity has cost me too dear to be thrown away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear <hi>Bertolin,</hi> I can do nothing now; for the truth is, I am loose in my belly with the fright.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you gilt, Mistress?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear <hi>Bertolin,</hi> another time command me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Courage, Mistress, 'tis a sign of good luck you know.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, <hi>Bertolin,</hi> as thou lovest me let me go; unbind me or I will cry out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Do, and proclaim it, one loud syllable more and I am gone; and here I will leave you like a Bird in a bush, 'twill be a credit for you, I need onely swear I have not touched you, and vehemently swear we were honest; That is the new fashion way of telling, which the Gallants use of late.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>I am undone, I am undone for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Not, if you will be quiet; for I am as secret as any boat|hook.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Bertolin, <hi>and drawes off his Boughes and Mistress.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>He is gone aboard, and when he comes back to Break|fast, my Master and I will be merry in the Arbor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>If ever I trust you again, <hi>Bertolin.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="173" facs="89"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bertolin, <hi>and brings his Mistress in again in the Boughes.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>You hope I will deceive you thus; why now you I am your faithfull <hi>Bertolin,</hi> for being a gracious Mistress endears me; <stage>He begins ●● unbind the Cord.</stage> we have nicked the jealous Rogue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>You had best tell him so; Prithee unbind, that I may get home; so, so, look out and see whether the coast be clear, for I am afraid <hi>Moretta</hi> and he should meet, for she is a Jade—Was not that her voice? <stage>Moretta <hi>within calls</hi> Bertolin.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, by this hand.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>Look out, quick.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis she coming this way, quickly, let me tie the cord and lie still till she be gone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>A pox upon her for a crafty Whore, she suspects some|thing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Be quiet, and all will be well, I warrant you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Why do you not come to Break-fast? my Master stayes for you, what are you studying?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis resolv'd I will do it, and then they are both at my devotion; they will fear me, and not dare accuse me, nor tell of each other.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Now I am alone with him, methinks, he is lovelier then my Master; Lord, how handsome any Man is, when a Woman is in my Case. <stage>Bertolin <hi>takes her in his Armes, and poynts to the Boughes.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Moretta,</hi> you understand me, else this occasion may prompt you; Prithee lay thy hand upon these Boughes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Why should I be coy? Here is an opportunity, and 'tis good to be sure of one; and in this case to take the Man is Wisdom, when the Master is uncertain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>You are dumb now, there may be more Dutch-men, and more shirts; however, there are Trees and Ropes enough in <hi>Pavia</hi> to ease a Lovers Heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>You do well to complain first, and judge by your self; Alass, I do not see my Mistress, I am blind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Mistress? where?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Where? you know where, in your Heart, dissembler.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>By this day, I had thought she had seen her. By this kiss, I am all thine, only I was angry and vexed to see thee cast Eyes upon my Master; But we will forgive each other, grow wise, from past follies take occasion by the lock, and laugh at the old Woman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Till you are next alone, and then this Story shall enter|tain her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Dost thou take me for a Devil, false to my Love?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Heark, I hear my Masters voice.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Trevallin <hi>at the other Door.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Bertolin, Bertolin,</hi> she stayes long; If the Rogue should
<pb n="174" facs="90"/>
mowe her to my hand, I have carried my business finely, to make my self his Baud; I have no patience, I will to the Door and call him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bertolin <hi>and</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>So, you had best brag, and tell leather face, my Mistress, with her spiders breath, what I have done.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Heark, I heard my Masters voice.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Be gone, I will follow you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertolin.</speaker>
                        <p>Farewell, little Rogue, till another time, but I will watch your water; how my Mistress stormes: Now if my Master will take an opportunity, and imploy <hi>Moretta</hi> upon the Boughes, what a Comfort 'twill be to my Mistress, 'till cure both their Jea|lousies—he comes, and I am gone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Trevallin.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>Where is this idle Villain?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not, I found him talking in's sleep here to him|self, laid all along upon the Boughes; But he is gone I think to call home my Mistress.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>But is he gone? Peepe Wench, be sure, lest the Enemy surprize us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>But look you keep your promise now; You shall not have my Maiden-head till you swear not to suffer my Mistress to beat me any more, nor dominere over me though she be jealous.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>Beat thee? By this light, I will sew up her tail like young Kites for spoile, if she but lift her Tongue against thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Will she not come, think you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Trev.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, hang her old Trot; Come Wench, whither shall we go?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Help me pull in the Boughes, and then I will talk with you; but you must be very civil.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Bertolin.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis done; lucky mischief as I could wish; O the knavery and the sport of this Jest, besides, my Revenge on all three: Now <hi>Bertolin</hi> is Master, and can have which he will. O for a fine familiar Devil to tell my Mistress thoughts; would I had so much money as she would give to be revenged, or as I would refuse, ra|ther then hold my tongue; I will steal off, and give them the Alarum. Cry only, my Mistress comes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Bertolin.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Trevallin <hi>and</hi> Moretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>A Boy, or Girl, Wench, for a pair of Gloves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Neither, for two pair, a pox on't; 'tis no marvel my Mi|stris is so jealous; By this light, he would press twenty women to death, ere he made one Quick.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>What say'st thou, am not I a young man still? and a bountiful Lover, for a man of my hair.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="175" facs="90"/>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>By my troth, Sir, if you took no more then you lay'd out I think there had been little spent to day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>A wag, a wag; But I shall see thy belly swell; if it prove a Boy, we will call him <hi>Trevallin</hi> the second.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>These old men think the best of themselves, and they have reason; for if their faith were no stronger then their works they were damn'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>A kiss, a kiss, Wench.—I am betray'd, undone, undone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>While they are kind, Enter</hi> Bertolin <hi>and discovers himself.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertolin.</speaker>
                        <p>My Act, for my freedom, quickly, your Seal-Ring, and Reversion of the Ferry, all the ready money in the house, and <hi>Mo|retta</hi> for my wife; Or all goes to the Inquisitor, and my Mistris, he cannot cuckold me; I have both their words for it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>I am undone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it a Bargain? or I am gone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Be rul'd, Sir, all is undone, I will consent rather then be dishonoured; But if I be not revenged on him when I am married.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>But will you be faithful, and secret, when this is done? and not tell my wife!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Hah! what house do you take me to be of? Is <hi>Bertolin</hi> of so little reputation in the world, as to proclaim my own horns my self? Hang her, Trot, she shall know nothing unless you tell her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>I tell her? the Divel I will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure, 'tis as probable you may have the vanity to say, you made my wife a whore, as I to tell it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Be but secret, and all is agreed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bortel.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it a match, <hi>Moretta?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, by this kiss.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Make haste, and let us part before she comes, she will be so jealous else.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, stay you two here, and stick up the Boughes; I told her you were making ready the Boat; fetch out the boughes <hi>Mo|retta,</hi> and dispatch, I will return strait.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Bertolin.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>This slave will tell her yet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>What will he tell? am not I his wife? <stage>Both of them pull in the Boughes.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>But shall not I be well-come still, when we can delude the old Woman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, but we must be secret, for he is a sullen Rogue, I cannot these boughs out, he has bound them so fast together, pray lend me your knife to cut the string.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>There, let me help thee. <stage>They set up some Boughes.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(Bertolin <hi>peeps.)</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Fetch me some more boughes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! what's here? my wife? <stage>Trevallin <hi>goes to pluck the Boughes, and findes his wife.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argent.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, impudence; Oh, that I were loose?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Bertol.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Did you call, Sir? my Mistris will be here presently.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Treval.</speaker>
                        <p>I am abused, but I shall be revenged; This is your Vil|lany, Sirrah.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="176" facs="91"/>
                        <speaker>Moret.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! my Mistris in the boughes! she can tell fine stories then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Argen.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, you double Whore; oh, for a Rat to gnaw this Cord.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Baptista <hi>and the</hi> Banditoes.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Sieze them, and bind them; so, strip those Fellows, and bring their Cloathes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir; my skin will never hold dressing; if your worship has use of a skin, pray take my Masters; he is a notable thick-skin'd knave, and so tough with the yellow, 'tis almost tann'd <stage>
                              <hi>The</hi> Banditti <hi>hold them.</hi>
                           </stage> to your hand, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Hah! What have we here, a bird in a bush? Away, gagg them; and lay them in the hole, behind the Hermitage, and follow me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza <hi>and</hi> Richardo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>NO more, <hi>Richardo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, 'tis my Love and Duty that makes me urge it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>I believe it; but no more, I know you are abus'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Rich.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I have letters here second yours, and from your best Friends, such whose affection, Faith, nor duty, ought to be suspect|ed; They are full of Amaze and Wonder, to finde your Highness will so tamely consent to lose a Countrey that cost so much blood to purchase; Was not <hi>Cosmo</hi> born Prince of <hi>Pavia?</hi> how think you, Sir, a man of his Spirit, and Title to the Place, should consent to hold his birth-right for another? You are deceived, Sir; Nor were <hi>Cosmo</hi> fit for your Friendship, if his Spirit could grow so tame and degenerate, as to set a Slave upon his Fathers Throne; Come, Sir, 'tis Flattery and dissimulation, and they are all false; this is the opi|nion of your best Friends.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Take heed, <hi>Richardo;</hi> yet your love pleads in this indis|cretion; but do not presume; You know, I dare be angry, though it be long before a friend can finde it; your faith shall priviledge you to as much freedom as any Subject can pretend with his Prince; but impertinency and rudeness no discreet man will Commit. Hadst thou said, <hi>Julia, Carlo,</hi> and <hi>Martino</hi> had been false, thou hadst found my faith; for I know they have wrought my disgrace, and 'tis their business to break the Friendship betwixt Prince <hi>Cosmo</hi> and my self; and against those Traytors thy words would have raised a Tempest in my heart; For against that Villain <hi>Martino,</hi> (till my Revenge finds him) even my soul makes War; for I know him ungrateful, bloudy, and all the several ills that make a Villain are met in that inhumane Wretch, and my very dreams arm against him; But when thou sayest all are false, including the Princess <hi>Fidelia;</hi> That Scan|dall questions the truth of that guilt which the rest are condemned for; No, <hi>Richardo,</hi> she has no share in that Treachery, she is all
<pb n="177" facs="91"/>
softness; piety and vertue are so natural to her that, for her sake, I can scarce be angry with the rest; For when her name but cros|ses my thought's, I can do nothing with Passion, save love <hi>Fidelia;</hi> Oh, Friend, thou dos't not know that Noble mind; and when thou shalt be acquainted with her thou wilt confess; The Princess <hi>Fi|delia</hi>'s vertues were given her, as Cordials, to defend us against the Poison of her Family; and if thou lovest <hi>Sforza,</hi> Honour and serve the Princess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Richard.</speaker>
                        <p>Since your Highness is sure of her faith I shall not fail to pay that respect and honour that is due to her; for my displea|sure was onely grounded upon the thought she was ingrateful to your Highness; yet I see not how you can acquit <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee, peace, he is her Brother; and I know he has Courage and honour, and such are onely guilty by chance; But suppose him as false as you believe him, I shall be more troubled that he can do an ill Action, (because I love him) then for any injury he dares do me; For I wear a sword, <hi>Richardo,</hi> which will heal all those injuries; and therefore let us not trouble our selves with much those lesser thoughts at <hi>Millain;</hi> we shall have time to inform our selves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Baptista, Pietro, Nicolet, and another Souldier, <hi>in the Ferrymans habit, but not quite dres't.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>SO, dispatch; and some one look out, lest some call to pass; how the old whore beat the fellow?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>She had reason; for the slave made her husband lie with the Maid upon her back.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, he lay with her himself upon her back, after he had layen with his Mistris.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas his trick, to get his Mistris into the boughs; and then the ill-natur'd Rogue left her, for her husband to find her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>What a dog 'twas? But she has punish'd him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>Hee'll be dead ere night, for I have bound them together, and left her hands loose.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>She will kill him then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>No matter, hang him Rogue; tell when his Mistris do's him a Curtesie? I would all that do so were so served.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>That folly makes us pay dear; for, by this light, the fear of telling keeps more women honest, then fear of Purgatory; But 'tis time to be gone, I hear some body call.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Phillipine.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillip.</speaker>
                        <p>Ferryman, is the Boat on this side?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! <hi>Phillipin? e Victoria</hi>'s Page, what business has he at <hi>Pavia?</hi> I must know; Some intelligence upon my life. Sir, if you will walk to the Boat; we will follow you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillip.</speaker>
                        <p>Make haste then; Is Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> past to day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Ex.</hi> Phil.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Not yet, but we Expect him. What, ho, where are these
<pb n="178" facs="92"/>
fellows; Do you here.—seize that youth, and blind him, make <stage>Aside.</stage> as if you would rob him, search his Pockets and his Cloathes well, for Papers; if you find any give them me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>I warrant you, Sir, we will search him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Pietro.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>What can his business be? The Duke perhaps is dead; it must be that, or the discovery of our design; Why should they be so impatient else? for they Expect him within these two hours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the</hi> Banditoes, <hi>and bring in</hi> Phillipine <hi>blinded.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, resist not, we must have money, Sir; we know the Courtiers want none.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillip.</speaker>
                        <p>And you will find so little 'twill scarce be worth your <stage>They search him and find a Letter.</stage> pains.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>What's that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>A Letter, directed to no body.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>Open it, and see if there be never a token in it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>A pox on't, heer's nothing but black and white.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>What says it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>For that you must execuse me, for I scorn to read, or write; search, search his Doublet, let his papers be hanged.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Baptista <hi>reads the Letter, throws it down, and goes out. When</hi> Baptista <hi>is gone, they unblin'd him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>A Pox upon you, you would be cudgeld, Sirrah, for offer|ing to wear such Cloathes and carry no money in your Purse, onely to couzen good fellows; here are three of us put fairly for the Gallows, for a Pistol.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>Let us geld the slave, for hanging out such a bush, when he has no Wine in the Cellar.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillip.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, Sir, I must wear what is given me; I am but a Servant.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pietro.</speaker>
                        <p>We shall have you a prating too, when you are on to'ther side.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillip.</speaker>
                        <p>No truly; give me but my paper, and I will go about my business, and do you no injury at all, O here it is, I am glad the <stage>He finds the Letter and takes it up.</stage> Rogues could not read; This chance had like to have spoil'd all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nicol.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, will you be gone, we will give you a Cast-ashoar, for your money; but we are no Ferry-men, my friend; onely we farm'd it, for an hour; and we shall leave you to take the possessi|on, if you please, for our work is done.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Piet.</speaker>
                        <p>If we had lighted upon nothing but your lean purse, what a purchase we had had?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Baptista.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Dispatch, and away, the Prince is for certain coming; and if he find us here, we shall pay dear for this reckoning.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phillip.</speaker>
                        <p>I must trust them, till I am over.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Phillip.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>What miraculous accident was this! all our plot is disco|vered; but I have handled it so, that the mischief shall fall upon their own heads; 'twas <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s hand, 'tis certain she loves <hi>Sforza,</hi>
                           <pb n="179" facs="92"/>
she could not else discover her mother and Family to him. No <hi>Bap|tista,</hi> 'tis visible <hi>Sforza</hi> had ruin'd thee; But if he obey thy counsel, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> I shall quickly have an Opportunity to take a full Re|venge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Carlo <hi>with a Letter.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>There is the Hermits Cell; now to finde <hi>Baptista;</hi> hereabout is a path that leads to the Ferry, where I am to ex|pect him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Baptista <hi>and</hi> Pietro.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>So, lie close till they call; that Letter will bring him were death in the way.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>That must be he. <hi>Baptista?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Carlo,</hi> what news?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Read that letter, and 'twill instruct you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Carlo <hi>gives him a Letter.</hi> Baptista <hi>reads the Letter.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis enough; but can you give me no directions how to know him, or guess when he will come, for we cannot long possess this place; The people that pass will miss the Ferry-man; But, for the other part of the Letter, there needs no Conjuration.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>If they should meet, you know it must be fatall; They have both too much Courage to part without revenge; and if <hi>Cosmo</hi> should fall all our hopes must perish.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>If he come, I shall not faile of my part, either to perswade or force him to stay; But <hi>Carlo,</hi> I tell thee, there has hapned such a chance to day that makes me believe fortune will be kind to us; In short, all Our Resolutions and Designs are known.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis not possible.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Deceive not your self, 'tis known; and yet shall not be prevented: <hi>Phillipine</hi> past this Instant with a Letter from <hi>Fidelia</hi> to <hi>Sforza;</hi> wherein she assures him of all our intentions, and by all that is dear to him conjures him to come privately, in some dis|guise, this night, to her chamber; where she and his sister will expect him, and give him a full Relation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>And where is the Villain and his Letter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Gone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Gone?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes gon, and upon good grounds; for knowing <hi>Phillipine</hi> I made them blind him, and under the pretence of robbing him, Search'd for Letters, and found that; which having read they pretended Ignorance, I threw it upon the ground; he not suspect|ing the secret was discovered took it, and is gone in haste to <hi>Sforza.</hi> By which means we shall be sure to act our parts with more Conve|nience; for I am confident he will come, and alone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas done like one that knows how to take revenge; Wicked and foolish Girle! unnatural <hi>Fidelia!</hi> Betray thy Mo|ther? This news will confirm thy hopes in her; for now the Dutchess will give her you, were it but to vex her, and cross her
<pb n="180" facs="93"/>
hopes in <hi>Sforza:</hi> Remember <hi>Julia,</hi> and as soon as you have di|spatch'd; pray, give notice to the Count <hi>Martino,</hi> by some trusty <stage>
                              <hi>He gives</hi> Bapt. <hi>a Ring.</hi>
                           </stage> messenger, with this Ring.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>I am instructed, farewell.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo <hi>in his Pilgrims Habit, and</hi> Antonio <hi>with him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>I Confess, <hi>Antonio,</hi> this is the greatest streight that ever cross Fate threw me upon; for I must now lose my value with <hi>Sforza,</hi> and the world, or else break with the Princess <hi>Victoria,</hi> whom I love above the world; and heaven and she know my soul has no other ambition but to deserve her favour: But that love must not make thy friend bear an injury that the world talks of, because she commands me to be silent; if I do, her reason will hate; and my honour will not suffer the world to wisper, <hi>Cos|mo</hi> is a coward.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I find many Lovers complain of Love, and the heavy burthens he lays upon them; yet few or none make haste to dis|charge themselves, but rather patiently lie down under their loads; your Highness now complains of two hard Masters, Love and Honour, and you make a difficulty of obeying either; Reason counsels you to prefer one, your Passion t'other; and to me no|thing appears easier then your part in both; for your Idle thought of coward, <hi>Cosmon</hi> is know above it; and if the Princess be all your aim, if her favour be your ambitious hope, as you say, What need you thus hunt your own dangers, and pursue her Brother, and your Prince, upon a most unreasonable jealousie; unless you will give satisfaction to others, by disobliging her that you profess to love and value above the world.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou mistakest, <hi>Antonio;</hi> 'tis <hi>Cosmo</hi> loves the Princess, 'tis not <hi>Victoria</hi> loves <hi>Cosmo;</hi> and obeying her now is but serving my self only; if she loved me, then for her sake would I put up this injury, because I would not hazard what she loves; but 'tis not so; no <hi>Antonio,</hi> 'tis <hi>Cosmo</hi> only that is a Lover; and Love in a Lover is no obligation nor tye on a Mistress; that is the great mistake which has so long misled the world; every Lover pretending a reward from his Mistress, because he loves her; which is most un|reasonable; unless he can say, I will love such a woman, which is impossible and false; for know, <hi>Antonio,</hi> that Prince of the mind will not come when he is called, nor go when he is sent; Love is a blind and stubborn Boy, and his will is his Law; therefore no woman is obliged to any man for loving her. We owe the root no thanks, while it lies sleeping in the ground; but when by the spring awakened, it sends forth its Clusters, then we cherish and admire the Vine, hoping to taste the rich Elixar. Love is that Root, and Love may bear such Fruit as may oblige a Mistress, by being diligent, finding and taking all occasions to serve her; yet then the Lover but obeys his Master; and to a Lover such an Act
<pb n="181" facs="93"/>
both makes and pays the debt; And this Consideration, <hi>Antonio,</hi> makes me pursue my first resolution; for since I can pretend no|thing from the Princess but what is due to a person of honour, I must be careful to preserve that honour which is currant through the world; and till the Princess loves <hi>Cosmo,</hi> I must not let her kindness to a Brother make me unfit for the friendship or value of that Brother, by tamely suffering injuries.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I submit; but why should you go thus alone, more now then at other times? you have heretofor thought me wor|thy to take a part in your dangers; but 'twas when your Highness did not grudge me a part in the honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis true, the honour I shall gain from <hi>Sforza</hi> I will share with none; yet let me tell thee, 'tis not that which makes me leave <hi>Antonio</hi> now; for you must stay here, and always keep in readiness those Souldiers I spoke with last night, to execute any design my revenge requires; for I am resolved to hunt the Au|thors of this disgrace, though I find them priviledg'd by a Sister, or a Mother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I am not curious to know more, and so I may serve you, I am indifferent in the kind or place.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Farewel, <hi>Antonio;</hi> prithee keep a watch about the Princess, and observe what she and my Sister do; and though you see me through my disguise, at any time, yet take no notice of me publickly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall observe, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza, Phillipine, <hi>and</hi> Richardo, (Sforza <hi>is reading a Letter.)</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>REad there, <hi>Richardo,</hi> and blush for the ill opinion thou hadst of the most excellent <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                           <stage>Richardo <hi>reads.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Richard.</speaker>
                        <p>Horrid villain! Sure the Dutchess has a hand in this; but who it should be that dares undertake this black deed, I can|not guess; the Duke being dangerously sick is the cause that makes them thus sudden in their mischief.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>There is no dispute now; haste, and provide those habits I use to make the Round in; we will away this night, as she desires, only you and I; Oh <hi>Richardo,</hi> thou art yet a stranger to that excel|lent Maid, whose faith is sent by heaven to guard us from those wounds that her Mother threatens this State with.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Richard.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Sir, let <hi>Phillipine</hi> stay here, as if he expected your Highness answer to his Letters, 'twill keep them at a Bay still, and make them uncertain what to resolve; and if any of your own fa|mily be their spy or traytor, his stay will deceive them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>And early to morrow I will take my time to follow your Highness.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>What were those that rob'd you? are they at the Ferry still?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="182" facs="94"/>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>I believe not, Sir, they seem to be poor Rogues, some stragling Souldiers of the next Garison.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, <hi>Richardo,</hi> let us away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo <hi>in his Pilgrims habit alone.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure I have lost my way; 'tis late, I will knock at this Her|mits Cell, and inform my self. <stage>He knocks at the Hermits.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[The Hermit within says who's there.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>A friend; pr●y, which is the way to the Ferry?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hermit within.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, come in, and afford your Charity; and then I will guide you to the Ferry.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo, <hi>and brings forth the Hermit, and unbinds him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>What Impious villains were those that could so rudely bind those holy hands?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hermit.</speaker>
                        <p>Speak softly, Son, they were Thieves, that have all this day robbed at the Ferry; pray, come in, and let me shut the door, lest they espy us; 'tis late, and they cannot stay long, the people are already alarm'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>But that I have other vows to pay, I would know who they are that thus boldly justifie their villany.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>For heavens sake, think not of going out, Son, 'tis late and dangerous.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis late, and, I confess, I am hungry and weary.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>Within I have some of yesterdays Charity left still, which I shall freely give you; Come, Son, and put off those weeds, and rest upon my poor bed, it knows no care of earthly things; and if you bring no troubles in your mind, you will find none there; I will watch, and call you early if the danger be removed; I am stiff with lying all day upon one side.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Let me help you in; Villains, to use an old Religious man thus!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza <hi>and</hi> Richardo, <hi>in their disguise.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>'TIs late; the Sun is upon the hill already, we shall scarce reach <hi>Millain</hi> to night.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Richard.</speaker>
                        <p>We must ride the faster, Sir; But once over the Ferry, the way is short.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Call the Ferry-man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Richard.</speaker>
                        <p>The Boat is upon this side, I saw it from the hill.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Baptista <hi>and his Company peeps and listen after'em;</hi> Baptista <hi>speaks to his Company, and then Enters.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis he, I know his voyce, as soon as the Boat is upon the other shore, draw upon him, and speed him any way.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="183" facs="94"/>
                        <speaker>Richard.</speaker>
                        <p>See, here is the Ferry-man. Honest friend, is the Boat on this side?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>What hour is it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Late, Sir; does not the Prince pass? we look'd for him to day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Not till to morrow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Our boughs will be wither'd by that time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>A noise of Weapons and fighting within; they set upon the Prince.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Hermit.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha! what noise is that? sure those villains have set up|on some passengers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter to him the Pilgrim without his Coat, with his Staff in his hand</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>How now Father, what noise is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas the noise of swords, good Son, come in; those Ban|ditoes I told you of, I fear they are now robbing some body; For heavens sake, come in, and let them not see you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven forbid it should ever be said, I stood and listned to the danger that threatens innocence, and hid my self for fear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>Heark, they come; and they are so many you can but lose your self in that attempt, and bring no safety to them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Who knows, since they are able to dispute it, but that my aid may save them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>See, 'tis they.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>No matter,—Hold, villains, what do you mean?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Upon them, kill them both.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Baptista <hi>and his party, four in all;</hi> Cosmo <hi>runs to them, and beats down</hi> Baptista<hi>'s sword pursuing</hi> Sforza <hi>and</hi> Richardo; <hi>who after two or three passes,</hi> Richardo <hi>and one of the Souldiers fall, with their wounds;</hi> Cosmo <hi>pulls off the head, and discovers a sword-blade in his Staff; they fight and are all wounded:</hi> Bap|tista <hi>falls under</hi> Sforza, <hi>and the Souldiers are kill'd by</hi> Cosmo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>I am lost for ever; Hold your hand, till I tell you a story may save you from the malice of others, since heaven has preserved you thus miraculously against my designs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Speak quickly.—Sir, I hope your charity has found no <stage>
                              <hi>He turns to</hi> Cos. <hi>and em|braceth him.</hi>
                           </stage> sad accident, to make you repent this action; have you any wound that you apprehend dangerous?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Sir, they are but scratches; pray, let us know what he would say.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>First, let me see my friend drest that lies bleeding here, <stage>
                              <hi>He goes to|ward</hi> Ri|chardo.</stage> is there no Surgeon neer?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>The Hermit is famous for his skill, and fortunate in what he undertakes; and see where he comes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Hermit.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>How fares my Son? is there any use of my skill, or is all desperate?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Father, heaven has been kind; and we must implore
<pb n="182" facs="95"/>
your aid, for their mischief is faln upon their own heads; this is he on whom you must practise your skill and charity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
                        <p>Help me to bear him to my Cell, and then return.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit with</hi> Richard.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo <hi>again.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Defer not to hear what I would say, it concerns your safety; and I shal discover a treachery your honest heart will scarce give credit to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>What made thee attempt my life? thou seest I am poor, no hope of gain cold tempt thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Hide not your self, Prince <hi>Sforza,</hi> from him that knows you, and the cause why you are thus disguis'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo</speaker>
                        <stage> aside.</stage>
                        <p>Ha! Prince <hi>Sforza?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Suppose I am <hi>Sforza,</hi> how came you by this knowledge?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>From <hi>Phillipine,</hi> whom we pretended this day to rob; and in his Pocket found the Princess <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s Letter, which gave you notice that your life was laid for; and this is one of those designs which heaven has prevented: In short (for I find I am going to my grave) your life, Sir, is sold to me and others; <hi>Julia</hi> and false <hi>Martino</hi> sold it; and <hi>Fidelia</hi> should have been my reward, for kil|ling you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo</speaker>
                        <stage> aside.</stage>
                        <p>Ye powers, what do I hear?—Sir, does he speak truth, in part, are you Prince <hi>Sforza?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>From you I will not hide my self; for since you durst pro|tect me, as a private man; I am confident, you will not quit me when you know I am your Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>To confirm you in the belief of what I say, turn this way, and look upon this Face.<hi>—Baptista</hi> pulls off his disguise, of a Beard and Perriwig.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Baptista?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>O heavens! 'tis he.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, <hi>Baptista,</hi> whom you so many ways have ruined:—All which I could have forgot, all but my loss in the hopes of my divine <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Knew she of this Plot?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>She know of it? No, nor could any but a fool or a devil ask that question; would I had fought with thee, thou could'st never have overcome me that art master of so base a doubt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Was Prince <hi>Cosmo</hi> at Court when you came thence, has he any knowledge of this design?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bapt.</speaker>
                        <p>No, upon my soul, they are a pair of matchless vertues.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Then I am happy; for I confess, I could not but with pain of mind think Prince <hi>Cosmo</hi> less then I esteemed him. 'Tis a gal|lant and a faithful Prince; and when you know him you will ad|mire him; there is nothing in him an enemy can accuse, or a friend wish a way, unless his choler may sometimes prevail: But that laid aside, he is Brother to <hi>Fidelia,</hi> which is all that can besaid of excellent.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="185" facs="95"/>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>I know the Prince, and was a Souldier under him; and I am glad to hear your Highness has this opinion of him; for we had a rumour in the Army, that your Highness wrought him out of his Command; believe me, Sir, he left the Camp, as we were told, up|on it, highly unsatisfied with your Highness about it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>The Prince, when he shall know the better, will not be perswaded I could be guilty of so low or meama crime; and when I believe him not fit for such a charge or trust, I shall not fear to tell him so; for I yet never flatter'd a friend, nor injur'd my enemy; why then should I be so unreasonable as to wrong Prince <hi>Cosmo?</hi> yet their malice had like to have been prosperous in their design of breaking our friendship; for till this minute I suspected the Prince had (by his Mothers interest) procured my being called from my Government, here in <hi>Pavia;</hi> but I have now found their design; and their malice has but given a growth to that friendship they meant to have withered,—How do you, Sir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Not well, I find I have lost more blood then I can spare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Father, pray lend us your help here.— <stage>Hermit, <hi>and</hi> Cosmo <hi>lean upon</hi> Sforza.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I would fain know upon what ground this <hi>Baptista</hi> ac|cused <hi>Count Martino</hi> and the Dutchess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baptista.</speaker>
                        <p>Read that Letter, and 'twill satisfie your doubts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis <hi>Martino</hi>'s hand.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baptista.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, and <hi>Carlo</hi> brought it this Evening.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven! thy hand is visible. Read, Sir, for I dare trust you with the secret of my Life; What course shall I take to prevent their malice?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baptista.</speaker>
                        <p>Haste, Sir, to Court, before the Fame of this attempt come to their knowledge, shew this Letter to your Father, and seize <hi>Martino;</hi> But spare to name <hi>Julia,</hi> 'twill break the Prince's and <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s Heart; for whose sake, if you love her, and her Noble Brother, you will hide her part of this fault: And <hi>Martino</hi> once removed, 'twill be easie to reclaim her Heart; for 'tis his am|bitious Mind has wrought her easie Nature to this bloody design. Oh! I faint, and yet ere I die, as you have Charity, forgive <hi>Baptista;</hi> Then live and love at the rate I have adored the excellent <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and you will then deserve her Heart; <hi>Fidelia</hi> is all Angel, and <hi>Baptista</hi> too earthly to think so.—Oh Father, your Charity, pray; that I may confess a sad Soul to you, and end better then I lived.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Can you read that Letter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo,</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir; but 'tis so sad a scene it makes my blood run backwards in my veines; lose no time, Sir, your Life is at stake; I will but dress these sleight wounds and follow you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>I will leave a Horse for you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Sir, quit not your disguise; 'tis better then a guard till you know whom you may trust.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>You have reason, and 'twas my own design. Farewel, Sir; at my Lodging I will expect you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Hermit, Sfor. <hi>and</hi> Bapt.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>That Villain, <hi>Martino,</hi> has ruin'd all our Family; but I will find him when his thoughts expects no such visit: I will in, and
<pb n="186" facs="96"/>
discover my self to <hi>Baptista,</hi> and make him write a Letter to my Mother and <hi>Martino,</hi> wherein he shall onely mention the Prince is escaped, and conceal his own Condition; He shall write to them that they should trust me with any design, as one he knowes faith|full and fit for their purpose. This recommendation will admit me to their Councells; he shall tell them too, that he has seized me accord|ing to their Order, and that I shall be private and safe in his custody till their Order require me; 'twill keep off the suspition of who I am, or fear of my coming till they send for me. Thus I am resolved to return to <hi>Millain,</hi> in this Periwigg and a Pilgrims Weed; and if that disguise can conceal me, I am resolved to undertake all their designes; by which means I may prevent their malice; But when the plot is ripe, if then I fall not with a sad Fate upon the wretch, till this fiery prompter has called to his despairing thoughts all those bloody designes his barbarous Soul has plotted, and with fatal wounds laid the Traytor at my feet a sacrifice to our injur'd Family, Heaven curse me strangely. But for thee, O <hi>Julia,</hi> my unfortunate Mother, though I will not lift a hand a|gainst thee; yet I have words in store that shall wound thee deeper then a sword.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. VI.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Victoria <hi>and</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O Cosmo, Cosmo,</hi> cruel Brother! why hast thou robb'd me of the Joy I had in thee? He has broke his Faith, Ma|dam, and is gone to be calmely wicked upon second thoughts, in cold blood: cruel! What wilt thou do, unworthy youth? Good Gods, would I have given Faith to him that should have told me <hi>Cosmo</hi> would have dissembled with <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and wept to a Sister when blood and revenge were in his Heart; water in his Eyes, and Murder in his Mind?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>Do not say so.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>Do not defend him, Madam; he is not worth your Anger nor Pity, that could lie to you, you that he loved: And he that dares look his Mistress in the face, and tell a lie, neither Religion, Honour nor Virtue, can have any ties upon him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>For my sake, do not revile him; he has some new reason, (I know he has) else I am certain he would have stayed; for his Heart is full of Truth and Honour, and blest with all that is glo|rious in a Man; and though his Rage, sometimes, like a storm throwes those Virtues into disorder, yet when he is collected, his calm Mind is all divine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>This Opinion makes me hate him, that he can be so faulty to you that are thus noble. Pray hate him, pray do, that I may learn to do it by your example; For Heaven knowes, 'tis hard for me to leave loving him, though I chide till the day sets, for <hi>Cosmo</hi> is next to <hi>Sforza</hi> in my Heart. But this falshood has stagger'd all my hopes, for his Love was that I built upon; The Ambitious,
<pb n="187" facs="96"/>
Jealous, Angry, nay, the Lustful Man can Love, but the false dissembler can never be just to himself or others; and till I found him so, my patience bore the present miseries; my Heart still hop|ing <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s Virtue would one day redeem our Family.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>So he will, my Soul prophesies he will. But oh, the War I have within me, when I think my Brother and <hi>Cosmo</hi> are Enemies! Should they meet, 'twould kill <hi>Victoria</hi> ere she can resolve who should be victor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>Unhappy <hi>Cosmol</hi> what would I have given to have saved thee Innocent, that it might not have been said, thy passion betray'd such a sweetness, whose Love is so far from being Angry, that she chides my Justice!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray be not thus passionate; when there is reason, I can be as angry as you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>Had you chid him I would not; and if you would have me defend him, let me see you angry; that may awaken the Sister in me, whose partial Mind may plead something for him; but now tis impossible while you are kind; had he been one that the world knew not, had he never given assurance of what he durst do; that bubble-vanity, and mens idoll, honour, might have pleaded his ex|cuse; but for him that has to sundry battles given a name, and won in Warr a glorious Fame, on whom the Sun yet never set ungloriously, for him to break his Faith and Friendship to quarrel with his Friend? That Friend that gave him his greatest Honour, by having once been his Enemy. Who but a vain Man would aspire higher in Honour and Armes, then to have been, first, Enemy, then Friend to <hi>Sforza;</hi> and after all, not unwelcome to the divine <hi>Victoria?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, then I conjure you by what is dearest to you, leave this discourse; and unless you despise the secrets we so late blushed for, you will cease to revile him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter her</hi> Maid.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Angelica.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, there is a Souldier without who desires to speak with you, his business speaks haste.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Admit him, my Heart fore-tells some sad accident.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza <hi>disguised.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>My business is with the Princess <hi>Fidelia,</hi> yet your Highness may partake of it; but I shall beg some place more pri|vate to deliver it in, for 'tis of consequence.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>In my Chamber, if you please, Madam, we may be pri|vate; follow us, Friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven avert what my fears would prompt me to believe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="scene">
                     <pb n="188" facs="97"/>
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. VII.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the</hi> Hermit <hi>and</hi> Cosmo <hi>in his Pilgrims habit.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I Must be gone, my business calls me hence; but to your care, Father, I must leave my Friend; you must be private in what has past to day; you know what persons are concern'd, Farewell. Your blessing, and be pleased to take this Charity to adorn your Altar.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hermit.</speaker>
                        <p>I am counsel'd, Heaven bless the Prince, and guide my Son; My prayers shall wait upon you; and when your Friend is able to travell, he shall come to Court; In the mean time, I will carry him to the Ferry-mans house, who, in return of your boun|ty to them, shall carefully attend him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray let the <hi>Count Baptista</hi> be privately buried; for though he be of a Noble Family, it must not yet be known he is dead.—I could have wished he had lived; yet this Letter and this Ring will (I hope) be sufficient to compass my designes. <stage>[Aside.]</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. III. SCEN. VIII.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Fidelia, Victoria, <hi>and</hi> Sforza.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>WHat have I heard! My Mother accused of a Murther, and by Prince <hi>Sforza?</hi> Heaven sure has changed its course, he would not else have told me this. <hi>Fidelia,</hi> be thy self, and let not thy fond Affection tame thy Soul so, as to sit calmely down and bear this Injury.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas my fear, Madam, that this truth would grieve your Heart; and had my Life been onely at stake, I should have died in silence: But when yours, my Fathers, and all our Families are thrown into the scale, Piety and Honour bid me warne the Innocent, that they may flie the slaughter; while a wilfull silence might make me not onely lament the misery, but guilty of that crime too. Yet, witness Heaven, 'tis a secret to all the world be|sides; And you can witness, when her Malice was most active and most prosperous, that she was <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s Mother was all satisfa|ction; for whose sake I have still had a Patience as great as her Injuries.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>Thinkes Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> I will justifie her follies? why else do's he stab me with a repetition of them? Do's your Highness think to heal my wounded Mind by telling me you have forgiven my Mother? Do's that take away her faults? No, but shewes her guilt, and his vanity greater, and urged but to upbraid me, and civilly tell me how much better he deserves then I. Yet, if I had not been mistaken, you would not have forgot, that I, to keep a spotless Friendship with Prince <hi>Sforza,</hi> have erred even against Nature, abandoning a Mothers and a Brothers Interest, in quitting all the world to justifie the value I had of him above it; and had
<pb n="189" facs="97"/>
he loved <hi>Fidelia</hi> with half that kindness, he would have hid this fault from me, as if it had been his own Crime; But all the world (Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> too) joynes to make <hi>Fidelia</hi> miserable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>O ye Gods, then I am miserable. Come, <hi>Martino,</hi> I will now call thee Friend, if thou wilt finish what <hi>Baptista</hi> but be|gun, since my Friend can thus mistake her servant.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>Gentle, Sister, why this passion? what is there more in his words then you your self have feared? had you rather we should all perish, then hear your danger from a Friend? Had a third person told you, would not you have broke the glass that brought you poyson? Good Heaven, I, without blushing, dare profess my self a Lover too, yet will not assume such a partial Dominion over his mind, as to prohibit him speaking what is just and honest; and if it be a truth, what he has said, me-thinks you are much to blame.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>If it be not, By all my hopes, I vow my self a Widowed Virgin, in some Holy-house, and bid farewel to <hi>Sforza</hi> and his Friendship, that could thus rashly accuse my Mother; and if it be a truth, I am then unworthy of his thought or Love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Why are you silent, Sir; Why do you not acquit your self?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Treason, war, or sickness, bring no wounds but I can bear; But the wounds of a friends unkindness strike the soul, it growes dumb, and the heart pale. But I have finished. Believe her Innocent, Madam; so that Errour wounds none but me, you shall never find me busie to prevent a danger; nor had I spoke now, but for your sake, and to preserve the Princess <hi>Fidelia.</hi> Read that Letter.—Nay, then I have lived too long; That frown this E|vening <stage>He offers her a Letter and she refuses it. He pulls his Playsters from his wounds.</stage> had saved <hi>Baptista,</hi> and malice had been prosperous, O for those wounds I gave him; those would have cured this misery; for when <hi>Fidelia</hi> frowns, why should <hi>Sforza</hi> live? but I talk, and prevent what these would do—Bleed, and weep, <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s lost.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sforza,</hi> brother, hold; for Heavens sake, hold; <hi>Fidelia</hi> bids you hold, <hi>Sforza;</hi> O stay, what misery do you fly to? your friend calls, and bids you stay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Sforsa.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>You wrong me, Madam; Those that can and will go, I scorn to hold.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>But those that obey you ought not to tread upon; why did you refuse to read the Letter, which might have quit|ted him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Because I have miseries enough, and will not hunt that knowledge which will but distract my mind. I am now ready for my Grave, and will not go a step out of my way to avoid it, but here stand and well-come fate; for since I have lived to see Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> angry with me, for a word, when passion and misery had distracted me, why should I desire to live? 'tis folly, 'tis madness, since I cannot hope a remedy for my sick mind; when he, who forgave his Enemies a murder would not forgive <hi>Fidelia</hi> a passi|onate word? O Madam, this Cruelty in your brother makes me invite malice and Murder. Come, both <hi>Baptista</hi> and <hi>Martino,</hi> come, come all that hate <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and see your selves reveng'd upon her, and behold her withered by her friend, see all she gloried in; Her
<pb n="190" facs="98"/>
friendship, and her Faith in <hi>Sforza,</hi> like early blossoms, by untime|ly storms, struck and blasted; but why do I hold this Infection— <stage>She throws the Letter away.</stage> Yet 'tis well-come, since it brings news of <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s death; and lest nature should grow weak, and tempt me to save my self, thus to the fire I offer all my means of safety.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The Scene must present a Chimney, in which she throws the Letter and goes out.</hi> (Victoria <hi>snatches up the Letter.)</hi> [Exit <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>Their passions must have way; 'Tis time, not Reason must prevail; Love, whose glory is built upon our misery, and our griefs his Triumph still, and our fears his food! Tyrant! whom none serves but slaves; Force, not affection, fills thy Train; who cares not to have his Servants splendid or great; The Pale, Lean, and desperate fill thy Court, which makes me fear, Reason, nor the gods come not there; But this is no time to dispute thy power. I will read this dangerous Letter.</p>
                        <floatingText type="letter">
                           <body>
                              <head>The Superscription.</head>
                              <opener>For my Friend, Count <hi>Baptista.</hi>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>KNow, the Duke was this day dangerous sick of his Imposthume, and he is yet without hopes of life;</hi> Sforza <hi>has notice of our de|sign; and if you strike not in time, all our hopes are desperate; if he out|live this day, and the Duke die, your hopes in</hi> Fidelia <hi>are lost; for we are certain, she and the prince hold Intelligence; The Dutchess salutes you;</hi> Cosmo <hi>is past in a Disguise, to fight with</hi> Sforsa; <hi>if you meet him secure him, till you hear from us; for the Dutchess will not ven|ture him in such a Danger as a Duel against the Prince; upon whose success all our designs and Hopes depend. Farewell, and burn this Letter: C. is the Messenger, to whom you may impart how business stands.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Yours, Martino.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>The other name is blotted out, O heavens! what a plot was here, to ruine all our hopes? This Letter I will shew my Father, whose recovery is miraculous; Heaven sure has lent him some few days, to preserve his name &amp; family; which if he had dy'd must, in this mischief, have shrunk to nothing; sure, when he shall see this paper he will cease to give faith to cursed <hi>Martino.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Ex.</hi> Vict.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza <hi>alone.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>This is his Chamber: Thus disguised he cannot know me, or if he do, nothing shall save him; nor is there such a thing as danger, when men are resolved to die, or Execute; Oh <hi>Fidelia,</hi> thus I will revenge thee on <hi>Sforza,</hi> and preserve thee against <hi>Mar|tino,</hi>
                           <pb n="191" facs="98"/>
I must not think of her, she puts womanish thoughts in my mind, I will knock.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(He knocks.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>One within.</speaker>
                        <p>Who is there?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>One in haste that should speak with the Count <hi>Mar|tino.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Martino <hi>and two</hi> Servants.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Martino.</speaker>
                        <p>How now? your news.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, my Lord, retire to some private place; I have something to say from <hi>Baptista.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Martino.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou art wounded, is the party dead?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, my Lord; but we had a hard bout on't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Martino.</speaker>
                        <p>Speak softly, and follow me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The Scene discovers the old Duke in his Chamber sleeping; his Guard and Physitians about him, and</hi> Carlo. <hi>[Enter</hi> Victoria.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>WHere is the Duke?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Physitian.</speaker>
                        <p>He sleeps, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>I must awake him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Physitian.</speaker>
                        <p>By no means, if you love his health.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>I must, His own, and the health of <hi>Millain</hi> depends up|on my news; Sir, Father, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Who calls?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis I, Sir? your <hi>Victoria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She kneels.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Rise my dear Child, thou wert with me in my dream too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, Sir!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Why weep'st thou?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She gives him the Letter.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>Read that paper, Sir, and save your Son, and speedily, or all our hopes are lost; for Murther and Treason, if not prevent|ed, will sweep your Family from the Earth, and <hi>Millain</hi> no more obey the name of <hi>Sforza.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(He reads the Letter.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven forbid the Execution of this wicked Design.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis not the heavens, Sir, must do it; their part is here in the discourse; you must act now, as their Minister here where Justice and Nature call for your Defence; and if you do not sud|denly Seize <hi>Martino,</hi> who thus long has abused your trust, you will see this last Seene of your life set in the blood of your self, and family.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so horrid it scarce finds my faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>If your goodness defer preventing this mischief till the guilt be visible, here, in few hours, you will see your Son, and my dear Brother, bleeding his own Testimony; and then your Ju|stice can onely punish, and not prevent the Traytor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Good Heaven, 'tis certain; This is his hand, I know the Character; and her modest &amp; Innocent nature confirms it; She durst not else thus confidently, without pregnant proofs, accuse him: Who is there? <hi>Carlo,</hi> command a guard to attend my daughter; Go, <hi>Victoria,</hi> and seize the body of the Count; If he resist, force
<pb n="192" facs="99"/>
him hither, if he yield, be civil; <hi>Carlo,</hi> where is <hi>Julia?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>Wher'ever she be, she dares not appear in this cause.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt all but</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Carlo,</hi> tell the Dutchess I would speak with her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall, Sir;—There is wonder and mystery in this disco|very; how the Devil came she by that Letter? 'Tis the same I gave <hi>Baptista;</hi> This day will be full of mischief; something bold and sudden, or all is lost; I will to the Dutchess with this News; The difficulty will be, how to save <hi>Martino,</hi> they have his hand to wit|ness against him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Cosmo <hi>in his Pilgrims habit.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>By your favour, Sir; I would gladly speak with the Dutchess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Some begging Pilgrim; I am in haste friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>If not with her, Sir, the Count <hi>Martino,</hi> or Seigniour <hi>Carlo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>What is your business with him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>From a friend; and of importance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>I am the man, Sir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Then you know this hand?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, 'tis the Count <hi>Baptista</hi>'s.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, and he salutes you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>What newes!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>This Letter will speak.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(He gives him the Letter, he reads it and goes in.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Stay here, till I call the Dutchess.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>She is guilty; Lust and Murder have stayn'd her soul; <hi>Mar|tino</hi> and this Villain have betray'd her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Julia <hi>and</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Escaped? Is <hi>Sforza</hi> escaped? Where is the Souldier that said he was dead? and my letter in the Dukes hand?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Madam; and the Princess <hi>Victoria</hi> is gone with a guard, to seize the Count <hi>Martino,</hi> with order to bring him, alive, or dead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <stage> aside,</stage>
                        <p>That is good news.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>This Pilgrim will give you a more Exact Account.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>I am full of distraction. Come you from <hi>Baptista,</hi> friend?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>What says my Letter, Madam!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, <hi>Carlo,</hi> we are lost; there is no safety for us, nor hopes of any, since <hi>Sforza</hi> is escaped; This is <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s Act, 'twas she be|tray'd us; but I'll be revenged on her ere I die; where is the poy|son I prepared? this night shall her be last.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <stage> aside,</stage>
                        <p>O horrid wickedness.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis no time, Madam, to think of such poor Revenge; Let us provide for our own safety.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <stage> aside,</stage>
                        <p>Villain, thou shalt fall with the earliest, or I will miss of my Aim.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>What says <hi>Baptista</hi>'s Letter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cosmo</hi> is his Prisoner; and he will detain him, tell we dis|miss him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Something may be built upon that yet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Baptista</hi> himself sore wounded, <hi>Sforsa</hi> escaped, and I must live to see my <hi>Cosmo</hi> stoop to him, and be a subject to the Branch
<pb n="193" facs="99"/>
of that Cedar, which my frowns have shaken, and my dear <hi>Marti|no</hi> too, is lost for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>What said she? her dear <hi>Martino;</hi> O, that I had been born deaf, rather then have heard that fatal sound.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, dare you trust me in this danger, when all is de|sperate; no matter who guides the Helm, if you will consent; I can from this Letter propose something like safety, but 'twill look desperate; this Pilgrim too must joyn, under which habit, <hi>Baptista</hi> says, you will find a Souldier stout and faithful; <hi>Cosmo</hi> is in prison, this is the ground I will build on; haste presently to the Duke, fall on your knees before him, pretend your Son <hi>Cosmo</hi> is murdered; let this Pilgrim second you, and affirm he saw him dead; and, friend, you shall urge you received those wounds in his defence; be but faithful, and bold in this desperate occasion, and thou shalt find a reward beyond thy hopes, or thy wishes; and when he has confirmed it, then call for revenge and justice against the Count <hi>Martino,</hi> for the murder of your Son; say that he is fal|len by his plot; and that you know Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> is marked for slaughter too; seem to know nothing of his escape, or any thing that is past concerning the Princess <hi>Victoria</hi>'s complaint, nor hear what they would say, to inform you; but put on all your craft, and plead with passion; no matter how unreasonable, nor how excessive it appears; the more violent, the more Mother; the more unnatural your griefs appear, your sorrows will be the more taking and infectious; and seem to be distracted with the loss, call for justice, call for present and exemplary justice upon that tray|tor, Count <hi>Martino,</hi> traytor to the Gods, and his friends.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, villain, leave to spit thy venom and thy malice; is this thy gratitude to him that rais'd thee? and can thy narrow soul hope I should be brought to betray my <hi>Martino?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, Madam, you must lay by this womanish humour; 'tis no time to express a fondness when Crowns and Lives are at stake; if you will save him you must take my counsel; If you now appear his friend, 'tis his certain ruine, and your own; to defend him will blot all your credit with the Duke, for the Count is for|feit in his opinion, beyond redemption; and will be lost before you can speak for him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>Let all perish, ere I have a hand in the ruine of my friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Hell of this foolish Love; that blind Boy misleads us more then Fortune or Ambition; is it better to have it said, you loved, or saved <hi>Martino?</hi> Be ruled, and I will save him, at least defer the mischief: thus we may redeem him from this certain ruine which threatens him, by discovery of that Letter; and by this means you may clear all doubts (which are not a few) that you had a share in this plot; and by this way you will move their pity, and turn their hate and fears into love of <hi>Julia;</hi> and thence will grow your power and our safety; in which cloud of tears and sadness <hi>Marti|no</hi> vanishes; for being once a prisoner in the Citadel, which I com|mand, we can through a private way release him when we have re|solved together what to do; and while they are secure in their
<pb n="194" facs="100"/>
minds, believing him a prisoner, we can with the less suspition pur|sue our first designs; for <hi>Sforza</hi> once dead, we shall quickly find life in our plot again. Friend, your Letter admits you to this trust, and you must again joyn in the business; and if you prove faithful you will find a grateful Patron.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>When you have tried me, Sir, speak as you find.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>Be private, and ready till occasion calls; and <hi>Carlo,</hi> see him rewarded for his former service: O <hi>Carlo,</hi> you must excuse my pas|sion, for being unwilling to accuse my friend; but now I confess, 'tis reason that you urged, and the rest we will leave to Fortune.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, lose no time; he is by this a prisoner.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>This Lemon in mine eye, that I may weep, and down with my hair; so: now Fortune if ever thou wert kind to Lovers, assist in this my last great action, that I may revenge and save a friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Go, and be prosperous; let <hi>Julia</hi>'s fortune still attend you, whose tears have still been more powerful then the sword; away Souldier, follow, and observe your—Q.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>To your grief, I shall; O heaven! what have I seen and heard?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Martino <hi>and a Servant.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>SEnd in that Souldier, then haste and find <hi>Carlo,</hi> tell him I have business of consequence with him; this news has given some life to our design; The Duke desperately sick, and <hi>Sforza</hi> living, had been a black day to <hi>Martino.</hi> Now the Duke recovers, and <hi>Sforza</hi>'s death will Crown the work;—Oh, you are welcome; so, shut the door, and tell me, how died <hi>Sforza,</hi> and how <stage>
                              <hi>Enter</hi> Sfor.</stage> fares <hi>Baptasta?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>At the Ferry, Sir, we set upon him, where it cost us many a wound; for he had notice of our design.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>For thy wounds, thou shalt not repent them; where is the Present thou spokest of, from <hi>Baptista?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Here villain, do you know this face? do you stare? is it <stage>
                              <p>Sforza <hi>draws his sword, and discovers himself.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Mart. <hi>draws his sword.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </stage> so horrid that it frights thy guilty soul? What will this sword do then, when justice draws it against a Traytor and a Murderer?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, then Fortune is a Whore still; but, for thy sword it brings no terrour; nor did I set <hi>Baptista</hi> on, because I doubted I could not kill thee my self; but to have it done, and the world not know how.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>I am in haste; this is not all the work I have to do;—So <stage>
                              <hi>They fight</hi> Sfor. <hi>wounds him.</hi>
                           </stage> wary—There I was with you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>And you are mortal too, or that blood lies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="195" facs="100"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>They close, and</hi> Sforza <hi>throws him, and is upon him when</hi> Victo|ria <hi>and the guard break in, and seize</hi> Martino.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Victoria, Giovanni, Ferdinando, <hi>and a Guard.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Then I am lost; <hi>Martino</hi> and all his hopes are withered; 'tis late, I find my shadow grows long, and night comes on apace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>How do you, Sir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Too well, <hi>Ferdinando.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Call a Surgeon quickly; Dear <hi>Sforza,</hi> retire to your Chamber.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>O dear <hi>Victoria,</hi> there is no end of <hi>Sforza</hi>'s miseries; Hea|ven wars against him, and <hi>Fidelia</hi> frowns.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Why do you say so? alas, she weeps, and will know no comfort, since <hi>Sforza</hi> is angry for a word when grief and passion had almost distracted her; pray, go to your Chamber.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>To my grave, <hi>Victoria;</hi> death is welcomer far then this life; till <hi>Fidelia</hi> smiles my heart can know no peace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>I would our fortunes knew no other difficulties; how easie and how certain would our joys be then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo <hi>and</hi> Antonio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>ANd did he hurt the Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir, and they are both wounded.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Generous and noble <hi>Sforza;</hi> well, we must lose no time; <hi>Antonio</hi> away; remember my directions, get those Souldiers in readiness, and stay about the Princesses Chamber; you know my call, when you hear my whistle, be ready; this night must finish all our miseries: and <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s love the innocent shall save, or mis|sing find a grave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The Scene discovers the sick Duke in his Chamber: Enter</hi> Victoria, Giovanni, Ferdinando, <hi>and a Guard leading</hi> Martino <hi>bound.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>SEE here, behold the Monster; ask these Lords if we did not surprize him in the act? executing his Treason upon my Brother, who now lies bleeding of those wounds this Traytor this minute gave him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain, what moved thee to this bloody purpose?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you hear me with patience, Sir; if I be not inno|cent punish me; be pleas'd to produce the Souldier, which now is Prince <hi>Sforza;</hi> by what reason urg'd, I know not, unless it be envy of your favour; who this morning, in disguise, pretended business, and being alone drew upon me; nature and honour bad me defend
<pb n="196" facs="101"/>
my self, these wounds he gave me, and some I gave him; and when he could not himself destroy me, then he cries out, 'tis <hi>Sfor|za</hi> the Prince; at which, Heaven (that only saw the action) wit|nesses how it struck my heart, till fear and amazement disarmed me, and at his feet I threw my self; in which posture his party found me; Come, Madam, 'tis neither honour nor vertue in your soft sex, to design or pursue this bloody purpose.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Julia, <hi>and</hi> Cosmo <hi>holding her; she falls upon her knees to him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>Where is the Duke?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>What means this distraction?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>O, Sir, if ever <hi>Julia</hi> were dear to <hi>Alphonso,</hi> now let her find his justice in all its horrour fall in execution upon that bloody monster: O, let sad fates close those eyes that have smiled upon the blood and ruine of my child.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>What means this? sure she has not heard <hi>Sforza</hi> is escaped.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria </speaker>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <p>Some new plot, I know; 'tis a subtile devil.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>My Son <hi>Cosmo,</hi> all my joy, my deat <hi>Cosmo!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>What of him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>He is dead, he is dead, fallen by murder.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Dead!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh! dead; and by that cursed monster, <hi>Martino;</hi> Hell upon thy black soul for it; O, Sir, let not the Traytor live to re|pent it; why should he find such charity that shewed no mercy to my Son? the ungrateful villain gave my dear <hi>Cosmo</hi> no warning of his grave which <hi>Martino</hi> digg'd; but sent him in haste to answer all his sins: Oh, let me see the villain struck into the earth with as little mercy as he shewed his Prince; and if not suddenly prevent|ed, Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> will meet the same fate; for the villain has writ his name too in the black book of death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo</speaker>
                        <stage> aside.</stage>
                        <p>O strange daring! Heaven, dost thou see and suf|fer this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cosmo</hi> dead? Oh heaven!—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>She faints and falls, they run to the Princess. [Ex.</hi> Vict.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Martino</speaker>
                        <stage> aside.</stage>
                        <p>There is more in this fury of hers then any man yet can judge of, unless all women-kind are damn'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>O, Sir, I beg you'le let them hale the villain to a Dungeon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Where heard you this sad news?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>By this Pilgrim, who past by chance, and took <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s part, in which he received these wounds.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Away to the Castle with the villain; come hither, friend; saw you Prince <hi>Cosmo</hi> fall?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>I saw him they call <hi>Baptista</hi> fall; and he confessed a young man that was then wounded, and now they say is dead, was Prince <hi>Cosmo;</hi> and he then affirmed, in my hearing, a Hermit being by, who lives at the Ferry, that there came order from Count <hi>Martino</hi> to kill Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="197" facs="101"/>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain, do's not thy soul grow pale at this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis not all your plots or malice shall make me quit my own innocence; and when you have murther'd me by a formal process, let <hi>Alphonso</hi> look to his own life, he will find <hi>Martino</hi> was his guard; for me, I scorn to beg my life till it be forfeited; and when ever <hi>Martino</hi> dies, you shall see him do it with less fear then those live with that struck him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Hale that bloody dog hence.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt all, but</hi> Cosino <hi>and</hi> Antonio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Antonio,</hi> the Princess <hi>Victoria</hi>'s tears had so much kind|ness in them; the Balsam has cured all my wounds, and this storm once over, I shall be the happiest of men; away, remember my directions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>I confess, Sir, such a silence as the Princess shewed when she heard you were dead, speaks love more then all that whining passion Poets would express.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear <hi>Antonio,</hi> I cannot be so cruel as to let her heart be afflicted when kindness to <hi>Cosmo</hi> wounds it; and therefore find her and <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and assure them that I live; but conjure them to secrecie, and tell them my life depends upon the thought that I am dead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall obey you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Souldier, come away; the Dutchess stays to speak with you.—This you must wear, 'tis the earnest of her bounty. <stage>He gives him a Jewel.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cos.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis an honour, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Victoria, Fidelia, <hi>and</hi> Antonio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>UPon my life and honour, Madam, he lives; but this se|cret must not pass your breast, for some few days, if you love his life.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>O, Madam, what a change is here? <hi>Antonio</hi> was ever ho|nest, and his friend; and my heart in despight of all that grief and fear which then possest it, believes and hopes in <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>My love to both of you divides my mind; I fear for <hi>Cosmo,</hi> and hope for <hi>Victoria,</hi> yet <hi>Antonio</hi>'s word must not be doubted; dear <hi>Antonio,</hi> once again speak the truth; do not fear, because we are women, to tell the worst of Fates; for know, to deceive us, is twice to wound thy friends.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, it has not been <hi>Antonio</hi>'s practice, nor his trade to lie; and again, if <hi>Cosmo</hi> be not living some strange curse strike me; more I must not say, not can I longer stay, my business calls me hence; which, with your Highness pardon, I must obey.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Antonio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>Since hath changed this Scene, gentle <hi>Fidelia,</hi> let me beg
<pb n="198" facs="102"/>
you will make it a perfect Jubilee; and since your Brother lives, why should mine dye? you saw I mourned yours, and will <hi>Fidelia</hi> kill mine? remember what he has been, and let not one mistake blot all his story.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>No more, Madam; you shall find my Heart both kind and just to <hi>Sforza,</hi> though he were harsh to me; you have not seen him since he was hurt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>No, but I shall now go find him out; and if you will go with me, be certain of a welcome.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>I shall not refuse to go, where <hi>Victoria</hi> and Honour lead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. VI.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza, Giovanni, <hi>and a</hi> Chirurgion.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Giov.</speaker>
                        <p>THis <hi>Chirurgion</hi> has a sovereign remedy to stop blood, 'twas his hand saved the Life of <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> when the rest gave him lost; and I doubt not but 'twill have a good effect upon your Highness.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, we must away; my Father stayes, he has called a Council at his Chamber concerning <hi>Martino;</hi> The Villain shall now pay for all his Treachery; tell <hi>Victoria</hi> she must be there; bid <hi>Richardo</hi> and <hi>Ferdinando</hi> make haste, and let us meet there.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. IV. SCEN. VII.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Alphonso, Julia, Carlo; <hi>to them,</hi> Sforza, Victoria, Ferdinando, Antonio, Giovanni, <hi>and</hi> Richardo. <hi>A Table and stooles, where they set the Council.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>WEighing the sad cause of this Assembly, the Persons too concern'd so near in blood and trust; I shall not need to urge you to a serious Consideration, how we may se|cure our Peace and Person, punishing the past crimes by taking a just Revenge on the Murtherer of my ever dear <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>I owe the world and your Highness many debts, but none that has greater tyes upon me then this your kindness; which has still esteemed and used my <hi>Cosmo</hi> as your Son, whose loss now comes so near my Soul; I cannot mourn his Murther, nor rest in peace, till I know what your Justice will decree for my Revenge. Nor should I appear thus undecently without a mourning garment, but that I hope, my impatiency will find a kind interpretation from these im|partial Judges; Amongst whom, though <hi>Cosmo</hi> was born an Ene|my, yet such was his Nature, that I dare say he has not left one behind him, but that ingratefull, ambitious, and treacherous <hi>Martino,</hi> whose Malice though it onely struck my <hi>Cosmo,</hi> yet it ap|pears by his Letters 'twas levell'd at the root of the Family, my ever Honoured, and your dear <hi>Sforza;</hi> who, though he found the Gods more kind then <hi>Cosmo,</hi> yet I will not doubt his voice to the
<pb n="199" facs="102"/>
Revenge of my Son; though some malicious people would have me believe (what my Heart abhors) that <hi>Sforza</hi> hated <hi>Cosmo.</hi> But I have done, because my Interest in this cause might be thought to sway me against the Justice of what may be pleaded in the defence of this villain; I will now be silent, and leave the Gods and this As|sembly to decree their pleasures, in mine and my Sons Revenge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Though I might urge his sword drawn upon me, when he knew me to be his Prince, and produce these wounds, yet I scorn to name them; and shall onely desire that Letter I sent your <stage>
                              <hi>The</hi> Duke <hi>●ives the Letter to</hi> Fer|dinando.</stage> Highness, by my Sister, may be produced and read, and what that confesses under his hand, (whose Character is well known to all this Assembly) may, according to the Law in that case be judged; 'Twill be observable too, how crafty his Malice has been in ma|king use of our Honoured Mothers Name, so to blind the world from having any design upon Prince <hi>Cosmo.</hi> But Heaven (juster then he hoped) sent that poor Pilgrim, whose honest Heart en|gaged him by chance, by which means, he is fallen in his own practice; And though I will not pursue him upon my own Interest, yet as a Traytor, and Murtherer of my Brother, I think speedy Ju|stice ought to offer his blood a sacrifice to <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                        <p>And to me there is nothing more visible then his guilt, nor any thing so easie as to give sentence upon him; and he has my voice to die some lingring infamous death, to expiate the ingrati|tude <stage>He reades the Letter.</stage> he has shewed his Prince and Friend; And since he could forget the favours and envied honours he has received from both Crowns, and thus, by a bloody Treachery cut from the Earth that hopefull Prince, let him fall despised and unpitied; for, sure, no honest Man can defend or intercede for him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>I am not satisfied with this name that is blotted out, 'tis some one that ought not to be concealed, I hate Treason both in the Root and Branch; no honest Man ought to have mercy on any that wishes it well; and I not onely consent to this present sen|tence upon <hi>Count Martino,</hi> but to all that had a hand in it; that they may share in the punishment as well as in the guilt, without exception of persons.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>He that can be ungratefull will upon occasion be all that is ill; To avoid which opinion, I shall now endeavour to justifie my self Loyal to my Prince, just to those Lawes that must pre|serve this State, and yet not forget to be gratefull to my Friend. The many Obligations I owe to the <hi>Count Martino</hi> are well known both to your Highness and this Assembly. And that, I hope, will excuse me, notwithstanding the past vote, if I shall (as far as Ho|nour and Justice shall authorize me) in this Assembly, defend the Honour of my Patron. First, I would gladly see a legal Con|viction of the <hi>Count;</hi> let the Crime appear, and then the Judge|ment; Let the dead body of Prince <hi>Cosmo</hi> be produced, upon which all this business depends: For who knowes he is kill'd? who saw the Body? There appears to me onely a report made by her Highness, who received the relation from a Pilgrim. 'Tis granted, her condition and authority ought to find faith and pity.
<pb n="200" facs="103"/>
Yet when Life and Honour are at stake, Justice cannot appear too circumspect; And though I will not deny he is dead, yet I will hope he lives, till I see some proof more visible; here is onely a passenger reports it; her Highness (like a kind Mother) believes her fears; and I, like the faithfull Servant of the unfortunate <hi>Count,</hi> will hope 'tis but her fears. And notwithstanding <hi>Count Ferdi|nando</hi>'s Passion, I shall believe this Action in me has much more Humanity then his sentence; I am sure, 'tis Charity, at least, to wish all men innocent; I know, Sir, the <hi>Count</hi> has many Enemies; your Highness trust and favour has made him fit for Malice; and who knowes but this is an Arrow of her shooting? Nay, I know he has been threatened, and when there is occasion will produce to whom. But to the business; here is a Letter produced, and they say the <hi>Counts</hi> hand is to it, and another that subscrib'd put out: why may not those that put out one name, put in another? <hi>Baptista</hi> is the <hi>Counts</hi> Accuser, you all know he was his Enemy, and I know he had reason to be so; yet 'twas your Highness service that gave him that reason: For the <hi>Count</hi> being certain he had ambiti|ous designes, not fit for a Subject to arrive at, (rather then dis|gust him, by telling him he was not worthy of what he aimed at) in Policy, to keep the State quiet, kept him banished. Never smile, my Lord, for this is truth, though the Camp knew it not; And Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> knowes, <hi>Fidelia</hi> was their quarrel; for whom the <hi>Count Baptista</hi> has alwayes born an ambitious Passion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>You know so much, <hi>Carlo,</hi> and are so ingenious, I shall hope, you will confess your knowledge of this Letter too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Your Highness has too much Honour, to fear to speak what ever you know; and if <hi>Carlo</hi> be guilty, pray, Sir, accuse him; <stage>Carlo <hi>speakes aside.</hi>
                           </stage> if not, (though my Prince) I shall beg you will not throw a Doubt upon Me.—(I know he dares not speak, <hi>Fidelia</hi> is too much concern'd.)</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>There will be a time when that may be fit too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Till then, Sir, confident of the Justice before whom we plead, and strengthened by my own Innocence, I am still de|sirous there may be some testimony produced against the <hi>Count:</hi> God forbid Accusations should make Men guilty; if that were so, few were safe that Princes call to their Councils or their trusts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>To the poynt, Sir; what can you say, why this Traytor should not die a publick example, to give a terrour and warning to others?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>When you, that have twice called him Traytor, can once prove him so, then let him die.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferdi.</speaker>
                        <p>The proofs are evident; here is a gallant Prince mur|ther'd, and another sold to slaughter; here is his hand to the bloody contract.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>If your Highness thinks me fit to speak, if there be reason in what I have said, I shall proceed; if not, I have done.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Monster, with what impudence hast thou thus long dared to tempt the patience of thy Prince; And thus, in the Ears and Eyes of his Mother and his friends, excus'd the Murtherer? Clear
<pb n="201" facs="103"/>
thy self from being one in the plot, thou Idolater of that Monster; <hi>Martino,</hi> or both of you shall find a hangman to attend your funer|alls. Traytors! thus to forget the kindness which I have shewed you! Is this the return your bloody minds have made me, for keeping up your Interest with this generous prince? O Sir, let me now beg your Justice may make them as publique Examples of your Justice as they once stood of your favour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphons.</speaker>
                        <p>Be patient, Give him leave to speak; Reason and Ju|stice dwell neer together; and when they either call, or point, you shall find I both hear and see. Proceed, <hi>Carlo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>If 'twere for a private obscure person, Sir, one fled from the Law or Justice; If 'twere for a stranger I pleaded, I should not wonder at this immoderate haste, and impatience to do Justice, or if I were now to inform this Assembly who the Count <hi>Martino</hi> is; There might be something said against the impertinency of such a discourse; But when I onely desire to know why, ere I consent to the death or dishonour of my Patron, one that two hours since all men honoured, one that this morning was trusted and reverenced by all, having had the faith of two Princes, and power of two Prin|cipalities reposed in him; Why should it then seem strange, that I, his Creature, wish and believe him Innocent, That hath the Evi|dence of so many Ages, and so many Princes favours, to plead for him? In whose name I onely desire Justice; Prove his Crime, pro|duce his Treason; shew the Body, proceed Legally, and if <hi>Carlo</hi> be not as ready to pronounce his sentence, as any, then accuse me; But since no one here saw the Prince dead, or wounded, Give me leave, again, to say I hope he is living; and that hope is more kind to the prince, and has more Charity in it, my Lord, then all that furious desire of Revenge which your malice shews; And if you loved Prince <hi>Cosmo,</hi> or vertue, as you pretend, you had rather he were living, and the Count <hi>Martino</hi> Innocent, then to have a prince murthered, that your hate might then see your Enemy destroyed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>Proceed, I shall answer anon, and make it appear, I scorn'd, and not envy'd your Idol.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>The Count, my Lord, had honour and parts would ra|ther deserve your envy, then your scorn; And by that time you have Commanded as many Armies, and govern'd as many Pro|vinces, as he has done, with honour, I shall then Envy your Lord|ship; prevail with your prince, and the world, to give you that esteem and trust he had two hours ago; shew the wounds you have received for your Countrey, produce those Arguments, for a Prince to trust you; 'twill be nobler far, then to sit and bark at one, in his Age, whose youth you bowed to; and you will find, my Lord, the Count has vertue, even to bear this scandal; 'tis not the first misery he has suffred, his fortune has been used to storms; and yet I dare say, the unkindness of some friends (turned Ene|mies this day,) has made his Imprisonment heavier then his first chains, at the loss of <hi>Pavia;</hi> Yet when malice has done her worst, he has the word of two Princes, that he is honest; which when your Lordship can produce, then you may laugh, as he and I do, at the
<pb n="202" facs="104"/>
malice of the world, which still pursues the favorite till he is fit for Pity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Did no body see his dead body; where is the Souldier that brought the news?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphons.</speaker>
                        <p>Let him be called, some one, that knows where he is, fetch him immediately; none stir? who saw him? whence came the Report? are you all silent? all accuse, and none know why?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, my Lord <hi>Ferdinando</hi> knows, sure; His violent and earnest calling for Justice has some ground. My Lord, his Highness would see your Evidence.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis visible enough in thy impudence; will your Highness be pleased to read your Letter, and behold those wounds upon your own flesh; the rest was a Fame I onely met; here is the Traytors hand set to this blood, is that too little to convince a Traytor? Good God? how black and partial is this Court grown; when a few gilded words, (from a party in this mischief) should be able to divert Justice from her Course? and my honest heart must humbly beg pardon, if I take liberty at full to answer this Impu|dence in his Creature; The first part of my wonder is, to find, even the best men are grown tame by Custome; slaved so by a favorite, that their mindes are scarce left free; Even their thoughts are led in Chains, and either dare not, or will not see, blinded either by fear, or Interest, through the mist his greatness throws before their eyes, else We might have grown wise, by our Neighbours miseries, ra|ther then have cherished a Frozen Viper; And whereas he boast|eth of his dead Masters Trust, Ask the deceased soul of Great <hi>Mat|thias,</hi> whether <hi>Martino</hi> be not a false and a bloody Villain? Nay, ask this Assembly, whether he was not a Traytor to that Master? And since I am urged, I must say, I know <hi>Martino</hi> sold the Battel of <hi>Pavia;</hi> And he that would then sell his old Master, and his Coun|trey, will not stick to betray the new one, when he finds a Chap|man; But he has now no need of these low Arts to rise by. Here he finds his way prepar'd, and, by easie steps now gains his designs; Lust, Covetousness, and flattery, in others, make his way; Who finding he growes powerful in your Highness mind, there rests one|ly, darkly to tell what he designs; And then let Signior <hi>Carlo,</hi> and his Emissaries, with all Arts and Diligence, strive who should first understand or serve his will, and procure that his ambitious desires may be offered ere he please to ask them; Nay, to such a height of Impudence his faction is grown, that here, even in the presence of your highness, where the Assembly is made up of the Royal Blood; One of them, and That, our Prince, calling for Justice; for those wounds which yet bleed in our Eyes, instead of punishing the Tray|tor, Behold, with what impudence one of his Parasites dares de|fend him, urging his honours, and his Trusts, so many Armys raised. Fool, those are so many Crimes onely, so many stains, so many why's he should be torn in pieces, being lost, or sold; I speak my own knowledge, this is a secret of the camps, Sir, that holp to buy one of them; since which my soul has abhorr'd the Traytors more for selling that gallant Prince, then him he has murd'red now.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="203" facs="104"/>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>aside,</hi> How came he by this knowledge?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>Here we find the Count confesled Debtor to the State, even by his favorite; and instead of paying it, he would have Cre|dit, to Cozen his Prince again; you confess, he has had his Evi|dence of both Crowns; shew, where he has done his duty; else you will find those Armies, those Provinces, those trusts you boast of, (if ill discharged) stand so many Evidences against him; and he so far from meriting the least grace or favour, for these, 'tis impu|dence to name them. And I dare say, (in the days of liberty and freedom, ere his power awed this Table so, That both Princes and Councel stooped to the Frowns of a Favorite and a Woman) <hi>Mar|tino</hi> had died upon a Scaffold ere he had found a place above his Fellows.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphons.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> you are honest; But yet know the respect you owe this place; else you will find I can be angry.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I shall not dispute against your Highness; yet being called this day where my Honour and Conscience are both at stake, I shall claime the liberty of an honest man, that I may dis|charge my duty both to my Prince and Countrey. What I have said, Sir, is truth; and if I make it not appear, let me answer it with my life; And the day has been, when your Highness would not have check'd me for speaking truth; Nor this Table have let any one man grow so great, by his guilt, that we durst not accuse him; 'Tis an ill President thus to encourage Traytors. Had <hi>Martino</hi> fal|len under your Justice when he sold his first Master, 'twould not have been a crime, in me, to have accused him now. What makes <hi>Carlo</hi> defend him, but he finds he is grown so powerful? non dare speak their fears; And your Highness bounty has so chang'd his condition, and set such a stamp upon him, that he appears the greater part of your self; Nay, the honest part of the world sticks not to say you have forgot what he was. Take heed, Sir, his wickedness be not called yours too; for his Crimes are such, even the Women (you see) have lost their pity for him, and I pray Heaven, it be not too late for your Highness, or Justice it self, to take notice of him; So powerful he is, that the Law dares not speak to him; and he is now so guilty, that he is become Inno|cent; for who is beyond the Laws reach, He is more guilty; And, if not prevented, we shall see him begin to give Laws both to your self and people; to prevent which, again, I beg your High|ness would but read that letter; Behold these wounds, do they speak less then destruction to the name of <hi>Sforza?</hi> Grant <hi>Cosmo</hi> living, Is he Innocent? Behold these wounds given your own Bowels; Do Justice for these, and Justice is easie to all but the wicked; Mercy is first due to the Innocent, and from them, let the guilty beg, and find it; 'tis safer far, then to leave the Innocent to the mercy of a Traytor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>What can you say against <hi>Ferdinando</hi>'s reason? His ho|nest heart will excuse his passion; and grant <hi>Cosmo</hi> living; yet be|hold his Prince wounded and design'd for his grave, if this be <hi>Mar|tino</hi>'s Letter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="204" facs="105"/>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>For the Princes wounds, I can say nothing, but mourn the unhappy accident; The Count made his own answer to that parti|cular; and for the Letter, it ought to be punished with exquisite tor|ture and death, if (as your Highness says) it be proved his; I know his hand, but cannot say, upon life and death, this is his, since the Count denies it; the Souldier would give some light in the busi|ness, could your Highness prevail to have him produced; 'tis not well to conceal or dismiss him at this time, in a business thus im|portant; for his evidence would sway much, either to the clear|ing or convicting of the Count; Treason has that curse with her, she is never quite rooted out; nor justice cannot cut so even, but even truth and innocence it self may suffer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>Who brought this Letter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas I, Sir, gave it your Highness.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>Where had you it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>That I would gladly know.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>I gave it her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>O, then 'twas your Highness brought the first news of this to Court; then I have done, else—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>What else, impudence? speak thy heart, without these abrupt and dark sayings, without your scandalous—else: Or, by my life, there is no place shall priviledge you from being nailed at my foot, you Traytor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, and give good reason for this anger; lest I doubt the justice of your cause.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>If your Highness fears had no more cause to put on your disguise to day, then you have to be angry now, I shall hope the Count innocent in the one cause, as I am in the other.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis enough, Sir, you know there is a cause; and time shall tell it, in the mean time I will take my leave.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>O stay, for heavens sake, stay; for honour and all our peace, stay; and if you know any thing can clear this business, speak it freely; and let not our souls be afflicted with the doubt; speak, Sir, and let the Traytors find the vengeance due to them only; now you afflict the innocent with your doubts and dark speeches.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Madam, let me go before murder has its will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>Why this answer? is this the return for all my kindness and love to <hi>Sforza?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>O impudence!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, 'tis but justice she and all the world desires; the Duke, Sir, would know where you had this Letter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain, Traytor, Murderer, whose impudence has broke my resolution; darest thou call for justice that wertt he Messen|ger of death? thou Traytor, impudent wretch, 'twas thou that gavest this Letter to <hi>Baptista,</hi> and this Ring; let who dare own it, <stage>He lays the Ring down upon the Ta|ble.</stage> and with it, a Murderer.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exit</hi> Sforza</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis sad to have my Prince my accuser; else the Law of Honour would do me justice, and the world find I wear a sword; 'tis hard, Sir, to be thus accused, and no witness dares appear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="205" facs="105"/>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>Give me the Ring, and all leave the place but you <hi>Vi|ctoria,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinando</hi> and; <hi>Giovanni</hi> bid <hi>Sforza</hi> come hither; and <stage>He looks up|on the Ring, and is full of trouble.</stage> you
<hi>Ferdinando</hi> command the Guard to watch this night upon my Chamber, and be you in person with them; this Ring I gave <hi>Julia;</hi> if she be false.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>If?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon,</speaker>
                        <p>If? <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> can you accuse her?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you have patience, Sir, till I prove what I say? if not you will yet see your whole name destroyed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>Speak, but remember I love <hi>Julia;</hi> yet if she can be guilty of this, the earth shall not redeem her; can <hi>Julia</hi> be false to me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>False as hell; 'tis her name is blotted out of the Letter; the Prince in pity of <hi>Fidelia</hi> did it, because he would not have her grieved with the infamy of her Mother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>But what could she hope by killing <hi>Cosmo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>O, Sir, that is a mischief which is yet a Riddle to the world; and secret to all but my self and <hi>Fidelia; Cosmo</hi> lives.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <hi>Alphonso</hi> and <hi>Ferd.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Live! <hi>Cosmo</hi> living!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>I must not, cannot, dare not speak my knowledge, much less my fears; only, for certain, <hi>Cosmo</hi> lives, and <hi>Martino</hi> disho|nours you, and <hi>Julia</hi>'s false; and now the villain is in hold we will make ready our proofs; and, for heavens sake, trust none of them till we have made it appear that they, or we, are faulty; this ac|cusing <hi>Martino,</hi> and railing against <hi>Carlo</hi> in publick, is too gross to blind any eye that has observed them as <hi>Victoria</hi> has done; <hi>Cosmo</hi> went hence in a disguise, to question my Brother about the Com|mand of the Army, which is the true cause why <hi>Sforza</hi> came in disguise to <hi>Millain.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>This is a knowledg your highness should have had sooner, but that we are resolved to accuse none till their treachery is visible; and pray be pleased to keep your old kindness to the Dutchess, and continue your coldness in believing the Princesses accusation, for a day or two, till all things are ready; this night we will meet at your Highness Chamber, and there resolve in order to our busi|ness; and, pray, let the Dutchesses part be concealed, for the Prin|cess <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s sake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>'T will break her heart; the first news of her Brothers death had almost distracted her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>They are a pair of vertuous minds, and I am glad to find <hi>Victoria</hi> so kind to them; and since he●ven has preserved him from this storm, My <hi>Cosmo</hi> shall find I lov'd and valued him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>Let us retire, Madam, that we may get the Guard in arms; and then I will wait upon you in the Princes lodging; our stay may beget their jealousie, for guilt is still upon the Alarm.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphon.</speaker>
                        <p>The Gods bless my child; and, pray, tell <hi>Sforza,</hi> I want not any of that kindness a Father owes to a good Son, though I cry not my love in the streets; which he shall now find, in cutting from my breast what has long been dearest to me, even <hi>Julia,</hi> since she is false.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="206" facs="106"/>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>God forbid, though the tree be guilty, let the fruit plead; <hi>Fidelia</hi> has goodness enough to expiate any crime she can com|mit with wishes, which is all the ill she is yet arrived to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="act">
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Julia <hi>and</hi> Martino, <hi>she in mans apparel, with a Dark|lanthorn.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>YOu are sad, <hi>Martino.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Madam; but my heart's awak'd with this storm; and I am glad to find our mischief was so unsuccessful, since <hi>Julia</hi> could accuse me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>And could'st thou be so faulty as to think <hi>Julia</hi> false? Oh, my soul! had not I my master-piece to act; and though we have bravely gone through with it, 'twas a troubled sea we wrought through to gain this Harbour; and here shall still be <hi>Martino</hi>'s safe|ty, My <hi>Cosmo</hi> is safe; and while the Duke rests in doubt, we must dispatch <hi>Sforza,</hi> let me alone to settle all the rest; this was <hi>Carlo</hi>'s plot; the honest Souldier (that is without) too did his part; whom they are now busie inquiring after; therefore, sor a day or two, till <hi>Sforza</hi> be dead, let him lie concealed here.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sforza</hi>'s death is a counsel I could wish you would aban|don; for though it may serve in this our desperate disease, yet what the success must be those that know there are Gods may easily divine; to murther three such innocents, one of them your own too, 'tis black and terrible; and I fear will be so far from confirm|ing <hi>Cosmo</hi> in the Throne you design him, 'twill rather make him odious to both Nations.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>I know the price of those Jewels; but since the storm would not be resisted, rather then let our Barque sinke we must throw over our richest goods.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Be patient till I am gone, and observe what effect that change will have; <hi>Cosmo</hi> has vertues enough, and needs none of those dark pathes to lead him to a Crown; and though he be inno|cent, yet I fear the Gods should punish our faults upon him; and we but make our selves monsters, and him miserable, only shewing him that Crown which will be snatched from him, and given to some third pretender.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>No matter; if <hi>Cosmo</hi> cannot keep a Crown when we have gi|ven it him, let him that wins it wear it; he is <hi>Julia</hi>'s heir that can succeed her; the generous Conqueror is my child; and I shall hate my self for designing <hi>Cosmo</hi> so much honour, if he want cou|rage to keep it; I am none of that sort of foolish women that love. their own fruit best though it be sower; 'tis thy interest, and the memory of those happy hours that makes <hi>Cosmo</hi> dear to me; I know not why dull custom should make us love a fool or coward, because got in Wedlock; a natural accident in Marriage, and the
<pb n="207" facs="106"/>
cold effect of a dull thoughtless Act, which every Beast and Bird does as well as we; and before it should be said I love <hi>Cosmo</hi> for those Reasons, he should this night fill a grave, with those foolish souls we have condemned, while the brave, the daring and the fortunate were adopted; and I will still believe the Conqueror is our Son, who ere he be; and <hi>Cosmo</hi> changed in the Cradle, though the false Nurse deny it. No, <hi>Martino,</hi> thou hast taught me to know we are our own Gods; those thrive here that dare Fortune, she knows neither conscience nor prayer, she is a woman, young, nak|ed and blind; they say, Youth and Courage binds her; and if <hi>Cos|mo</hi> cannot force a naked woman, let him rest despised for <hi>Julia.—</hi>See where <hi>Carlo</hi> comes. <hi>Carlo,</hi> what news?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Carlo <hi>at a hole in the Vault.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>You have no time to spare; the Duke has all this while been in counsel with his Daughter and <hi>Ferdinando;</hi> and you may find by <hi>Victoria</hi>'s briskness, she knows Prince <hi>Cosmo</hi> is safe; the Guard is in arms too, commanded by <hi>Ferdinando;</hi> and we must expect no|thing but ruine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Cosmo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>And where is the Prince and Princess?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>They are all safe, at the Princes Chamber, upon a visit; we have laid our design, I am now come for the Souldier: Come, friend, when we have plaid this part all is our own; when they are in the grave we will return, and call you; till then, pray be pri|vate here.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Exeunt</hi> Carlo <hi>and</hi> Cosmo, <hi>by the Vault.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. II.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza, Victoria, Ferdinando, <hi>and</hi> Fidelia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                        <p>IF it be possible I will find the Pilgrim, his testimony will confirm all; and then I will return with a guard to prevent the worst of malice.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Kind and faithful <hi>Ferdinando</hi> still; all good success attend thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Sir, retire to your lodging; small wounds neglected may bring a dangerous consequence; you know, Sir, there be many lives depend on Prince <hi>Sforza.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Fear not, Madam, since I have cured those wounds that grief and distraction gave by your displeasure, my heart can know no danger; when <hi>Fidelia</hi> smiles, <hi>Sforza</hi> is all joy and peace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                        <p>Heaven protect the Prince; and when I lose not his value, I care not who frowns; I had wounds too, and they bled as long as <hi>Sforza</hi> was angry; but we are now perfectly happy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>The Gods were kind to <hi>Victoria,</hi> that spared <hi>Sforza,</hi> and preserved <hi>Cosmo; Julia</hi> too is innocent, in spite of Treason, which false <hi>Martino</hi> would have betrayed her into; and time will heal all these wonnds that Love and Fortune have dealt among us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>What noise is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="208" facs="107"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio <hi>and Souldiers, and seize them all.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>Resist not, Sir; these dye, if you resist.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>Is <hi>Antonio</hi> false too? Heaven! is there nothing but trea|chery among men? this I foresaw in that feigned death of <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Antonio</hi> false! perhaps <hi>Cosmo</hi> is dead too; if he be, let thy words stab <hi>Victoria</hi> to the heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>If there be any honest thought left in thy mind, <hi>Antonio,</hi> lead me to the Princess <hi>Fidelia,</hi> that I may dye (what I could not live) her <hi>Sforza.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>O, Sir, these men have added cruelty even to death! had I died yesterday when <hi>Sforza</hi> was angry, 'twould not have been half the grief; but to be reconciled to <hi>Sforza,</hi> and then snatch'd from his friendship, is beyond Murther, cruel. O, Sir, 'tis now too late to say that truth which my modest heart could never find yet strength enough to utter; yet, witness heaven, 'tis a truth my heart will break with; Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> was all the business of my mind, how I loved him I shall not live to tell; yet here up|on his breast, with my last breath, I vow my first and most unspot|ted faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sfor.</speaker>
                        <p>This cold kiss on your fair hand shall be both our <hi>Epitha|lamium</hi> and our <hi>Epitaph;</hi> O, gentle <hi>Fidelia!</hi> we were one in friend|ship, and one in misery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>That the Gods should give to Beasts venom in their eyes, and death in their teeth, to destroy the innocent, and not afford us that power in an hour of misery, for a guard against Murther and Treason.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                        <p>Away, where I appointed, and observe your Order.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exe.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. III.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Martino <hi>and</hi> Julia, <hi>in the same disguise.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>THey have been long, but now I believe he comes; for now I hear a noise in the Vault.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis they.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Ent.</hi> Car. <hi>and</hi> Cos. <hi>at the Vault.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Carlo,</hi> is all ready?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, they are seiz'd and bound, and in the <hi>Cyprus</hi> Grove expect us, your horses too are ready, we shall have the sport to pass that way; and see them whine and dye, and then away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>But whither shall I go? that I may hold a correspondence, and advise you of my resolutions, as occasion presents.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
                        <p>You must find out my Son and Count <hi>Baptista;</hi> but you must not let the foolish Boy know of what is past; his passion makes him deaf to all our reasons.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, come dispatch, Sir, the time is pretious.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, this shadow goes, you see, forced hence by cruel stars; other joy I never knew then <hi>Julia</hi>'s friendship, with whom I must leave this parting kiss. Farewel to all that is dear to <hi>Mar|tino;</hi>
                           <pb n="209" facs="107"/>
witness my Soul, I have no joyes but in those Eyes, and till we meet again my sad heart will know no peace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Farewell, <hi>Martino; Julia</hi> can yet say she found a friend that was faithful, and 'tis not in Fate to divide our hearts; How unwillingly shall I let my Eyes lose this object, witness all the kind|ness that my life has shewed thee; I should hate my self, if I thought I had words to express how much I have loved <hi>Martino.</hi> Farewell, I have too much Woman in my Eyes, I cannot suffer this separation without tears; Separation is death of Friendship, my Soul and I now part. <hi>This kiss to my dear</hi> Cosmo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Ye Gods, what do I see and hear? O Villain, Villain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Go afore with the Lanthorn.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Cosmo <hi>goes afore, with the light down the hole,</hi> Carlo <hi>and</hi> Martino <hi>follow him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Carlo,</hi> give me your hand.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. IV.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza, Fidelia, Victoria: Antonio <hi>and the Souldiers bind them to the Tree.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>WHy dost thou delay thy bloody purpose? If it be Repentance holds thy hand, make it good; I will purchase it at any rate to save those Innocents; and I will die too, that thou maist have thy reward from those that hire thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidel. Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>O Sir, we hear them coming; now 'tis the time, farewell for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                        <p>Are they bound?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Sir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis they, wear your swords in readiness.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cosmo <hi>with a light,</hi> Carlo <hi>and</hi> Martino <hi>following him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Where are they?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>In the Arbor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Let us dispatch them, <hi>Carlo,</hi> and away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Cosmo <hi>whistles,</hi> Antonio <hi>and the</hi> Souldiers <hi>seize</hi> Martino <hi>and</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Hah! O <hi>Carlo</hi> we are betray'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>What noise is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>This way, <hi>Antonio.—</hi>Do you see this sight, Sir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>They lead them after the light to the place where the Princesses and the Prince were bound.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, what is thy meaning? art thou false, or no? Why dost thou fright our hopes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Upon them, and dispatch; you will find this no jesting matter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha, <hi>Martino</hi> at liberty?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Martino</hi> loose? nay then we are lost for ever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Why dost thou not kill them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="210" facs="108"/>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Or let me do it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>That is the Souldier brought news of my Brothers death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>And that face I have seen before.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I thought you had forgot it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>No, 'twas thou that savd'st me, when <hi>Baptista</hi> would have murthered me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>What sayes he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Enough to satisfie me, we are all betray'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I saved you once.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>And why shouldst thou not again be honest? Threats are lost where they meet Minds resolved like ours; yet if thou dar|est save these, they will pray so faithfully for thee, that thou maist kill me and be forgiven; All the horrour thou canst put into thy look I can despise; for the valiant man, in his first thought, digests the necessity of death; And since we cannot avoid that sight, I have long since Philosophyed upon my grave, as the second womb, and the certain way to the other world, as my Mothers led to this; and he that is honest onely sees those dangers. The guilty trembling Coward, 'tis he that tasteth the bitter cup, while his pale Soul labours and feels the throws of every apprehended Dart, whose anguish <hi>(Gentle Fidelia)</hi> is in leaving thee, and kind <hi>Victoria;</hi> Those that fear him suffer in every thought, and languish in ex|pectation; For, dying, not death is the wound; and when death will appear, though in a Fever, <hi>Martino, Carlo,</hi> Treason and the Sword, are there.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>O <hi>Sforza,</hi> talk of death, but not of parting; when we can die without that, these threatned wounds are welcome; Fever, Sword, nor Treason, I fear not, they are our slaves, and would be tame things if death and malice (Enemies to Nature and <hi>Fidelia)</hi> did not set them on to destroy Noble <hi>Sforza.</hi> O be still that good man, and let not these Villains prevail with thee to murther the Prince; Hell and curses are on their side, Innocence and Virtue on the Princes; if thou kil'st him, thou art damn'd; save him, and become an Angel.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Strike, fool, or she will talk thee to the Gallows; Dos't thou not know the intent in Treason, is as guilty and as mortal as the blow?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou art a fool, we are all betray'd; and now I see him thorow all his cloud; 'tis <hi>Cosmo, Carlo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Cosmo <hi>discovers himself.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis so, horrid Villain; what can thy Soul tell thee now, but death and misery attend thee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cosmo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cosmo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis my Brother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Villain, canst thou look upon this spectacle? Do's not thy Soul melt with horrour? Dogg, I will kill every limb of thee apart. Kill that Villain.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[The</hi> Souldiers <hi>kill</hi> Carlo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Carlo.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh! oh!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[He dies.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I beg your pardon for this fright, there was no safe|ty
<pb n="211" facs="108"/>
without it; I could not else have betray'd these Monsters from their security, but with the hope of such a bait; But now I will offer their hated limbs a sacrifice to all our fears.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>O my <hi>Cosmo,</hi> joy of my life, unbind the Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I have another business to dispatch first; I must be grate|full as well as just; The sword, <hi>Antonio.—</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Ant. <hi>gives him a sword.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you know it, Sir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and what of it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>When I was down in the battle of <hi>Pavia,</hi> then thou be|stridst me, and gavest me this with a wish I might never lose when I drew it against my Enemy; Here, take this other, while I prove thy wish upon thee. <hi>Antonio,</hi> if I fall, let the Law proceed to Justice against this Villain, and secure the lives of these Princes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Why do you arm the Traytor?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>There is no danger in a known Traytor: 'tis the Trust that makes them dangerous; and Traytors in the field are but upon their way to Execution.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>I will not hope to escape; yet I have known the day when I would have forced my safety thorow more stops then your Arm threatens; But I was innocent then, and yet the greatest of <stage>[Aside.]</stage> my Crimes is <hi>Cosmo;</hi> and Heaven is just in making him my scourge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>I will hear no more.—That for <hi>Fideli●.</hi>
                           <stage>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Theyfight and are both wounded.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Martino <hi>falls.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>For <hi>Martino,</hi> that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>For <hi>Sforza,</hi> that, and that, and that for <hi>Julia;</hi> let that name sink thee and thy Soul.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                        <p>I faint, O <hi>Cosmo!</hi> I have yet kindness enough in all this blood, to fear and pity what Fate attends thee that hast kil'd thy Father; a secret yet to <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>What said he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>No matter what.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>How do you, Sir? has he hurt you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, but not much; Take up their Bodies, <hi>Antonio,</hi> and carry them to my Mothers Lodging; Madam, to prevent this danger, I was fain to break my word with your Highness; and that necessity, I hope, will plead your pardon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fide.</speaker>
                        <p>I am glad, you had a reason for that fault.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>The Story of this accident, how laid and how prevent|ed, will ask an ages time to relate; but till the danger is past we must defer it; and I must beg, for an hour or two, you let me lie conceal'd, and in this disguise, till I have finish'd my work; I must now find my Mother; O Sister, she must be reclaimed with Tears, not Wounds; And I must beg your Highness company, to make her shame the greater. The horrour of her designes I will present unto her as things executed; and when I have brought her to a repentance, and a despair of Peace, then, as a Mercy beyond her hopes or merit, she shall know how Heaven has miraculously preserved her innocency from all this blood; This way I hope to reclaim that unfortunate Woman, now the authors of her sins are gone.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray lead the way.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <pb n="212" facs="109"/>
                     <head>ACT. V. SCEN. V.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Julia <hi>alone, in Mans Cloathes.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>THis night is full of change; within this hour nothing but despair, yet now my heart has Joy again; and <hi>Sforza</hi> once dead, <hi>Victoria</hi> shall marry <hi>Cosmo;</hi> The fright <hi>Carlo</hi> will put her in, when she sees <hi>Fidelia</hi> die, will make her proud heart stoop to <hi>Cosmo,</hi> I know she loves him; This day her Passion appear'd, at the report of his death; and though she pretends that she has vowed her self to a Monastery when her Father dies, yet I doubt not but she may be won to forsake that cold pretence for a warm Palace; Those Nuptials will crown all my thoughts; and then 'twas a happy loss of <hi>Pavia,</hi> if we gain <hi>Millain;</hi> both which will be the reward of my long travel. The Duke must die ere they can Wed; for since we are stept in, we must now go thorough with the work: Lust and ambition know no bounds; and rather then we will see my <hi>Cosmo</hi> less then we design him, we will raise new diseases, scourges of the time, and Act what Age and sickness could not do. What noise is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>[Enter</hi> Cosmo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, the Count, and <hi>Carlo,</hi> kiss your hands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Are they gone?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>And the rest? how? how?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Dead, all Dead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>And was not <hi>Sforza</hi> sad to depart with <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and the World?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>They made a great Ceremony of it; and by my troth, it was sad; <hi>I did what I was not wont to do,</hi> I pityed him; for 'twas a gallant and a stout Gentleman; the Women too lamented so, it almost stagger'd my resolution; and I think, though your soul hates them, 'twould have grieved your heart to have seen them part; She that died, <hi>(Fidelia</hi> I think you call'd her) fell, ere we struck, upon the sight of <hi>Sforza</hi>'s death.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <stage> aside,</stage>
                        <p>Are you so pityful? he will tell, if not prevented.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, the Count bid me tell your Highness, he thinks it fit <hi>Carlo</hi> dies too; for he knows too much, and grows too sawey, upon the Trust you have given him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>We will think on't; let us talk no more at this time, 'tis late; is any body stirring in the Gallery?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Madam, all is whist.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Take this purse, and conceal thy self for a day or two, and then find <hi>Martino;</hi> for I would have thee always neer him; thou hast a bold heart, and a ready hand; here, give him this Ring from me; you wear a privy Coat?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>The more fool you, in these dangerous Occasions; I will try.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She stabs him.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh! hold, wretched Woman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She stabs him again.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="213" facs="109"/>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou art too pityful a fool to trust a Crown to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cosmo.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold, hold, 'tis <hi>Cosmo</hi> that thou hast murdered.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>What said he? <hi>Cosmo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She runs to him.)</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Sforza, Victoria, Fidelia, Antonio <hi>and Souldiers, with the dead Bodies of</hi> Carlo <hi>and Martino.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>O my Brother! poor <hi>Cosmo!</hi> unfortunate youth!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victo.</speaker>
                        <p>Cursed Woman, shame of thy Sex, what hast thou done?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Inhumane Act, O <hi>Julia,</hi> thy soul will ake for this; lift him up <hi>Antonio,</hi> and send for a Surgeon quickly, some one raise the Court; Try if there be any hope of life.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sforza</hi> alive? and <hi>Fidelia</hi> too? <hi>Cosmo</hi> dead? and <hi>Martino</hi> Dead! O wretch, 'tis too sad a Truth; 'tis he, my dear <hi>Cosmo?</hi> Thou wert my beloved sin, all my crimes were loves to <hi>Cosmo,</hi> and now my greatest sin is thy blood; all that I loved dead? And all <stage>She Looks about her.</stage> those I hated living? Hence foolish Woman, quickly be gone; what business hast thou now upon the Earth? despair, and die; I cannot talk, my grief is too great for words, and yet I could be angry with fate; But 'tis too late; Make room, <hi>Cosmo,</hi> for thy mother: I struck not thee with half so good a will; Thus I shall be <hi>Julia</hi> still, my story is of one piece now.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She stabs her self, and falls.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vict.</speaker>
                        <p>O! hold her desperate hand—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(They run, to take the Dagger.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>No, 'tis too late, <hi>Antonio; Julia</hi> was <hi>Julia</hi>'s Fate; yet ere I die, you that live, forgive, and bring <hi>Fidelia</hi> hither. <hi>Fidelia,</hi> whom my life hated, but my death loves, forgive thy mother; and live still the thing she hated, the Religious, Chaste, and faithful <hi>Fidelia;</hi> and let thy name redeem the Honour I have lost, in story; does any know how <hi>Martino</hi> came by his death?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, Madam; <hi>Cosmo,</hi> in Duell, killed him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Julia.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cosmo</hi> kill <hi>Martino?</hi> Nay, then 'twas fate, not <hi>Julia,</hi> struck <hi>Cosmo;</hi> Unfortunate youth! wicked and guilty by chance; What fate guided him to <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s sword? Heavens! None but a Son to spill a Fathers blood, and a Mother to revenge it!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>(She dies.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>What does she say?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Antonio.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I am loath to be the Author of such a scandal; yet I heard <hi>Martino,</hi> when he fell under <hi>Cosmo</hi>'s sword, tell him he had killed his Father; your Highness knows their Friendship has been scandalous, though the world durst not speak of it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter the Duke,</hi> Ferdinando, Giovanni, <hi>and a Guard.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Dead? heaven forbid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray, Sir, retire the Scene is too sad; for a Fathers Eyes; The Story, Sir, will be fitter to be mourned then spoken of; the Gods have taken a severe vengeance upon those people, and we may lament, but not redeem, their faults; Come, Madam, when you can digest this grief you shall find <hi>Sforza</hi> is ready to pay all his vowes to Love and Friendship.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Victoria.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Brother, Sister, Father, all that were guilty, in ma|king me break my vows with Heaven, here I beg the dead Body
<pb n="214" facs="110"/>
of my <hi>Cosmo</hi> may be interred in our Chappell, where again I vow to waste my days in Holy Orders, and with the Penance of my life redeem my past faults, and lament poor <hi>Cosmo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fidelia.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, Sir, let me retire too; Let not such a poysonous fruit be cherish'd in your breast, lest the displeased Gods take some farther vengeance on Our Family; and so distract my soul, to find Prince <hi>Sforza</hi> punish'd for <hi>Fidelia</hi>'s sins.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
                        <p>This misery is so strange, and so infectious, that even my heart grows sick of Love, and fear; Heaven, if thou hast decreed more affliction for this gentle maid, let them not fall till I am earth. O <hi>Fidelia,</hi> nothing but death shall divide me from thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Alphonso.</speaker>
                        <p>Take up their Bodies, and let all Funeral Rites be gi|ven to these unfortunate people: and since they have born the pu|nishment of their Crimes, let their faults have no more memory, but, with them, lie buried in their Grave; And let their Example teach us; Impious men may play with Heaven, but they can hope no better fate to Win. Dry thy Eyes, <hi>Fidelia,</hi> Heaven forbid, thy Innocency should suffer for the Crimes of others; To whom there is a reward due, as a punishment to these; And if <hi>Sforza</hi> do not pay his Debts to <hi>Fidelia,</hi> he will neither have Heavens nor my blessing; and when Our griefs have given place, I shall onely wish, that my last Scene in this world may wait on thy Hymens; for I am quite tyred with the Affliction of this World, and will onely refresh my soul with seeing <hi>Fidelia</hi> and <hi>Sforza</hi> happy; And then I care not how soon Nature and Death decide their dispute; That I might make an <hi>Exit</hi> from this Theatre where misfortune hath made me Act a Part in so sad a Tragedy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         </TEI>

