<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Six new playes ... the five first were acted at the private house in Black Fryers with great applause, the last was never acted / all written by James Shirley.</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>244 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 September (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12294493</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing S3486.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Woodward and McManaway 1134.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">58985</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59992</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Six new playes ... the five first were acted at the private house in Black Fryers with great applause, the last was never acted / all written by James Shirley.</title>
                  <title type="alt">Plays. Selections</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, William, fl. 1617-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 v. : port.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Robinson ... and Humphrey Moseley ...,</publisher>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>Added t.p. in Latin with port. engraved by W. Marshall, dated 1646.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Each play has separate paging and special t.p.; all are dated 1652 except The court secret, 1653.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>"Never printed before"</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Appended to The Cardinall is "A catalogue of the authors poems already printed".</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of original in Folger Library.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2001-12-12.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="118"/>
                  <pb facs="118"/>
                  <p>THE
IMPOSTVRE
A
Tragi-Comedie,
<hi>AS</hi>
It was Acted at the private House
IN
<hi>BLACK FRYERS.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WRITTEN
By JAMES SHIRLEY.</p>
                  <p>Never Printed before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Humphrey Robinson</hi> at the Three
Pigeons, and <hi>Humphrey Moseley</hi> at the Prince's
Armes in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Curch-yard.
1652.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="119"/>
                  <pb facs="119"/>
                  <head>TO
SIR ROBERT
BOLLES
Baronet.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>_IT hath been a Complement with
some, when they have treated
Friends, to profess a barrenness
in that which they had prepared not without
studied charge, and Curio sitie. As I was ne|ver
so insolent to magnifie my own, being
best acquainted with my weak abilities: so
I should deserve a just affront to my self, and
undervalue your person, to present you with
any thing were first cheap in my own opini|on.
Sir, this Poem, I may with modesty affirm,
had a fair reception, when ●t was personated
<pb facs="120"/>
on the stage, and may march in the first rank
of my own compositions, which directed now
by my humble devotion, comes from the press
to kiss your hand, and bear your noble Name
in the dedication. I cannot have so much pre|judice
upon your nature, to think you will de|cline
it, and should I abate those other cha|racters
of honour that shine upon you, your in|dulgence
to Musick and singular love to the
worthy professors eminently, shew the harmo|ny
of your soul, and while Poetry is received
a Musicall part of humane knowledge, I can|not
despair of your candid entertainment. Sr.
I beseech you take it, as an earnest of my
thoughts to serve you, I am assured it brings
with it, beside the acknowlegment of your late
obligation upon me, ambitious desires to pre|serve
my interest in your favour, while I sub|seribe
my self,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </closer>
                  <signed>The humblest of your
Honourers,
<hi>Ia: Shirley.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </div>
               <div type="prologue">
                  <pb facs="120"/>
                  <head>The Prologue.</head>
                  <l>OUr poet not full confident he says,</l>
                  <l>When Theaters free vote had crown'd his plays,</l>
                  <l>Came never with more trembling to the stage,</l>
                  <l>Since that poetick S●hism possest the age.</l>
                  <l>A Prologue must have more wit than the play,</l>
                  <l>He knowes not what to write, fears what to say.</l>
                  <l>He has been stranger long to'th' English scene,</l>
                  <l>Knowes not the mode, nor how with artfull pen,</l>
                  <l>To charm your airy soules; beside, he sees</l>
                  <l>The Muses have forsook their groves, the trees</l>
                  <l>That fear'd no thunder, and were safely worn</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Phaebus</hi> own priests, are now rudely torn</l>
                  <l>By every scurrile wit that can but say</l>
                  <l>He made a Prologue to a new—no play.</l>
                  <l>But let 'em pass; you Gentlemen that sit</l>
                  <l>Our judges, great Commissioners of wit,</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd I may one humble motion make,</l>
                  <l>'Tis that you would resolve for th' authors sake,</l>
                  <l>I'th' progress of his play not to be such</l>
                  <l>Who'l understand too little, or too much</l>
                  <l>But choose your way to Iudge; to th' Ladies one</l>
                  <l>Address from the Author, and the Prologue's done,</l>
                  <l>In all his Poems, you have been his care,</l>
                  <l>Nor shall you need to wrinckle now that fair</l>
                  <l>Smooth Alablaster of your brow, no fright</l>
                  <l>Shall strike chast eares, or dye the harmlese white</l>
                  <l>Of any cheek with blushes, by this pen</l>
                  <l>No Innocence shall bleed in any scene,</l>
                  <l>If then your thoughts secur'd you smile, the w●se</l>
                  <l>Will lear● to like by looking on your eyes.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <pb facs="121"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>Persons.</head>
                     <item>Duk <hi>of</hi> Mantua.</item>
                     <item>Honorio, <hi>his Son.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Flaviano, <hi>The Dukes Creature.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Leonato, <hi>The Duke of</hi> Ferrara's <hi>Son.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Petronio, <hi>a noble man of</hi> Ferrara.</item>
                     <item>Bertoldi, <hi>an insolent Coward, son to</hi> Florelia.</item>
                     <item>Claudio, <hi>a creatvre of</hi> Flaviano.</item>
                     <item>Volternio</item>
                     <item>Hortensio</item>
                     <item>Colonells.</item>
                     <item>Antonio, <hi>a Gent.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Frier.</item>
                     <item>Pandolfo, <hi>a servant of the Tavern.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Soldiers.</item>
                     <item>Servants.</item>
                     <item>Abbess.</item>
                     <item>Fioretta, <hi>Daughter to the Duke of</hi> Mantua.</item>
                     <item>Donebella, <hi>Sister to</hi> Leonato.</item>
                     <item>Juliana, <hi>A Mistris of</hi> Flaviavo.</item>
                     <item>Florelia, <hi>A noble Lady, Mother to</hi> Bertoldi.</item>
                     <item>Ladies.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="play">
                  <pb facs="121"/>
                  <head>THE
IMPOSTURE</head>
                  <div n="1" type="act">
                     <stage>Enter Duke Honorio, Flaviano.
(at severall Doors.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <l>_NO Army yet discover'd?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>None.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>We are lost.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Despair not sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>Away, thy confidence is folly,</l>
                        <l>Is not danger round about us,</l>
                        <l>From every part destruction staring us</l>
                        <l>I'th' face? this City, like a fatall Center,</l>
                        <l>Wherein the bloody lines of War, and Famine,</l>
                        <l>Prepare to meet?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>And every minute we expect a Battery.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>The walls are not so easily made dust,</l>
                        <l>As the besiegers would perswade our faith;</l>
                        <l>Disarm not your own hearts, my confidence</l>
                        <l>Tells me we sha'not suffer, the Duke of</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ferrara</hi> may send yet to raise the siege.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>Fond Boy, it was thy counsell to depend</l>
                        <l>Upon his aids, and promise <hi>Fioretta,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thy Sister, with so great a dowry to</l>
                        <l>The Dukes vainglorious Son; fame has beli'd</l>
                        <l>His valour, and we now are cheated of</l>
                        <l>Our lives and Dukedome.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="2" facs="122"/>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, with my duty safe, let me intreat you</l>
                        <l>Not stain the character of a Prince so much;</l>
                        <l>The interest we have in that great Title</l>
                        <l>Should make us wise in our belief; for when</l>
                        <l>Princes break faith, Religion must dissolve,</l>
                        <l>And nature grone with burthen of the living</l>
                        <l>Beside his Son <hi>
                              <unclear>Leonato</unclear>,</hi> how ever</l>
                        <l>Traduc'd or sullied by some Traitors envy,</l>
                        <l>Deserves a noble fame, and loves the hope</l>
                        <l>Of our <unclear>alliance</unclear>; I ne'r saw his person</l>
                        <l>But, twere a sin, honor could not forgive</l>
                        <l>In us to question him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>We fool our selves;</l>
                        <l>Lets think of timely <unclear>Articles</unclear> and yield.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Whilst there <unclear>is hope</unclear> of mercy.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon</speaker>
                        <l>Oh! this want</l>
                        <l>Of man will make all our well meaning starres</l>
                        <l>Forfiet their kind aspects, &amp; turn their influence to death</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>My Lord, I cannot be concern'd in name</l>
                        <l>And honour with your <unclear>person</unclear>, whose least blood</l>
                        <l>Is worth ten thousand arteries of mine,</l>
                        <l>Therefore while such necessities invade us</l>
                        <l>I cannot but prefer your lives, and in</l>
                        <l>My duty counsell, you would think of what</l>
                        <l>Is offer'd here, rather than hazard all</l>
                        <l>By a vain expectation of an Army</l>
                        <l>From <hi>Leonato,</hi> who with all his forces</l>
                        <l>Is not yet sure to prosper in our cause.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <l>Consider that <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, should Heaven</l>
                        <l>So smile upon us, that his sword o'r come,</l>
                        <l>This to weak apprehension may promise</l>
                        <l>Our glory, but examine well the close,</l>
                        <l>There may be greater danger in his victory,</l>
                        <l>Than all our want of him can threaten.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>You perplex my understanding.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="3" facs="122"/>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>He expects your Sister the reward of his great service.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Is it not Justice?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, forbid it goodness,</l>
                        <l>He should not thrive in his fair hope, and promises;</l>
                        <l>But if her Highness find not in her heart</l>
                        <l>Consent, to meet the Prince with love and marriage,</l>
                        <l>Who shall defend us from his power? that must</l>
                        <l>Keep us in awe, and this earth, panting yet</l>
                        <l>With frights and sufferings of the Warre.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>It is my wonder Lord <hi>Flaviano,</hi> your wisdome</l>
                        <l>Should weave these wild impossibilities;</l>
                        <l>My Sister not consent? nature, her birth,</l>
                        <l>Obedience, honor, common gratitude,</l>
                        <l>Beside ambition of what can be hop'd for</l>
                        <l>To make her happy, will give wings to her desires.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>I cannot tell.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>I cannot think,</l>
                        <l>Your reason sir can be so much corrupted,</l>
                        <l>To look upon my Sister with that fear,</l>
                        <l>She should not fly to meet our great preserver;</l>
                        <l>Do you believe, she now 'mong holy Virgins,</l>
                        <l>Lead thither by her own devotion,</l>
                        <l>During this Warr to pray, and weep for us</l>
                        <l>(Teares, whose clear Innocence might tempt an Angel</l>
                        <l>To gather up the drops, and string for Saints</l>
                        <l>A Christall Rosarie) can wish us safe</l>
                        <l>By his victorious arm, without a will</l>
                        <l>To be her self his own reward? her virtue</l>
                        <l>Must needs instruct her that, and we apply</l>
                        <l>No motive to her heart—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>A shout within.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <l>What news?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Claudio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>From the Watch-tower we descry an Army</l>
                        <l>Marching this way; the Sun which hath thus long</l>
                        <l>Muffled his face in clouds, as it delighted</l>
                        <l>In their approach, doth gild their way, and shine</l>
                        <l>Upon their burgonets to dazle the faint eyes</l>
                        <l>Of our beseigers.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>'<hi>Tis</hi> Leonato.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="4" facs="123"/>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>Our Enemies, whose Troops circle the Town,</l>
                        <l>Are making hast to meet 'em, and the Foot</l>
                        <l>Quitting their trenches, now are gathering</l>
                        <l>Into a body, as it seemes resolv'd</l>
                        <l>To give 'em battle.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <l>We have life again.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>H●norio,</hi> collect what strength we have,</l>
                        <l>And make a sally at your best advantage.</l>
                        <l>'Tis good to engage 'em both waies.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                        <l>How my thoughts triumph allready!</l>
                        <stage>Ex.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <l>Now my Son is gone,</l>
                        <l>Who is not of our Counsell; wee must think</l>
                        <l>How to behave us, if the Prince succeed,</l>
                        <l>Our daughter which wee promis'd him in marriage,</l>
                        <l>Being already sent away, the price</l>
                        <l>Of his great Victory.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Trouble not your self,</l>
                        <l>Great Sir, your wisdom that inclin'd your faith</l>
                        <l>To my true Character of the Prince,</l>
                        <l>And took my counsell for her absence, shall</l>
                        <l>Applaud my future policy; hee's not come</l>
                        <l>To conquest yet, however Princes are not</l>
                        <l>Oblig'd to keep, what their necessities</l>
                        <l>Contract, but prudently secure their states</l>
                        <l>And dear posterity; trust to my care,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fioretta</hi> is no match for <hi>Ferraras</hi> Son,</l>
                        <l>A Prince deep read in lusts, faithless, and cruell,</l>
                        <l>So will a Turtle with a Vulture shew,</l>
                        <l>Or Lamb yoak'd with a Tiger: shee's a pledge</l>
                        <l>Destin'd by better fate to Crown your age</l>
                        <l>And heart with blessings Sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <l>Hark,</l>
                        <l>The d●ums talk lowder, from the battlements,</l>
                        <l>I may behold their fight, and see which Army,</l>
                        <l>Conquest, now hovering in the air, will mark</l>
                        <l>Her glorious perch, upon whose Plumed heads</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="5" facs="123"/>
She may advance, and clap her brazen wings.</l>
                        <stage>Ex.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Soft Alarum</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir I'l attend: <hi>Claudio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>My Lord.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou left'st the Princes <hi>Fioretta</hi> safe at Pla|centia?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes Sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>How did she like her progress? thou didst urge</l>
                        <l>It was my care of her, to take her from</l>
                        <l>The fright and noise of War.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>I did my Lord.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>And did she taste it well?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>To my apprehension exceeding well,</l>
                        <l>And gave me strickt commands</l>
                        <l>To say she will remember, and reward</l>
                        <l>Your love and care of her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Did she name love?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>The very word she us'd, and I return'd,</l>
                        <l>How much your study and ambition was</l>
                        <l>To merit her fair thoughts.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>And didst thou scatter, as I instructed</l>
                        <l>Here and there dark language, to</l>
                        <l>Dissafect her with the Prince, to whom</l>
                        <l>The Duke hath rashly made a promise?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>All; I had fail'd my duty else my Lord.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Call me thy friend, thou hast deserv'd me, now</l>
                        <l>Attend the Duke—so, now my next art must be,</l>
                        <stage>Exit. Claud.</stage>
                        <l>How to come off with with <hi>Leonato,</hi> if his</l>
                        <l>Army prevail, the Duke must be instructed;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Honorio</hi> thinks his Sister still i'th' Nunnery;</l>
                        <l>That thought must be preserv'd; a thousand wheels</l>
                        <l>Move in my spacious brain, whose motions are</l>
                        <l>Directed by my ambition to possess</l>
                        <l>And call <hi>Fioretta</hi> mine, while shallow Princes</l>
                        <l>I make my State decoyes, then laugh at 'em.</l>
                        <stage>
                           <pb n="6" facs="124"/>
Alarum, Enter Honorio lead by Claudio over the
Stage wounded.</stage>
                        <l>The Prince <hi>Honorio</hi> wounded; fate I bless thee.</l>
                        <l>How is it with your highness?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon</speaker>
                        <l>I am shot sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Would it were dangerous—be carefull of him;</l>
                        <l>A curse upon that hand that mist his heart.</l>
                        <stage>Ex. Hon.</stage>
                        <l>So, so, fortune thou shalt have eyes agen</l>
                        <l>If thou wouldst smile on mischief, I will build thee</l>
                        <l>An Altar, and upon it sacrifise</l>
                        <l>Folly and all her children, from whose blood</l>
                        <l>A curled smoak shall rise, thick as the mists</l>
                        <l>That breath from Incense to perfume and hide</l>
                        <l>The sacrifising Priest; sight on,</l>
                        <l>Ye are brave Fellows, he that conquers may</l>
                        <l>Get Honor, and deep wounds, but I the day.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                        <stage>Alarum and Retreat. Then Enter Leonato, Volternio,
Hortensio, and Souldiers in Triumph, at one door; at
the other, Enter Men with boughes of Laurell
singing before the Duke, Flaviano, Claudio.</stage>
                        <lg>
                           <l>You Virgins, that did late despair</l>
                           <l>To keep your Wealth from cruell men,</l>
                           <l>Ty up in silk your careless hair,</l>
                           <l>Soft peace is come agen.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Now lovers eyes may gently shoot</l>
                           <l>A flame that wo'not kill:</l>
                           <l>The Drum was angry, but the Lute</l>
                           <l>Shall wisper what you will.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Sing Iö, Iö, for his sake,</l>
                           <l>Who hath restor'd your drooping heads,</l>
                           <l>With choice of sweetest flowers make</l>
                           <l>A garden where he treads;</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <pb n="7" facs="124"/>
                           <l>Whilst, we whole groves of Laurell bring,</l>
                           <l>A petty triumph to his brow,</l>
                           <l>Who is the Master of our Spring,</l>
                           <l>And all the bloom we ow.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <l>Our hearts were open sir before the gates</l>
                        <l>To Entertain you, I see <hi>Laurells</hi>
                           <unclear> grow</unclear>
                        </l>
                        <l>About your temples, where, as in a grove</l>
                        <l>Fair Victory Enamour'd on your brow</l>
                        <l>Delights to sit, and cool her reeking head</l>
                        <l>And crimson tresses in your shade.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>The City</l>
                        <l>In glory of this day shall build a Statue</l>
                        <l>To you their great preserver, whose tough brass</l>
                        <l>Too hard for the devouring teeth of age</l>
                        <l>Shall eat up Time, to keep your fame Eternall;</l>
                        <l>Our active youth in honor of your name</l>
                        <l>Shall bring agen the old Olympick games,</l>
                        <l>And willing to forget what's past in time,</l>
                        <l>And story, count their years from this dayes triumph,</l>
                        <l>As if the World began but now; the wives</l>
                        <l>As if there were no legends past of love,</l>
                        <l>Shall only talk of you, and your great Valour;</l>
                        <l>And careless how mans race should be continu'd</l>
                        <l>Grow old in wonder of your deeds; our Virgins</l>
                        <l>Leaving the naturall tremblings that attend</l>
                        <l>On timorous maides, struck pale at sight of blood,</l>
                        <l>Shall take delight to tell what wounds you gave,</l>
                        <l>Making the horror sweet to hear them sing it;</l>
                        <l>Their hands at the same time composing Garlands</l>
                        <l>Of Roses, Mirtle, and the conquering Bay,</l>
                        <l>To adorn our Temples, and the Priests, and while</l>
                        <l>The Spring contributes to their art, make in</l>
                        <l>Each garden a remonstrance of this battle,</l>
                        <l>Where flowers shall seem to Fight, and every <unclear>plant</unclear>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="8" facs="125"/>
Cut into Forms of green Artillery,</l>
                        <l>And instruments of War, shall keep alive</l>
                        <l>The memory of this day, and your great Victory●</l>
                        <l>Yet all that can be studied short of you,</l>
                        <l>Our best, a rude Imperfect Monument</l>
                        <l>Of your deserved honors.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are too bountifull</l>
                        <l>In language sir, the service wee have done</l>
                        <l>May merit your acknow●edgment, which though</l>
                        <l>The Justice of your cause directed first</l>
                        <l>To this success, was not without a hope</l>
                        <l>Of a reward you promis'd, and I value it</l>
                        <l>More than you can esteem all your pr●servings;</l>
                        <l>So much hath fame prefer'd your Daughters Virtue</l>
                        <l>To every excellence.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <l>This adds to what</l>
                        <l>Wee held before excess of honor to us.</l>
                        <l>I had but a part i'th' Universall benefit</l>
                        <l>Your Valour gave, but this affection</l>
                        <l>Falls like a happy Influence on my self</l>
                        <l>And blood, whose aged s●●r●ams you fill with blessings.</l>
                        <l>My Daughter shall be yours, in which I sum</l>
                        <l>My lives chief satisfaction. My Lord</l>
                        <l>Go to the house of Benedictine Nuns,</l>
                        <l>Among whose sweet society our Daughter,</l>
                        <l>During this War and tumult, went to offer</l>
                        <l>Her prayers for our deliveran●e.</l>
                        <l>I am in a storm, and now must stand</l>
                        <stage>(aside)</stage>
                        <l>My desperate fate.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Horten.</speaker>
                        <l>I hope shee's not turn'd Nun?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>I should not like it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vol.</speaker>
                        <l>May not we visit the holy house? 'tis pitty so much</l>
                        <l>Sweet flesh, should be engros'd and barrell'd up</l>
                        <l>With penitentiall pickle 'fore their time,</l>
                        <l>That would keep fresh and fair, and make just work</l>
                        <l>For their Confessions. I do not like the women</l>
                        <l>Should be cabled up.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="9" facs="125"/>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <l>I think so.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vol.</speaker>
                        <l>I would this Virgin would be peevish now.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <l>Why so?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>That we might ha' some sport among the Leve|rets.</l>
                        <l>For I would so inflame the Generall</l>
                        <l>He were affronted, that wee should have all</l>
                        <l>Commission to work into the Warren.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Le.</speaker>
                        <l>We do want a person here, whose name is great</l>
                        <l>I'th' Register of honor, it would much</l>
                        <l>Enlarge our present happiness to Embrace him,</l>
                        <l>Your Son the prince <hi>Honorio. Duke.</hi> 'Twas his chance</l>
                        <l>Upon a sally, when your colours gave</l>
                        <l>Us Invitation to the Field, and spirited</l>
                        <l>Our souldiers, to receive a shot, whose cure</l>
                        <l>May excuse the want of his attendance sir,</l>
                        <l>Nor will I doubt his wounds are doubled by</l>
                        <l>The thought he cannot wait upon your person.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Le.</speaker>
                        <l>He should have honor'd us, and made me proud</l>
                        <l>To know, whom so much fair desert hath made</l>
                        <l>Dear in the voice and love of men: but I</l>
                        <l>Shall not despair to see him. We want</l>
                        <l>A limb of our own Army, where is Signior</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Bertoldi,</hi> that came with us to see Fashions?</l>
                        <l>I hope we have not lost him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Horten.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, I know not, I fear hee's slain.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>He wo'not dy so nobly;</l>
                        <l>He'l nere give up the ghost without a Fetherbed.</l>
                        <l>He vvas sick last night at the report vve vvere</l>
                        <l>But three leagues off the Enemy, and call'd</l>
                        <l>For a hot caudle. I that knevv his cold</l>
                        <l>Disease perswaded him to drink, which he</l>
                        <l>Did fiercely as I could vvish, in hope to see him</l>
                        <l>Valiant and vvalk the round, but quite against</l>
                        <l>Nature his ague shook him more, and all the Drink</l>
                        <l>Which vvas the full proportion of a gallon</l>
                        <l>Came out at's forehead in faint svveat; he had</l>
                        <l>Not mov'd ten paces, but he fell dovvn backward</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="10" facs="126"/>
And swore he was shot with a cold bullet; how</l>
                        <l>They rould him like a Barrel back to his Tent,</l>
                        <l>For levers could not raise him to make use</l>
                        <l>Of's feet agen, I know not, nor since saw him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I hope hee's still asleep.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>But when he wakes,</l>
                        <l>And finds the Army marcht away, He dares not,</l>
                        <l>Go home agen alone, &amp; how hee'l venture</l>
                        <l>O'r the dead bodies hither—he has don't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Bertoldi.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>Where is the General?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Here comes our mirth.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>A walking Armorie; noble Signior <hi>Bertoldi.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bertol.</speaker>
                        <l>If you want Pikes or Muskets there, I could</l>
                        <l>Ha brought field peeces, but I durst not venture</l>
                        <l>My chine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Where had you these?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Ask, ask the men I kill'd, if they deny</l>
                        <l>A syllable I'l forswear the Warrs.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>He has disarm'd and rob'd the dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>A coward has impudence to rob a Church.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>He durst not take 'em from a man that had</l>
                        <l>But so much life in him to gasp or grone,</l>
                        <l>That noise would fright him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I rejoyce <hi>Signior,</hi> y'are safe come home.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I would I were at home, and you get me</l>
                        <l>Among your Guns agen—how ist <hi>Volterino?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Flaviano.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>This news wil much exalt your Mothers heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>He is return'd but with a melancholy face.</l>
                        <l>Where is the Princess?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <l>Where is our Daughter?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Where her devotion I fear will make</l>
                        <l>This Dukedome most unhappy, if your virtue</l>
                        <l>Exceed not what is read in other Princes,</l>
                        <l>It was my fear that place, and conversation,</l>
                        <l>Would mortisie too much that active heat</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="11" facs="126"/>
Sh●uld wait on the desires of high-born Ladies.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>The mystery?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Do not you find it? they have nunnified her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, your pardon;</l>
                        <l>She whom first fear and fright of War perswaded</l>
                        <l>To joyn her prayer and person with the Virgins</l>
                        <l>In the religious Cloyster, by what art</l>
                        <l>Or holy magick won, is now resolv'd—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>What, hath she vow'd?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
                        <l>Untill a year be finished</l>
                        <l>By revolution of the dayes great guide,</l>
                        <l>Not to forsake the Nunnery, but spend</l>
                        <l>Her hours in thankfull prayers to Heaveu for this</l>
                        <l>Great victory.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>So, so, It will come to the battery I talk'd on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>It cannot be.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>It must not be</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>I am of that opinion my Lord,</l>
                        <l>It must not be, this is a stratagem.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
                        <l>She humbly praies you would interpret this</l>
                        <l>No breach of filiall piety, nor your</l>
                        <l>Highness a will to wrong so great a merit</l>
                        <l>As hath engag'd all fortunes here, and lives</l>
                        <l>To bleed for you, but weigh in your best charity</l>
                        <l>That duties are first paid to Heaven, the spring</l>
                        <l>And preservation of what makes us happy,</l>
                        <l>And she is confident when you consider—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>How much my honor suffers, to imploy</l>
                        <l>The strength I have to punish this affront.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>A pox upon't, we shall ha' more fighting now</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>I hope you have no thought of any p●●ctice</l>
                        <l>Here to deserve that language?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are abus'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>If you be her Father sir, I must expect</l>
                        <l>What did ingage me hither, and without</l>
                        <l>Delayes, or leave this City in a flame.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="12" facs="127"/>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>More Fire-works?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>In whose Ashes I will bury this foul ingra|titude.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>We are ruin'd all.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>There is not so much danger, to be put</l>
                        <l>In Rank and File with Pye-meat in an Oven,</l>
                        <l>If a man were certaine to come out agen</l>
                        <l>Dow-bak'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet stay. I have considered,</l>
                        <l>I may have leave to see this Frozen Lady.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>We are more undone.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Your person may prevail sir,</l>
                        <l>And by some better charm, gain her consent,</l>
                        <l>Or if you please not to ingage your self</l>
                        <l>Upon the trouble of a hasty visit,</l>
                        <l>The presence of her Father, and what else</l>
                        <l>We can prepare to keep your smile upon us,</l>
                        <l>Shall be inforc'd, to clear how much we aim</l>
                        <l>At the perfection of your wishes.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>So, so. Leon. Prospen.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I have now● courage sir to serve your will,</l>
                        <l>And am o'th' sudden confident.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>It pleases.</l>
                        <stage>Exit Leon.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>It is impossible.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Promise any thing</l>
                        <l>In such a strait, and not despair to effect it.</l>
                        <l>Be private men content with their poor Fathom,</l>
                        <l>Since Heaveu we limit not, why should not Kings</l>
                        <l>Next Gods, perform the second mighty things?</l>
                        <l>Your ear—</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="act">
                     <head>ACT II.</head>
                     <stage>Enter Flaviano and Abbesse (with a Letter.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>YOu will obey the Dukes command?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Abbes.</speaker>
                        <l>Good Princes,</l>
                        <l>Punish, not teach us sacrilege; I'l obey</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="13" facs="127"/>
A thousand sufferings ere such a rape—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>A rape?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Abbesse.</speaker>
                        <l>Of honor, Honesty, Religion;</l>
                        <l>I am plac'd here to preserve, and not betray●</l>
                        <l>The Innocent; should I instead of prayer,</l>
                        <l>Chast life, the holyness of vow, of discipline,</l>
                        <l>With those austerities that keep wild blood</l>
                        <l>In calm obedience, now begin to teach●</l>
                        <l>Soul-murdering liberty, the breach of all</l>
                        <l>Was promis'd Heaven.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Wy' Madam you mistake,</l>
                        <l>We ask no Virgin to turn Whore, we onely</l>
                        <l>Desire you would perswade some pretty Nun,</l>
                        <l>In this extremity, to take upon her</l>
                        <l>The Princess <hi>Fioretta,</hi> whom <hi>Leonato</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ne'r saw, and be his Wife in honest marriage.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>Can you be thus</l>
                        <l>Unjust to him, so late preserv'd your lives?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Trouble you not your reverend head with that,</l>
                        <l>He shall be satisfied, and you remain</l>
                        <l>Still mother of the Maid, no more sour faces,</l>
                        <l>But turn your wit to'th' bufiness.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>Never sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Take heed and have a care of this inclosure,</l>
                        <l>The Dukes breath makes all flat, tis yet no common;</l>
                        <l>〈◊〉 are old, and should be wise.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>I would be honest.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Shew it in your obedience; will you do't?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>Never.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>D'ee hear? I sent unto this holy place,</l>
                        <l>A Damzel call'd <hi>Iuliana,</hi> she's in your Catalogue,</l>
                        <l>And yet but in probation, cause I see,</l>
                        <l>You make so nice a conscience, so severe,</l>
                        <l>I'th' rules of honesty, and would not have,</l>
                        <l>Your Virgin province touch'd with least defilemen●,</l>
                        <l>Pray let me speak with her, it will concern you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>Would you pervert her?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I know not what you call perverting,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="14" facs="128"/>
But she has not too much Nuns flesh,</l>
                        <l>And tis my charity to your chast Order</l>
                        <l>To give you timely notice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>What do I hear?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>No more than you may justifie in time,</l>
                        <l>If things prove right, she was a merry soul</l>
                        <l>And you ha' not spoild her, if you mean to be</l>
                        <l>No Midwife, let me talk with her a while.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>Protect us Virgin thoughts</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>So, so, this was reserv'd to wind up all,</l>
                        <l>It may be fortunate;</l>
                        <l>I know her spirit high, and apt to catch at</l>
                        <l>Ambitious hopes and freedom, some good counsell</l>
                        <l>May form her to my purpose, I have plung'd</l>
                        <l>Too farre, to hope for safety by return,</l>
                        <l>I'l trust my destiny to the stream, and reach</l>
                        <l>The point I see, or leave my self a rock</l>
                        <l>In the relentless waves; shee's here, I'm arm'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Iuliana and Abbesse.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>By your own goodness, reverend Mother give</l>
                        <l>No belief to him; though he be a great man,</l>
                        <l>He hath not been held guilty of much virtue,</l>
                        <l>Yet tis my wonder he should stain my Innocence;</l>
                        <l>Pray in your presence, give me leave to acquit</l>
                        <l>My Virgin honor; for the wealth of all</l>
                        <l>The World, I would not have this shame be whisper'd</l>
                        <l>To the stain of our profession.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Nunne.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>N.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, the Duke.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>The Duke?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Peace to the fair <hi>Iuliana.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit Abbesse.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are not noble,</l>
                        <l>A most dishonord Lord, your titles cannot</l>
                        <l>Bribe my just passion, who will trust a man?</l>
                        <l>Oh sir, you are as black, nay have a soul</l>
                        <l>As leprous with ingratitude, as the Angels</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="15" facs="128"/>
Are white with Innocence; was't not enough</l>
                        <l>To rob me of my honor, the chief wealth</l>
                        <l>Of Virgins, and confine me to my tears,</l>
                        <l>Which ne'r can wash away my guilt (should I</l>
                        <l>Live here to melt my soul into a stream</l>
                        <l>With penitence) but when I had resign'd</l>
                        <l>The World with hope to pray, and find out mercy,</l>
                        <l>You must thus haunt me with new shame and brand</l>
                        <l>My forehead here, as if you meant to kill</l>
                        <l>My better essence by despair, as you</l>
                        <l>Have stain'd my body.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Deer <hi>Iuliana</hi> I</l>
                        <l>Confess I injur'd thee thou knew'st no sin</l>
                        <l>But from my charm, 'twas only I betraid thee</l>
                        <l>To loss of thy dear honor, then of liberty,</l>
                        <l>For 'twas my practice, not thy pure devotion</l>
                        <l>Made thee a Recluse first; but let not passion</l>
                        <l>Lose what I would not only save from shipwrack,</l>
                        <l>But make as happy as thy thoughts can wish thee;</l>
                        <l>By thy wrong'd self tis true, nor could I choose</l>
                        <l>Another way than by discovery</l>
                        <l>Of both our shames to right thee, I am come</l>
                        <l>To make thee satisfaction in so high</l>
                        <l>And unexampled vvay of honor, thou</l>
                        <l>Shalt say I did deserve to be more vvicked,</l>
                        <l>When thou hast vveighed the recompence.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>You amaze me</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Collect thy senses, and discreetly mind me;</l>
                        <l>Thou canst not be concern'd so much alive</l>
                        <l>In any other story, hear me gently</l>
                        <l>And prize the vvealth of every syllable.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Duke and Abbesse.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>Had you been pleas'd to have left your daughter still</l>
                        <l>My charge and svveet companion, I should</l>
                        <l>Have left no duty unessaid, to have shevvn</l>
                        <l>In vvhat degree I honor'd her, but I</l>
                        <l>Must not dispute your royall pleasure, though</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="16" facs="129"/>
With some sad thoughts to separate, I resign'd her</l>
                        <l>To your commands.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <l>It was your virtue Madam, she found no</l>
                        <l>Consent to be profest, nor love the Prince,</l>
                        <l>To whom I promis'd her a Wife, although</l>
                        <l>Our fears keep warm his hope, in his belief</l>
                        <l>Shee's here inclos'd still, but without thy help,</l>
                        <l>We are all lost.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>The Prince <hi>Leonato?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Ther's a preferment, this is considerable.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>If you my Lord be serious; a Princess!</l>
                        <l>The change would do well.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Be but confident to manage it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>Hath he not seen the Princess by picture?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>Never.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>Strange!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>'T was a ceremony, in the necessities of our state,</l>
                        <l>The Duke ne'r thought on, &amp; I meant not to insert it,</l>
                        <l>As knowing <hi>Fioretta</hi> had no zeal,</l>
                        <l>To what her Father darkly had contracted;</l>
                        <l>His Highness doth expect thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>It would be</l>
                        <l>More for my honor, if he took the pains,</l>
                        <l>To visit our Religious house, and then—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>It shall be so.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>But twill be necessary,</l>
                        <l>You purge me to the <hi>Abbesse,</hi> no suspition,</l>
                        <l>Must live within her thought.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I apprehend;</l>
                        <l>Oh! you have shot a trembling through my soul,</l>
                        <l>I dare not kiss your hand, the Earth you tread on,</l>
                        <l>Would too much grace the lips have so prophan'd you.</l>
                        <l>Madam your pardon; sir be you the witness,</l>
                        <l>I have wrong'd this noble Virgins honor,</l>
                        <l>It was my anger, and revenge upon</l>
                        <l>Your goodness that so late oppos'd me made</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="17" facs="129"/>
Me careless, where I flung disgrace and scandall,</l>
                        <l>Thus I implore her mercy and forgiveness,</l>
                        <l>Take her white thoughts to your agen, she is</l>
                        <l>As innocent from sinfull act by me</l>
                        <l>As the chast womb that gave me life.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>Tis piety,</l>
                        <l>Thus to restore the Innocent, I conceive not</l>
                        <l>His aym in this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Abbesse</speaker>
                        <l>Tis satisfaction.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>VVhen I stray from your sweet precepts—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Abbes.</speaker>
                        <l>In, I am confirm'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>All to our expectation, shee's prepar'd,</l>
                        <l>A Mistris for the Prince.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>But now I think on't</l>
                        <l>She must not marry him, it will breed ill blood.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>By all means marry him, there's no other way</l>
                        <l>To send him hence, and quit us of the Army,</l>
                        <l>I'l instantly acquaint him how I prosper.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>It must not be, my honor will bleed for it.</l>
                        <l>I have been too much guided by <hi>Flaviano.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Madam—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Abesse</speaker>
                        <l>Your face is troubled.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>No, my heart</l>
                        <l>VVhich you may curc with honor, as I have</l>
                        <l>Contriv'd it now—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Abbesse</speaker>
                        <l>I shall study with my loss of life</l>
                        <l>To gain your bosom peace.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>I like this Virgin,</l>
                        <l>I know my Lord here hath been practising,</l>
                        <l>But finds her not inclin'd to that extent</l>
                        <l>VVe had propos'd, she is virtuous, you shall</l>
                        <l>Counsell her onely but to take the name</l>
                        <l>Of my <hi>Fioretta,</hi> but not change her life</l>
                        <l>To marry with the Prince; I do believe,</l>
                        <l>Her chast, Oh let your goodness keep her still so,</l>
                        <l>And fortifie her vertuous thoughts, I doubt not</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="18" facs="130"/>
But she with holy eloquence, and pretence</l>
                        <l>Of vow, and Virgin sanctity,</l>
                        <l>May so prevaile upon him both to save her self,</l>
                        <l>Our honors, and the Kingdom from a sacrifice.</l>
                        <l>May not this be?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                        <l>Such extremes I know not.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <l>If she persist a chast, and noble Virgin,</l>
                        <l>You must dispence, we have but little time</l>
                        <l>For pause, unless this present care be found,</l>
                        <l>We all must bleed to death upon the wound.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Bertoldi.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Hum! shall I never fight? drink wo'not do't,</l>
                        <l>No nor a Whore the greater provocation;</l>
                        <l>I speak it to my shame, I never durst</l>
                        <l>Fight for my wench, yet Gentlemen commend</l>
                        <l>My confidence at paying of a reckoning,</l>
                        <l>There I can kill 'em all with curtesie,</l>
                        <l>Discharge my Peeces like a Mr. Gunner at a great sup|per,</l>
                        <l>Yet I am not valiant, this must be mended someway.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Volterino.</stage>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Volterino?</hi> a word;</l>
                        <l>Tis not unknown to you, that I am a coward.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>No, not a coward, but you, are not sir,</l>
                        <l>If I were put to answer upon Oath,</l>
                        <l>So valiant altogether as <hi>Don Hercules,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That strangled a great Bull with his forefinger</l>
                        <l>And's Thumb, and kil'd the King of <hi>Troys</hi> great Coach horse</l>
                        <l>With a box o'th' car.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>Pox on't, do not abuse me, I shall take it</l>
                        <l>Scurvily and you deny it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>But you wo'not beat me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>Ther's the thing, I know't</l>
                        <l>As well as you can tell me, I am base,</l>
                        <l>And in plain terms a coward.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Why dost not beat thy self for being one?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="19" facs="130"/>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Then I durst fight; no, I was begotten</l>
                        <l>In a great Frost, between two shaking Agues,</l>
                        <l>I never shall be valiant, who can help it?</l>
                        <l>But when you come home agen, if you vvill but</l>
                        <l>Svvear I am valiant—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall pardon me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Come, my Mother shall make you amends; a ha,</l>
                        <l>You love her, she's a Lady and a Widdow,</l>
                        <l>That has the Goldfinches, hark in your ear,</l>
                        <l>You shall have her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Shall I have her?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>A vvord to the wise.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Would I were sure on't.</l>
                        <l>If I have thy Mother, I vvill not only svvear thou art,</l>
                        <l>But make thee valiant.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Would it vvere possible, upon that condition</l>
                        <l>You should ha' my Sister too.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vo●t.</speaker>
                        <l>She's dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>B●●t.</speaker>
                        <l>〈◊〉 she were alive I mean—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>●arewell, wee'l treat agen, and if I live</l>
                        <l>Thou shalt be <hi>Iulius Caesar.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Hortensio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>When I dye, thou shalt be <hi>Caesa●s</hi> heir.</l>
                        <l>Noble <hi>Hortensio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I am in hast, what's the matter?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>There lies your way, a hundred thousand Ducats</l>
                        <l>Will find entertainment somewhere else.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Canst thou help me to 'em?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, and a better business.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>How? where noble <hi>Bertoldi?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Wy—but you are in hast.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>No, no, where is all this money?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Safe enough in a place.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>But how shall I come by it?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You know my Mother.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>The rich Lady <hi>Florclia,</hi> the Court Widdow,</l>
                        <l>Shee's my Mistris.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="20" facs="131"/>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall have her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Shall I?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Leonato, Flaviano, Volterino.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, and be Master of as much money</l>
                        <l>As will make you mad.</l>
                        <l>The Prince, hark in your ear.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>I knew I should prevail, and I am happy,</l>
                        <l>There's no frost now within her, if your excellence</l>
                        <l>Would grace the Monastery with a visit</l>
                        <l>And satisfie your self, your presence will</l>
                        <l>Perfect the business, and be a just excuse</l>
                        <l>To some nice ceremonies that detain</l>
                        <l>Her Person to comply with virgin modesty,</l>
                        <l>The Duke will meet you there.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>I will attend him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>You will consider Sir it is a place</l>
                        <l>Not us'd to publique treaties, though dispenc'd with</l>
                        <l>For this your solemn view, and conference,</l>
                        <l>Your person may be trusted there, without</l>
                        <l>A numerous train.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall direct me Sir.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Volterino,</hi> you shall only wait upon me.</l>
                        <l>Sir when you please.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I'm proud to be your conduct.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit. Leo. Flav. Volt.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall have her</l>
                        <l>And her Estate, that's fair, she has enough</l>
                        <l>To undo the Devill if he go to law with her,</l>
                        <l>My Father's dead and has told him that already.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l do't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Here's my hand, my mother's thine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Not my mother.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>She shall be any thing I'l have her,</l>
                        <l>Do you but perswade her I am valiant,</l>
                        <l>And I'l venture to beat her, and she dare</l>
                        <l>Deny to marry any man I please</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="21" facs="131"/>
To call my Father in law.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Let's walk and think on't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You may swear any thing,</l>
                        <l>And you pawn your soul for me,</l>
                        <l>You know you cannot be a loser.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Ex.</stage>
                     <stage>Nunns Discovered singing</stage>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O fly my soul, what hangs upon</l>
                        <l>thy drooping wings,</l>
                        <l>and weighes them down,</l>
                        <l>With love of gaudy mortall things?</l>
                        <l>The Sun is now i'th' East, each shade</l>
                        <l>as he doth rise,</l>
                        <l>is shorter made,</l>
                        <l>That Earth may lesson to our eyes:</l>
                        <l>Oh be not careless then, and play</l>
                        <l>untill the Star of peace</l>
                        <l>Hide all his beames in dark recess;</l>
                        <l>Poor Pilgrims needs must lose their way,</l>
                        <l>When all the shadowes do entrease.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <stage>Enter Duke, Leonato, Flaviano, and Volterino.
Soft Musick, after the Song
Enter Iuliana Abbesse, and Nunns.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Le.</speaker>
                        <l>She is exceeding fair, what pitty 'twere</l>
                        <l>Such beauty and perfection should be</l>
                        <l>Confin'd to a melancholy Cell: I approach</l>
                        <l>You Madam with the reverence of a votary,</l>
                        <l>You look so like a Saint, yet nature meant</l>
                        <l>You should not with such early hast translate</l>
                        <l>Your self to heaven, till earth had been made happy</l>
                        <l>With living modells from your excellent figure.</l>
                        <l>You that become a cloud, and this dull dress</l>
                        <l>So well, whose sight doth pale, and freeze the blood,</l>
                        <l>How will you shine to admiration</l>
                        <l>Of every eye, when you put on those Ornaments</l>
                        <l>That fit your name and birth? if like a statue</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="22" facs="132"/>
Cold and unglorified by art, you call</l>
                        <l>Our sense to wonder, where shall we find eyes</l>
                        <l>To stand the brightness, when y'are turn'd a shrine,</l>
                        <l>Embellisht with the burning light of Diamonds,</l>
                        <l>And other gifts that dwell like starres about you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>If you do fancie me an object so</l>
                        <l>Prodigious, for the safety of your eyes</l>
                        <l>And others, tender-sighted, give consent,</l>
                        <l>I may not change this poverty a●d place,</l>
                        <l>(More pleasing to my self, than all the pride</l>
                        <l>Can wait those Goddesses, at Court you bow to)</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>And yet 'twere heresie in me to say</l>
                        <l>You could receive addition or glory</l>
                        <l>By the contributary blaze of Wealth,</l>
                        <l>Or other dress, which art and curiosity</l>
                        <l>Can form; you are not by them grac'd, but they</l>
                        <l>By you made beautifull. Iewells near your eye,</l>
                        <l>Take soul and Lustre, which but once remov'd</l>
                        <l>Look dull as in their quarry.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>He is taken.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>I now applaud my fate, and must account</l>
                        <l>My undertaking in this War to save</l>
                        <l>Your Dukedom, but the shadow of a service,</l>
                        <l>When I consider my reward. Oh! hast</l>
                        <l>To make me Envi'd of the World, and once</l>
                        <l>Possest of you, to undervalue all</l>
                        <l>But Heaven, of which you are the fairest coppy.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>My Lord, our study here is life, not language,</l>
                        <l>And in that little time I've had of practice,</l>
                        <l>My tongue hath learn'd simplicity, and truth;</l>
                        <l>You are a Prince, and in your Cr●ation</l>
                        <l>But one degree from Angels, strive to rise</l>
                        <l>That one round higher, and y' are perfect; I am</l>
                        <l>By my good Fathers leave, and the sweet rules</l>
                        <l>Of this Religious order, now i'th' way</l>
                        <l>To meet another Bridegroom, before whom</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="23" facs="132"/>
While you stand a competitor, you fall</l>
                        <l>To Atomes; sir my love is planted here,</l>
                        <l>And I have made a vow, which your own charity</l>
                        <l>Will bid me not to violate, (your triumph</l>
                        <l>Being the spring of my imperfect duty,)</l>
                        <l>That for a year, I'l spend my time among</l>
                        <l>This happy Quire, to offer up my Prayers</l>
                        <l>And humble gratitude to Heaven, a weak</l>
                        <l>Oblation for our safeties.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha? how's this?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>My Lord, did you not say you had prevail'd?</l>
                        <l>What mockery is this?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I am undone.</l>
                        <l>What does the Gipsey mean, shee'l betray all.</l>
                        <l>Most excellent Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh my Lord imploy</l>
                        <l>Your counsell, to advance not Kill our Virtue,</l>
                        <l>Remember where, and what I am.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>So, so.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir will you suffer this? a new affront.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>I am resolv'd</l>
                        <l>To live and pay you better tribute here</l>
                        <l>For your affection, and unequal'd service.</l>
                        <l>Here no distraction will afflict my prayers,</l>
                        <l>Which trust me I will offer chastly for you,</l>
                        <l>At every hour of my devotion.</l>
                        <l>'Tis you, next Heaven, that gave this blessing to us,</l>
                        <l>To meet, and in the holy Quire breath up</l>
                        <l>Our sacred Hymes, while Angells Eccho to us,</l>
                        <l>And Heaven delighted with our harmony,</l>
                        <l>Opening her azure curtaines will present us</l>
                        <l>A vision of all the joyes we pray and hope for.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>This my instructions?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>O think my Lord</l>
                        <l>To what a loss of Heaven your love invites me,</l>
                        <l>Yet let me not be thought while I pretend</l>
                        <l>The choice, and sweetness of a Recluse, I</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="24" facs="133"/>
Should in a thought accuse your worth, who are</l>
                        <l>The man of all the World I most could fancie;</l>
                        <l>If I be seen 〈◊〉 blush, make it no sin,</l>
                        <l>I know it is but honourable love</l>
                        <l>Wings your desire, and that which should prefer you,</l>
                        <l>Is merit of your Sword that cut our way,</l>
                        <l>To freedom and soft peace, Religions Pillow,</l>
                        <l>The Nurse of Science, and the generall blessing,</l>
                        <l>You have a title yet more strong pleads for you,</l>
                        <l>The contrac●, ●nd the promise of a Prince</l>
                        <l>A chain with many Links of Adamant.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>I like not that.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>To bind and make me yours,</l>
                        <l>When I have nam'd these severall interests,</l>
                        <l>And look upon my self so short of merit,</l>
                        <l>I chide your unkind destiny, at such</l>
                        <l>Expence of honor to go off unsatisfied,</l>
                        <l>And quickly should despise my self the cause</l>
                        <l>Of your distast, but that my vow confirms me,</l>
                        <l>And mustring up Religious thoughts prevailes,</l>
                        <l>Above my other will, made to obey you,</l>
                        <l>Tis but a year my Lord, that I have bound</l>
                        <l>My self this exile.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis an age.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>But whil● Time hath one minute in his Glass of that,</l>
                        <l>Nothing shall take me hence, unless you bring</l>
                        <l>An impious strength upon this holy dwelling,</l>
                        <l>And force me from my cell, but you are far</l>
                        <l>From such a sacrilege, oh think not on it,</l>
                        <l>I'l place you in my heart while you are virtuous,</l>
                        <l>But such an Act might lose those noble thoughts</l>
                        <l>Of you I wish preserv'd, but I offend,</l>
                        <l>And am too large in this unwelcome argument,</l>
                        <l>May wisdom guide your Princely thoughts,</l>
                        <l>Whilst I return to pray for you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="25" facs="133"/>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>She has orethrown all.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, if you love her she</l>
                        <l>Hath taught you a cunning way to make her yours,</l>
                        <l>This habit is compel'd, a little force,</l>
                        <l>For form will disingage her, she does love you,</l>
                        <l>And pleaded hansomely against her self.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>N●more—I'l not despair yet of your Daughter,</l>
                        <l>This is but Virgin nicety, at the next</l>
                        <l>Meeting she may incline to smile upon me,</l>
                        <l>Shee's too much treasure to be won at first</l>
                        <l>Assault, <hi>Volterino.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit Leon. Volt. Ho●●</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <l>Flaviano.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I did expect a storm.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>We are not safe yet.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I wonder why Iuliana kept not promise,</l>
                        <l>The Dog-dayes thaw her chastity, I'm mad,</l>
                        <l>Oh for some stratagem to save all yet,</l>
                        <l>But you Sir (give me leave to say) are timorous,</l>
                        <l>Princes should fix in their resolves, your conscience</l>
                        <l>Should be as subject to your will, as I am.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>I must confess <hi>Flaviano</hi> I had</l>
                        <l>No fancy to <hi>Iulianas</hi> mariage.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>That was all my hope, how could I love the man</l>
                        <l>Durst kill him now.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>I shudder, what noise is that?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>These horrors will eternally affright us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Leon. Bert. Volterino, H●rtensio, with swords drawn.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>The man that dares be guilty of least Insolence,</l>
                        <l>To any Virgin, dyes.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt Leon. Volt. Horten.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>My hopes are nipt, I thought to have tasted,</l>
                        <l>Nuns flesh, but the General has made it fasting day.</l>
                        <stage>Ex.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I hope he means to force away <hi>Iuliana</hi>—</l>
                        <l>Ha? they attempt it, prosper'em deer fate.</l>
                        <l>Blest beyond expectation.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>Dost think,</l>
                        <l>We shall be safe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="26" facs="134"/>
Enter Leonato, Iuliana in her habit,
Volterino, Hortensio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Injoy the other benefit of my Sword</l>
                        <l>In peace, this shall be mine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit Leon. Iul. Vol. Hort.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>The stars dote on us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Honorio and Claudio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                        <l>VVhat unexpected tumults fright the City?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <l>You are too bold upon your wound <hi>Honorio</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To come abroad.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>The Prince has stoln your Sister</l>
                        <l>From the Nunnery.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>He dares not</l>
                        <l>Blemish his honor so, though he deserv'd her,</l>
                        <l>And all our lives, should she be obstinate.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis done.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>This Act shall lose him, death upon</l>
                        <l>The Surgeon, that hath dallied with my wounds,</l>
                        <l>But I'l revenge this rape.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>Look to the Prince.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I could adore my destiny, the wench sure,</l>
                        <l>Meant to be ravish'd thus, I kiss thy policy;</l>
                        <l>This chance hath made a dancing in my blood,</l>
                        <l>While sin thrives, tis too early to be good.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="act">
                     <head>ACT III.</head>
                     <stage>Enter Antonio and Fioretta.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>IS this <hi>Ferraras</hi> Court?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Anto</speaker>
                        <l>Yes Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>I will not yet discover, I shall find,</l>
                        <l>A time <hi>Antonio</hi> to reward thy faith</l>
                        <l>And service to me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="27" facs="134"/>
Enter Donabella, Florelia, Ladies.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                        <l>Here are Ladies Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>I have a great desire to see this wonder,</l>
                        <l>The Princess <hi>Fioretta,</hi> so much fam'd</l>
                        <l>For beauty.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Comes she with his Excellence?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Most certainly, so speaks the Prince <hi>Leonato's</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>My Brothers Letters, and that with some difficulty,</l>
                        <l>He gaind her from the Nunnery.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Who is this?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Don.</speaker>
                        <l>She has an excellent shape, some stranger;</l>
                        <l>Prethee <hi>Florelia</hi> ask.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                        <l>This Lady Madam,</l>
                        <l>Seems to make some address this way; I know not,</l>
                        <l>Upon what Jealousie my Lady left</l>
                        <stage>aside.</stage>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Placentia</hi> so privatly, where she</l>
                        <l>Was entertain'd by <hi>Flavianos</hi> Mother,</l>
                        <l>Though old, a Lady of no decrepit brain.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Antonio.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>A Lady, Madam, calls her self <hi>Lauriana,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Born in <hi>Placentia,</hi> but the Warrs affrighting,</l>
                        <l>Both <hi>Mantua</hi> and the confines, she came hither</l>
                        <l>With confidence of safety, till the storm</l>
                        <l>At home be over.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>It is not fit a person of your quality</l>
                        <l>And presence should be ingag'd to common persons,</l>
                        <l>And if I may entreat, you shall consent</l>
                        <l>To be my guest at Court, which will be proud</l>
                        <l>To entertain such beauty.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>It must be</l>
                        <l>Too great an honor Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Don.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Leonato</hi> my Brother hath secur'd your peace at home,</l>
                        <l>Which cannot be less pleasing, if you tast</l>
                        <l>The freedom I can here provide and promise you,</l>
                        <l>We expect him every minute with the Princess</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fioretta,</hi> in whose love he holds more triumph</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="28" facs="135"/>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>And yet his fame was Earlier than this conquest,</l>
                        <l>For many noble Virtues, but has your grace</l>
                        <l>A confidence that he brings <hi>Fioretta</hi> with him?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Since he left <hi>Mantua</hi> we received such letters.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Petronio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, the Prince is come to court, and with him</l>
                        <l>The gallant Lady wee expected.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>I am not well o'th' suddain.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Virue defend!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                        <l>The good old Duke your Father, will</l>
                        <l>Shew comfort in his sick-bed to behold</l>
                        <l>A Son and Daughter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Are they married?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                        <l>No Madam, but I am confident</l>
                        <l>So great a joy will not be long deferr'd,</l>
                        <l>'Twere sin such hope should wither by delay,</l>
                        <l>They both wish to be happy in your presence,</l>
                        <l>And you at first sight of this Princely sister</l>
                        <l>Will much applaud your brothers fate.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>I hope so,</l>
                        <l>How is it Madam yet?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>I do beseech you</l>
                        <l>Let not your graces too much care of me</l>
                        <l>Detain you from the joy your brother brings.</l>
                        <l>Another <hi>Fioretta?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Leonato.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Donabella?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>I shall not fear a surfet in my joyes</l>
                        <l>To see you safe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>A gallant Gentleman.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>What Ladie's that?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>A stranger, sir, with whom I have prevail'd</l>
                        <l>To grace our court a while, which will be Honor'd</l>
                        <l>In such a guest.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>And I should call it happiness</l>
                        <l>If you would please to dwell for ever with us,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="29" facs="135"/>
I have brought home such a companion,</l>
                        <l>For both your beauties you will not repent.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>The Duke of <hi>Mantuas</hi> Daughter, I congratulate</l>
                        <l>Y●●● double victory, and if I may,</l>
                        <l>Without imputed flattery speak my thoughts,</l>
                        <l>You did deserve her, had she to her birth,</l>
                        <l>All the additions that grace a Woman.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon</speaker>
                        <l>You have conferr'd a bounty on me Madam,</l>
                        <l>And leave me hopeless to reward the debt</l>
                        <l>Iow this fair opinion.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, the venture</l>
                        <l>You made through blood, and danger, doth deserve it,</l>
                        <l>And she were impious, did not think her self</l>
                        <l>Much honor'd to be call'd your valors triumph.</l>
                        <l>I shall betray my self. Censure me not,</l>
                        <l>Immodest or suspectfull of her virtue,</l>
                        <l>Whom you have made the darling of your heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Bertoldi.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir the Duke calls for you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Signior Bertoldi.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Graces creature.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Will it please you Madam?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>I humbly pray your Highness to excuse me,</l>
                        <l>I may have time and happiness to attend you,</l>
                        <l>When with more health I may present my services,</l>
                        <l>I dare not see this Lady.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Wait you upon that Lady <hi>Signior.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>With all my heart; incomparable Lady—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>●ior</speaker>
                        <l>I have servants to attend me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>But not one,</l>
                        <l>More humble, or more active for your service,</l>
                        <l>You cannot choose but know my Lady Mother;</l>
                        <l>I have not seen her yet, but she shall stay,</l>
                        <l>I'l kneel to her when I have done with you.</l>
                        <stage>Exit</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="30" facs="136"/>
Enter Florelia, Volterino.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>But is my Son so valiant, Signior?</l>
                        <l>This War hath wrought a miracle upon him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>He was a coward beyond <hi>Ela,</hi> Madam,</l>
                        <l>I must acknowledg, to whom men in pitty</l>
                        <l>Of his Birth, and care of your much-loved honor</l>
                        <l>Often forgave his life, but see the turn,</l>
                        <l>He that went forth (for all our conjurings</l>
                        <l>And promise of no danger) as he had</l>
                        <l>Been marching towards <hi>Aetna,</hi> nay before</l>
                        <l>The instant fight would have given all the World</l>
                        <l>To have been assur'd when he came home, but one</l>
                        <l>Of every thing about him—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                        <l>What d'ee mean?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>One eye, one ear, one arm, and but one leg</l>
                        <l>To have hopt home withall, strange, how i'th' heat</l>
                        <l>O'th' Battle he grew double, and there fought</l>
                        <l>As he had two soules; oh! had you seen</l>
                        <l>When like a Magazine he march'd, with pikes</l>
                        <l>With guns &amp; Corslets, which he took from th' Enemy,</l>
                        <l>With swords more than a Surgeons sign, stuck round,</l>
                        <l>And seeming like a porcupine to shoot</l>
                        <l>The Iron Quills—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                        <l>But is this possible?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>I never saw a Dragon do such thing●</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>This was not by instinct, but some example</l>
                        <l>He saw in you, that wak'd his sleeping spirit.</l>
                        <l>And he must owe all that is Valiant in him</l>
                        <l>To your brave soul, which like a burning Comet</l>
                        <l>Flew with prodigious terror to the Enemy.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>You do not Jeer your servant?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>And so he, by your great blaze</l>
                        <l>Saw his next way to honor;</l>
                        <l>Nor can I but acknowledge all my joyes</l>
                        <l>Now in my Son do flow from you; a souldier</l>
                        <l>Was ever high in my esteem, but you</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="31" facs="136"/>
Have plac'd the title nearest to me, pray</l>
                        <l>Favour me often' with your visit.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>The Town's my own.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>No complement good <hi>Signior,</hi> your love</l>
                        <l>If plac'd on me, shall find an object, though,</l>
                        <l>Not equall to your favors, not ingratefull;</l>
                        <l>I wonder he absents himself so long.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>My care shall be to find him out and bring him</l>
                        <l>A welcom present to your eye. She's caught.</l>
                        <stage>Exit</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>These Soldiers think if they but once lay siege,</l>
                        <l>We must come in by force or c●mposition.</l>
                        <l>Although a Maiden Town may not hold out,</l>
                        <l>A Widdow but well vittled with the bare</l>
                        <l>Munition of her tongue, will tire an Army;</l>
                        <l>I must suspect my Son, for all this legend,</l>
                        <l>No mighty man at armes; hee's here.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Bertoldi, Hortensio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Your blessing.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Take it, and with it all my prayers, thou maist</l>
                        <l>Grow up in honor, and deserve to be</l>
                        <l>Thy Fathers Son.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Kiss her <hi>Hortensio,</hi> do, she is thine own.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>'Twas my ambition Madam</l>
                        <l>To wait upon my Convert, and to kiss</l>
                        <l>Your white hand.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fler.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Signior Volterino</hi> was here but now, and has</l>
                        <l>Told me such stories, Son—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Of me?</l>
                        <l>He had better eat my Spaniard, then mention me</l>
                        <l>With any scruple of dishonour.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>He extolls you for ● Soldier, and tells me won|ders.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>If you dare believe me Madam, your Son has</l>
                        <l>Behav'd him like a Gentleman.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I confess,</l>
                        <l>I was—but that's no matter, thank this Cavalier;</l>
                        <l>can receive and give a gash, and look on't</l>
                        <l>When I ha' don without your cordial waters</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="32" facs="137"/>
Shall I cut you o'r the face Mother?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir I am poor to recompence the honor</l>
                        <l>You have done my Son, I see he is your convert,</l>
                        <l>You that infus'd a soul in him cannot</l>
                        <l>Enough be glorified.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis within your power</l>
                        <l>Madam to overpoise all my deserts.</l>
                        <l>True, I did stir those dormant seeds of nobleness</l>
                        <l>Your blood left in him, and made glow those sparks,</l>
                        <l>Into a flame, were hid in hills of Ashes;</l>
                        <l>Now he is yours, and if you Madam think</l>
                        <l>I have done any service by an Act</l>
                        <l>Or precept that could light your Son to honor,</l>
                        <l>You make me fortunate, and encourage</l>
                        <l>A Souldier to imploy his whole life here.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                        <l>How d'ee mean?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ho</speaker>
                        <l>Without more complement to love you, and—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                        <l>VVhat?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
                        <l>VVish my self with you Madam when you dream</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flr.</speaker>
                        <l>You would be with me when I dream.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>But I should wake you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>But I should be very angry to have my sleep broke.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>But I would please you agen,</l>
                        <l>And rock you into a traunce with so much harmony,</l>
                        <l>You shall wish to dye in't. I am very plain.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Me thinks you are very rough.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>A Souldiers garb,</l>
                        <l>The old but the best fashion; a Sword,</l>
                        <l>And flattery were not meant for one mans wearing;</l>
                        <l>Madam I love you, but not doat upon you,</l>
                        <l>For you are something old.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I am indeed sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet you are very handsome, and I love you;</l>
                        <l>Y'are witty, fair, and honest, but a VViddow,</l>
                        <l>And yet I love you; I do know you are rich,</l>
                        <l>Exceeding mighty rich.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                        <l>And yet you love me▪</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="137"/>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>But Madam, I am a man.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I do not mean to try you <hi>Signior,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Pray Son do you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Now put your vote in.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>What should I do Madam?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Try whether he be a man or no.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Should I?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>D'ee hear? they say you are grown valiant●</l>
                        <l>Upon my blessing I command you strike</l>
                        <l>This Gentleman, and do it presently.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Strike him?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>A way, away, what here?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Even here, this very minute.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Not for your house, and all the monies in't,</l>
                        <l>Not for my Fathers Wardrob, and I were</l>
                        <l>An Adamite a top o'th' Alps, though you</l>
                        <l>Admire the reliques, and have turn'd your Gallery</l>
                        <l>Into a Chapel, where his severall suites</l>
                        <l>Hang up like Images for you to pray to:</l>
                        <l>Strike one taught me to fight?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit Flor.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Is she gone? what said she?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>The foolish woman—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Why what's the matter?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Shee shews her breeding, but do not you despair.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Florelia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>If I mistake not sir, you would pretend</l>
                        <l>You love me honourably.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>May I perish else.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>When you can make't appear in visible wounds</l>
                        <l>Upon your head' or body, that my Son</l>
                        <l>Dares fight—you and I'l be maryed.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I told you Signior you should have my Mother.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>The Devill shall have you both upon easier conditions;</l>
                        <l>Visible wounds upon my head or body?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>And here's my hand upon the sight thereof,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="34" facs="138"/>
I'l be your wife; and so farewel till dooms-day.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>But hark you Lady</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>My Mother's a Witch. I shallne'r be valiant</l>
                        <l>In this World, what quarrels I may have i'th' next,</l>
                        <l>I know not,</l>
                        <l>There are some dead threatned to cudgell me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Is there no hope, that I may catch you in</l>
                        <l>The Noose of Matrimony, unless your Son</l>
                        <l>First break my head?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I wo' not swear.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>It is not your best course, take heed of vows.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Why my dear <hi>Signior?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>For your souls sake, and yet</l>
                        <l>Dispose that as you please, I'l see who dare</l>
                        <l>Cary your body from me, spight o' <hi>Lucifer</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I will ha' that, and come by't ●awfully;</l>
                        <l>And so my service; think on't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>A fine fellow.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt. Mane● Bert.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Would I had his audacity; my Mistris,</l>
                        <l>Yet knows not what I mean, but I will to her,</l>
                        <l>And kiss her Glove immediatly.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Honorie.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                        <l>This Court is like a twilight, where I cannot</l>
                        <l>Distinguish day, or perfect night, some faces</l>
                        <l>Are c●eerfull as the morn, others agen</l>
                        <l>Are dark, and wrapt like evenings in a mist</l>
                        <l>●s is instinct for my approach, that brings</l>
                        <l>A resolution to revenge the rape</l>
                        <l>Upon my Sister; grow more strong my thoughts,</l>
                        <l>And let no fear distract you. Prince I have</l>
                        <l>Con●ider'd thee in all thy pride of merit,</l>
                        <l>Allow'd my Fathers Contract, and did give thee</l>
                        <l>My Sisters heart in thy own vote, but when,</l>
                        <l>She onely made a pause for ceremony,</l>
                        <l>Not disaffection, since thou could'st forget</l>
                        <l>Thy honour of a Prince, to invade her Chastity,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="35" facs="138"/>
And forfeit thy Religion, thus I come,</l>
                        <l>To whip thy blood, or leave my own a sacrifice.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Petr●mo:</stage>
                        <l>Sir, may a stranger ask without offence, why</l>
                        <l>The Court like <hi>Ianus</hi> doth present a double</l>
                        <l>Face, as it labour'd twixt the fierce extremes</l>
                        <l>Of triumph and despair▪</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir you mistake not</l>
                        <l>The mixture of our passions, the Court</l>
                        <l>Smiles in our happiness to entertain</l>
                        <l>The Prince, and his fair Mistris, but doth wear,</l>
                        <l>A grief and paleness, for the Duke, whose want</l>
                        <l>Of health delayes their marriage.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>I apprehend;</l>
                        <l>Sir I am bold, May not a Gentleman</l>
                        <l>Engag'd to visit other Courts of <hi>Italy,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Make his ambition fortunate to receive</l>
                        <l>A favour from this Prince, and kiss his hand,</l>
                        <l>Before he leave the Dukedome?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Leonato.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                        <l>He is here Sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Lord <hi>Petroni●,</hi> intreat the Princess</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fioretta,</hi> and my Sister meet me i'th' grove—</l>
                        <l>This Gentleman—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Hono. kisses his hand.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>You have made me happy;</l>
                        <l>Though I want honor to be known, your fame</l>
                        <l>Speaks you a valiant Prince, and fortunate,</l>
                        <l>And I must with the World congratulate</l>
                        <l>Your victory at <hi>Mant●a,</hi> upon which,</l>
                        <l>So rich a triumph waites.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>What triumph fir?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                        <l>The Princess <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>I acknowledge,</l>
                        <l>That Garland is my glory, such a treasure,</l>
                        <l>Was worth more service, than my sword could merit:</l>
                        <l>But I must be a debtor to my starres,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="36" facs="139"/>
And can release all other happiness,</l>
                        <l>Within their influence to come, so they</l>
                        <l>Confirm me Lord still of her beauties Empire.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>This doth becom your Excellence; what error</l>
                        <l>(Receive it not prophane) should Heaven and nature,</l>
                        <l>Have made, to have kept your hearts too long asunder?</l>
                        <l>And yet I may mistake, for though your Grace,</l>
                        <l>Affect her with all height your soul can fancie,</l>
                        <l>I know not how her love may answer this</l>
                        <l>Desert in you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>How sir?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon●.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Highness pardon;</l>
                        <l>I am no Prophet, nor do wish to see,</l>
                        <l>Upon your spring, another winde than what</l>
                        <l>The wings of pregnant Western gales do inrich</l>
                        <l>The air withall, which gliding as you walk,</l>
                        <l>May kiss the teeming flowers, and with soft breath</l>
                        <l>Open the Buds to welcom their preserver;</l>
                        <l>I wish you might grow up two even Cedars,</l>
                        <l>Till your top-boughs kiss Heaven that made you flou|rish,</l>
                        <l>When stooping to behold the numerous branches</l>
                        <l>That prosper in your growth, and what refreshing</l>
                        <l>The World below receives by your cool shade,</l>
                        <l>You wave your heads in the applause and wonder.</l>
                        <l>This is the Song I bri●g to your chast <hi>Hymen,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And thus would every good man pray, but that</l>
                        <l>They fear.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Fear, what?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>The blessings they invoke,</l>
                        <l>With all their importunity of prayers,</l>
                        <l>Will not descend.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Icannot reach you sir</l>
                        <l>Without a perspective, but this wanders from</l>
                        <l>The doubt you made of <hi>Fiorettas</hi> love,</l>
                        <l>To answer mine, that talk was dangerous,</l>
                        <l>I must not hear't agen.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="37" facs="139"/>
                        <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                        <l>You must, unless</l>
                        <l>You can be deaf, or cut the tongue of fame out.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>The man hath somwhere lost his senses; go back</l>
                        <l>And sind thy strangled wits, this language has</l>
                        <l>No chain of reason, I lose breath upon</l>
                        <l>A thing distracted.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis not come to that,</l>
                        <l>I've no such hot vexation, but a soul</l>
                        <l>Possest with noble anger, and with pitty.</l>
                        <l>Prince, I must tell you there are dangerous symptoms</l>
                        <l>Of a State Apoplex; those aiery stilts</l>
                        <l>Of fame you walk on, will deceive your pride,</l>
                        <l>When every honest breath, angry at what</l>
                        <l>You did so late in the contempt of goodness,</l>
                        <l>Will tell the wind how it mistook your praise,</l>
                        <l>And in a sigh conclude her sad repentance.</l>
                        <l>I come not sir to flatter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>It appears so.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>But tell you what hath eat into your soul</l>
                        <l>Of honor, and there poisond all the worth</l>
                        <l>The VVorld once lov'd you for.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>You talk as if</l>
                        <l>You had consulted with my fate, and read</l>
                        <l>The leaves of my inevitable doom;</l>
                        <l>VVhat action hath so much incens'd my late</l>
                        <l>Kind starres to this revolt, and threatneth like</l>
                        <l>To busie tongues in my disgrace?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>The noise is lowd already, would there were</l>
                        <l>No truth in men, who say, you ravish'd <hi>Fioretta</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Sweet Princess from her Prayers, and left a Monument</l>
                        <l>Of such a sacrilege committed by you,</l>
                        <l>The very stones since groan in her behalf</l>
                        <l>You ravish'd from the Nunnery, on this</l>
                        <l>Must needs depend her hate,</l>
                        <l>VVhose person and Religious vow you have</l>
                        <l>Unlike a Prince prophan'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="38" facs="140"/>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are very bold,</l>
                        <l>What confidence can that outside raise in you</l>
                        <l>To be thus sawcie?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Sawcie?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Impudent.</l>
                        <l>Is life a burden, that you dare my anger?</l>
                        <l>What art?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
                        <l>A gentleman, that have more right to honor</l>
                        <l>Than he that is a Prince, and dares degenerate.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Le.</speaker>
                        <l>There's somthing in thy face would have me think</l>
                        <l>Thou maist be worth my punishment, that I</l>
                        <l>●ould uncreate thee, if thy veines do house</l>
                        <l>But Common blood, to make thee a fit Enemy</l>
                        <l>In Birth, and soul to me, that I might kill thee</l>
                        <l>Without a blush to honor, do not tempt</l>
                        <l>My Just rage, that provok'd will scorn a sword,</l>
                        <l>And make thee nothing with a look; be gone,</l>
                        <l>Get hence with the same speed, thou wouldst avoid</l>
                        <l>A falling Tower, or hadst new seen a Lioness</l>
                        <l>Walking upon some cliff, and gazing round</l>
                        <l>To find a prey, which she persues with eyes</l>
                        <l>That shoot contracted flame, but when her teeth</l>
                        <l>And pawes arrive, they quickly leave no part</l>
                        <l>Or sign of what there was.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
                        <l>Iust heaven, how high he talks, and counterfeits</l>
                        <l>Your noise! I have a charm against your thunder;</l>
                        <l>If thou hast courage to stay, thou quickly shalt repent</l>
                        <l>Heavens Iustice in my arm sent to revenge</l>
                        <l>Thy sacrilege, the more to encourage thee</l>
                        <l>To fight, I am thy equall, and a Prince.</l>
                        <stage>They Draw</stage>
                        <l>Or may thy sin o'take my blood, and set</l>
                        <l>A weight upon my soul when thou hast kil'd me</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Donabella, Iuliana.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas my Lord?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Don.</speaker>
                        <l>Dear Brother?</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="39" facs="140"/>
Help, what traitor's this?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Away sweet <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Fioretta.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha? I am undone, alas what do you mean?</l>
                        <l>My Brother, Prince <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Thy brother?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh let me hold thee safe in my Embraces.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Don.</speaker>
                        <l>Leo. Honorio.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>The same, but not her brother.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Pardon me,</l>
                        <l>Whose soul disdain'd in my belief thou wert</l>
                        <l>An insolent stranger, to acknowledge any thing</l>
                        <l>Of satisfaction, but let thy sister</l>
                        <l>Now speak for both.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Give space to my amazement.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                        <l>If changing thus soft kisses, armes and heart</l>
                        <l>You interpret violence, <hi>Fioretta,</hi> then</l>
                        <l>Thy sister has been ravished; who hath thus</l>
                        <l>Abus'd your faith, and wrong'd this Princes Virtue?</l>
                        <l>Clear as the light of stars. I must confess</l>
                        <l>I seem'd to wave his courtship, when he first</l>
                        <l>Beheld me veild, which modesty instructed,</l>
                        <l>And though my heart were won, I kept it secret,</l>
                        <l>To make more proof of his, who not consenting</l>
                        <l>To be depriv'd too long of what he lov'd,</l>
                        <l>He brought a force to' th' Cloister: but took me</l>
                        <l>His own away without a rape, and since</l>
                        <l>All his adresses have been honorable.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Instead of satisfaction, you inlarge</l>
                        <l>My wonder, what Impostures here? the Prince</l>
                        <l>Is cosend, yet she ownes me; pardon sir,</l>
                        <l>I was made believe, you did most impiously</l>
                        <l>Compell my sister, and by force injoy'd her,</l>
                        <l>But now I find we are all abus'd, to what</l>
                        <l>Misfortune might this error have engag'd us?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>This is my sister.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="40" facs="141"/>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>You cannot want a charity</l>
                        <l>That are so fair.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Would <hi>Leonato's</hi> Sword</l>
                        <l>Had prosper'd in his death; I must be confident;</l>
                        <l>You have not yet made glad my heart <hi>Honorio,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>With our good Fathers health, I have some trembling</l>
                        <l>Within my blood, and fear all is not well.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Gypsye?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                        <l>You look not cherefully.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>My Father injoyes a perfect health.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>That word hath blest me.</l>
                        <l>Sister and <hi>Leonato,</hi> you'l excuse,</l>
                        <l>If I transgress with joy to see my Brother;</l>
                        <l>Were but the Duke my Father here, I summ'd</l>
                        <l>All my delights on earth—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>She confounds me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Honorio</hi> and I will follow you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>You are not my Sister?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit Leon. Do●a.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, tis very true.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Where is she?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall know what will make you happy sir,</l>
                        <l>If you preserve this wisedom.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>I have seen you before.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>But I am destin'd here, to do such service</l>
                        <l>To your Family you shall know more—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Give me breath for two minutes,</l>
                        <l>Be confident of my silence, they expect you.</l>
                        <stage>Ex. Iul.</stage>
                        <l>So let me have some air, am I <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <stage>Enter Fioretta, Bertoldi.</stage>
                        <l>What prodigies are these? we are all bewitch'd,</l>
                        <l>Ha Sister,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Brother <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis she, what's he?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fio.</speaker>
                        <l>Not worth the interruption of one kiss.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>My friend—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>My fool—<hi>Fioretta</hi> shew me where</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="41" facs="141"/>
We may injoy a shade, I'l tell thee wonders.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt, manet B●rt.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir I shall meet with you agen; a pretty fellow.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="act">
                     <head>ACT. IIII.</head>
                     <stage>Enter Fioretta and Donabella.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>MAdam I fear this walk into the Park,</l>
                        <l>May engage your grace too far without som more</l>
                        <l>To attend you,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Our own thoughts may be our guard,</l>
                        <l>I use it frequently; but to our dlscourse</l>
                        <l>Of Prince <hi>Honorio,</hi> for we cannot find</l>
                        <l>A nobler subject, I observe that he</l>
                        <l>And you have been aquainted.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Twas my happiness,</l>
                        <l>To have my breeding in the Court of <hi>Mantua,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Where I among the rest of his admirers,</l>
                        <l>Seeing his youth improv'd with so much honor,</l>
                        <l>Grew into admiration of his virtues,</l>
                        <l>VVhich now he writes man do so fully crown him,</l>
                        <l>His Fathers Dukedome holds no ornament</l>
                        <l>To stand in competition.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>You speak him high,</l>
                        <l>And with a passion too, that tasts of love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, I honor him,</l>
                        <l>As may become his servant.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>As his Mistris rather.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>My heart is clear from such ambition,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>But yet not proof against all <hi>Cupids</hi> shaf●s;</l>
                        <l>I do not think but you have been in love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>VVho hath not felt the wounds? but I ne'r look'd</l>
                        <l>Above my birth and fortunes; Prince <hi>Honorio,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>May become your election, and great blood.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="42" facs="142"/>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>I find it here already.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Nor could you</l>
                        <l>Endear it where so much desert invites</l>
                        <l>It to be belov'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>My looks do sure betray me,</l>
                        <l>I do believe him all compos'd of honor,</l>
                        <l>And have receiv'd your Character from the World</l>
                        <l>So noble, all your praise can be no flattery.</l>
                        <l>I know not by what powerfull charm within</l>
                        <l>His person, Madam, I confess my eyes</l>
                        <l>Take some delight to see him, but I fear—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>I find your Jealousie, and dare secure you.</l>
                        <l>If in your amorous bosom, you feel, Madam,</l>
                        <l>A Golden shaft, the cure is made by cherishing</l>
                        <l>The happy wound; my destiny hath plac'd</l>
                        <l>My thoughts of love, where they cannot concern</l>
                        <l>Your trouble or suspition, nor indeed</l>
                        <l>My hope, for I despair ever to meet,</l>
                        <l>His clear affection whom I honor.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Would</l>
                        <l>This Court containd whom you would make so pre|cious;</l>
                        <l>I should with as much cherefullness assist</l>
                        <l>Thy wishes, as desire thy aid to mine;</l>
                        <l>I do believe you have much credit with</l>
                        <l>His thoughts, and virtue to deserve it Madam,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>If you trust me,</l>
                        <l>The favor I have with his Highness, shall not</l>
                        <l>Create your prejudice, be confident,</l>
                        <l>Your birth, your beauty, and those numerous graces</l>
                        <l>That wait upon you, must command his heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam you force a blush for my much want</l>
                        <l>Of what y'are pleas'd to impute my ornaments,</l>
                        <l>You are acquainted with your self, and shew</l>
                        <l>What I should be, if I were rich like you,</l>
                        <l>But my disparity of worth allow'd,</l>
                        <l>Would you would call me Sister, and impose</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="142"/>
Somthing on me, my act of confidence,</l>
                        <l>And free discovery of my soul, may</l>
                        <l>Deserve faith from you, that I shall never</l>
                        <l>Injure his name you love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>There is no hope</l>
                        <l>In my desires, and therefore I beseech,</l>
                        <l>Dear Madam, your excuse, yet thus much I</l>
                        <l>Dare borrow of my grief to say, he lives</l>
                        <l>Now in the Court, for whose sake I thus wither.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas I fear agen, is he compos'd</l>
                        <l>Of gentle blood, and can to thee he cruell?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>No, he is very kind, for he did promise</l>
                        <l>To be my Husband, we ha' been contracted.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Don.</speaker>
                        <l>Disperse these mist●, &amp; clear my wonder Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>When time and sorrow shall by death prepare</l>
                        <l>My sad release of love, you may know all;</l>
                        <l>Were the condition of my fa●e like others,</l>
                        <l>It were no grief to name him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>This doth more inlarge my Jealousie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>But let us leave this subject, till time fit,</l>
                        <l>To ope the maze of my unhappy fortune.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Bertoldi.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I heard that she was come into the Park,</l>
                        <l>They cannot far be; they are in view,</l>
                        <l>And no man with'em, I'l now be valiant.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Florelia and Honorio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>It was her Highness charge I should direct you,</l>
                        <l>I know her walk.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>The blustring Prince agen;</l>
                        <l>Who sent him hither? I think he conjures.</l>
                        <l>Now dare I with as much confidence undertake</l>
                        <l>To cure a Lyon rampant, o' the' Tooth-ach,</l>
                        <l>As but go forward; and my valiant Mother—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Son; I must excuse my self then to him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>Now shall I be fit for a Carbonado.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>I hope you'l pardon sir, if I appear'd,</l>
                        <l>Less smooth when I la●t saw you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="44" facs="143"/>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>My good Lord; your Grace is too much humble,</l>
                        <l>I'm your blow-ball, your breath dissolves my being,</l>
                        <l>But to shew how free my wishes are to serve you,</l>
                        <l>If you have any mind, or meaning to my Mother—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>How do you mean?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>In what way your Grace pleases,</l>
                        <l>She shall be yours, your Highness may do worse,</l>
                        <l>Although I say't she has those things may give</l>
                        <l>A Prince content.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Son is very curteous.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I should prepare you sir to look with mercy</l>
                        <l>Upon his folly. But the Princess.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Mother.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>VVill you be still a fool,</l>
                        <l>VVhat said you sir to th' Prince?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>VVill you be wise and use him tenderly.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Stain to thy Fathers blood—</l>
                        <l>I was comming Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt, manet Bert.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Vmh: he is my rivall, would my hilts</l>
                        <l>VVere in his belly; they are out of sight;</l>
                        <l>It is no rutting time, no trick?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Flaviano and Claudio disg●is'd.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Signior Bertoldi.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I do not know you friends, but how soever,</l>
                        <l>There is a purse of mony</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, I want not.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>That Gentleman perhaps can drink; I like not</l>
                        <l>Their goggle eyes, twas well I gave 'em mony:</l>
                        <l>VVhat d'ee want else? you are Souldiers;</l>
                        <l>I love a Souldier.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I am a Gentleman of <hi>Mantua</hi> sir,</l>
                        <l>That owe my life to your command, as one,</l>
                        <l>That had an interest in the preservation,</l>
                        <l>Your army brought when the Enemy besieg'd us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Your mercy <hi>Signior,</hi> and how do all</l>
                        <l>Our limber friends 'it 'h Nunnery? I was one</l>
                        <l>O'th' Cavaliers went with the Generall,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="45" facs="143"/>
Into the Orchard of <hi>Hesperides</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To fetch the golden Dragon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Golden Apple,</l>
                        <l>You mean the Princess <hi>Fioretta Signior;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Is she married sir?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>No, no, the Duke will neither dye, nor live,</l>
                        <l>To any purpose, but they will be shortly;</l>
                        <l>Have you a mind to kiss her hand?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I shall be proud—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall be as proud as you please sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>You can resolve me, is <hi>Honorio</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Our Duke of <hi>Mantuas</hi> Son here?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, he is here,</l>
                        <l>Heaven were a fitter place for him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha! look to him,</l>
                        <l>For he is come with bloody thoughts to murder</l>
                        <l>Your Prince <hi>Leonato,</hi> caution him to walk</l>
                        <l>VVith a strong guard, and arm himself with all</l>
                        <l>That can be proof against his Sword or Pistoll,</l>
                        <l>He cannot be too safe against the treason</l>
                        <l>And horrid purpose of <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>His mouth is Musket bore; but are you sure</l>
                        <l>He did resolve to kill our Prince?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>Most certain.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I am very glad to hear't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>Glad sir?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, I cannot wish him better then a Traitor,</l>
                        <l>Now I shall be reveng'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Has he been guilty of any affront to you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>He is my Rivall.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Why do not you kill him then?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Pox on him, I cannot indure him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>He is then reserv'd to fall by me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis too good to be true; are you maryed <hi>Signior?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>VVhat then?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>If you be not, do this &amp; you shall have</l>
                        <l>My mother, a Lady that has Gold enough to pave</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="46" facs="144"/>
The Streets with double Ducats, heres my hand,</l>
                        <l>Kill but this huffing Prince, my Mothers yours,</l>
                        <stage>Enter Honorio.</stage>
                        <l>And all her moveables—tis he alone too,</l>
                        <l>There's convenient bottom sir hard by</l>
                        <stage>Exit Hon.</stage>
                        <l>The finest place to cut his throat, I'l not</l>
                        <l>Be seen.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I am resolv'd, charge home thy litle Murderers,</l>
                        <l>And follow.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cland.</speaker>
                        <l>I warrant you my Lord.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit after Hono.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Volterino and Hortensi●.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>But tell me hast thou any hopes of Madam Flo|●elia?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I had a lusty promise.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>From her?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Ye Coxcomb her sweet Son.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Why so had I, he did contract her to me,</l>
                        <l>A flat bargain and sale of all she had,</l>
                        <l>So I would say he was valiant.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>That was the price he made to me, but I,</l>
                        <l>Had hope last visit from her self.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Be plain, I'l tell thee, she gave me strong expecta|tion,</l>
                        <l>And came on like a Cheverell.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I hear,</l>
                        <l>She has given out she wi●l have one of us,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Flor●a.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>She cannot love us bo●h.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Would she had on●, &amp; then the toy were over,</l>
                        <l>I could make shift to love her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>And to lye with her estate, one helps the tother well.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Florel.</speaker>
                        <l>I finde a change within my self, I hope,</l>
                        <l>I sha'not prove in love now after all</l>
                        <l>My jeasting, and so many coy repulses,</l>
                        <l>To men of birth and honor.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis she.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Florel.</speaker>
                        <l>Why do I think upon him, then? I fear,</l>
                        <l>This man of War has don't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="47" facs="144"/>
                        <speaker>Horte●.</speaker>
                        <l>I have it, wee'l finde whether she affect</l>
                        <l>Or Juggle with us presently.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Florel.</speaker>
                        <l>Those postures,</l>
                        <l>Would shew some difference, here I can observe—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Mistris?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Horten.</speaker>
                        <l>Mine if she be pleas'd, what interest</l>
                        <l>Can all your merit challenge above me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>You will repent this insolence, I must,</l>
                        <l>Forget to wear a sword, and hear thee name</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Florelia,</hi> with that confident relation</l>
                        <l>To her fair thoughts, and not correct your pride,</l>
                        <l>I'l search your heart, and let out those proud hopes,</l>
                        <l>That thus exalt you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>You are cofend <hi>Signior,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I do not fear your probe—she lets us fight,</l>
                        <stage>Fight</stage>
                        <l>If we had no more wit, we might foin in ear●●st.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Florel.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha, ha, ha, are you at that ward Gentlemen?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>She laughes to see us fence o' this fashion,</l>
                        <l>Lets come a little closer.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Fight.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Hold, hold Gentlemen,</l>
                        <l>For your own honors, is this valour well</l>
                        <l>Employ'd? what cause can urge effusion,</l>
                        <l>Thus of that noble blood was given you</l>
                        <l>To serve your Country? are you mad?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>We are but little better to be both in love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>What Woman,</l>
                        <l>Considered in her best is worth this difference;</l>
                        <l>She is cruell cannot ●inde a better way</l>
                        <l>To reconcile you, than by letting blood.</l>
                        <l>Do you both love one?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>It does appear so Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I would I knew the Lady makes you both</l>
                        <l>Unhappy, I would counsell her some way,</l>
                        <l>To set your hearts at peace.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis in your power.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Without more circumstance, do but look upon</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="48" facs="145"/>
Your self, and end our civill Wars; we ha' both</l>
                        <l>Opinion of your virtue, and both hope</l>
                        <l>An interest in your love, if you will please</l>
                        <l>To point which of us two is most concern'd</l>
                        <l>In your affection, ●ou conclude our danger,</l>
                        <l>And oblige one your everlasting Servant.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>This Madam is a charitable way</l>
                        <l>To know your own, and save two lives, for we</l>
                        <l>Shall fix upon your sentence, and obey</l>
                        <l>The fate you give us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Do you fight for me?</l>
                        <l>And will it save ●ncision and preserve</l>
                        <l>Your noble veins to know whom I prefer</l>
                        <l>In my best thoughts of love? this is but reasonable,</l>
                        <l>And twill be hard to set a period</l>
                        <l>To this contention, for I love you both</l>
                        <l>So equally, observe me Cavaliers,</l>
                        <l>Tis most impossible to distinguish which</l>
                        <l>Is first in my neglect, for I love neither:</l>
                        <l>Fight or be friends, you have your choice, and I</l>
                        <l>My liberty—I had forgot to thank you,</l>
                        <l>For your infusion of that fierce courage</l>
                        <l>Into my Son, there is great hope if he</l>
                        <l>Live till next year, he may be a Constable,</l>
                        <l>He has an excellent art to keep the peace. Farewell.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, for all this I believe you love—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I believe now shee's old and has no teeth,</l>
                        <l>Else she would bite at one of us—Reverend Madam,</l>
                        <l>That word has fetch'd her,—we ha' no other cordiall,</l>
                        <l>At this dead pang for your disdain, but drink now;</l>
                        <l>If you will have your Son made a fine Gentleman,</l>
                        <l>Be sure you send him to the Tavern to us,</l>
                        <l>He knows the rendezvous, though you despair,</l>
                        <l>We may wind him up yet with spirit of Wine,</l>
                        <l>How ever wee'l be merry, and perhaps,</l>
                        <l>For all this, drink your health.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="49" facs="145"/>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Buoy Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>If you love your Baby send him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I am to blame, but I must help it some way.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Honorio, Flaviano, Claudio with Pistols.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Two Engins of so small extent to do</l>
                        <l>Such mighty execution? may I see</l>
                        <l>These instruments you say you have invented,</l>
                        <l>And so commend for service?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes my Lord,</l>
                        <l>Shew 'em to th' Prince, do they not fright already?</l>
                        <l>Your Grace may take full view, and quickly be</l>
                        <l>The proof what force they have.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>I am betrai'd,</l>
                        <l>Who hath conspir'd my death</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>To vex you, see him—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Flaviano,</hi> what mak'st thou here?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>To put of these commodities; you are</l>
                        <l>A princely Marchant, and affect this kind</l>
                        <l>Of traffick, that you may not dy i'th' dark,</l>
                        <l>I'l tell you a brief story, which you may</l>
                        <l>Report i'th' other world, I did affect</l>
                        <l>Ambitiously thy Sister <hi>Fioretta,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Abus'd thy Father with a false opinion</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Leonato,</hi> for my end remov'd</l>
                        <l>His Mistris from the Cloister, and perswaded</l>
                        <l>A witty Nunne to take her name, and cheat</l>
                        <l>The Prince, whom he suspects not yet.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Dam'd rascall?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>For pure love to your Sister I did this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Why having been so impious, does thy malice</l>
                        <l>Persue me, ignorant of all thy treasons?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Would you know that?—because I am undone</l>
                        <l>In my chief hope, the Princess whom I thought</l>
                        <l>Thus plac'd secure, and apt for my own visit</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="50" facs="146"/>
Is gone, is vanish'd, and as soon I may</l>
                        <l>Find the impression of a Ship at Sea,</l>
                        <l>And by the hollow tract in waves oretake</l>
                        <l>The winged Bark, distinguish where the Birds,</l>
                        <l>At Chace 'ith' air, do print their active flight,</l>
                        <l>As find in what part of the envious World</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fioretta</hi> is bestow'd; this sad intelligence</l>
                        <l>Surpriz'd me like a storm, nor was it safe</l>
                        <l>To look upon the Duke, who must too late</l>
                        <l>Repent his trust, and punish it. In this conflict</l>
                        <l>Of desperate thoughts, I thus resolv'd to see</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and the Lady I preferr'd,</l>
                        <l>But find things cannot prosper, if you live?</l>
                        <l>Whose angry breath will throw down waht my policy</l>
                        <l>Wrought high, and strike my head beneath the ruines.</l>
                        <l>Are you now satisfi'd why you must not live?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Hear me, shee's still in silence, and believ'd</l>
                        <l>My Sister by the Prince.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>When you are dead, then</l>
                        <l>You VVill be sure to tell no tales; now shoot—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>In my opinion, if all this be truth,</l>
                        <l>The mischief you ha' done may be sufficient,</l>
                        <l>And he may live.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Villain vvilt thou betray me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>You have betraid your self, and after this</l>
                        <l>Confession, as I take it, I may be</l>
                        <l>Your Ghostly Father, and prescribe you a Penance.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Hold.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>I will but Physick you, your soul has caught</l>
                        <l>A vehement cold, and I have tvvo hot pills</l>
                        <l>Will vvarm you at heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Shall my revenge be idle?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>Good Prince, you are too forvvard, &amp; you be</l>
                        <l>So hasty, I'm o' this side; did you think,</l>
                        <l>I vvould be false? yet lest my aim be unlucky,</l>
                        <l>Trust your ovvn hand to guide 'em.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="51" facs="146"/>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou art honest,</l>
                        <l>Thus I salute thy heart <hi>Honori●</hi>—ha, no charge.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis time sir to be honest, I could serve you</l>
                        <l>In some Court sins, that are but flesh-colour,</l>
                        <l>A wickedness of the first dye, whose brightness</l>
                        <l>Will fade, and tincture change; your murder i●</l>
                        <l>Crimson in grain, I have no fancy too't.</l>
                        <l>Sir you are safe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>I see thou hast preserv'd me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I'm lost for ever.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis but a minute</l>
                        <l>Since you were found, you must be plea●'d to walk</l>
                        <l>Into the Court, the Vestall you preferr'd</l>
                        <l>No doubt will bid you welcome. Fate I thank thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>False starres, I dare you now.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Clau.</speaker>
                        <l>I shall wait on you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Iuliana.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>I have collected all my brain, and cannot</l>
                        <l>In any counsell of my thoughts find safety;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Honorio's</hi> death wo'not secure my strength,</l>
                        <l>Or prop my languishing greatness; tis but like</l>
                        <l>A cordiall when the pangs of death hang on us,</l>
                        <l>Nay to my present state no other than</l>
                        <l>Some liberall portion of a quivering stream,</l>
                        <l>Drunk to abate the scorching of my Feaver,</l>
                        <l>It cooles to'th' tast, and creeps like Ice dissolv'd</l>
                        <l>Into my blood, but meeting with the flame,</l>
                        <l>It scalds my bosom, and augments the fire</l>
                        <l>That turnes my heart to ashes; poor <hi>Iuliana,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To what a loss hath thy first ●in betray'd thee▪</l>
                        <l>Ambition hath reveng'd thy breach of Honor,</l>
                        <l>And Death must cure Ambition, for I have</l>
                        <l>No prospect left, but what invites to ruine.</l>
                        <l>I am resolv'd not to expect my fate,</l>
                        <l>But meet it this way.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="52" facs="147"/>
Enter Leonato.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Dearest <hi>Fioretta?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ha, what offends my Princess? there is something</l>
                        <l>That dwells like an Ecclipse upon thy eyes,</l>
                        <l>They shine not as they did, a discontent,</l>
                        <l>Is like a mildew fallen upon thy cheek,</l>
                        <l>Tis pale and cold, as Winter were come back</l>
                        <l>To over-run the Spring.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>My dearest Lord,</l>
                        <l>My face is but the title to a volume</l>
                        <l>Of so much misery within, as will</l>
                        <l>Tire your amazed soul to read.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou dost</l>
                        <l>Freez up my blood already. O call back</l>
                        <l>Part of this killing language, if thou mean'st</l>
                        <l>To make me understand thee; the amazement</l>
                        <l>Doth fall so like a deluge, I am drownd,</l>
                        <l>Ere I can think my feares; how have we liv'd</l>
                        <l>At distance? thou shouldst walk upon this Earthquake</l>
                        <l>And my ground tremble not, but with this fright</l>
                        <l>I am awake, open the volume now,</l>
                        <l>I will read every circumstance.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Observe then, what first becomes my sorrow.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Dost thou kneel?</l>
                        <l>That posture is for them have lost their Innocence;</l>
                        <l>We must do this to Heaven.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>I must to you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>What guilt can weigh thee down so low?</l>
                        <l>Dost weep too!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>I should not love my eyes if they were silent,</l>
                        <l>They know this story will too soon o'rcharge</l>
                        <l>My fe●ble voice, that every tear could fall</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="53" facs="147"/>
Into some character which you might read,</l>
                        <l>That so I might disp●nse with my sad tongue,</l>
                        <l>And leave my sorrows legible; oh my Lord,</l>
                        <l>I have wrong'd you above hope to find your mercy.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Take heed, &amp; think once more what thou hast don</l>
                        <l>Ere thou describe such an offence, lest I</l>
                        <l>Believe a fault, will drown us both with horror;</l>
                        <l>T●ou hast not broke thy vow▪ nor given away</l>
                        <l>Thy honor, since thy faith did seal thee mine?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Not in a thought.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>I wo'not see thee kneel,</l>
                        <l>Rise, and be welcome to my armes, thou hast</l>
                        <l>Done nothing can offend me <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas—I am not <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha! this doth confirm me, thou hast all this while</l>
                        <l>But mock'd my fear, and yet this weeping is</l>
                        <l>Not counterfeit, thou art too blame my love,</l>
                        <l>Is it thy jealousie, that I am cold</l>
                        <l>In my returnes to answer thy affection?</l>
                        <l>Or have I less in thy esteem of merit</l>
                        <l>Than thy hopes flatterd thee? or doth the time</l>
                        <l>That dully moves, and intermit the joyes</l>
                        <l>We promis'd when the Altar had confirm'd us</l>
                        <l>Sit heavy on thy thought? we will awake</l>
                        <l>From this our sullen sleep, and quit off those</l>
                        <l>Sick Feathers that did droop our wings; fly to</l>
                        <l>The holy man whose charm shall perfect us,</l>
                        <l>And chain our amorous soules.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Divide us rather;</l>
                        <l>Joy is a fugitive of late, and while</l>
                        <l>You think of <hi>Hymen,</hi> you remove your wishes.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fioretta</hi> will forbid the Priest.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Canst thou forget thy love so much?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas my Lord,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="54" facs="148"/>
You have been all this while abus'd, and when</l>
                        <l>I have said enough to assure your Faith, that I</l>
                        <l>Am not your <hi>Fioretta,</hi> but a Virgin,</l>
                        <l>Compell'd to take her name, you will I hope</l>
                        <l>Kill me your self, and save me a despair,</l>
                        <l>That will conclude my breath else in few Minutes.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Are not you <hi>Fioretta,</hi> but a Virgin</l>
                        <l>Compell'd to take her name? who durst compell thee?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>The Duke of <hi>Mantua.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>I dissolve in wonder.</l>
                        <l>Durst <hi>Mantua</hi> use me thus? thy name?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Iuliana;</l>
                        <l>My blood, (excepting what does fill the veins</l>
                        <l>Of Princes) flowing from the noblest spring</l>
                        <l>Of honor.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Where was <hi>Fioretta</hi> then?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Conveid I know not whither, ere you came</l>
                        <l>To save their lives that did betray you thus.</l>
                        <l>I was too careless of my fate, that I</l>
                        <l>Kept such a glowing secret still within me,</l>
                        <l>I had no fear to be consum'd, that had</l>
                        <l>Another Fire within me, whose wide flame</l>
                        <l>Had soon devour'd all my considerings.</l>
                        <l>Alas my Lord, You did appear so full</l>
                        <l>Of honor, virtue, and such Princely love,</l>
                        <l>Twas easie to forget on whom you smil'd,</l>
                        <l>I had no thought to wish my self unhappy,</l>
                        <l>Or own another name to my undoing,</l>
                        <l>Yet now more tender of your birth and fame</l>
                        <l>Than my own life, I cast my self beneath</l>
                        <l>Your feet a bleeding sacrifice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Am I awake and hear all this?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul</speaker>
                        <l>I see my Lord,</l>
                        <l>In your inraged eye, what lightning is</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="55" facs="148"/>
Prepar'd, tis welcom; since I danot hope</l>
                        <l>To live upon your smile, I would fain dye</l>
                        <l>Betime, before the shame of my dishonour</l>
                        <l>Inforce a mutinie upon my self▪</l>
                        <l>But think my Lord while I confess all this</l>
                        <l>Against my self, how free I might have been,</l>
                        <l>How happy, how near Heaven, above those glories,</l>
                        <l>Had not you forc'd me from the blessed Garden</l>
                        <l>Where I was planted, and grew fair, though not</l>
                        <l>Oblig'd by any solemn vow, 'twas you,</l>
                        <l>Your own hand ravish'd me from that sweet life,</l>
                        <l>Where without thought of more than should concern</l>
                        <l>Your welfare in my prayers, I might have sung,</l>
                        <l>And had converse with Angells.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Petronio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, I bring sad news.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>I prethee speak, I am prepar'd for all.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pet●.</speaker>
                        <l>The Duke is dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>My Father dead?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                        <l>I do not like the Princess at that posture.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>I have forgot your name Lady—you may rise.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Henorio, Flaviano, Claudio, and Guard.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                        <l>My Lord I bring you news welcom as health</l>
                        <l>Or liberty, your soul will not be spacious</l>
                        <l>Enough to entertain what will with joyes</l>
                        <l>And strong amazement fill it; how I swell,</l>
                        <l>With my own happiness to think I shall</l>
                        <l>Redeem your noble heart from a dishonor</l>
                        <l>Wil weigh down death. You think you vvalk on Roses</l>
                        <l>And feel not to vvhat Dragons teeth, and stings,</l>
                        <l>You vvere betraid. I bring a disinchantment,</l>
                        <l>And come vvith happy proofs.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>To tell me this is not</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="56" facs="149"/>
Your Sister <hi>Fioretta:</hi> but a Nunne</l>
                        <l>Subornd to cheat me—I know all the business,</l>
                        <l>And am resolv'd in my revenge. <hi>Iuliana,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Svveet suffering Maid, dry thy fair eyes, tis I</l>
                        <l>Must make thee satisfaction, I thus</l>
                        <l>By thy own name receive thee to my bosom,</l>
                        <l>But you that practis'd cunning, shall e'r time</l>
                        <l>Contract the age of one pale Moon, behold</l>
                        <l>The Countrey I preserv'd a heap of ruines.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Flaviano?</hi> sir—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Do you knovv vvhom you embrace?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Flaviano</hi> has confest</l>
                        <l>Himself the Traitor, and the black contriver</l>
                        <l>Of all this mischief; <hi>Leonato</hi> hear me,</l>
                        <l>Or by thy Father nevvly falln to ashes,</l>
                        <l>I shall repent I had an honorable</l>
                        <l>Thought of thee. <hi>Flaviano;</hi> Madam, vvitchcraft,</l>
                        <l>My rage vvill strangle my discourse, my soul</l>
                        <l>Is leaping forth to be reveng'd upon</l>
                        <l>That Devill; Prince keep off, his very breath</l>
                        <l>Will stifle thee, and dam thy honor to</l>
                        <l>All ages▪ <hi>Fioretta</hi>'s now in Court.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha! in the Court?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>This is some nevv device.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>I charge thee by thy blood throvv of these Harpies,</l>
                        <l>And do my Sister justice, vvhom their treason</l>
                        <l>Hath made a scorn, that minute she usurps</l>
                        <l>Her name of Bride, I shall forget the Altar,</l>
                        <l>And turn my self the Priest, with all your blood</l>
                        <l>To make a purging sacrifice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>If when we</l>
                        <l>Receive our rites, thou dost but frovvn, or vvhispe●</l>
                        <l>To interrupt one ceremony, I</l>
                        <l>Will make thee hold the tapers while the Priest</l>
                        <l>Performes the holy office; tell thy Sister</l>
                        <l>Here I bestovv, vvhat you have made me forfeit.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="57" facs="149"/>
Present her to the Nunnery, and counsell</l>
                        <l>Thy ignoble Father, when I next see <hi>Mantua</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To be a sleep in's Coffin, and his vault</l>
                        <l>Deep, and thick rib'd with Marble, my noise else</l>
                        <l>Will shake his dust; thy youth finds mercy yet,</l>
                        <l>Take the next whirl-wind, and remove—our guard;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Petronio</hi> we confine him to your house.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hono.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou coward Prince, there's not one honest man</l>
                        <l>In all the World, our sins ascend like vapours,</l>
                        <l>And will, if Justice sleep, stupifie Heaven,</l>
                        <l>For thine own glory wake, if thou dispense</l>
                        <l>With this, proud man will cry down providence.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="act">
                     <head>ACT. V.</head>
                     <stage>Enter Volterino, Hortensio, Pandolpho (with a Towell.)
A Table set out and stooles.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>SUch Wine as <hi>Ganimede</hi> doth skink to <hi>Iove</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>When he invites the Gods to feast with him</l>
                        <l>On <hi>Iunos</hi> wedding-day.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pandol.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Iove</hi> never drank so brisk a Nectar as I'l draw.</l>
                        <l>But does <hi>Signior Bertoldi</hi> come?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>What else? my Alderman o'th' Cellar.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>He is our <hi>Hilas;</hi> shall we not ha Musick?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>By all means, and the Mermaids.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall have any thing;</l>
                        <l>But if <hi>Signior Bertoldi</hi> come, I have</l>
                        <l>A boon to beg, I have a pretty plot</l>
                        <l>To make you laugh.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>What is't?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>As you are Gentlemen, do not deny me;</l>
                        <l>I have been your up-and-down-stairs-man to draw</l>
                        <l>The best blood o'th' Grape these ten years,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Troy</hi> held out not longer, I have a device</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="58" facs="150"/>
Shall make you merry when he comes, if you</l>
                        <l>Will give me leave to shift, and help a jeast.</l>
                        <l>He is a Coward still, under the Rose?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>As any lives under the Sun, be confident.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>The same senseless peece of timber,</l>
                        <l>You may cut him into a Bed-staff.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l send you Wine, say I am valiant,</l>
                        <l>Let me alone with the Catastrophe.</l>
                        <stage>Exit</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>What will he do?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>I know not, he were best make us laugh,</l>
                        <l>I shall expound the matter else.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Bertoldi, and Drawer (with Wine.)</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>My Mother remembers her service Gentlemen,</l>
                        <l>I left my Mistris to come to you; and how?</l>
                        <l>Shall we drink like Fishes? <hi>Tolle roll lolly, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Sit, sit, a health to the Lady you kist last.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Let it come, I'l pledge it,</l>
                        <l>And it were the Gulf of <hi>Venice.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>And who's your Mistris?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith I do not know her name, nor ever kist any
thing but her Glove in my life.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt:</speaker>
                        <p>But you have told her your mind?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Not I by this Wine—but thats all one,</l>
                        <l>She is a Lady, well bred, and companion</l>
                        <l>To the Princess, that's enough.</l>
                        <l>Here <hi>Signior</hi>—would we had some Wenches here.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <p>Some bouncing bona robas, hang this dul City
there's no musick in't, no silken Musick.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vol.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh for a Wench could spit fire now, that could
whizze like a Rocket, and fall into a 100 blasing stars,
such a Fire-drake would be warm company in a close
room, <hi>Signior.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <p>And it were in a Cellar under the <hi>Alpes,</hi> it
would make <hi>Hercules</hi> melt in the back.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="59" facs="150"/>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>But for all that, I do not like a sinner of such
a fiery constitution.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <p>You would not venture upon the golden Fleece
then, which is but the morall of a Maidenhead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>I never heard that afore.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <p>So say the learned, first for the difficulty to ob|tain
it, being watch'd by a Dragon, and then for the
Rarity, there being but one in all the World.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>But one Maidenhead?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <p>And that some hold as doubtfull as the Phoenix
or Unicorn, such things are in History, but the man's
not alive that will take his Oath in what climat they
are visible. Here's to the <hi>Swan</hi> that broke her heart
with singing last.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <p>And to the <hi>Dolphin</hi> that was in love with a
Fidlers Boy of <hi>Thebes,</hi> who carryed him cross the Seas
on her bak a fishing, while he sung the ●iedge of <hi>Troy</hi> to
the Tune of <hi>Green-sleeves,</hi> and caught a Whale with an
angling rod.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>I'l pledge 'em both; they are very fine healths.
Are these your Mistresses names Gentlemen?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Pandolfo like a Soldier.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <p>Mysticall, Mysticall.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>I Understand they are mysticall—who's this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <p>Save you Gentlemen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis the Drawer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <p>I do not like the odor of your Wine</p>
                        <stage>He throws it in Bert. face.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>Was it a health? let it go round Gent.
I am troubled with sore eyes, &amp; this <hi>Signior</hi>
has wash'd 'em for me, I hope I shall see to thank him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <p>Cry mercy <hi>Signior,</hi> you are like a noble Gent.
I saw at <hi>Rome,</hi> you are the very same, to whom his Ho|liness
gave a pension, for killing 6 great Turks in <hi>Tra●|silvania,</hi>
whose heads were boyl'd, and brought home
in a Portmantua.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="151"/>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>It was but 5 sir and a Sarasens.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>You are the man?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Pray give me leave to honor you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I desire to be your poor admirer too,</l>
                        <l>My eyes are clear to see your worth, my name</l>
                        <l>Is <hi>Bertoldi</hi> at your service.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>To you <hi>Signior,</hi> a health to <hi>Iulius Caesar, Prester</hi> Iohn,</l>
                        <l>And the grand <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartaria.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>You sha'not pledge him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>No.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Make your exceptions, I'l justifie 'em.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>This Cavalier drank t'ee sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I do remember, but I cannot pledge him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>How sir?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>No sir, I'l pledge my friend <hi>Prester Iack,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But for <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> and the grand <hi>Cham</hi> they are</l>
                        <l>Pagans, I ha' nothing to say to 'em.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                        <l>Here is a Gentleman, he seems of quality,</l>
                        <l>Enquiring for <hi>Signior Volterino</hi> and <hi>Hortensio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Admit him, and he be a Gentleman.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Florelia like a Gentleman.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>You'l pardon if a stranger that has had</l>
                        <l>A long ambition to kiss your hands,</l>
                        <l>Rather intreat for his access, than lose</l>
                        <l>The happiness of your knowledge.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, y'are most welcome.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>If you will keep us company</l>
                        <l>You must be equally ingag'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>My humble service, <hi>Signior Hortensios</hi> Mistris.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>You honor me; would I were off agen.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Excuse me <hi>Signior.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are too full of ceremony.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, is there any difference between you &amp; <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>You would not pledge his health?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>No difference in the world.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="61" facs="151"/>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>How, no difference between you, and a Roman Emperor?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Divide'em, what's the matter?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>O for some Trumpets.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Somebody hold my Sword, give me the Wine,</l>
                        <l>I'l drink it—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>So, we are friends.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>O shamefull!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>But I shall find a time—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>Find twenty thousand years, there's time e|nough.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l be your stickler.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>I ha' not pledg'd the <hi>Cham</hi> yet, nor I wo' not,
come, I know you well enough.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <p>Know me, for what?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>For a brave fellow, and a man may believe thee
thou hast done things as well as the best on 'em, but
I know not where, nor I care not, tel me of <hi>Iulius Caesar:</hi>
I am a Gentleman, and have seen fighting afore now,
here's a Cavalier knows it, I scorn to be baffel'd by any
<hi>Transilvanian</hi> Turk-killer in Christendom, I; thar't a</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <p>Well said, and a Sandiack.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <p>And a Sandiack, I defie the grand <hi>Cham,</hi> and Muftie.
all his Tartars, y'are a stinking obstreperons fellow to
tell me of a Turd and a Fart, and I honor you with all
my heart. <hi>Hort.</hi> He call'd you Muftie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>What's that?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
                        <l>And a Sandiack, that is son of whor in 2 languages.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>How? in two languages? then my honor is</l>
                        <l>Concern'd, have I in 30 battells gainst the <hi>Turk</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Stood the dire shock, when the Granadoes flew</l>
                        <l>Like Atomes in the Sun,</l>
                        <l>Have I kil'd 20 <hi>Bashawes,</hi> and a Musselman,</l>
                        <l>And took the Sultans Turbant Prisoner,</l>
                        <l>And shall I be affronted by a thing</l>
                        <l>Less than a Lancepresado?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Will no body hold me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Gentlemen, this heat must needs be dangerous.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>Let me but speak with him</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="62" facs="152"/>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>No danger o' my life, let 'em go together:</l>
                        <l>And let us mind our business.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Signior,</hi> I am your friend, and pitty you</l>
                        <l>Should lose so much your honor, be advis'd,</l>
                        <l>I'l show a way how to repair your fame,</l>
                        <stage>Pand. &amp; Bert. talk privately.</stage>
                        <l>And without danger.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>To <hi>Volterinos</hi> Mistris.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I receive it, I shall have my share, I now</l>
                        <l>Repent my curiosity to see</l>
                        <l>Their humors, and to hear what they would say</l>
                        <l>Of me—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Let 'em alone—to <hi>Volterinos</hi> Mistris.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Come, to my Whore.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Whore <hi>Signior?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Does that offend you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Not me—I ha done you right.</l>
                        <l>I am well enough rewarded &amp; they beat me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
                        <l>I knovv not hovv to deserve this curtesie being a stranger●</l>
                        <l>But if you vvant a Wife noble sir, and will accept of my</l>
                        <l>Mother, you shall have her before any man in <hi>Italy.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>I thank you sir,</l>
                        <l>But be sure you hit me full o'th' head.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis too much, a cut o'th' leg and please you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>No, let it be o'th' head.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You wo'not strike agen?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>Mine's but a foil.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>They measure and give back—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh I am slain, a Surgeon. <hi>Bertoldi strikes Pand.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l take my leave.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>By this hand, I'l drink his Mothers health <hi>first,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>There's no danger &amp; he were dead; a health to the Lady</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Florelia,</hi> I drink it for his sake.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Away, and get a Surgeon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Come, to my Lady Mother.</l>
                        <l>A man is not born to be a coward all his li●e.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>I can no more sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="63" facs="152"/>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>You should ha' told me sir at first,</l>
                        <l>There is no remedy, tis to an honorable Lady.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>You must excuse me sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Throw't in his eyes.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>At your request.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Hor. throwes the Wine.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are most uncivill.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Y'are a mushrump.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>strikes Flor.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>So sir, y'are a multitude, and in a Tavern,</l>
                        <l>I did believe you sir a Gentleman,</l>
                        <l>If you be, give me satisfaction nobly.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>With all my heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Then thus—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Signior Bertoldi</hi> flye, his wound is dangerous,</l>
                        <l>We fear he wil bleed to death before the Surgeon come.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Out by the Postern.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Pox, a conspiracie, I shall kill but one, I see that;</l>
                        <l>Would I were a Mite in a Holland Cheese now.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I wo'not fail you sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                        <l>He desires to speak with you before he dye.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Is Bertoldi gone?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Hortensio, I guess you may be ingag'd:</l>
                        <l>Leave me to these things, There may be danger.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I know the private way.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Ex●unt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Honori●.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                        <l>Virtue and honor, I allow you names,</l>
                        <l>You may give matter for dispute, and noise,</l>
                        <l>But you have lost your Essence, and that truth</l>
                        <l>We fondly have believ'd in human soules,</l>
                        <l>Is ceas'd to be, we are grown fantastick bodies,</l>
                        <l>Figures, and empty titles, and make hast</l>
                        <l>To our first nothing, he that will be honest,</l>
                        <l>Must quite throw off his cold decrepit nature,</l>
                        <l>And have a new creation—my poor Sister,</l>
                        <stage>Enter Fioretta.</stage>
                        <l>She has heard the Dukes resolve.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="64" facs="153"/>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh let me dye, upon thy bosom Brother,</l>
                        <l>I have liv'd</l>
                        <l>Too long; they say the Duke resolves to marry</l>
                        <l>With <hi>Iuliana,</hi> so they call her now,</l>
                        <l>Whose sorcery hath won upon his soul;</l>
                        <l>I have walk'd too long in dark Clouds, and accuse</l>
                        <l>Too late my silence, I am quite undon,</l>
                        <l>There was some hope while he did love my name,</l>
                        <l>But that and all is banish'd; is't not in</l>
                        <l>The power of fancy to imagin this</l>
                        <l>A dream that hath perplext us all this while?</l>
                        <l>If it be reall, I will be reveng'd,</l>
                        <l>Tis but forgetting what I am, and then</l>
                        <l>I am not concern'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Rather forget the Duke,</l>
                        <l>And live to triumph in a love more happy.</l>
                        <l>He is not worth a tear.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Don●bella.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>How's this? my heart!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Come, I wil kiss these sorrows from thy cheek,</l>
                        <l>This Garden wants no watering, preserve</l>
                        <l>This rain, it is a wealth should ransom Queens,</l>
                        <l>As thou dost love me, chide thy saucie grief,</l>
                        <l>That will undo the spring here, and inforce</l>
                        <l>My heart to weep within me equall drops</l>
                        <l>Of blood for these.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh my abus'd confidence,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lauriana</hi> now I find hath but betraid me,</l>
                        <l>Instruct me rage and jealousie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>I am resolv'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit Donab.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Well said, take courage <hi>Fioretta,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Appear with thy own name and sufferings,</l>
                        <l>Thy sight will strike the proud Impostors from</l>
                        <l>Their Pyramids of glory.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>It were more revenge to dye.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>Not so deer <hi>Fioretta,</hi> somthing glides</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="65" facs="153"/>
Like cheerfulness o'th' suddrn through my blood;</l>
                        <l>Despair not to be happy: Let's consult,</l>
                        <l>And form the aptest way for all our honor.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Flaviano.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>There's but one cloud in all our sky, were that</l>
                        <l>Remov'd, we were above the rage of storms:</l>
                        <l>That <hi>Claudio</hi> knows too much. I look upon</l>
                        <l>His life like a prodigions blazing Comet;</l>
                        <l>He palls my blood; if I but meet him hansomly,</l>
                        <l>I'l make him fixt as the North-star. I hear</l>
                        <l>No whisper of him yet; were but he dead,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Iuliana</hi> and her friend might revell here:</l>
                        <l>The Duke should have the name, but we would steer</l>
                        <l>The Helm of State, and govern all. I have</l>
                        <l>Gain'd much upon <hi>Leonato</hi>'s easie faith,</l>
                        <l>Who thinks me innocent, and that only duty</l>
                        <l>Mislead my nature and my tongue to obey</l>
                        <l>The Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> and the Prince, upon</l>
                        <l>Whose heads I have translated all my guilt,</l>
                        <stage>Enter Leonato, Claudio.</stage>
                        <l>And fram'd their jealousie at home my cause</l>
                        <l>Of flight for refuge hither—Ha, my eyes</l>
                        <l>Take in confusion! The Duke and <hi>Claudio!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>'Tis doomsday in my soul.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Can this be justified?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>I dare confirm this truth with my last blood.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I dare not hear it. That I now could fling</l>
                        <l>My self upon the winds—</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>And should be happy</l>
                        <l>Were <hi>Flaviano</hi>'s life put into ballance</l>
                        <l>Against my own, to make it clear by his</l>
                        <l>Confession. To my shame I must acknowledge</l>
                        <l>was the agent 'twixt 'em; he was pleas'd</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="66" facs="154"/>
To choose me his smock Officer, a place</l>
                        <l>Poor Gentlemen at Court are forc'd to serve in,</l>
                        <l>To please luxurious greatness, younger brothers,</l>
                        <l>Who cannot live by fair and honest wayes,</l>
                        <l>Must not sterve sir.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon:</speaker>
                        <l>Flaviano's Whore?</l>
                        <l>Where can we hope to trust our faith, when such</l>
                        <l>White browes deceive us?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Iuliana.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul</speaker>
                        <l>I do not like</l>
                        <l>This <hi>Claudio</hi>'s business here, the Duke is troubled;</l>
                        <l>My whole frame trembles.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam <hi>Iuliana?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>My excellent white Devil, you are welcome,</l>
                        <l>Where is your Catamountain <hi>Flaviano?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>You are no Serpents spawn?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh hear me sir, by your own goodness.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>When didst thou kneel to Heaven?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>I see my leprosie unveild, that sin</l>
                        <l>Which with my loss of honor first ingag'd</l>
                        <l>My miserie, is with a Sun-beam writ</l>
                        <l>Upon my guilty forehead, but I have not</l>
                        <l>(Excepting the concealment of my shame,</l>
                        <l>Which charity might privelege) offended</l>
                        <l>●bove what I confest, and you have pardond.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>She hath a tongue would almost tempt a Sai●●</l>
                        <l>To unbeleeve Divinity, she learnd</l>
                        <l>●●me accents from the first Apostate Angell</l>
                        <l>That mutin'd in Heaven; away,</l>
                        <l>● dare not trust my frailty; where's <hi>Flaviano?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit. Leon. and Claud.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>My soul doth apprehend strange shapes of horror.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Fioretta.</stage>
                        <l>●a—tis the Princess <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Can you direct me Madam, how I may</l>
                        <l>〈◊〉 with the noble Lady <hi>Iuliana?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="67" facs="154"/>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <l>I can instruct you Madam where to find</l>
                        <l>A miserable woman of that name.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Where?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Here.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>K●eels.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Do not deceive me,</l>
                        <l>I came to visit her whom the Dukes love</l>
                        <l>And confluence of glories must create</l>
                        <l>A Duchess, to whose greatness I must pay</l>
                        <l>My adoration.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Do not mock her, Madam,</l>
                        <l>To whose undoing nothing wants but death;</l>
                        <l>Let not my sin, which cannot hope your pardon,</l>
                        <l>Make you forget your virtue; Princely natures,</l>
                        <l>As they are next to Forms Angelicall,</l>
                        <l>Shew the next acts of pitty, not derision,</l>
                        <l>When we are fall'n from Innocence.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Do you know me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>For the most injur'd Princess, <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>You must know more, I come to take revenge</l>
                        <l>And kill thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Thus I kneel to meet your wounds,</l>
                        <l>And shall account the drops my proud veines weep</l>
                        <l>Spent for my cure; oh Madam you are not cruell,</l>
                        <l>You have too soft, too mercifull a look;</l>
                        <l>When you see me, your countenance should wear</l>
                        <l>Upon it all the terrors that pale men</l>
                        <l>Can apprehend from the wild face of War,</l>
                        <l>A civill War, that wo' not spare the womb</l>
                        <l>That gron'd and gave it life, this would become you,</l>
                        <l>Or fancie meager Famine when she hunts</l>
                        <l>With hollow eyes, and teeth able to grind</l>
                        <l>A rock of Adamant to dust, or what</l>
                        <l>Complexion the devouring pest should have,</l>
                        <l>Were it to take a shape, and when you put</l>
                        <l>Their horrors in your visage, look on me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="68" facs="155"/>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>What hath prepar'd this bold resolve?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>A hope</l>
                        <l>To be your sacrifice; I was not before</l>
                        <l>Without a thought to wish my self thus layd,</l>
                        <l>And at your feet to beg you would destroy me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Can you so easily consent to dy,</l>
                        <l>And know not whither afterwards this guilt</l>
                        <l>Would fling thy wandring soul?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes. I would pray</l>
                        <l>And ask your self, and the wrong'd world forgiveness.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Why didst thou use me thus?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>weeps.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>I could, if you</l>
                        <l>Durst hear me, say something perhaps would take</l>
                        <l>Your charity. Do you weep? gentle Madam?</l>
                        <l>And not one crimson drop from me, to wait</l>
                        <l>Upon those precious shewers? not to invite</l>
                        <l>Your patience upon the lost <hi>Iuliana,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But to call back your tears into their spring,</l>
                        <l>And stay the weeping stream, I can inform you,</l>
                        <l>The Duke looks on me now with eyes of anger;</l>
                        <l>I have no interest in a thought from him,</l>
                        <l>That is not arm'd with hate and scorn against me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>This will undoe my pitty, and assure me</l>
                        <l>Thou hast all this while dissembled with my Justice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>I would I might as soon invest my soul</l>
                        <l>With my first purity, as clear this truth;</l>
                        <l>Or would the loss of him were all that sits</l>
                        <l>Heavy upon my heart; I cannot hope</l>
                        <l>For comfort in delayes of death, and dare</l>
                        <l>Attend you to him, though it more undo me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Rise, and obey me then.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>I follow, Madam;</l>
                        <l>My use of life is only meant to serve you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Hortensio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>This is the place within the wood he promis'd</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="69" facs="155"/>
To meet in, there is Saint <hi>Felices</hi> Chapell,</l>
                        <l>That Father <hi>Cyprians</hi> cell, I hope my Gamster</l>
                        <l>Will think it fit, I should not walk and wait</l>
                        <l>Too long for him, these businesses of fighting</l>
                        <l>Should be dispatch'd as Doctors do prescribe</l>
                        <l>Physicall Pills, not to be chewd but swallow'd;</l>
                        <l>Time spent in the considering deads the appetite,</l>
                        <l>If I were not to fight now, I could pray;</l>
                        <l>These terms of honor have but little grace with 'em,</l>
                        <l>Like Oisters we do open one another●</l>
                        <l>Without much preface; he that fights a duell</l>
                        <l>Like a blind man that falls but cares to keep</l>
                        <l>His staffe, provides with art to save his honor,</l>
                        <l>But trusts his soul to chance, tis an ill fashion.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Frier.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
                        <l>This is the Gentleman by her description</l>
                        <l>That comes to fight, another Champion?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Flaviano.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>Do none persue me, what a timerous Hare</l>
                        <l>This guilty conscience is, I am not safe,</l>
                        <l>I had no time to think of a disguise,</l>
                        <l>And this can be no wilderness, the Duke</l>
                        <l>Would give his Pallace for my head.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <l>Say so?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh for some <hi>Pegasus</hi> to mount! a Frier?</l>
                        <l>His habit will serve rarely, seeming holiness</l>
                        <l>Is a most excellent shrovvd to cheat the world.</l>
                        <l>Good Father sanctity, I must be bold,</l>
                        <l>Or cut your throat, nay I can follovv.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
                        <l>Help, help.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou sacrilegious Villain.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I am caught already.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="70" facs="156"/>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>My good Lord <hi>Flaviano.</hi> Father</l>
                        <l>You may come back, and help to bind the Gentleman</l>
                        <l>If I did understand him well, he said</l>
                        <l>The Duke has some affairs to use his head-peece;</l>
                        <l>I would not have him out o'th' way, when I●</l>
                        <l>Return—to that tree—you were best be gentle.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I can but dye.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Flav. is tied to a Tree.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh yes, you may be damn'd</l>
                        <l>All in good time, and it is very likely.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
                        <l>You have preserv'd my life Son.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>It was my happiness to be so near,</l>
                        <l>VVhen virtue was distrest.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Frier.</speaker>
                        <l>You have not done sir,</l>
                        <l>As you are noble follow me, there is</l>
                        <l>Another ●nemy to meet, but I</l>
                        <l>Dare be your second and direct you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>VVhat means the <hi>Fryer?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I'l walk and see the worst on't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt all but Flav.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Be●to●di.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh for a Tenement under ground to hide me▪</l>
                        <l>This wood will hardly do't, if I can lurk</l>
                        <l>Here but till night; I am furnish'd well with ducats;</l>
                        <l>Your melancholy mole is happy now,</l>
                        <l>He fears no Officers, but walks invisible;</l>
                        <l>Would I were chamber-fellow to a worm,</l>
                        <l>The Rooks have princely lives that dwell upon</l>
                        <l>The top● of Trees, the Owls and Bats are Gentlemen,</l>
                        <l>They fly and fear no warrants, every Hare</l>
                        <l>Out-runs the Constable, only poor man</l>
                        <l>By nature slow and full of flegm, must stay,</l>
                        <l>And stand the cursed Law, I do not think</l>
                        <l>Tis so much Penance to be hang'd indeed,</l>
                        <l>As to be thus in fear on't.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="71" facs="156"/>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, look this way.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh! if I had but the heart of a womans Tailor,</l>
                        <l>I might run away now.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I am rob'd and bound.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Umh, are you bound? there's the less danger in you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>For charity release me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You are surely bound—whats that?</l>
                        <l>I hear another whispering o' that side;</l>
                        <l>Now I sweat all over, I but think</l>
                        <l>If I were naked, how Maids might gather dew</l>
                        <l>From every part about me—Tis the wind</l>
                        <l>Among the leaves. I do not like the Trees</l>
                        <l>Should lay their heads together o' this fashion.</l>
                        <l>You are my fast friend still.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Signior Bertoldi.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Does he name me?</l>
                        <l>You and the Tree shall grow together now,</l>
                        <l>I came not hither to be known; some Thief,</l>
                        <l>Or sturdy rogue; I have heard of these devices</l>
                        <l>In woods before; should I unbind him now,</l>
                        <l>Hee'd cut my throat, or rob me for my charity.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>I am the man for your sake undertook</l>
                        <l>To kill the Prince your rivall.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Did you so? I'l trust you ne'r the sooner;</l>
                        <l>Well remembred, I'me glad y'are not at leisure;</l>
                        <l>You that will kill your Prince, will make but little</l>
                        <l>Conscience to quarter me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>But he is still alive.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Is he so?</l>
                        <l>Why then I am the less beholding to you.</l>
                        <l>So, you shall cancell your own bonds your self.</l>
                        <stage>Enter Hortensio, Florelia and Frier.</stage>
                        <l>How now, more persecution?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Here was a Duell quickly taken up,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="72" facs="157"/>
And quaintly too, I did not think to marry</l>
                        <l>The Gentleman that challeng'd me to fight,</l>
                        <l>I thank your device Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Thank the blow you gave me sir,</l>
                        <l>I love a man dares strike.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l please you better with my after striking.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>My Mother and <hi>Hortensio?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Volterino and Officers.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Signior Bertoldi</hi> well met, lay hands on him</l>
                        <l>And bind him fast, he has a dangerous spirit</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Who I? you may as well say I have skil in the</l>
                        <l>Black art, <hi>Volterino,</hi> Gentlemen, there's my Mother.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Son is valiant Madam now I hope,</l>
                        <l>As you can wish, he has kil'd his man; but I</l>
                        <l>Studious to gain your favor have procur'd?</l>
                        <l>His pardon from the Duke.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Is the Drawer dead?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Dead as the Wine he sometimes drew.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Farewell he; will you salute my Lady <hi>Signior</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And give us joy? yon Frier married us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Let me go, I have my pardon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Not yet; now you shall be hang'd agen,</l>
                        <l>Did not you swear I should have your Mother</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall have her yet.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>If it be so,</l>
                        <l>He shall be worth your suit, and compound fairly.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>No, I have thought of my revenge; because</l>
                        <l>I cannot have your Mother, d'ee observe,</l>
                        <l>If you expect the benefit of this pardon,</l>
                        <l>You shall marry mine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l marry any living soul,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Shee's somethi●g old, till the last night I see her not</l>
                        <l>These forty years, since when shee's grown so ugly,</l>
                        <l>I dare not own her, and some think the reason</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="73" facs="157"/>
Of her deformity to proceed from witchcraft.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas good Gentlewoman.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>I mean she is a Witch her self,</l>
                        <l>And has two Cats they say,</l>
                        <l>Suck her by turnes, which some call her Familiars;</l>
                        <l>She has not had a tooth this thirty years;</l>
                        <l>And you must kiss her with a spung i' your mouth,</l>
                        <l>She is so full of flegm, else sheel go near</l>
                        <l>To strangle you, and yet they say she has</l>
                        <l>A most devouring appetite to mans flesh,</l>
                        <l>You may have a devill of your own to attend you,</l>
                        <l>And when y'are melancholy,</l>
                        <l>Sheel make you Ghosts and Goblins dance before you</l>
                        <l>Bring Bears and Bandogs with an o'r grown Ape</l>
                        <l>Playing upon the Gittern.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>Where is this creature? shall he not see her first?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>I left her in a Sive was bound for <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>This morn to see some kindred, whence she was</l>
                        <l>Determin'd to take Eg-shell to <hi>Skeedam.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <stage>Enter Pandolpho disguis'd.</stage>
                        <l>From thence when she has din'd she promis'd me</l>
                        <l>To ride post hither on a Distaff.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>How?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh here she is, what think you of a Husband</l>
                        <l>Mother? can you love this Gentleman, hee's one</l>
                        <l>Will be a great comfort to you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pandol.</speaker>
                        <l>I like the stripling well,</l>
                        <l>He will serve to watch my pits, and see that non●</l>
                        <l>Of my spirits boile over.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Is this your Mother</l>
                        <l>Come I'l be hang'd, tis the more hansome destiny</l>
                        <l>Unless you will take composition—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pandol.</speaker>
                        <l>Let me talk with the Gentleman.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I am at leisure now to wait on you sir.</l>
                        <l>Unbind, and lead him to the Duke.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="74" facs="158"/>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Flaviano?</hi> you are the Gentleman his Higness</l>
                        <l>Gave strict command should be persu'd, I shall</l>
                        <l>Be proud to wait upon you to the Court.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                        <l>I wo'not lose my passion on such bloodhounds.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>We are agreed, hey, here's my pardon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, I am satisfied, and can thank you <hi>Signior</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In severall shapes—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>The Drawer.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pand.</speaker>
                        <l>I did want a sum like this to set me up: I was</l>
                        <l>Provided gainst your Sword, a pretty night-cap,</l>
                        <l>And almost Pistoll proof, I shall be rich,</l>
                        <l>I thank your bounty, and so rid the Witch.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Here's none of the Dukes hand.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>It needs not Madam.</l>
                        <l>I know not yet by what device you came together thus.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l tell you as we walk.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Pay for a pardon and not kill my man?</l>
                        <l>The Duke shall hear o' this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeu●t.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Leonato.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>No news of <hi>Flaviano</hi> yet? some furies</l>
                        <l>Have sure transported him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Petronio.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                        <l>A Gentleman with Letters sir from <hi>Mantua.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Duke of Mantua.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha! admit him—leave us, the Duke himself?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <l>That comes to offer</l>
                        <l>A pledge for young <hi>Honorio,</hi> not in thought</l>
                        <l>Guilty of that unprincely entertainment</l>
                        <l>You h●d at <hi>Mantua.</hi> if my Son, as fame</l>
                        <l>Is ●●sie in <hi>Ferrara,</hi> be expos'd</l>
                        <l>To your displeasure, change my fate with his,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="75" facs="158"/>
That to my shame in part consented to</l>
                        <l>The practice of a Traitor <hi>Flaviano,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Who us'd my power to advance his own ambition</l>
                        <l>To your dishonour, and instead of my</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fioretta,</hi> whether now alive or dead</l>
                        <l>I know not, cheat your faith with <hi>Iuliana,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To quit the noble safety your Sword brought us,</l>
                        <l>My life is troublesome in the loss of fame,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Where is <hi>Flaviano?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Duke</hi> Fled like a guilty villain from my Justice,</l>
                        <l>May hortor overtake him; let my Son</l>
                        <l>Live by some noble deeds to expiate</l>
                        <l>His Fathers forfeit, and disgrace; I come</l>
                        <l>Without a guard, and were it not a crime</l>
                        <l>To my eternity, cou'd sacrifice</l>
                        <l>My self without expecting your revenge,</l>
                        <l>Or nature to conclude my age.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Donabella, Fioretta, Iuliana.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Let me have Justice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Give me Justice Prince.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>Let me have Justice too.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Against whom Sister?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>Against this Lady.</l>
                        <l>She hath conspir'd to take away my life.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>My enemy is Duke <hi>Leonato</hi> sir,</l>
                        <l>Who hath conspir'd to take away himself,</l>
                        <l>A Treasure equall with my life.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>My enemy is <hi>Iuliana</hi> sir, that hath con●pir'd</l>
                        <l>To rob her self, both of her life and honor.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mant.</hi> Tis she, my aged eyes take leave of seeing,</l>
                        <l>Expect no object after this so welome.</l>
                        <l>My Daughter <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Deerest Father.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dona.</speaker>
                        <l>How, <hi>Fioretta?</hi> she is then but Sister</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="76" facs="159"/>
To my <hi>Honorio,</hi> life of all my joyes,</l>
                        <l>My feet have wings at this glad news.</l>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Were you the Suffering Lady <hi>Fioretta?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>How could you live so long within the Court,</l>
                        <l>And no good Angell all this while acquaint me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>This joy is too too mighty, and I sha' not</l>
                        <l>Repent my exile to be thus rewarded.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Confirm my happiness again, no treason</l>
                        <l>Shall now divide us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>Your hearts grow together.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>I have receiv'd by <hi>Claudio</hi> the particular</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Flavianos</hi> treason, he has guilt</l>
                        <l>Above your knowledge sir, <hi>Iuliana</hi> findes it,</l>
                        <l>And is confest his strumpet.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>You amaze me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>I bless now my suspition, when I was</l>
                        <l>Convaid from <hi>Mantua,</hi> which directed me</l>
                        <l>To leave <hi>Placentia</hi> secretly, and invite</l>
                        <l>My self a stranger to this Court, where now</l>
                        <l>I meet as much joy as my soul can fancie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                        <l>You have not all this while pronounc'd my doom,</l>
                        <l>I fear you hold intelligence with my soul,</l>
                        <l>And know what pains I feel while I am living,</l>
                        <l>You will not be so mercifull to kill me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Claudio, Volterino, Hortensio, Florelia,
Bertoldi, Flaviano.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>Flaviano!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor●.</speaker>
                        <l>I present you with a Gentleman,</l>
                        <l>I took rifling a Hermit in the Wood,</l>
                        <l>As it appears in hope to scape persute,</l>
                        <l>Hid in a Friers habit, who dispatch'd</l>
                        <l>After a matrimoniall betwixt</l>
                        <l>This Lady and my self.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="77" facs="159"/>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>That old Gentleman should be Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>What think you sir?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>And that his Daughter <hi>Fioretta.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>She is my Mistris.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Claud.</speaker>
                        <l>She is like to prove the Duchess of <hi>Ferrara.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>His Grace will not use me so,</l>
                        <l>I will have Justice, Justice Gentle Duke.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Are you mad.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I'l be reveng'd o' somebody.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Honorio, Donabella</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Honorio</hi> your son, to meet your blessing.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Don.</speaker>
                        <l>This was the life I feard to lose by her,</l>
                        <l>Whom I suppos'd my rivall, pardon Madam.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>Thus circled, I must faint beneath my happiness</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Forgive my passion, and receive a Brother.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Honor.</speaker>
                        <l>That name doth honor us, where is <hi>Flaviano?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                        <l>Whose witty brain must sentence me? let it</l>
                        <l>Be home and hansom, I shall else despise</l>
                        <l>And scorn your coarse inventions.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Fior.</speaker>
                        <l>Let me obtain, since providence hath wrought</l>
                        <l>This happy change, you would not stain our joyes</l>
                        <l>With any blood, let not their sins exceed our charity.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
                        <l>Let him for ever then be banish'd both</l>
                        <l>Our Duke-doms.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
                        <l>What shall become of <hi>Iuliana?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                        <l>She (if your grace more fit to judge, consent)</l>
                        <l>Shall to a house of converts and strict penance,</l>
                        <l>Where <hi>Flaviano,</hi> as the price of her</l>
                        <l>L●st honor, shall pay her dowry to Religion;</l>
                        <l>What doth remain of his estate, shall be</l>
                        <l>Emploid toward the redeeming Christian Captives.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <l>I chearfully obey, and call it mercy.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis a most pious Justice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="78" facs="160"/>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>Justice, thats my kue, Justice, Justice to <hi>Bertoldi</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Against <hi>Signior Volterino,</hi> I am cheated.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                        <l>Will you be a fool upon record?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>You shall have Justice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volterino,</speaker>
                        <l>we appoint you, till he learn</l>
                        <l>More wit, to be his Guardian, and at your</l>
                        <l>Discretion govern his estate, so leave us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Volt.</speaker>
                        <l>I shall with my best study manage both.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Bert.</speaker>
                        <l>I am as good as begg'd for a fool.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
                        <l>And thus we chain our hearts and provinces.</l>
                        <l>Madam I wish you joyes, to <hi>Fioretta</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I give my self, my Sister to <hi>Honorio.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Treason is sick in her short reign, but when</l>
                        <l>Heaven sees his time, Truth takes her Throne agen.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="epilogue">
                  <pb facs="160"/>
                  <head>Epilogue, by Iuliana.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>NOW</hi> the play's done, I will confess to you,</l>
                  <l>And wo' not doubt but you'll absolve me too.</l>
                  <l>There is a mysterie, let it not go far;</l>
                  <l>For this Confession is a●ricular:</l>
                  <l>I am sent among the Nuns to fast and pray,</l>
                  <l>And suffer piteous penance, ha, ha, ha,</l>
                  <l>They could no better way please my desires,</l>
                  <l>I am no Nun—but one of the Black-Friers.</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         </TEI>

