<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The ile of gulls As it hath been often acted in the Black Fryers, by the Children of the Revels.</title>
            <author>Day, John, 1574-1640?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent> 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2008 September (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">AUA7312</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 6414</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 235(b)</idno>
            <idno type="vid">9948</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">The ile of gulls As it hath been often acted in the Black Fryers, by the Children of the Revels.</title>
                  <title type="alt">Ile of guls</title>
                  <title type="add">Colección Arcadia.</title>
                  <author>Day, John, 1574-1640?</author>
                  <author>Sidney, Philip, 1554-1586.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Augustine Mathewes] for William Sheares, at the Harrow in Britaines Bursse,</publisher>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>By John Day.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>The plot is taken from: Sidney, Sir Philip.  Arcadia.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Signatures: A-HÛp4Ûs.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note>
                     <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script marc2tei.pl on 2003-10-07.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="1"/>
                  <pb facs="1"/>
                  <p>THE ILE OF GVLLS.</p>
                  <p>As it hath been often Acted in the Black Fryers, by the Children of the REVELS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed for WILLIAM SHEARES, at the Harrow in <hi>Britaines Burſſe.</hi> 1633.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="2"/>
                  <pb facs="2"/>
                  <head>THE ILE OF GVLLS.</head>
                  <stage>I Enter ſeverally three Gentlemen, as to ſee a Play.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>_HOW now gallants, what iſt? what iſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>The Ile of Guls.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3</speaker>
                     <p>The Ile of Guls, what ſhould that be?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>A play by the name, but come ſhals quarter our ſelues?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>If ſome had had the wit to doe ſo in time, they might haue ſau'd the hang-man a labour. But come boy, furniſh us with ſtooles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Prologue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon mee ſir, my office is to ſpeake a Prologue, not to provide you ſtooles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>And you were the Epilogue to ſir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Fie be not incivill: doſt heare youth, prethee what's he that diſcovered your new found Land, <hi>the Ile of Guls?</hi> what is he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>A meere ſtranger ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3</speaker>
                     <p>A ſtranger? the better welcome: comes hee Eaſt-ward, Weſt-ward, or North-ward hoe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>None of the three wayes I aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee where is he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Not on his knees in a comer to <hi>Apollo,</hi> praying that his play may hold in a good hand at Paſſage, nor on the ſtage amongſt gal|lants, preparing a beſpoke Plaudite; but cloſe in his ſtudy writing hard, to get him a handſome ſuite againſt Summer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>And where ſit his friends? hath he not a prepared company of gallants, to applaud his jeſts, and grace out his play?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>None I proteſt▪ Do Poets uſe to beſpeake their Auditory?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3</speaker>
                     <p>The beſt in grace doe, and but for that, ſome that I know, had never had their grace in Poetry till this day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Then muſt our Author looké for a certaine diſgrace, for he is altogether unfurniſht of ſuch a friendly audience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>Then he muſt lay his triall upon God and good wits But why
<pb facs="3"/>
doth he call his play <hi>The Ile of Gulls?</hi> it begets much expectation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Not out of any dogged diſpoſition, nor that it figures any certaine ſtate, or private government: farre bee that ſuppoſition from the thought of any indifferent Auditor: and the argument being a little ſtring or ●ivolet, drawen from the full ſtraine of the right worthy Gentleman Sir <hi>Phillip Sydnies</hi> well knowne Arca|dia, confirmes it: only a Duke, to make triall of certaine experi|ments, retires with his retinue into a nameleſſe deſert. Now as well for faſhion ſake, as that all thoſe which haue to doe in that de|ſert, are guld in the reach of their hopes; therefore he cals it, (and as he preſumes, not improperly) <hi>The Ile of Gulls.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>Out a queſtion he hath promiſed thee ſome fee, thou pleadeſt ſo hard for him, but and he be a right Poet he will never performe it. But what method obſerues he in his Play, iſt any thing Criticall? Are Lawyers fees, and Citizens wiues laid open in it? I loue to heare vice anatomizd, and abuſe let blood in the maſter vaine, is there any great mans life charactred in't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>None I proteſt ſir, only in the perſon of <hi>Dametas,</hi> he ex|preſſes to the life the monſtrous and deformed ſhape of vice, aſwell to beget a loathing of abuſe, as that his villany may giue the greater luſter to the vertuous diſpoſitions of true-borne gentility.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>All that's nothing to mee, and there bee not Worme-wood water and Copperes in't, Ile not like it, ſhould <hi>Apollo</hi> write it, and <hi>Roſius</hi> himſelfe act it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Fie upon thee, thou art too too criticall: is there any good baudry in't, jeſts of an ell deepe, and a fathome broad, good cuckol|ding, may a couple of young-ſetters-up learne to doe well in't? Giue me a Scene of venery, that will make a mans ſpirits ſtand on their tiptoes, and die his blood in a deepe ſcarlet, like your <hi>Ovids Ars Amandi,</hi> there flowes the true Spring-head of Poetry, and the very Chriſtall fount of <hi>Parnaſſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Chaſt eares would never endure it fir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Chaſt eares? now deafeneſſe light upon them, what ſhould chaſt eares doe at a play?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3</speaker>
                     <p>Tis ſtrange now, I am of neither a both your opinions, I like neither rayling nor baudry: no, giue me a ſtately pend hiſtorie, as thus: <hi>The rugged winds, with rude and ragged ruffes, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Fie upon't, more fuſtian; I had rather heare two good baudy jeſts, then a whole play of ſuch teare-cat thunder-claps.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="3"/>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas Gentlemen, bow iſt poſſible to content you? you wil haue rayling, and invectiues, which our Author neither dares, nor affects: you baudy and ſcurrill jeſts, which neither becomes his modeſty to write, nor the eare of a generous Auditory to heare: you muſt haue ſwelling compariſons, and ●um●aſt Epithites, which are as fit for the body of a Com●edy▪ as <hi>Her●●les</hi> ſhooe for the foote of a Pigmey: yet all theſe we muſt haue, and all in one play, or tis already condemn'd to the hell of eternall diſgrace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>Looke to't, if there be not gall in't, it ſhall not paſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>If it be not baudy, tis impoſſible to paſſe:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3</speaker>
                     <p>If it bee both criticall and baudy, if it bee not high written, both your Poet and the houſe too, looſe a friend of me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay I beſeech you ſir, if you be his friend, ſtand ſo to him ſtill, for he hath too many enemies already, in whoſe judgements, he and his labours ſtand excommunicate, as though unworthy to preſent themſelues in this aſſembly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1</speaker>
                     <p>Enemies? nays foote then there's ſome hope in his play, for Envie never workes but againſt deſert and merit. If he be envied theres ſome worth in him, and ile ſee out his play for that onely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Faith and Ile ſee an act or two out, but I tell you afore-hand I cannot ſee it out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſee it out? your reaſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Fore God I lay in bed till paſt three a clock, ſlept out my din|ner, and my ſtomacke will toule to ſupper afore fiue, therefore you muſt pardon me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>Either ſee it all or none; for tis growen into a cuſtome at playes, if any one riſe (eſpecially of any faſhionable ſort) about what ſerious buſines ſoever, the reſt thinking it in diſlike of the play, though he never thinks it, cry mew, by ●eſus vilde; and leaue the poore heartleſſe children to ſpeake their Epilogue to the empty ſeats.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3</speaker>
                     <p>Why doeſt thinke thy audience like a flock of ſheepe, that one cannot leape over a hedge, but all the reſt will follow? they haue more of reaſon in them then ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Well, Ile ſit out the play, an't bee but to avoyd that ſheepiſh imputation, but ſee it be baudy, or by this light I and all my friends will hiſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhould not deale gentleman-like with us els.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="prologue">
                  <pb facs="4"/>
                  <head>Prologus.</head>
                  <l>THe miſery that waytes upon the pen</l>
                  <l>Of the beſt Writers, iudge it Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Let them expreſſe the very ſoule of wit,</l>
                  <l>And want Opinions voice to count'nance it,</l>
                  <l>Tis like the idle buzzing of a Flie,</l>
                  <l>Heard, not regarded: wretched Poetry!</l>
                  <l>If he write mirth, tis ribaldry, and meane,</l>
                  <l>Scorn'd of chaſt eares: If he compoſe a Sceane</l>
                  <l>Of high writ Poeſie, fitting a true ſtage,</l>
                  <l>Tis counted ſuſtian: If Poetickerage</l>
                  <l>Strike at abuſe, or op● the veine of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Hee's ſtraight inform'd againſt for libelling.</l>
                  <l>Neither quicke mirth, invective, nor high ſtate</l>
                  <l>Can content all, ſuch is the boundleſſe hate</l>
                  <l>Of a confuſed Audience: Then we</l>
                  <l>That ſcarcely know the rules of Poeſie</l>
                  <l>Cannot ſcape check. Yet this our comfort is,</l>
                  <l>The wiſe will ſmile to heare th'impartiall hiſſe.</l>
                  <l>We neither bragge, nor tremble, faint nor intreat,</l>
                  <l>Our merits nothing, yet our hopes are great,</l>
                  <l>Yet this our Author bad me boldly ſpeake,</l>
                  <l>His play ſhall paſſe, let Envie ſwell and breake,</l>
                  <l>Detraction he ſcornes, honours the beſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tanti</hi> for hate; thus low to all the reſt.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <p>Exit.</p>
                  </stage>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="play">
                  <pb facs="4"/>
                  <head>The Ile of Gulls.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="act">
                     <head>ACTVS. I. SCENA. I.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <p>Enter <hi>Baſilius, Gynetia, Hipolita, Violetta,</hi> Lords attendants.</p>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>VVElcome gallants, welcome honor'd bloods; the reaſon that we haue uncloth'd us of our princely government in <hi>Arcadia,</hi> and haue to doe with this private retire|ment here in this deſert Ile, you ſhall find in that ſhedule, only thus much for publicke ſatisfaction: Tis not ſtrange to you, that the choiſeſt treaſure Nature indow'd us with, is min'd up in the veines of my two daughters: how much their quiet, and the ſmooth ſtreame of our government in <hi>Arcadia,</hi> was troubled by the im|petuous concourſe of untruely ſuters, is familiar with your know|ledge; this to avoid, I haue for my Image there in my abſence ap|pointed my brother, and undertooke this private retirement.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Gy.</speaker>
                        <p>Why my Lord, are you ſo covetous of your daughters beau|ties, that their perfections ſhall bee a meanes to hinder their prefer|ment?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſi.</speaker>
                        <p>Rather to further it faire Queene: they are the only pearles of our age, and to ſee them wel ſet in honourable and well-befitting Marriage, is our wiſhes happineſſe.</p>
                        <l>To which effect we haue ſent a generall challenge</l>
                        <l>To all the youthfull bloods of Affrica,</l>
                        <l>That whoſoever (borne of princely ſtem)</l>
                        <l>Dares foote the boſome of this deſert Ile,</l>
                        <l>(The ſtage where Ile performe this lovers prize)</l>
                        <l>And by his wit and actiue pollicie,</l>
                        <l>Wooe, win, intice, or any way defeate</l>
                        <l>Me of my charge, my daughters of their hearts,</l>
                        <l>Shall with their loues weare my imperiall crowne</l>
                        <l>Wreath of their conqueſt.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>A prize, a prize, rare worke for Fencers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>What coward would not venter a crackt crowne for ſuch a bootie?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>To that intent our Iland is fenc't in</l>
                           <l>By ſea and land, and at each corner built</l>
                           <l>A Caſtle for defence, which like great men,</l>
                           <l>Doe over-looke <hi>Arcadia:</hi> over which,</l>
                           <l>Wee haue appointed Captaines. More to deſire,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="5"/>Is more then we are willing to diſcover.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Well then ſiſter, I ſee we muſt to hap-hazard for husbands.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>God ſend me one with a good face and I care not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Loue an't be thy will, ſend me one with a faire table in his forehead, like Time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, and his face be good, let me alone to tricke his fore|head, a countrey-gentlewoman taught me how: But father I won|der how you dare undertake ſuch a peremptory challenge againſt all commers, conſidering you haue beene ſo long troubled with ●● Ague.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>An ague? what ague?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Why your quotidian, <hi>Dametas</hi> the Court ſurfet, hee that dwels in your eye, like a diſeaſe in your blood.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>And the Preſence were not exceeding empty-ſtomackt, it would never diſgeſt ſuch Almes-basket-ſcraps, the very fall and gar|bidge of gentry; fie upon him, hee becomes the great chamber worſe then a Gentleman-uſher with wry legges.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>He is the moſt miſhapen ſute of gentility that ever the Court wore.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Had hee not beene of my fathers owne making, I ſhould haue condemned his taylor for an exceeding botcher.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>If you retaine the loue of children, or the dutie of ſub|jects, expreſſe it in your obedience, we know <hi>Dametas</hi> loues us▪</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>As Captaines and Courtiers doe old widdowes, for pro|fit and preferment.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>In ſigne whereof wee make him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, you haue beſtowed too much of the making of him up already.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>The very making of him up, has ſtood you in more then the whole outſide's worth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>In my free thoughts you wrong him, therefore to ex|preſſe our loue, aud to giue the world publicke note of his loyaltie, we create him your Gardian.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>How father, my Gardian?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>I minion, yours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe you heare father, bid him beſpeake ſpectacles, for my fingers haue vowed to haue a blind match with his eyes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Well ſaid Haggart, Ile make your proud heart ſtoope to the lure of obedience. But come, by this time our challenge is pub|liſht,
<pb facs="5"/>
and our gallants wits ſweating in the field of Invention, and it behoues us not to reſt unexerciſed.</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>So to our lodge, in the meane time be it knowne,</l>
                           <l>Our breath has power to raiſe, or caſt men downe.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter two Captaines.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Now Captaine Obſervation, times bawd, thou that haſt kept the Ages doore, whilſt up-ſtart baſeneſſe crept into the bed of greatneſſe, what doeſt thou thinke of this change?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>That it pleas'd the Duke, and becomes not ſubjects to examine his actions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Thats no part of my meaning, yet would I gladly bee better inſtructed why the Duke broke up his Court in Arcadia, and removed it into this Iland.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I am not Secretary to his thoughts, but the generall rumour is, that out of the freeneſſe of his ſpirit, he hath ſent a chal|lenge to all his neighbour Princes, that whoſoever (within a twelue moneth) can defeate him of his daughters, ſhall with their loues enioy his Dukedome, the garland propos'd for the victors.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Your words throw ſenſe into me, and thats the cauſe the Iland is ſo ſurely guarded with Watch-towers, over which our ſelues and other Captaines haue the charge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>And to the end that not affection, but deſert may proue victor, are the two Ladies ſo narrowly obſerved, the one never out a the eye of her Father, the other continually in the lodge of <hi>Da|metas,</hi> the Dukes chiefe director.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>If inquiſitiueneſſe be not too bold a gueſt, what do you thinke of <hi>Dametas?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>As of a little hillock, made great with others ruines.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Your compariſon holds, for by report, his avarice has unmade many to make him up.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>How did he firſt ſtumble on the Princes favour?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>As ſome doe upon offices, by fortune and flattery, or as truth ſayes, the Prince having one day loſt his way, wandring in the woods, found this <hi>Dametas,</hi> affected his diſcourſe, tooke him along to the Court, and like great men in loue with their owne doings, countenanc't his defects, gaue him offices, titles, and all the additi|ons that goe to the making up of a man worſhipfull.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I cannot commend the Duke for raiſing him, nor yet
<pb facs="6"/>
praiſe him, that hee proportions not his carriage anſwerable to his fortunes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Your thoughts and mine are twinnes in that: but I heare the warning bell, ſome ſtrangers are arrived.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Lets to our office then, and conduct them to <hi>Dametas,</hi> whoſe cuſtome is to ſpit and hem, whilſt his Scribe Major takes their Examinations.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Dametas <hi>and</hi> Manaſſes.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> how doeſt like my play at Tennis?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>You play well, but you loſe ſtill.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Pollicie <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> pollicie; for when any man upbraides me with my gettings at Court, I may ſweare truly, I haue loſt more then I haue got by't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>By the Tennis-court I thinke you haue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>If by any Court, tis enough to ſaue mine oath. But what doe our ſpruce-witted gallants ſay of my bountie?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith ſir, according to the proportion of it, little or nothing, they ſay tis a banckrout, and dares not ſhew his head.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Then let em leaue jeſting at me, though it pleaſe the Duke for ſome few good parts that hee ſees in me, to make me his fami|liar, I ſcorne to be publike, or every Courtiers companion: but who comes heere?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter the two Captaines, with <hi>Aminter</hi> and <hi>Iulio,</hi> two princes, one attired like a poore ſouldier, the other like a poore ſcholler.</stage>
                     <p>The Captaines of the watch-towers? what newes with you?</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>A couple of petitioners, ant like your worſhip.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Had I beſt take their Petitions, <hi>Manaſſes?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>O in any caſe, though you never peruſe em, tis the onely courſe in requeſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Fellowes, deliver your petitions to my Scribe Major, and doſt heare? put em up <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> they may be wrongs to us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>And they bee, I hope they be not the firſt wrongs I haue put up for your worſhip.</p>
                        <stage>Puts up their papers.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>That fellowes pocket is like a Tailors hell, it eats up part of every mans due: tis an Executioner, and makes away more inno|cent petitions in one yeere, then a red-headed hangman cuts ropes in an age.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Now, what are you ſirra?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="6"/>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>A poore ſouldier, ant like your Worſhip.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Poore ſouldiers doe not like my vvorſhip, they are bad members.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Then if they had a woman to their Iudge, they ſhould be ſure to be cut off, for they cannot indure bad members in a Com|mon-wealth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>What are you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>A poore ſcholler, ant like your Worſhip.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Poore ſchollers do not like our worſhip neither, they raile againſt rich Cormorants, they are bad members too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Cut them off both ſir, and make the land an Eunuch.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile take order with em I warrant thee; and I may haue my will, ile neither ha poore ſcholler nor ſouldier about the Court.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>The next way to make it the Ile of fooles.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Whats he talks of fooles there? why how now ſir, know you to whom you ſpeake?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Cry your worſhip mercy, I had forgot your authority.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>But I remember well enough I warrant you; I command you in my name and the Dukes, to attend your guard, and you re|gard me no more then a careleſſe Lawyer doth an undone clyent, but ile informe: the Duke ſhall know, out, packe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Command your ſlaues ſir, we are gentlemen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſo I hope are we ſir, and of the beſt and laſt edition, of the Dukes owne making.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Cry your authoritie mercy, will you diſcharge us of theſe paſſengers?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>You are diſcharg'd, about your buſineſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1. <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Bad fate, that wrong ſhould ſet his foot on right, And true borne Eagles ſtoope to this baſe Kite.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>What an excellent trade it is to be an officer maker, ile haue more officers, and one ſhalbe to keepe ſchollers and ſouldiers out of the Court, for they dare not come in the great Chamber already, for want of good clothes. But gods me <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> go tell the Duke I muſt ſpeake with him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Preſently ſir, Ile goe fetch the head to giue the foot a poſſet: and my maſter had wit to his villanie, he would make an ex|cellent diſh for the hang-man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Right vvorſhipfull.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſir, I know my place is vvorſhipfull; I tell thee Knaue, I
<pb facs="7"/>
could hang thee by my pattent, if it were granted once, ile tell thee how it runs, it allowes me 24. knaues, 6 knights, 10. fooles, 13. fel|lons, and 14. traytors by the yeare, take them how, why, when, and where I pleaſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe not thinke the Duke will ever grant it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Why not grant it? why ſhould you thinke hee will not grant it? Such another word and ile ſend you to Limbo inſtantly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>We thanke you good <hi>Dametas. Diſcover themſelues.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>I hope you'l take reaſonable baile for our forth comming.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                        <p>The caſe is alter'd with you ſince you came out of <hi>Arcadia.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>My honorable friends, <hi>Iulio</hi> and <hi>Aminter,</hi> my ſelfe and the beſt abilitie of my power, lies at your ſervice.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>You ſee how confidently wee preſume upon your Let|ters promiſe, in furthering us to attaine the lovers prize.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>The Dukes daughters are your owne, and in a word thus ſhall you attaine them, ſome 3 dayes hence I will appoint a hunting, to which I will invite the Duke &amp; both his daughters: in this hunt will I upon ſome ſudden occaſion divide the traine, and having ſin|gled out the two Does, I hope you haue wit enough to ſtrike.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>To ſtrike, how meane you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>As headſmen doe, off with their maiden-heads, or if the Duke offer reſiſtance, off with his crowne too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>That were violence, and cleane oppoſite to the intent of the challenge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Damet.</speaker>
                        <p>Come yee are ſhallow, to't <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> to't, Ile bee your ſecond, thinke of the Crowne, haue my Letters travaild for you, my wit wrought for you, and my invention ſweat for you, to poſſeſſe you of your loues, and ſeate you in the Dukedome, and come you now with tis violence, and againſt the intent of the challenge? I am aſhamed to heare you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay <hi>Dametas,</hi> and your reſolution bee ſo forward, ours ſhall over-take you, wee doubted leaſt the preferments your Lord hath heapt upon you, had ſmothered your affection to us|ward.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>That was the father that begot the doubt in us, you will appoint the hunt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Sever the Duke, divide the traine, and then—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>We haue your meaning.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Put it in execution then, but firſt entertaine ſome new
<pb facs="7"/>
diſguiſe, as at our next meeting Ile informe you. Adew, I ſhall thinke long till I ſee you againe.</p>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>As a Lawyer doth for his Clyent for a ſecond fee. Here's no <hi>Iudas?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and a damn'd one too, for he would betray and ſell his Maſter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis common in ſuch baſe fellowes, ſuch Court-ſpiders, that weaue their webs of flattery in the eares of greatneſſe, if they can once entangle them in their quaint-treachery, they poyſon them ſtraight.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>They are like unneceſſary wormes, whom the ſun of greatneſſe creates of the groſſe and ſlimy multitude, as ſoone as they recover ſtrength, they eate into the credite of true borne gentry, undermine and worke out the true nobilitie, to inroote and eſtabliſh themſelues.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                        <p>And in the end, like <hi>Eſops</hi> ſtaru'd ſnake, having lapt the ſweet milk of greatneſſe, made themſelues ſtrong in authority and friends, they turne their ſtings of envie into their preſervers boſome.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>The example liues in this <hi>Dametas,</hi> who notwithſtanding the Duke hath raiſd him to that height that he lookes equall with himſelfe, yet for the baſe hope of incertaine government, he offers him to ſale; but let his treaſon liue to the laſt minute.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>For my part Ile make that uſe of him that Phyſicians doe of poyſon, uſe as much of him as ſerues for mine honeſt intent, and caſt downe the reſt, as unfit for any neceſſary imployment.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Let our carriage in this attempt put on no ſhew of violence, either to the Duke, or his daughters.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>And let our diſcourſe goe ſo ſmoothly apparelled, that it mooue not the patience of the moſt tender eare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>About it then, though his intent be baſe,</l>
                           <l>Our enterpriſe ſhall weare a noble face.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Liſander</hi> like an Amazon.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Arcadia, thou heaven, within whoſe ſpheare</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>The ſtarre that guides my motion is fixt,</l>
                           <l>I court thy gracious boſome with a kiſſe</l>
                           <l>For this admittance: in thine amorous armes,</l>
                           <l>Faire <hi>Violetta,</hi> fairer then the flower</l>
                           <l>That chriſtned her, and grac't her with that name,</l>
                           <l>Do's play the wanton:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="8"/>Onely her Father like a covetous churle,</l>
                           <l>Owner of that vnvalewed Diamond,</l>
                           <l>Hath made this deſart Ile th'unwilling cheſt</l>
                           <l>In which he lockes her. But the faire advantage</l>
                           <l>Of this large Challenge, and my ſtarres to friend,</l>
                           <l>Ayded by this diſguiſe, I ſhall breake ope</l>
                           <l>His yron Casket, and inlarge my hope.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Dametas and Manaſſes.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>This way ſhe went ſir, this way.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>But I ſay this way, I would thou ſhouldſt know, we old Courtiers can hunt a Cony, and put her to the ſqueak, and make her crie out like a yong married wife of the firſt night.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>For more helpe, as ſome of them haue done: But there ſhe is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile upon her preſently: doſt heare me ſirra? thou veſſell of infirmitie, woman, and by thy out-ſide little better then one of the wicked, come hither and ſhew thy ſelfe before us, ſhew thy ſelfe before <hi>Dametas.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dametas? Liſander</hi> then diſſemble,</p>
                        <p>For hee's the man muſt worke thy entrance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>What art thou? ſpeake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>My mother is the Queene of Amazons,</l>
                           <l>My ſelfe a Virgin, married unto Armes,</l>
                           <l>And bold atchieuements, who haue pac'd the world</l>
                           <l>In queſt of fayre <hi>Antioſte</hi> my ſiſter:</l>
                           <l>And turning homeward, the unconſtant winds,</l>
                           <l>And wrathfull <hi>Neptune</hi> caſt me on this ſhore.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>And what's your buſineſſe now you are landed?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>My buſineſſe is in private with the Duke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>The Duke is buſie, and ſhall ſpeake with no body.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>I beſeech you ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis no beſeeching matter I aſſure you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>No, never beſeech for the matter, for except you could beſeech with the tongue of Angels, tis to no purpoſe with him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis ſtrange, I haue heard thy maſter is a very good man where hee takes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>True, where he takes he is, but he takes nothing of you, and therefore looke for no kindneſſe from him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Good, and doſt thou take after thy Maſter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="8"/>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>No Madam, I take commonly afore my Maſter, for where he takes, he takes all, and leaues nothing for me to take.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, I feele your meaning.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Let my maſter haue ſome feeling of yours, and heele pre|ferre your ſuit.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis not the Dukes pleaſure Petitioners ſhould buy their acceſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>All's one, tis my maſters pleaſure, and uſuall faſhion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>And I muſt maintaine the faſhion. Worſhipfull <hi>Dametas,</hi> my late ſhipwrack as you ſee, hath made a defeat both of my friends and treaſure; notwithſtanding, Fortune hath referv'd me one jewell, which if I might requeſt your Worſhip in loue to accept, and be a meanes to worke my admittance to the Duke, I ſhould become a true debter to your loue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dame.</speaker>
                        <p>Well Madam, tho I hate nothing more then a man that takes bribes, yet preſt by your importunity, and that you tender it in loue, leſt I might ſeeme too nice to withſtand a Ladies favour, Ile weare it for your ſake, and if the Duke be not too buſily employed, worke your acceſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>So doing, you ſhall performe the office of a deare-bought friend.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Dametas.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>How quickly the tide's turn'd! but doe you heare Ma|dam? though I take neither afore nor after my Maſter, yet take my counſell, and do not truſt my maſter: if you haue a ſute to the Duke, keepe it to your ſelfe, for if you truſt my maſter with it, heele pre|ferre it for you, but heele beg't for himſelfe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Thats plaine coozenage.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Fie no, tis cunning in him, marry twould be thought little better then coozenage in a country gentleman: but he returnes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Dametas <hi>againe.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, I haue been earneſt, very earneſt with the Duke for your admittance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>And haue you wrought it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue, marry you muſt think I beſtowd much labour in't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tmay be you did.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam,</speaker>
                        <p>'Tmay be you did: and looke a ſcance like a Pothecaries wife pounding <hi>Colliquintida;</hi> haue my braines ſweat for this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Why the jewell is right <hi>Dametas,</hi> had I but an Aſſe that would ſweat me ſuch pearle.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="9"/>
                        <speaker>Dame.</speaker>
                        <p>An Aſſe? and ſweat ſuch pearle? Ile bar her admittance, here take your jewell, the Duke will allow no admittance, and I will keep you backe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Keep me backe? thou couldſt doe no more and I were a poore mans petitioner.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dame.</speaker>
                        <p>And Ile doe ſo much being a rich petitioner.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>You cannot ſit, you Court ſpaniell, you unneceſſary muſh|rump, that in one night art ſprung out of the root of greatneſſe, I have bought my admittance, and Ile ha't in <hi>deſpetto del fato.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dame.</speaker>
                        <p>I muſt admit her, theſe Ladies are ſo inward with our trickes, there's no good to be done upon them: well Madam, your admittance is open, will you follow?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>With all my heart ſir, Ile be the blind man and poore peti|tioner, and thou ſhalt play the Court-ſpaniell with the ſilver bell, and lead me into the Preſence.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Court-ſpaniell? mum: Ile boſome what I thinke, Old Gib's not blind, I ſee, although I winke.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="act">
                     <head>ACTVS II. SCENA I.</head>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Demetrias</hi> a Prince attired like a Wood-man, with him his Page.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>BOy, how doſt like me in this attire?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>As the Audience doth a bad play, ſcurvily.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it not ſtrange a Prince ſhould be thus metamorphoſed?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>Not ſo ſtrange as the Metamorphoſis of <hi>Ajax,</hi> an't like your Grace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Grace you Aggot, haſt not forgot that yet?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>No, and yet tis a wonder I ha not, grace being ſo ſeldome uſed, I'm ſure they ſay none at ſome Ordinaries, for at ſitting down they cannot intend it for hunger, and at riſing up, they are either drunke, or have ſuch mind a dice, they never remember, my Lord then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Demet.</speaker>
                        <p>No more Lord, ſirrah.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pag.</speaker>
                        <p>Indeed there are too many already, but is not this ſtrange, that rich men ſhould forſake their titles? maſter then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Deme.</speaker>
                        <p>Your will ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pag.</speaker>
                        <p>You have left many Countries behind you in ſeeking your friend <hi>Liſander,</hi> and yet you cannot find him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>True ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="9"/>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue ſeene much gold lying upon Lombards ſtals, and could never finger penny of it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Very well.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, twas not well ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>What conclude you then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>That you were beſt ſit downe, and ſee what you haue got by your journey.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue ſeene a face as beautifull as heaven.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>Thats nothing, a priſoner ſees the face of heaven it ſelfe, when hee lookes but out at the priſon-gate, ile ſtand to't, a man were as good be hang'd, ſo a meet a handſome hangman, &amp; a ſtrong rope, as be in loue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Your reaſon for that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>Mary this ſir, hanging is end of all troubles, and loue the beginning: Nay further, I thinke a Lover cannot be ſaved, for hee is of all religions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Your proofe for that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>This; hee thinkes with the Atheiſt there's no God but his Miſtreſſe, with the Infidell no heaven but her ſmiles, with the Papiſt no Purgatory but her frownes, and with the familie of loue, holds it lawful to lie with her, though ſhe be another mans wife.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>So ſir, what followes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>Serving-men ſir, the Maſter goes in before his wife, and the Servingman followes his maſter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Sirra forbeare, I muſt meditate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>As the Vſurer before hee parts with money, meditates upon the aſſurance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Liſander</hi> privately, and over-heares them.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>If <hi>Violettaes</hi> preſence ha'not quencht</l>
                           <l>The memory of all things but her ſelfe,</l>
                           <l>I ſhould be more familiar with that face.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Shroud &amp; obſerue.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue left my countrey to ſeeke my friend.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>And I my countrey and my friend for loue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>And in the ſearch of him haue loſt my ſelfe</l>
                           <l>In the ſtrange Region of a womans eye.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>In loue, and in Arcadia.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>As much as heaven tranſcends the humble earth,</l>
                           <l>So towres her praiſe her face differs as farre</l>
                           <l>From others, as a glo-worme from a ſtarre.</l>
                           <l>She is a Princeſſe that my ſoule affects.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>And rich.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Halfe heire unto this Dukedome.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſhe were whole heire to the foure morall vertues,
<pb facs="10"/>
twere nothing: when ſhall I ſee the time that men will loue for vertue, or a rich heire marry a poore wench without a portion? ne|ver I thinke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Had not my friend <hi>Liſander.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>What of mee?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Den●.</speaker>
                        <p>Left me in Thrace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>We had never met in loue,</l>
                           <l>His ſillables betray him. I arreſt you.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>At whoſe ſute?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>Not at his Taylers in any caſe, for there's no greater ſtitch to a younger brothers conſcience, then to pay for a ſute of apparrell when tis worne out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Liſander</hi> or his ghoſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Demetrius,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Or ſome illuſiue tenant in his ſhape?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Vnkind, why didſt thou leane my company?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>For that which made the amorous Gods leaue heaven, ●or loue: but why is <hi>Demetrius</hi> thus diſguiſ'd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>For that which would make a Iackanapes a Monkey, and he could get it: a tayle.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Deme.</speaker>
                        <p>Peace rogue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Why wagge, is thy maſter in loue?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                        <p>Faith ſit he hath entred his action in <hi>Cutids</hi> Court, and mean● to proceed in the ſute it ſhould ſeeme.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Deme.</speaker>
                        <p>Why didſt not take my counſell in thy choice?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe I fear'd a chiding, for doubting their honoura|ble thoughts would not haue not haue conſented to my effeminate attempts, I ſtole this ſecret courſe, and manner of diſguiſe, as beſt helping to acceſſe, which it hath begot, now what acceſſe will bring forth, I commit to unborne induſtry.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Deme.</speaker>
                        <p>It cannot but be proſperous: only the ſtrict obſervance of our loues hinders the paſſage of our hopes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Indeed that's not the leaſt hinderance, yet the Duke him|ſelfe, and my quaint diſguiſe hath removed it out of my way, who not only takes me for a woman, but hath allowed me for my loues companion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Fortune deales kindly with thee, I am as farre from acceſſe to my loue, as when I was in Thrace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dametas</hi> is the oyſterſhell that holds thy pearle, our wits muſt fiſh for him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Will the Cods head bite?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Like an old Vſurer at a young heires inheritance, and I
<pb facs="10"/>
haue it ready hookt for him: and here he comes, my plot is to pre|ferre thee to his ſervice.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Dametas.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Prethee doe, and ile ſerue him in his right kind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dametas,</hi> my loue is yours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Which madam I am as proud of—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>As a malecontent of a change, or an old Lady of a new faſhion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>To be round, I haue a ſute to you in the behalfe of this wood|man</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>To me ſweet bloſſome, though I be ſomewhat ſtrict in mine office, I cannot be ſtony to Ladies. Fellow is thy petition drawne?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Petition?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Your onely way to moue a fute by: Humbly complay|ning to your good worſhip, O tis moſt patheticke, &amp; indeed, with|out money, can doe juſt nothing with authority.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Come hether ſtripling, whoſe ſonne wert thou?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I am not ſo wiſe a child as you take me for, I never knew my father.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Didſt not know thy father?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>A common fault, his betters forget themſelues when they grow rich, then blame not him to forget his father.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>What was his name?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>If I may giue credite to my mother, they cald him <hi>Me|nalchas,</hi> who on his death-bed made me his heire, with this charge, to ſeeke your worſhips ſervice, and gaue me this gold as a remem|brance to purchaſe your favour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Gold? hem.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Now doth my Maſter long more to ſinger thar gold, then a young girle, married to an old man, doth to run her husband aſhore at Cuckolds haven.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, I could doe for this fatherleſſe youth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>As many Executors and Overſeers haue done, cheate him of his portion, and then turne him out of doores a begging.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>But for I haue the Gardian-ſhip of the Princeſſe, I dare doe nothing without the conſent of the Duke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, come ſir, your worſhip ſhall not refuſe him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Well then I woo not, but tis for your ſake I aſſure you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Meaning the gold.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>What ſhall I call thy name?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="11"/>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dorus</hi> an't like your worſhip.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Ah, good <hi>Dorus,</hi> be an honeſt youth <hi>Dorus,</hi> reverence your Maſter, and loue your ſelfe: bee ſure to get under me, and you ſhall looſe nothing in my ſervice. Madam, the Duke and Dutcheſſe ex|pect you at the hunt, and await your comming at <hi>Dianaes</hi> oake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>●e attend them preſently, be a good ſervant <hi>Dorus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Twill be his owne another day Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>In the meane time let it be yours to lead the way.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>My ſervice doth attend you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                        <p>As the Purſevant doth the priſoner for a double fee.</p>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Welcome ſlaue to a ſlaue, a faire preſage,</l>
                           <l>The hope of loue ſweetens loues vaſſ lage.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Aminter</hi> and <hi>Iulio,</hi> attired like Satires.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Now and <hi>Dametas</hi> bee the mettle hee was ſtampt for, a right villaine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>And he be not, hang him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay he deſerues hanging too if he be: but will you truſt him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes as farre as I ſee him, and he that truſts him further, my truſt is he will be deceived.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Indeed, he that will proue falſe to his maker, will be true to no man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, for the preſent time, like a bawd to him that giues moſt</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Thats not for loue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes of the money: he that lookes for other loue in this age—This is the place his Letter ſpeakes of, and here he comes himſelfe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Dametas</hi> like a Huntſman.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſo lo: now is the web of my hopes upon the Loombe of perfection, and in this quech of laſhes <hi>Aminter</hi> &amp; <hi>Iulio,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>See and ſee not, all mum, you know your cue,</l>
                           <l>The game's your owne, if you can hunt it true.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter the Duke <hi>Baſilius.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dametas,</hi> were thine cares ever at a more muſicall banquet? how the hounds mouths like bels are tuned one under another like a ſlothfulneſſe, the ſpeed of the cry out-ran my ſenſe of hearing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Croſſe over the Forreſt to <hi>Dianaes</hi> oake my liege, &amp; there your grace advantag'd by the height of the ground, ſhall not onely at pleaſure heare, but be eye-witneſſe of their muſicall contention.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Thankes good <hi>Dametas,</hi> bee thy directions our wiues convoy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <pb facs="11"/>Enter <hi>Gynetia, Violetta,</hi> and <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Gyn.</speaker>
                        <p>Where is his highneſſe <hi>Dametas?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>At <hi>Adonis</hi> bower Madam, where he expects your pre|ſence, to ſee the fleſhing of a couple of Spartane hounds, in the waſting blood of the ſpent Deare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Gyn.</speaker>
                        <p>Thankes good <hi>Dametas,</hi> mine eyes would not be good friends with my feet, ſhould they not bring 'em to that kingly ſport.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Sweet Ladies, to ſaue you the expence of much breath, which muſt be laid out in the purchaſe of the game, I haue provi|ded you this ſtand, from whence your eyes may be commanders of the ſport: ſuch ſport as you little dreame of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>We are your loues debters kind <hi>Dametas.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>As I loue vertue I pitty theſe poore beaſts,</l>
                           <l>Theſe Syl●ane commoners, to ſee what taskes</l>
                           <l>Our covetous Forreſters impoſe upon them,</l>
                           <l>Who not content with impoſt of their breath,</l>
                           <l>(Poore hearts) purſue them ſmiling to their death.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Twas the end of their creation Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>So was the end of ours to liue in peace,</l>
                           <l>And not to tyranniſe on harmeleſſe beaſts,</l>
                           <l>But Forreſters, like Images ſet forth</l>
                           <l>The tyrannie of greatneſſe without pitty,</l>
                           <l>As they the Deare, ſo covetous wealth purſues</l>
                           <l>The trembling ſtate of their inferiors,</l>
                           <l>And to claſpe up the volume of their ſinnes,</l>
                           <l>They drinke their blood, and cloath them with their skins:</l>
                           <l>Then ceaſe to preſſe poore beaſts with tyrannie,</l>
                           <l>You loue your liues, thinke they are loath to dye.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>You are too tender-hearted to bee a good huntſwoman Lady.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſome of you too hard-hearted, but leaving this diſ|courſe of hunting, haue all our gallantry of Lacedemon and Greece, ſpent the vigor of their wits, that not one dares venter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>For our loues ſiſter, you may ſee, the properer women, the worſe lucke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Tuſh you ſhall haue ſuters, feare not Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>No at any hand ſiſter, for with a feare it comes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Then ile feare of purpoſe, becauſe I would haue 'em come.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>And they doe not, they are notable cowards.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Then let them keepe away ſtill, for I haue vowed my mai|denhead
<pb facs="12"/>
ſhall never doe homage to the bed of a coward.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Sweet Ladies, will you beguile a minute or two with this diſcourſe, till I ſtep up to the top of the hill▪ and make diſcovery of the game.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Let your returne be ſpeedy good <hi>Dametas.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile put on wings and fly.</p>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Out of the Court, and the whole Countrey ſhall haue a good riddance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>So, he hath put'em faire to the ſtand, lets iſſue &amp; ſurpriſe them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Be reſolute and ſuddaine.</l>
                           <l>Aminter <hi>and</hi> Iulio <hi>iſſue out, and beare them away.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Murther, treaſon, reſcue, helpe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter firſt <hi>Dametas,</hi> and then the Duke.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes much reskue, much helpe, much <hi>Dametas:</hi> why ſo, this jeſt was drawen home cloſe to the head, it cannot chuſe but cleaue the very white of our hopes, the Dukes wit: to thy tackle good wit, ſome ſudden ſea roome, or our ſtratagem is run a ground.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Tell me <hi>Dametas,</hi> was not the Deare a prodigall? did hee not ſpend his breath freely amongſt us?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>And his blood too my liege, but did you obſerue how the hounds like politicians nos'd out the game?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>True: and comming to the loſſe, <hi>Melampus,</hi> but where are our daughters?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Did you obſerue that my liege, that <hi>Melampus</hi> as a true hound is ever horce cheerd or hollow, yet he kept time too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>Certaine <hi>Dametas,</hi> but where are our daughters man?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Buſie my Lord under a brake buſh, diſputing of the vertue of ſweet water, and ground Iuie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Cry within, treaſon, murder, reskue, helpe.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>What cry of treaſon's that <hi>Dametas?</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Pray God no danger ſets upon my daughters,</l>
                           <l>Seeke out our wife, ile haſte unto their reskue.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>And my ſword un-employd? alleageance ſayes nay to that my ●i●ge, I am for the adventure my ſelfe, if they be ſurpris'd (I am a mad man) your grace ſhall heare more: if not (I am the more ſorry) your grace ſhall heare more too: make peace with your thoughts till my returne, and doubt not their recovery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter the Dutcheſſe with her daughters, <hi>Demetrius, Liſander,</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Gyn.</speaker>
                        <p>Speake, where's the Duke?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſi.</speaker>
                        <p>Here my <hi>Gynetia.</hi>
                           <pb facs="12"/>
What meane theſe weapons, are our daughters ●afe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>As a thiefe in a mill father, we thanke our redeemers▪</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>The more my griefe, were you ſurpriſ'd then madam?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes faith <hi>Dametas.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>And how ſweet Ladies, and how were you reſcued?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Gyn.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Being ſurpriſ'd, this gallant <hi>Amazon</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Preſt to their re●cue, had you ſeene what worth</l>
                           <l>She and this woodman ſpent in our defence,</l>
                           <l>Wonder would ha' bereft you of all ſenſe,</l>
                           <l>She rai▪'d her ſword with ſuch a manly grace,</l>
                           <l>As had not her mild ſexe contrould my thoughts,</l>
                           <l>I could haue falne in loue with her high worth.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>You over-priſe us madam, not our deſert,</l>
                           <l>But the weake ſpirits of our oppoſites,</l>
                           <l>Gaue luſter to the dimneſſe of our worth.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>It pleaſeth your modeſty to leſſon it,</l>
                           <l>But it ſhall ſtill liue great in our regard. What woodman's that?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>My follower, my liege.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>What ere he be, he hath deſeru'd our loue,</l>
                           <l>Fellow be neere us, and for this deſert,</l>
                           <l>Perform'd againſt thoſe Traytors to our blood,</l>
                           <l>Vnder thy maſter we giue thee an attendant,</l>
                           <l>To guard the life and ſafetie of our daughter.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Thanke you good father, who ever looſe by the bargaine,</l>
                           <l>I haue got me a ſervant by the match: woo't ſerue me fellow?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>In the beſt I can.</l>
                           <l>In heart your fellow, though in ſhow your man.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Ile try your dutious ſervice: I command</l>
                           <l>Your knee to ki●●e the ground, your lip my hand.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Pardon me Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Here's hot loue no doubt,</l>
                           <l>I may command my man, and goe without.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Truce to this ayrie warre, theſe paper bullets</l>
                           <l>Better become a Cloſſet then a Parke,</l>
                           <l>The Forreſt muſicke is to heare the hounds</l>
                           <l>Rend the thin ayre, and with a luſty cry</l>
                           <l>Awake the drowſie Eccho, and confound</l>
                           <l>Their perfect language in a mingled ſound,</l>
                           <l>Then to the Court, our Forreſt ſport being done,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="13"/>A ſecond chace of lovelier ſports begunne.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>If fortune croſſe not what our hopes purſue,</l>
                           <l>Our feares have met their deaths, our loves their due.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dame.</speaker>
                        <p>Croſt in my hopes, the Ladies reſcu'd, and the Princes like ●ravens beat out of the game-place, my invention muſt turne traveller for more ſtratagems: what &amp; I ſhould diſcover their plot to the Duke, attach em for traitors, and beg their lands for my la|bour, though they be my friends, twere a pretty parcell of pollicy.</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>All things are lawfull that doe profit bring,</l>
                           <l>A wiſe mans bow goes with a two-fold ſtring.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Enter <hi>Liſander</hi> and <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Did ever two Princes meet ſuch ſtrange changes in their loves? now we have wrought our admittance, and in a manner got em into our poſſeſſions, our hopes like falſe fires having brought us within ken, vaniſh, and leave us out of all comfort.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>That the Duke ſhould doat upon thee for a woman, makes for our purpoſe, but that the Dutcheſſe ſhould be enamourd on thee for a man, is prepoſterous.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Whether my valour ſhown in the reskue of the Ladies, or the ardent glances her daughters beauty ſteales from my eyes, give her thoughts encouragement, I know not, but her hopes ſtand con|fident I am a man, and for that cauſe am I barr'd from acceſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>De.</speaker>
                        <p>I weigh thy combrances by my own, for though by the dukes allowance I am her priviledg'd attendant, yet ſuch is the deviliſhnes of <hi>Dametas,</hi> that I cannot joy ſo much acceſſe as to confer with her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Pag.</speaker>
                        <p>I can compare my lord &amp; his friend to nothing in the world ſo fitly, as to a couple of water buckets, for whil'ſt hope winds the one up, diſpaire plunges the other down, whil'ſt I, like a Harlakene in an Italian Comoedy, ſtand making faces at both their follies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, ſince the ſhape of our proceeding growes ſo mon|ſtrous, lets caſt our inventions in a new mold, and having ſo firme a foundation as this diſguiſe to build upon, lets draw the modell, and raiſe the whole frame of our attempts anew.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem</speaker>
                        <p>Indeed, lovers ſhould be condition'd like tyrants, who ha|ving the aime of a crowne in their eye once, runne violently over all lets that intervent their courſe, and ſo muſt we.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſo will we, my reſolution is already bent, and if I ſhoot not, the next levell I take, Love I beſeech thee breake thy bow a|bout mine eares, and ſtrike thy hornes in my forhead, for married
<pb facs="13"/>
men to hang their cap● on.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I have met a meanes fit for my purpoſe already: <hi>Mopſa Dametas</hi> onely daughter is overſhooes in love with me, &amp; to her ●le feigne extreame ardor of affection, and make her the ſhadow under which Ile court the true ſubſtance of my divine <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>About it then, Ile ſweat my invention to death but Ile o|vertake thee; but heere comes one of my Burres▪ I muſt beare his importunity, for no reaſonable denyall will bruſh him off.</p>
                        <stage>Enter the Duke.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Zelmane.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>My Liege.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>My thoughts come like a ſaile afore the wind, ſwolne big with news, and thine eares the midwife muſt deliver me of this bur|den: my Dutcheſſe is ſicke, heart-ſicke for thee <hi>Zelmane.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>For me? why my Lord, I am no <hi>Roſa ſolis,</hi> nor <hi>Aqua mi|rabilis</hi> to recover ſicke folkes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Shall I be ſhort with thee? My Ladie's in love with thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>With me my Lord?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>With thee my Lady: her amorous glances are her accuſers, her very looks write Sonnets in thy commendations, ſhe carves thee at boord, and cannot ſleepe for dreaming on thee in bed, ſhee's turn'd ſunne-riſer, haunts private walkes, and like a diſgrac'd Courtier, ſtu|dies the Art of melancholly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Now alas good Lady.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay never pitty her, ſhe deſerves none, rather lets bend our indeavors to intangle her more. To ſee the kindnes of fortune, who fearing we ſhould be acquainted with ſollitude in this our 12 month retirement, hath begot a domeſticall merriment, and made our own thoughts Actors in't, and as bad a Poet as I am, Ile ha one ſcene in't of my owne invention.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dametas</hi> will ſtorme at that, for hee cannot abide Poetry ſhould be countenanc'd; but how is't my Liege?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis ready plotted already, and that the Dutcheſſe may not find thee unprovided when ſhe comes to court thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Court me, court a woman my Liege?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Why that's the very happineſſe of the jeſt, but in any caſe confeſſe thy ſelfe a man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>A man my Liege? I ha no colour for't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Tuſh, Ile furniſh thee, ſay thou art a Prince, no matter who, and haſt to doe with this diſguiſe of purpoſe to court my daughter <hi>Violetta.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Is this ſcene of your owne inventing my Liege?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="14"/>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>Mine own ifaith, and to confirm't the rather, uſe more oft and private conference with my daughter, interchange diſcourſe &amp; amo|rous dalliance, oh twill ſet my Dutcheſſe affections afire, to think her rivalld by her daughter, and give us ſmooth paſſage to our love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>How occaſion playes the wanton with me. Well my liege, do but you work my admittance to your daughter, and ●le beſtow al the art I am worth in courting her; and ſee, as if Fortune had a hand in our Comoedy, ſhe hath entred the Dutcheſſe juſt at her cue, ſhaddow your ſelfe in your Arke, and leave me to give her entertainment.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>Forget not to perſonate ſome Prince in any caſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>I warrant you, Ile play the Prince with much art.</p>
                        <stage>Enter the Dutcheſſe.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dutch.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>This way he went, on this ſweet violet bed</l>
                           <l>Still dwells the print of his inamour'd tread,</l>
                           <l>The depreſt flowers have ſtrengthened their ſweet</l>
                           <l>By ſtealing amorous kiſſes from his feet.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>Abſolute Poet. <hi>Penelope</hi> was a ballad-maker to her.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Oh doe not fly my preſence, gentle wanton ſtay,</l>
                           <l>What haue I found you, faith you run-away</l>
                           <l>Ile tye a chaine about your waſt for this,</l>
                           <l>And make you buy your freedome with a kiſſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Fie Madam, this courteſy is more then needes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Be not ſo coy, let not a loving Dame</l>
                           <l>Find thee leſſe kind then ſenſeleſſe elements,</l>
                           <l>Thou never walk'ſt, but the enamour'd aire</l>
                           <l>Like an officious lover beares thy traine,</l>
                           <l>Whil'ſt the coole wind doth with his velvet wing</l>
                           <l>Fanne the thinne ayre upon thy ſweaty cheeke,</l>
                           <l>Stealing ſweet kiſſes from thy ſilken lip.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Shield this vain breath, beat at ſome Ladies eare.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>But you are none, you are not, come you are not.</l>
                           <l>Your valour, lookes, and geſture ſhow you are not,</l>
                           <l>Your manly brow, and your commanding eye,</l>
                           <l>Where warre and fortune dwell in majeſtie,</l>
                           <l>Your private walkes, and varied paſſions,</l>
                           <l>Your glances to my daughter, ſure you are not,</l>
                           <l>And my firme love is confident you are not.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>There's a lover of a right temper, ſhee'l out-face the name of her ſexe inſtantly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="14"/>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Well Madam, ſith your obſervation hath diſcover'd me, upon promiſe of your ſecrecy, I confeſſe my ſelfe a man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>Good, excellent, how truely ſhe takes my directions.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>I knew my judgement could not be deceiv'd,</l>
                           <l>Nor durſt proud love have done me ſo much wrong</l>
                           <l>To caſt my thoughts unto a womans eye.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Love durſt not, good, good, excellent, what next?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>But Madam, now I am known to you, what further requeſt you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Exchange of lookes, and freedome of thy bed,</l>
                           <l>Thy preſence, thy embracements, thy kind love,</l>
                           <l>For which my amorous thoughts have long lyen ſicke.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                        <p>Thank you good wife; nay, and a Dutcheſſe long to give her husband the horning, let it never grieve Butchers to doe homage at Cuckolds haven.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Well Madam, to give content to your affections, and in a ſtrong hope you will mediate my ſute to your daughter, ſort out but fit time and opportunity, and maſter your deſires.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil▪</speaker>
                        <p>And he were a man now I might be rarely tupt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Give me thy hand then, with this amorous kiſſe I ſeale thee mine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>And I confirm't with this.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Rare, rare, rare, ſhee's his, ſeald and deliverd in the pre|ſence of her husband.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Now leſt my husband ſhould ſuſpect our love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Now, what for that now?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Heare a good jeſt, perſwade him thou art a woman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>That's not to doe now Madam, for he as confidently beleeves and ardently courts me for a woman as you for a man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Good, excellent, maintaine that humour ſtill,</l>
                           <l>Seeme coy, looke nice, and as we women uſe,</l>
                           <l>Be mild, and proud, imbrace, and yet refuſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <p>Excellent vertues in a woman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>I prithee doe, twill be a ſcene of mirth</l>
                           <l>For me to quote his paſſions and his ſmiles,</l>
                           <l>His amorous haviour, and how his eye</l>
                           <l>Will beget ſtrange variety of lookes,</l>
                           <l>And ſhoot em into thine; but the chiefe ſport's this,</l>
                           <l>To ſee an old man with a young man kiſſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exit Dutcheſſe.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>To ſee an old Dutcheſſe a young Lady kiſſe.</l>
                           <l>Now the plot packs, the ſcene's all comicall,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="15"/>I cannot ſpeake for laughter, to ſee theſe women,</l>
                           <l>That would be counted wonders for their wit,</l>
                           <l>Lay plots to gull themſelves, ſilly conceit.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>To take me for a man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Baſil.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>And arme her ſelfe</l>
                           <l>To laugh at me, make jeſts and ſcoffes at me,</l>
                           <l>But ſooth her humour, the revenge ſhee'd throw</l>
                           <l>Vpon my head, ſhall fall on her owne brow.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Vpon you both, ſo, ſo, ſo, how greedily their inventions like bugles follow the ſent of their owne gullery, yet theſe are no fooles, God forbid, not they: but to the drift, mirth in my warme blood ſits Laughing at this diviſion of their wits.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Violetta</hi> and <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Woo't beleeve mee ſiſter? I never eat a cherry, but it puts mee in mind of a husband, it kiſſes my lips with ſuch a harmeleſſe prettineſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Now in good deed lo I loue em a liſe too, I thinke I ſhall never ha my belly full on em.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Of what, not of husbands <hi>Violetta?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>No, of cherries <hi>Hippolita,</hi> but take heed of em, they bee a very filling meat, and dangerous things for us Maydes I can tell you, we may ſurfet after em preſently.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Surfet after what, a husband?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>I, and after cherries too <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>I warrant you ſiſter, an old Lady in Lacedemon taught me a preſervative againſt that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>For the love of cherries what?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Marry this it was, ſtill ſaid ſhe, betwixt every cherry ſaid ſhe, be ſure to cracke a ſtone ſaid ſhe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Then let me alone, Ile cracke a couple of ſtones betwixt e|very cherry, rather then ſurfet on them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>You muſt take heed you cracke not too many too, for you may ſurfet of the ſtone as well as of the cherry.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay and they be ſuch dangerous things, I ha done with em.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>So have I too for this time, but ſiſter, is it not a ſtrange kind of ſervile liberty that we live in here in Arcadia?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>For all the world as Engliſhmen keep their fellons, and Ita|lians their wives, we never ſtirre abroad without our laylors.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>And for what cauſe forſooth? only to keep us from mariage.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ʋiol.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure it is either ſome high content, or extreame diſcom|moditie,
<pb facs="15"/>
that our father debarres us of it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>By this ſtone, me thinks I long like a woman with child, till I know the difference betwixt a Mayd and a wife.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, god a mercy of all curſen ſoules, I was neere the know|ledge on't laſt night I can tell you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>O that I had bin with thee I might ha been ſo too: for the love of marriage how?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Why thus: As I lay ſlumbring in my bed,</l>
                           <l>No creature with me but my mayden-head.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Is that a creature?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Some maintaine it is,</l>
                           <l>Got in the eye, conceived in a kiſſe;</l>
                           <l>Others, whoſe ſpeech ſeemes neere akin to truth,</l>
                           <l>Say tis a paſſion, bred i'th heat of youth,</l>
                           <l>Some call't a ſigh, and ſome an amorous grone,</l>
                           <l>All differ in the definition:</l>
                           <l>But in th'allow'd opinion of moſt,</l>
                           <l>Tis never truely had till it be loſt.</l>
                           <l>But lying thus alone, as Mayds doe uſe,</l>
                           <l>Me thought I dreamt, as Mayds can hardly chuſe,</l>
                           <l>And in my dreame me thought twas too much wrong</l>
                           <l>A pretty Mayd ſhould lye alone ſo long;</l>
                           <l>With that a gallant comes, gallants can doe</l>
                           <l>Much with young Mayds.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>And with old women too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>He courted me once, and agen, and thrice,</l>
                           <l>Tis vertue to ſay nay, to bee too nice</l>
                           <l>Agrees not with my humour, yet ſome ſay,</l>
                           <l>We Mayds wiſh things, to which we anſwer nay;</l>
                           <l>Briefely, me thought he ſtood ſo long a wooing,</l>
                           <l>I rather could ha wiſht he had been doing</l>
                           <l>Some other buſineſſe, yet at laſt we'greed,</l>
                           <l>Twere ſtrange if earneſt futers ſhould not ſpeed.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>In what agreed you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>In our Wedding-ring,</l>
                           <l>Time, place, and houre, indeed in every thing;</l>
                           <l>The day appoynted, and each thing in frame,</l>
                           <l>I thought each houre an age untill it came,</l>
                           <l>Well, come it is, the morning once in ſight,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="16"/>I thought it ten times longer till twas night.</l>
                           <l>At dinner time me thought I ſweld with pride</l>
                           <l>To be drunke to by name of Miſtreſſe bride,</l>
                           <l>Muſicke ſpake loud, no delicates were ſcant,</l>
                           <l>Yet ſtill me thought another thing did want,</l>
                           <l>For ſure thought I, there's ſomething in a man</l>
                           <l>That wiues loue well, hope brides may wiſh it than.</l>
                           <l>Long lookt for comes at laſt, to bed we goe.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Would I had dreamt I might ha' done ſo too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>My bed-mate turn'd, and as he would ha' ſpoke,</l>
                           <l>I ſweat with feare, and in that feare I woke,</l>
                           <l>But ſeeing my kind bed-fellow was gone,</l>
                           <l>Lord how it chaft me that I wakt ſo ſoone,</l>
                           <l>One minuts dreaming longer, I had tride,</l>
                           <l>The difference twixt a virgin and a bride.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Otwould ha' vext a Saint, my blood would burne</l>
                           <l>To be ſo neere, and miſſe ſo good a turne.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſo did mine too I warrant you, nay though I bee but a little pot, I ſhall be as ſoone hot as another.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>You ſhould not be my ſiſter elſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>Nor my mothers daughter neither.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>And in good earneſt wee are not fath●r●〈…〉 amiſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you avis'd of that, and Ifaith tell● what thinke you of your ſervant <hi>Dorus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>As of a ſweet Almond in a rugged ſhell, the Sun in a cloud, or a wealthy Diamond in a rocke, indeed cleane contrary to the world, hee weares the worſt ſide outward, and is much better then he ſeemes: but what thinke you of your manly <hi>Amazon??</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay the ſport is I know not what to thinke, <hi>Zelmanes</hi> hu|mour would afford project for a pretty Court Comoedy, my father courts her for a woman, and as I feare ſhe is, my mother doats upon her for a man, and as I wiſh he were, and that with ſuch an ardor of affection, that I could find in my heart to turne my mother out of the company, and play the lovers part my ſelfe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>How ever man or woman, the jeſt holds currant in one.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not what knaviſh motion hath had to doe with my thought, but my mind tels mee that your ſervant <hi>Dorus</hi> and my <hi>A|mazon,</hi> are other then they ſeeme: and here he comes.</p>
                        <stage>Enter firſt <hi>Liſander,</hi> then <hi>Miſo, Mopſa, Demetrius.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="16"/>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>Why how now madam, Ladies gadding, is this the obedi|ence of your fathers charge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Pardon Miſtreſſe <hi>Miſo,</hi> 'twas my doing and the Dukes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>But the Dutcheſſe will like neither the Dukes doings nor yours, neither in this caſe I can tell you. The Duke ſtaies your com|ming, and yet the Dutcheſſe is very deſirous on't, my husband is in the next Arbour to man you. For you Lady, my preſence be your priviledge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Miſo</hi> ſhould be either a hang man or a He|rald, for ſhe never comes amongſt us, but ſhe quarters our company and armes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>De.</speaker>
                        <p>Excellent beauty, &amp; therefore more excellent, becauſe ſituate in ſo faire a creature.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>You are a merry man <hi>Dorus,</hi> but all this cannot make me loue me, how ſay you mother doth he?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Mary let him chuſe daughter, when I was as thou art—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>You were as ſhe is? but faith madam <hi>Mopſa,</hi> I perceiue my ſer|vant <hi>Dorus</hi> beares a moneths mind to you, bee not ſo ſtraight laced to him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Straight lac'd? ſgod mend me I am not lac'd at all, am I <hi>Dorus?</hi> no in ſooth, I goe wide ope wenſday, I never lace my ſelfe but on ſundayes, &amp; that for feare I ſhould burſt with cating of plum-porridge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>I meane let fall ſome comforta|ble lookes on your ſuter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Sgod mend me, ile let fall or take up any thing I haue to doe him good.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Why that's kind|ly ſaid, and <hi>Dorus</hi> your loue is very ambitious, to climbe ſo high as the beautifull <hi>Mopſa.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>O are you avis'd of that, 'twould make a horſe breake his bridle to heare how the youth of the vil|lage will commend me, oh the pretty little pincking nies of <hi>Mopſa</hi> ſayes one, oh the fine flat lips of <hi>Mopſa</hi> ſayes another, and then doe I bridle my head like a malt-horſe thus, ſet mine armes a kembo thus, wreath my necke and my body thus, winke with one eye thus, and ſpread my peacocks tay le as broad as the proudeſt minxe of em all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Theſe extraordinary graces muſt not want admira|tion, but where's your mother?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>Speake ſoftly in the Lobby there, for waking my Ladies foiſting hound.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Godſme, my mother's ſtealing of a nap.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, ſhee cannot bee ſaid to ſteale a nap, for the noiſe ſhee makes herſelfe would diſcover her theft: but <hi>Dorus</hi> ſith your for|tunes are poore, you ſhould ſtudy to enoble your deſerts, and beget effects worthy to court and win your Ladies acceptance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Laſſe madam, I chuſe no better moderater then your ſelfe,
<pb facs="17"/>
betwixt me &amp; my unworthy ſervices, ſuppoſe your ſelfe though but a Cucko compar'd with this ſweet ſinging Nitingale, ſhould be ſued to by a Prince like me, I meane like me in loue, for loue in Princes &amp; peſants admits compariſon: ſuppoſe <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſhould in like diſguiſe court you as I doe, <hi>Mopſa,</hi> ſigh for you, as I doe, for <hi>Mopſa,</hi> kneele to you thus, as I doe, to <hi>Mopſa,</hi> lay downe his life to you, as I doe, to <hi>Mopſa,</hi> prefer your good before his owne, as I proteſt I do, <hi>Mopſaes,</hi> ſuppoſe he ſhould ſhew you the knowen marke of his neck, to aſſure you he were <hi>Demetrius,</hi> as I doe this to <hi>Mopſa,</hi> to witneſſe I am the ſonne of <hi>Menalchas,</hi> could your disdaine ſtand out like <hi>Mopſaes?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>What a keenes neceſſitie ſets upon the edge of invention, truſt me <hi>Mopſa</hi> your ſervant ſpeakes well, and if hee can proue himſelfe the man he ſpeakes of, and my wiſhes well hope, <hi>Demetrius,</hi> you haue no reaſon to thinke ſcorne of him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Why what ſhould I doe Madam? my mother tels me I muſt not ſay as I thinke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>I am no counſeller, but ſhould <hi>Demetrius</hi> in like diſguiſe court me, thus would I embrace him, thus ſeale my affections with a kiſſe, and thus argue: thinke not <hi>Demetrius</hi> that the clouds of baſe|neſſe could ſo muſfle thee, but that the Sun of valour ſhind through them long ſince, and in regard of thy ſerviceable dutie in concealing, and unprevented policy in thus making knowen thy loue, ſort but out fit opportunity, and in deſpight of al guardians ſtrict obſervance, goe where thou wilt, the worth of <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſhall draw <hi>Hippolita,</hi> this would I vow, and this will I performe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>De.</speaker>
                        <p>And were I <hi>Demetrius</hi> and you <hi>Hippolita,</hi> I would deceiue <hi>Dametas,</hi> outreach <hi>Miſo,</hi> forſweare <hi>Mopſa,</hi> and forſake <hi>Arcadia,</hi> to ſhare the fortunes of divine <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>And what ſhould I doe then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe but ſpeake in the perſon of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and under <hi>Hippolita</hi> ſhadow what I intend to the rare, and never enough won|dred at <hi>Mopſa,</hi> the blacke ſwan of beauty, and madg-howlet of admiration.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe not you flout me <hi>Dorus?</hi> and you doe not, provide a Prieſt and ile marry you, and my father and mother ſhall never know on't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>De.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manaſſes</hi> is the man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>And ile bee the woman, whoſoever ſay nay to't, little dreames my mother of what we haue done.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>De.</speaker>
                        <p>T'may be ſhe did, for ſhe ſigh'd &amp; groand much in her ſleepe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis well ſhee was ſo quiet, for ſhee eate peaſe-poridge to breakefaſt, and they'l make mebreake wind in my ſleepe like a horſe,
<pb facs="17"/>
and ſee as the devill will ha't ſhe wakes, and here comes my father, no words and yee loue me.</p>
                        <stage>Enter Dametas.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Why God a mercy <hi>Dorus,</hi> this diligence becomes the ſer|vant of <hi>Dametas,</hi> and ile preferre thee for't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>You were worſe then the devill elſe, for they ſay hee helps his ſervants, then you may doe little and you cannot helpe yours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you breake your jeſts againſt the bars of your chamber window, and cleare the greene? the Duke is comming to bowles, and I would not for halfe mine office you ſhould be a rub in the way of his patience: daughter and wife, conduct her to the Lodge, <hi>Exit.</hi> And <hi>Dorus,</hi> make you haſte about your buſines.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I warrant you Sir: be my hopes rightly plac't, You will condemne me for my too much haſte.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſo: this tis to be in authority: Inferiour perſons, I and the Princes themſelues, fly from my preſence, like the chirping Birds from the ſight of the Faulcon: my very breath like a mighty wind blowes away inferiour Officers (the Court rubbiſh) out of my way, and giues me a ſmooth paſſage: I am the morning ſtarre, I am ſeldome ſeene but about the riſing of the Sunne: indeed I am never out of the Dukes eye; and here he comes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Duke, Dutcheſſe, <hi>Liſander, Violetta.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Doth our match hold?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dutch.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, whoſe part will you take?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Zelmanes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dutch.</speaker>
                        <p>Soft, that match is yet to make.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Lets caſt a choiſe, the neereſt two take one.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>My choice is caſt, helpe ſweet occaſion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, here's agood.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, better'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dutch.</speaker>
                        <p>Beſt of all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>The Duke and I.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk</speaker>
                        <p>The weakeſt goe to the wall.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile leade.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile follow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>We haue both one mind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>In what?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>In leaving the old folke behind.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Well jeſted daughter, and you leade not faire,</l>
                           <l>The hindmoſt hound, though old, may catch the hare.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="18"/>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Your laſt bowle, come.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>By the faith a me, well lead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Would I might leade you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Whither?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>To my bed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>I am ſure you would not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>By this aire I would.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>I hope you would not hurt me, and you ſhould.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I'de love you ſweet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Soure, ſo I heard you ſay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>A cept it then.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Of what acquaintance pray?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Of loves and mine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>Daughter, your bowle winnes one.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>None of my Maydenhead father, I am gone,</l>
                           <l>The <hi>Amazon</hi> hath wonne one.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Yield to that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>The caſt I doe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Your ſelfe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay ſcrape out that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Whoſe is it yet?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>The Dukes: play ſmooth and fine.</l>
                           <l>The ſmalleſt helpe that is will make you mine.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Me yours?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>You mine, for though the caſt I loſe,</l>
                           <l>I ha wonne your love.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Much: in my tother hoſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, the laſt marke; this caſt is worth all the reſt,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>The leader as the follower.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Bad's the beſt.</l>
                           <l>I winne her for ten Crownes, and there they be.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>I take your lay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>A match twixt you and me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile be your halfe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>That were unkindly done.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Pardon me mother, Ile beare all or none.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>I ha wonne you Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>I meane your bet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="18"/>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Then take your winnings, Ile not die in debt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam beleeve mee, I am, as I proteſt, a Prince, my name <hi>Liſander.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>Looke to the Dukes ſtanding Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>So I will I warrant you, and to your falling.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Thus clouded as you ſee for your love, my ſoule ſpeakes in my tongue; I appoynted this match at Bowles a purpoſe to acquaint you with it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Barre ſtealing Father; yet and all hit right,</l>
                           <l>Here's one would ſteale a piece of fleſh to night.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Deere Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>No more words, I have perceived as much in your eye, as you can expreſſe with your tongue, and as farre as my mothers jea|louſy would give me leave, anſwered it with kind lookes: your bias ſtands wrong mother.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Why? it ſtands toward <hi>Zelmanes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>Hath it ſtood ſo long?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>All the game through.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>Then all your game's bowld wrong: furniſh you with neceſ|ſaries befitting an eſcape, and my will ſhall be as ready to take wing as yours: put in a caſt now mother, or the game is gone indeed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Whoſe is the throw?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Ours, till the laſt bowle came;</l>
                           <l>But that hath wonn't em cleere, both caſt and game.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Our winnings, come, a kiſſe and bate the reſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>What, doe you kiſſe in eaneſt or in jeſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>In earneſt in good truth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Troth kindly ſed,</l>
                           <l>Take heed you kiſſe not out your Mayden-head.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>In jeſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>In earneſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Tis the faſhion,</l>
                           <l>Much in requeſt among our nation.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>To kiſſe away their Maiden-heads?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Now and then,</l>
                           <l>And being gone, to kiſſe it backe agen:</l>
                           <l>For lovers indentures nere are fairly drawn,</l>
                           <l>Vntill the Maiden-head be left in pawne,</l>
                           <l>As earneſt of the match, ſo mothers ſed,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="19"/>And ſo will daughters doe when mams be dead.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>What pawne their Maydenheads?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ʋiol.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, and loſe em too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>And you'● maintaine that faſhion?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>Signeor Noe.</p>
                        <stage>Muſicke of bells, &amp;c.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Lay by this home-bred mirth, and prepare your eares to en|tertaine ſtrangers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>Strangers? why father ſtrangers are as welcome to mee, as mine owne Country-men, if they bring good manners and civill hu|manity in their company; otherwiſe, they are like foule weather, come afore they be ſent for.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Dametas, Manaſſes, Iulio, Amintas.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dametas?</hi> nay then we ſhall have newes enough, for he ne|ver comes into the preſence, but he brings a whole ſacke full of lies, of newes I ſhould ſay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Welcome <hi>Dametas:</hi> what officious fellow is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>A pure well willer of your Majeſties, and a follower of mine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>O tis <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and he could make armes as well as he ma●res legs, hee would grow in great requeſt for Heraldry: What's your newes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Theſe <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> ſubjects to your Majeſty, having a meſſage to deliver to your Majeſties inſtruments of hearing, com|monly eclip'd eares.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>How, hath any one here clipt eares?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Manaſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Sweete Feminine, clip off the taile of thy diſcourſe with the Siſſars of attention, as I ſay, theſe <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> have choſen me their tongue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
                        <p>Of a long tongue thou ſpeakeſt very little.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>That proves me no woman, for they ſpeake over much.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk</speaker>
                        <p>What grievances oppreſſe them? briefely ſpeake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Merchandize (my Liege) through the avarice of purcha|ſing Officers, is wrackt with ſuch unmercifull impoſt, that the very name of Trafficke growes odious even to the profeſſour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio</speaker>
                        <p>Townes ſo oppreſt for want of wonted and naturall liber|ty, as that the native Inhabitanus feeme Slaves, and the Forreiners free Denizens.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Offices ſo bought and ſold, that before the purchaſer can be ſayd to be placed in his office, he is againe by his covetous Patron diſplac'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="19"/>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>Common Riots, Rapes, and wilfull Homicide in great mens followers, not onely not puniſhed, but in a manner countenan|ced and applauded.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Indeed ſince your Majeſtie left the Land, the whole body of the Common-wealth runs cleane againſt the bias of true and pri|ſtine governement.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>And your honourable Brother, like a ſhip toſt upon the violent billowes of this inſurrection, by us intreats your Majeſties Letters of ſpeedy reformation, for feare the whole Kingdome ſuffer inevitable ſhipwracke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Which after ſhort deliberation with our Councell, your ſelfe ſhall returne. <hi>Dametas</hi> reward their travels with two hun|dred Crownes: in the meane time, let them taſte the beſt entertaine|ment of our Court.</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Proud Rebels, they ſhall ſee that a Dukes frowne,</l>
                           <l>Can at his pleaſure, turne Rebellion downe:</l>
                           <l>See them rewarded.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Auri.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> ſee the fellowes entertayned; I muſt attend of the Duke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Boy, ſee the fellowes entertayned; I muſt waite of my Lord.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Fellowes, be as merry as you may, I muſt follow my M.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>So, here's Petitioners attendance right; good words, and ſhort Commons: But tis not their entertainement wee come for. I made a ſimple ſhift to get entertainement into the Court.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <p>Well <hi>Cupid,</hi> pray for our liues, for and wee were gone, I know not where thou wouldſt haue two ſuch ſtates-men againe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>His Common-wealth could not ſtand without us; and that his Mother knowes well enough: and hee ſends no better ſuc|ceſſe then we had at our hunting, he looſes a friend of me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twill not ſinke in my thought yet, but that old muſty ſlaue <hi>Dametas</hi> played the ſlaue with us.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>Would I could proue it once: but ſince wee are againe admitted our Realme, ſhall wee be idle? ſomewhat weele doe, though they'l giue us but ſmall thankes for our labour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <p>The Duke ſhall not ſay his Daughters are ſo ill beloved, but vveele change a thruſt or two vvith his intent for'em.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>T'vvould put the poore Wenches out of conceit vvith themſelues, and there ſhould not be ſome contending for them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="20"/>
                        <speaker>●.</speaker>
                        <p>We are in the way to catch the old one, and then our ayme 〈…〉.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>●.</speaker>
                        <p>We are ifaith: Invention could not weaue, 〈…〉, Suſpition to deceiue.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Liſander</hi> and <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>●.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, paſſe off this groveling imitation; a Lovers 〈…〉 muſt bee ambitious, and like the Eagle, ſcorning the baſe 〈…〉 where Kites and Crowes lie flagging: mount the cleare sky of 〈…〉, and overpeere all hindrances:</p>
                        <p>The Ladies themſelues are willing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Ready to embarke upon the next tide of occaſion whatſoever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Demet.</speaker>
                        <p>Let mee alone to worke it then▪ But here comes my Boy.</p>
                        <stage>Enter Page.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twere more for your credite Sir, and you could ſay your man: but men and warre were worne out of faſhion both in a Sum|mer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>I am of thy beliefe in that Boy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Would my Lord were ſo too ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Suppoſe I were Sir, what then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſhould (as many upſtarts haue done) proue rich: for I be|leeue you would make me your heire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Is that part of your beliefe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>A principall poynt ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Renounce it then, for I beleeue you'l never be ſaved by't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>I am ſure I cannot looſe by't. I beleeue further, that many Knights, and ſome Ladies, were never of Gods making.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Of whoſe then, wagge?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile tell you: the Minters coyne Gold, Gold makes He|ralds, Heralds makes Knights, and Knights ſtampe Ladies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>And what doe Ladies?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>They liue not idle neither; they make ſome Knights, and marre many Gentlemen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Ladies are good worke-women too, then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Farre better then any Taylor: they'l make you an end of a ſuite, eſpecially a Court ſuite, when all the Taylors in a Countrey know not how to ſet a ſtitch in't▪</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I am of the beliefe you are a knaue, ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>I had no faith, ſhould I ſay you were not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, what a Knaue?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>In a Knaues beliefe ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="20"/>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe in yours?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe you ſay't, and ile ſweare it, my Lord.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>No more <hi>Boy,</hi> I am weary of your jeſts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>That confirmes them to be good ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Your reaſon for that, ſir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe travellers and lovers, are ſoone weary of goodneſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Goodly ones indeed: but leaving this high-way of cir|cumſtance; I ſent you for <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>The learned Scribe attends you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Manaſſes.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you fall off ſir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Like an Apple at Michaelmas, without ſhaking.</p>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Welcome <hi>Manaſſes:</hi> I haue preſent employment for thee, in which I muſt borrow—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Pardon me Madam, I learned of my Lord, to lend nothing without ſecuritie and pawnes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis not money (<hi>Manaſſes</hi>) but counſell and furtherance that we deſire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Good counſell is worth good money Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou ſhalt bee well conſidered; there's twenty Crownes in earneſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay Madam, this hand is like a fellow that takes every thing in jeſt; if you be in earneſt, let me feele it here: So Lady, now betwixt earneſt and jeſt, if your Will be ready drawne, before your friend delivered as your deed, and put me in truſt to execute it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Take it this, in a word honeſt Sheepheard, and thy Lords daughter Madam <hi>Mopſa,</hi> are man and wife.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Man, and woman perhaps, but not man and wife: for though moſt women haue a will to bee Ladies, like my Lords wife; yet every Lady hath not wit to bee a wife, as my Lords Daughter. But what good can I doe in this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Overy much: for though they bee man and wife by oath and proteſtation, the chiefeſt ceremony of all; namely Mariage is yet unperformed, and hearing that you haue ●ane orders.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>That I haue: I haue tane order for the making away of a hundred Maidenheads in my time, and not ſo few: but I am in the mind of you now, theſe two beagles, <hi>Dorus</hi> and <hi>Mopſa,</hi> haue runne themſelues breathleſſe in the chaſe of loue, you would ha' me couple them up in the leaſes of Matrimonie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="21"/>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>We are in the way to catch the old one, and then our ayme deceiues not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>We are ifaith: Invention could not weaue,</l>
                           <l>A quainter web, Suſpition to deceiue.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Liſander</hi> and <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Demet.</speaker>
                        <p>Come, paſſe off this groveling imitation; a Lovers thoughts muſt bee ambitious, and like the Eagle, ſcorning the baſe ayre where Kites and Crowes lie flagging: mount the cleare sky of Invention, and overpeere all hindrances:</p>
                        <p>The Ladies themſelues are willing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Ready to embarke upon the next tide of occaſion whatſoever.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Demet.</speaker>
                        <p>Let mee alone to worke it then, But here comes my Boy.</p>
                        <stage>Enter Page.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twere more for your credite Sir, and you could ſay your man: but men and warre were worne out of faſhion both in a Summer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>I am of thy beliefe in that Boy.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Would my Lord were ſo too ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Suppoſe I were Sir, what then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſhould (as many upſtarts haue done) proue rich: for I be|leeue you would make me your heire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Is that part of your beliefe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>A principall poynt ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Renounce it then, for I beleeue you'l never be ſaved by't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>I am ſure I cannot looſe by't. I beleeue further, that many Knights, and ſome Ladies, were never of Gods making.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Of whoſe then, wagge?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile tell you: the Minters coyne Gold, Gold makes He|ralds, Heralds makes Knights, and Knights ſtampe Ladies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>And what doe Ladies?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>They liue not idle neither; they make ſome Knights, and marre many Gentlemen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Ladies are good worke-women too, then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Farre better then any Taylor: they'l make you an end of a ſuite, eſpecially a Court ſuite, when all the Taylors in a Countrey know not how to ſet a ſtitch in't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I am of the beliefe you are a knaue, ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>I had no faith, ſhould I ſay you were not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, what a Knaue?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>In a Knaues beliefe ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="21"/>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe in yours?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe you ſay't, and ile ſweare it, my Lord.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>No more <hi>Boy,</hi> I am weary of your jeſts.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>That confirmes them to be good ſir.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Your reaſon for that, ſir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe travellers and lovers, are ſoone weary of goodneſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Goodly ones indeed: but leaving this high-way of cir|cumſtance; I ſent you for <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>The learned Scribe attends you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Manaſſes.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you fall off ſir?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Like an Apple at Michaelmas, without ſhaking. <hi>Exit.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Welcome <hi>Manaſſes:</hi> I haue preſent employment for thee, in which I muſt borrow—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Pardon me Madam, I learned of my Lord, to lend nothing without ſecuritie and pawnes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis not money (<hi>Manaſſes</hi>) but counſell and furtherance that we deſire.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Good counſell is worth good money Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou ſhalt bee well conſidered; there's twenty Crownes in earneſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay Madam, this hand is like a fellow that takes every thing in jeſt; if you be in earneſt, let me feele it here: So Lady, now betwixt earneſt and jeſt, if your Will be ready drawne, before your friend delivered as your deed, and put me in truſt to execute it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Take it this, in a word honeſt Sheepheard, and thy Lords daughter Madam <hi>Mopſa,</hi> are man and wife.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Man, and woman perhaps, but not man and wife: for though moſt women haue a will to bee Ladies, like my Lords wife; yet every Lady hath not wit to bee a wife, as my Lords Daughter. But what good can I doe in this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>O very much: for though they bee man and wife by oath and proteſtation, the chiefeſt ceremony of all; namely Mariage is yet unperformed, and hearing that you haue ●ane orders.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>That I haue: I haue tane order for the making away of a hundred Maidenheads in my time, and not ſo few: but I am in the mind of you now, theſe two beagles, <hi>Dorus</hi> and <hi>Mopſa,</hi> haue runne themſelues breathleſſe in the chaſe of loue, you would ha' me couple them up in the leaſes of Matrimonie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="22"/>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>You are in the right.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>And you in the wrong, ile keepe your jeſt, but in any caſe take backe againe your earneſt: ile not purchaſe my Lords diſpleaſure with your gold.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Thy Lord ſhall never know't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh ſir! though my M●hath but bad eyes, hee hath excee|ding long eares: and though a Forrayner may play with a Citizens wooden Dagger, I would not wiſh any to jeſt with a Courtiers ſteeld Sword; tis ſeldome drawen but it drawes blood.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Tuſh man, be not ſo timerous, my credite ſhall countenance thee: bee not an Aſſe, make uſe of thy time: thy maſters ſervice is no heritage; the world knowes hee gets under the Duke, thou art a foole, and thou wilt looſe under him: there's a hundred Crownes for thee; tuſh man, thy betters will ſtraine curteſie with aleagence for a bribe</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, could you to every one of theſe Crownes giue me a Kingdome?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>What then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſhould haue more ground then halfe the Kings in Chri|ſtendome: here's my hand, ile do't: my M. is my M. and I loue him; but my gold's my God, and I honour it: ile do't; the time and place?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Soone in the evening at <hi>Adonis</hi> Chapell. Art reſolute?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>As your Adamant: thinke you 'twas feare made me keepe out? no twas hope of theſe flattering ſweet lipt d●abs. I feare to marry my Ladies daughter? no nor to goe to bed with her neither, Why, I haue counterfeited his hand and ſeale. Hee has beene content with mee, to come neerer to him, at his entertainement of the laſt Embaſſadour, when hee was heate with drinking of healths. As I led him to his Chamber, I nimd●his Chaine, and drew his Purſe, and next morning perſwaded him he lo●t it in the great Chamber at the Revels. Hee puts me in truſt with his whole eſtate: he buyes Ma|ners, I purchaſe Farmes: he builds houſes, I plucke downe Churches: he gets of the Duke, and I of the Commons: he beggers the Court, and I begger the whole Countrey.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Theſe are notable knaviſh courſes. What breeding haſt had?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                        <p>Very good breeding ſir: My great Grandfather was a Rat-catcher, my Grandſier a Hangman, my father a Promooter, and my ſelfe an Informer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="22"/>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou wert a knave by inheritance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>And by education too: but bawdy Informations growing ſtale, I gave up my cloake to a Broker, and crept into credite for a Gowne, and of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> a penurious Informer, I turned Coppy, and became <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> a moſt preciſe and illiterate expoſitor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Were you a Reader then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>And a Writer too Bullie, I ſet ſome of my Pariſhioners wives ſuch coppies, as their husbands might caſt their caps at it, but could never come neere.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>But and you us'd ſuch a high and elevate ſtile, your auditories low and humble underſtandings ſhould never crall over't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Tuſh, I could faſhion the body of my diſcourſe fit to the eare of my auditory: for to caſt Eloquence amongſt a company of Stinkards, is all one as if a man ſhould ſcatter pearle amongſt the hog|giſh animals ecliped Swine: no, I had paraphraſticall admonitions of all ſorts; Some againſt couetous Land-lords, and that would I ſquirt amongſt beggarly Tennants; Some againſt Vſurers, and that would I throw in at Priſon Grates amongſt prodigall Bankroutes; Some againſt the pride of the Court, and that honies the eare of the Citizen; Some againſt the fraud of the city, and that's cake and cheeſe to the Countrey; Some againſt Proteſtants, and that plumps the laſy Catholike; againſt Papiſt and Proteſtant, and that fattens the ranke-witted Puritan; againſt Papiſt, Puritan, and Proteſtant, and that tic|kles the eare of the luxurious Athieſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why you never light upon any Athieſts, doe you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh very many.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>In the countrey perhaps, and the out-skirts of the City.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>In the very boſome of the City, and by your leave, here and there one in the Court too: But wee fit em all; for indeed wee wandring Lights have (as other Tradeſ-men have) Commodities of all ſorts and prices.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>How doe they come by them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>As many doe by Offices, ſteale into them ere the Duke be aware of em. Some buy em at Booke-ſellers ſtalls, but the beſt they beſpeake of Poets.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Mee thinkes Poets of all men ſhould not edify, they are ſo envious.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>One to another, to nobody elſe: a Proud Poet is for all the world like a Puncke in requeſt, covetous of many Clients, when ſhe
<pb facs="23"/>
hath more then ſhee can handſomely play off: You ſhall have ſome Poet (<hi>Apolloes</hi> Vicar eſpecially) write you a Comicall, Paſtorall, Tra|gicall, Muſicall hiſtory in Proſe, will make the Auditors eyes runne a water like ſo many water-ſpouts; I had one of them my ſelfe, and your eares bee in caſe, Ile give you a taſt on't; his argument was fet out of the Poem called, The loſt ſheepe, and thus it is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Prithee be briefe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay peace, and it were in place where you might wake the beſt men in the pariſh, for commonly they ſleepe the beginning, becauſe they love not diviſion: but to the loſt Sheepe. Beloved, you muſt imagine this Sheepe was a Sheepe, a loſt Sheepe, a Sheepe out a the way; but my deare Flocke and loving Sheepe, whom like a carefull Shepheard I have gathered together, with the whiſtle or pipe, as it were of mine Eloquence, into this Fold of peacefull Communitie, doe not you ſtray, doe not you flie out, doe not you wander, doe not you looſe your ſelves; but like kinde Sheepe and valiant Rams, I ſpeake to you the better part and head of my Flocke: As I ſay, you ſhall ſee the valiant Rammes turne all their hornes to|gether, and oppoſe themſelves againſt the Wolfe, the hungry Wolfe, the greedy Wolfe, the Lambes-devouring Wolfe, the Wolfe of all Wolfes, to defend their Eawes and young ones. Durſt you lay all your heads together, and with the hornes of your Man|hood defend your Families, your owne Wives, and your neighbours children: Was not this ſtinging geere?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>A good Sheepiſh admonition.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>The fitter for my audience; while you live have a care to fit your audience.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou ſpeakeſt like a Chriſtian, prithee what Religion art of?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>How many ſoever I make uſe of, Ile anſwer with <hi>Piava|no Orlotto</hi> the Italian; I profeſſe the Dukes onely.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>What's his reaſon for that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>A very ſound reaſon: for ſayes hee, I came raw into the world, and I would not willingly goe roſted out: ſo cloſe up the ſtomacke of your diſcourſe with that dry anſwer, and every man a|bout his buſineſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>You'l be mindfull of tomorrow night?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>As your Lawyer of the Tearme, or your Landlord of the Quarter-day.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="23"/>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſo: the mettle I muſt forge my plot on, lies a war|ming in the furnace of my braine; and I muſt faſhion it inſtantly, for feare it burſt vvith heat. Giue my conceit way, for here comes one muſt helpe to proportion it.</p>
                        <stage>Exit Liſan.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Dametas.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>How now <hi>Demetrius,</hi> what wind hath blowne up this ſtorme of melancholy? thy countenance was not wont to bee thus cloudy; Whence proceeds this ſudden alteration?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>From mine owne hard fortune my Lord, that my ill-ſtard nativitie ſhould continue thus oppoſite.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Art croſt in a ſute at Court? or what's the matter? ſpeake.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile acquaint your Honour: I hope no other eare over|heares us. Vnder <hi>Dianaes</hi> Oake I found an inſcription upon a ſtone, which told me, that wealthy <hi>Ariſtomones</hi> ſometimes brought into <hi>Arcadia,</hi> had there under hid a maſſie ſumme of treaſure.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Vnder <hi>Dianaes</hi> Oake? <hi>Dorus</hi> ſhall haue my daughter <hi>Mopſa:</hi> no more words on't, and thou loveſt me <hi>Dorus:</hi> ſmother thy golden hopes a day or two; thou ſhalt haue <hi>Mopſa,</hi> but ●le haue all the Gold, then marry my daughter to ſome great man, though he be poore, tis the faſhion: Ile bee nobly allied what ere it coſt me: ſhalt bee my Sonne in law <hi>Dorus.</hi> haue an eye to the Princeſſe, fall cloſe to my daughter <hi>Mopſa,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Court her and ſpare not: now begins the ſport,</l>
                           <l>Kiſſe her, doe, kiſſe her; thou ſhalt pay ſweetly for't:</l>
                           <l>I can gull you, know what faire words can doe,</l>
                           <l>I'me an old Knaue, and a young Courtier too.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>So, ſo; how violently hee devoures his bane, and ſteales himſelfe into the order of Gullerie: me thinkes I ſee how betwixt hope and feare he ſweats in his practice, and like a fooliſh dreamer, caſts how to lay out his wealth before it comes in▪ So much for him: Now to my Lady Beauty his wife; and as the Devill would ha●t, here ſhe comes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter▪ Miſo.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dorus,</hi> how now <hi>Dorus?</hi> What time a day is't with you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>What time a day ſoever it bee with me, tis ſleeping time with my Lord, I am ſure of that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Sleeping time <hi>Dorus,</hi> what doſt thou meane by that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay nothing, hee is troubled with a kind of malady called <hi>Inſurrectio carnis.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="24"/>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>How, a diſh of Crevices? nay and that be the worſt, good enough; I am glad a falls to Fiſh, for hee was given to Fleſh a late too too bad.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Maſſe I thought as much, for I ſaw him goe a angling.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I hold my Ladiſhip, to ſome ſtru●et.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Life a jealouſy, I think you are a witch, twas ſo indeed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay I thought as much; he was wont to kiſſe me, and doe all ●indneſſe a man could doe, till he came to the Court, and now he will not lye with me for ſooth, and why? tis the Court faſhion: he will not love me, and why? tis the Court faſhion: I muſt not come neere him at his downe-●ing, nor his up-riſing, &amp;c. And this bee the Court faſhion, would I were an honeſt woman of the Countrey againe, be Courtiers who liſt: I, I, <hi>Dorus,</hi> I tell thee in teares, hee hath not dealt by me as a husband ſhould doe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis nothing to mee, I cannot doe withall Madam, would I could.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes marry mayſt thou <hi>Dorus;</hi> thou mayſt, and ſhalt doe withall too and thou wilt: but as thou lookeſt to enjoy my daugh|ter <hi>Mopſa,</hi> acquaint me with the old Foxes ſtarting hole.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>That's paſt my cunning, the old Foxe has more holes then one to hide's head in: But not to goe long about the buſh with you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>No good <hi>Dorus,</hi> I doe not love a man ſhould goe long a|bout my Buſh: what is ſhe for a woman?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not what ſhe is for a wom●n, marry I feare ſhee's little better then a whore for your husband; hearke in your eare, ſhee's <hi>Manaſſes</hi> wife.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Manaſſes</hi> wife? marry fire maſter gunner, a Puritan turnd Punke: Gods my precious. Ile ſlit her noſe, as I am a Lady will I; is ſhe the party you wot on?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes faith Madam, ſhee is the Mare the man rid on.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile ſpoyle their ſport, ſaddle my Mule there, have an eye to the Princeſſe; ſhaltha my daughter, an't be but to ſpite him withal, faith Fox Ile ha you out of your hole, or Ile fire you out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay that will doe no good, but for your owne good Ma|dam, take heed you doe not ſcold.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, may not a Lady ſcold <hi>Dorus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Scold? O in no caſe, twill marre a Ladies beauty cleane, and make her looke as hard-favoured as any ordinarie woman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="24"/>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Godamercy for that <hi>Dorus,</hi> Ile not loſe my beauty for twenty on em: ſaddle my Mule, bring mee my chopping-knife, Ile geld the lecherous Goat, and mince his Trull as ſmall as herbs to the pot. This is not ſcolding <hi>Dorus,</hi> is't?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>No this is tollerable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay then I care not, ſaddle my Mule I ſay, let her pray God her feeling be good, for as I am a Lady, Ile not leave her an eye to ſee withall, and yet I will not ſcold neither.</p>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh take heed of that at any hand. So, ſo, ſo; now it be|ginnes to quicken, me thinkes I ſee already how ſhe runnes atilt at the wenches eyes, calls the Mayd Bawd, the woman whore, and her husband Lecher; and when all comes to all, like an Iriſh wolfe, ſhe barkes at her owne ſhaddow; but committing her and her Aſſe to their wild-gooſe chace, now to my ſweet-heart <hi>Mopſa,</hi> for ſhee's all the blocke's laſt in my eye to ſtumble on; and God bleſſe my wits, for the foole haunts me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Mopſa.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Dorus,</hi> where's my Father <hi>Dorus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Your father? O my deere <hi>Mopſa.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay now you flowt me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Flout you? Oh the faire heavens! but this 'tis for a man to caſt away himſelfe in violence of paſſion, and extremity of ſighs, on a piece of beauty that cares not for him, but it is the trickes of you all.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Trickes? no as God mend mee; and I ſhould not have a husband till I got him with trickes, I ſhould leade Apes in hell: but faith tell me, doſt thou love me <hi>Dorus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe I love you quoth ye? It cuts my very heart-ſtrings, doe I love you? why tis the onely marke my endeavours ſhoot at.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>If thou doſt not hit the marke then, thou art a very bung|ler: but where is my father?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Why I have ſent him and your mother out of the way of purpoſe, and appoynted <hi>Manaſſes</hi> to meete us this evening at <hi>Ado|nis</hi> Chappell, in the <hi>Amazons</hi> aparrell, to marry us; I thinke theſe are ſignes I love you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>I but you jeſt, I doubt you will not marrie me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you meet me there?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>As I am a virgine I will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>And come with an intent to marry me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="25"/>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>As I hope to be a wife I will.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>You muſt take heed you keepe our purpoſe cloſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>As I did the loſſe of my Maydenhead.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Why haue you loſt it then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Many a deare day agoe, yet I told no body on't but my Mother and our Horſe-keeper, and they ſay I am nere the worſe maid for that, and I can keepe my owne counſell, as I hope I ſhall; but will you meet me ſoone?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Iuſt in the mid-way, as Tilters doe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile goe afore and ſtay, but doe not deceiue me, and you doe, ile ſhew my Fathers Horſe-keeper all as God mend me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>So <hi>tria ſequuntur tria,</hi> now am I rid of a triumuirie of fooles, and by their abſence haue wonne a free acceſſe to an eſcape.</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>If my <hi>Liſanders</hi> hope proue like to this,</l>
                           <l>This night ſhall crowne us Monarches of our bliſſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Duke</hi> and <hi>Liſander.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                        <p>No more of theſe delayes ſweet Madam, your loue hath broken day oft with my expectance, I dare giue it truſt no longer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I confeſſe it my Liege, and like a ſpent Deare, not able to maintaine longer flight, I caſt my ſelfe downe breathleſſe at your loues mercy: yet I beſeech your Majeſtie, let not your eager deſires practiſe any preſent violence upon my yeelding chaſtitie: 'twas only poſſeſſion of my loue you had in chace, which with convenient time and place purchaſed, I put your grace in full poſſeſſion of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Although thy breath bee never but muſicall, yet it never raught the ſtring of true happineſſe till now: and to approue thy heart ſets hand to thy word, appoint the time.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Then this preſent evening (and yet my Virgine blood is aſhamed to conſent to the betraying of my modeſtie) meet me at <hi>Adonis</hi> bower, where ile make tender of ſubdued chaſtitie to your high Majeſtie, as my firſt and moſt victorious conquerour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>By my Imperiall Globe, and hope of thoſe joyes, thy pre|ſence ſhall bring to enrich mee with, Ile meet thee, and make thee Queene over the moſt ſubmiſſe Captiue that ever loue tooke pri|ſoner.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>If you deceiue me—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Not except warme life,</l>
                           <l>Deceiue my veines of their innatiue heat.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="25"/>Then haſte ſlow time, exchange thy leaden feete</l>
                           <l>For <hi>Hermes</hi> wings till I my faire hopes meet.</l>
                           <l>But lockt once in the armes of my delight,</l>
                           <l>Cloath all the world in an eternall night.</l>
                           <l>And ſteed of morning when the Sun ſhould riſe,</l>
                           <l>They ſhall ſee two in my <hi>Zelmanes</hi> eyes.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>So farewell thought I, I haue prepar'd you a <hi>Zelmanes</hi> an|ſwerable to your expectation.</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Then triumph in thy will, and let thy thoughts</l>
                           <l>Proclaime a Iubilee: my teeming hopes</l>
                           <l>Are now deliver'd of a gratious birth,</l>
                           <l>Which I haue chriſtened, opportunitie,</l>
                           <l>Vnto whoſe ſhrine in honour of this day,</l>
                           <l>My thoughts ſhall hold a monethly ſacrifice.</l>
                           <l>Loue grant <hi>Demetrius</hi> meet the like ſucceſſe,</l>
                           <l>Our paines are crown'd with double happineſſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Iulio</hi> and <hi>Aminter.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>Only our diſguiſes hold firme, but all other attempts meet untimely deaths, even in their cradles.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>What and we ſhould acquaint the Ladies with our in|tents?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twould argue a kind of cowardiſe in our wits, that haue ſuch ſuſpectles admittance to their preſence, as this diſguiſe hath purchaſed us, wee ſhould not haue that abilitie of inventure to en|tangle them in their owne ſecuritie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Well howſoever, wee muſt not dwell long determining for the libertie of ſtay with <hi>Dametas,</hi> who out of his covetous diſ|poſition in detayning our reward allowed us, the eldeſt day of our licenc't aboad at Court, is run out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis very true, and for my part, Ile rather goe home with a private repulſe, then managing any unlikely attempt, become ſufferer under a publicke diſgrace.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>That's my very thought, yet that our ſecond arrivall bee not altogether empty of employment, lets practiſe ſomething upon <hi>Dametas,</hi> and acquaint the world with his coward baſeneſſe; in which, hee not onely detracts from his maſters bountie, but looke how as a Conduit head or maſter-ſpring that is poyſoned, doth his
<pb facs="26"/>
beſt, to infect the whole body of the Court, with the leaproſie of his covetouſneſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul</speaker>
                        <p>There's no action of his begetting can be ſaid to bee truely honourable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>How can they when their Father is a mungrell? the Duke out of his honourable bounty commanded him to reward our tra|vels with ●00. Crownes: and now after two moneths attendance, and enforc't delayes, In which time an ordinary Petitioner might haue ſpent the valew of the reward, hee packs us off with fiftie Crownes, his excuſe being that his maſter hath forgot us, and what he doth, is of his owne bounty, as if the Moone ſhould brag ſhee gaue the world light, when all the luſter ſhe hath, comes from the heat of the Sunne.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Should his villanies be ſuffered to proſper, they would grow to ſuch height, as the Dukes authority ſhould haue much trouble to prune them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>To prevent which, his Majeſty ſhall haue private note of it, knew we in whoſe truſt to conduct it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis an office very few dare undertake, he is ſo riveted to the Dukes good opinion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>Lies there no jarre twixt none of the Nobilitie and him, what ſay you of <hi>Zelmane?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>The gallant <hi>Amazon:</hi> you could not haue caſt your choice fitter, for her honourable minde maintaines deadly feud againſt his baſe proceedings; and here ſhee comes, attended by <hi>Dameta's</hi> ſer|vant, lets waite on opportunity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Liſander</hi> and <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Liſander.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Demetrius.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Liſander</hi> and <hi>Demetrius?</hi> ſtand cloſe, of my life wee are come to the birth of ſome notable knavery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>How blowes the winds of our hopes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Faire to the poynt of our expectation, I haue made away the Duke and the Dutcheſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>How made away them? poyſon'd them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>With a confection of loue, which I haue ſo tempred with faire promiſes, as their mindes are in loues haven already, <hi>Videlicet</hi> in <hi>Adonis</hi> bower, where this evening I haue given them my word
<pb facs="26"/>
to meet them; but I haue ſo caſt it, that <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſhall meet them in my ſteed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twill be a rare Scene of mirth, to heare what coſtly diſ|courſe they'l beſtow upon the foole in thy outſide.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe you heare that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, thanke loue and my eares, but liſt the concluſion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue cleard the way to <hi>Violetta,</hi> but what order haſt thou ●ane with thy burbolts, <hi>Dametas, Miſo,</hi> and amorous <hi>Mopſa?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Shot them away, at three ſeverall markes, yet ſo conveyed it, that in the end they ſhall all meet at <hi>Adonis</hi> Chappell.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>This project cannot but bring forth ſome notable deceit.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>My hopes ſhould want of their will, and it doe not—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Now we haue made a ſmooth paſſage to our eſcape, how ſhall we convey our loves out of the Iland?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue determined of that ſir, and better to effect, my boy this time hath caſt ſuch a baite of knavery to the two Captaines, <hi>Kalander</hi> and <hi>Philanax,</hi> as we may paſſe without ſuſpition.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>But how for tranſportation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>I am furniſht of that too, you remember the two Lacede|mon intelligencers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Now what of us?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Hold my life, we ſhall be put in this Scene of Gullery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh in any caſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>For the loue of <hi>Cupid</hi> doe, inquiry is paſt, lets take our en|trance, and paſſe over the ſtage like mutes, to furniſh out a ſhow.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſee occaſion like a kind wench preſents them in the very inſtant, my honeſt friend welcome, haue you not your diſpatch with a letter to Lacedemon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam we haue, and ſtay onely to take our leaues of your Ladiſhip, and know what ſervice your honour will command.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>You haue my thankes, for the truth is, I muſt commit buſines of much import unto your truſt, and to prevent much cir|cumſtances take my word, your are not ignorant of the Kings ge|nerall challenge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>About his daughters.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>You underſtand mee, with theſe few crownes receiue my mind, which is to convey the two Ladies, whom we in theſe diſgui|ſes haue wonne to Lacedemon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>Were we but confirm'd of your eſtates.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="27"/>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Wee'l giue you ſufficient aſſurance of that, and the Prin|ceſſes themſelues ſhall confirme it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>Wee craue no better Madam, but ſhall we not haue your honours company?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>No: having brought them aboard, wee'l make returne to the Duke, to let him underſtand we ſtole not our prizes but wonne them manfully at the poynt of wit.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>A noble reſolution.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>His foile will appeare the more palpable, and your conqueſt the more applauſible, where ſhall we receiue the Ladies?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>De●●.</speaker>
                        <p>Be that our care, but on your liues be heedfull of their▪ ſafe|ties.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ami.</speaker>
                        <p>More then of our owne my Lord.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Enough, whilſt you attend weele to the Duke, and play all Guls or none.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>All Guls indeed ſince you had follies vvhip,</l>
                           <l>No Guls, to all Guls, fooles loue fellowſhip.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Miſo</hi> and <hi>Mopſa.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>Looke well to mine Aſſe there, Lord how I ſweat with an|ger; this ſames the houſe ſure, and now like a wiſe Lady let me count my hurts, and ſee how I ſhall be reveng'd: it ſhall be ſo, ile haue them both carted, and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſhall goe afore like a whif●er, and make way with his hornes: where be theſe whores? open the doore, where bee theſe panders? O that I vvere not a Lady, I could ſcold like a butter-vvhore.</p>
                        <stage>Enter Wife.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                        <p>Whoſe there a Gods name? Lord for his mercy is the vvoman mad?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes I thanke yee fo●'t▪ horne mad, vvhere's your companion, vvhere's the old leacherous Goat my husband? open the doore I ſay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Ieſus for thy mercy ſake, Madam vvhat doe you vvant?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>What do I vvant? the chiefe implement a vvoman ſhould haue; I vvant that as a vvoman cannot be vvithout, I meane my husband I vvant.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Your husband? I ſavv him not as I am an honeſt vvoman.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Not as you are an honeſt, ſo I thinke, but as you are an ar|rant vvhore you did, you muſt haue your Creviſhes vvith a pox, can|not Citty Maunchet and freſh God ſerue your turne, but you muſt haue Court Cake-bread and Creviſhes vvith a vengeance? but come giue me my husband, or Ile haue him ou● of the fleſh on thee, and yet I vvill not ſcold neither.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray madam ha' patience: vvhat ſhould your husband doe here?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>That vvhich he ſhould doe at home vvith his vvife, and he
<pb facs="27"/>
were worth his eares.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Lady I protect I doe not know him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Not know him? thou lieſt in every ve●e i'th heart, thou lyeſt thou knoweſt him, and as <hi>Adam</hi> knew <hi>Eue</hi> thou knoweſt him, he hath beene as in ward with thee, as ever he was with me, he hath, by his owne confeſſion he hath, and thou denieſt it, thou lieſt in thy throat like a Puritanicall whore as thou art, O that I were a butter who●e for an houre I might ſcold a little.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam they are no honeſt men that bring theſe tales to you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Men bring tales to me? I de●ie thee in thy guts, I defie thee. men bring tales to mee? thou takeſt me to bee one of thine owne Church doſt? they are no honeſt men that bring tales to thee and ha' wiues of their own, &amp; my husbands one of them, go thy waies now.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>I beſeech you Madam doe but heare me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Heare thee? I haue heard too much of thee, too too much, too much, where's my husband? bring forth my husband, ile teach him to put a difference betwixt <hi>Ioan</hi> and my Lady I hold him ten pound on't, and yet I will not ſcold neither, and I had beene an old hag paſt teaming, as his whore is a puritan, it had bin ſomewhat, but being a woman of Gods making, &amp; a Lady of his own, and wearing mine owne haire which is much in a Lady of my ſtanding I can tell you, to uſe me thus, fleſh and blood cannot endure it, let me come in, open the doore let me come in, O that I were any vile thing in the world but a Lady that I might ſcold a little.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Kalander</hi> and <hi>Philanax, Demetriu's Boy.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>So, ſo, ſo, take your places, for this ſame bald pated oake is the ſtage, where yee ſhall ſee the part of a doting foole performed by an old man and a young wench.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kal.</speaker>
                        <p>Who worſhipfull <hi>Dametas?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>The ſame man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Hath he no fellow Acters in his moſt lamentable, comicall, hiſtoricall, tragicall, muſicall, paſto●a'l?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>None that require any mouthing but his Aſſe and himſelfe, marry then he has Signior <hi>Mattocke,</hi> a very ſharpe ſatyricall humo|riſt, and <hi>Mounſier le ſpade,</hi> but he goes ſomewhat more bluntly to his buſines, yet heele ſerue for mutes, and as good as the beſt to fur|niſh out the ſtage.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kal.</speaker>
                        <p>But dares <hi>Dorus</hi> being but <hi>Dametas</hi> ſervant ſo abuſe his mad maſter thus groſly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>O Lord Sir, there haue beene ſerving men haue done their Maſters farre greater abuſe, yet had their wiues conceald it, their eares ſhould never haue beene acquainted with it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="28"/>
                        <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                        <p>Is that a faſhion in requeſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>Altogether ile aſſure you, but obedience, Gentlemen the Scene begins.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Dametas,</hi> with mattocke and ſpade.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kal.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray God it be good he ſtayes ſo long, Ridiculous enough, and good enough.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>So, ſtand Aſſe, ſtand gentle Aſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
                        <p>What Countrey-man is his Aſſe, he ſpeakes ſo familiarly to him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>A'th Citie breed, marry hee picks up his living ath burs and nettles that grow about the Court gate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Be in readineſſe good mattocke, play thy part ſweet ſpade, let mee ſee; <hi>Dianaes</hi> oake? I held <hi>Dianaes</hi> oake divine, true pure gold, honeſt <hi>Dorus,</hi> fortunate <hi>Dametas.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kal.</speaker>
                        <p>An excellent comoedian, what life he puts into his part.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>So, by thy leaue ſtone, by thy patience honeſt ſtone, the very gravell ſavours of treaſure, this ſame's the bed-chamber of my Lady <hi>Pecu●ia,</hi> and ſee, ſee ſome of her golden haires, more, more, more yet divine tree, pure gold, honeſt <hi>Dorus,</hi> fortunate <hi>Demetrius,</hi> ſoftly, ſoftly, not too faſt, let me not devoure my content too gree|dily, leſt like a cormorant I take a ſurfet on't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh take heed of that maſter in any caſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Pure mettle, excellent gold: but let me ſee now, I ſhall by computation haue ſome three millions of 'em, ● ſome three or foure mi●lions, how ſhall I employ them to make the moſt profit of them</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>That would be knowen indeed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile put out one million to uſe, after the rate of ſeven ſcore to the hundreth: and yet I wont, no fie, for then you will haue my humour brought ath ſtage for a vſurer; to prevent with ſcandalous report, ile put it into my Scribe-majors hand, &amp; he ſhall dea●e for me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kal.</speaker>
                        <p>There's a ſimple cloake▪ to cover his villany.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis a very ſhort one: and paſſing ſl●te to hide his knavery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>It cannot chuſe but be ſeene through.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>An other million ile lay to beſlow in Offices. I will haue wealth, or ile rake it out ath kennels elſe, chimnies ha' ſmoakt for't already, and now ile deale upon ſea-cole and ſalt, now, now, now, it comes, ſweet gold, honeſt <hi>Dorus,</hi> fortunate <hi>Demetrius,</hi> divine gold, how, how ſhal I adore thee? O let me doe the homage of my knees: now, now, for the tongue of a Poet, though I hate poetry worſe then ●ny of the ſeven deadly ſins, I could wiſh my ſelfe a Poet for ſome
<pb facs="28"/>
houre, to write a Poem in the praiſe of my divine miſtreſſe; and ſee he very bed wherein her divinitie is lodged: happy, happy, thrice happy <hi>Dametas,</hi> now like an o're joyd lover, let mee open the ſheets of my heavenly miſtreſſe with reverence, ſo with humble re|verence, and like a bluſhing lover that puts out the light ere he pre|ſumes to touch the bed of his loue, ſo let me darken the candles of my body, mine eyes, and firſt bleſſe my hands with touching, next enrich mine eares with hearing, and laſtly make happy my eyes with ſeeing, and let them convey the joy downe into the boſome of my thoughts by degrees, ſoftly by degrees.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                        <p>Did you ever ſee Aſſe make ſuch a ceremonious preparation?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Be not offended ſweet mi●treſſe that I preſume to touch.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>A fooles head of your owne.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kal.</speaker>
                        <p>Has a beene at any coſt of all this invocate for a coxcombe and a bell.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                        <p>Beſhrow my judgement but he deſerues it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <p>And his deſert were nere ſo much, he could but beare away the bell, and ſo you ſay he doth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>A coxcombe and a bell, oh indignity: damnable oake, vile and evill accurſt <hi>Dorus,</hi> unfortunate <hi>Dametas; Diana</hi> I tell thee thou art no honeſt goddeſſe to uſe a Gentleman thus. Whats here a wri|ting, your helpe good ſpectacles, lend me your helpe good ſpectacles, ſome comfortable newes good ſpectacles:</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Who hath his hire, hath well his labours plac't,</l>
                           <l>Earth thou didſt ſeeke, and ſtore of earth thou haſt.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>He that vaine hopes purſues for loue of pelfe,</l>
                           <l>Shall looſe his vvits and likely find himſelfe.</l>
                           <l>Then thinke thy paines revvarded vvell,</l>
                           <l>Thou broughſt the foole, beare backe the bell:</l>
                           <l>Of other matters vvhat enſues,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Adonis</hi> bovver ſhall tell thee nevves,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p>Villanous poetry, I am made a flat foole by poetry; But though I can doe them no▪ further diſgrace, my fatall curſe, A vvronged gentlemans fatall curſe dvvell ever upon them: <hi>Diana</hi> here me, and let my vvords find gratious acceptance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Kal.</speaker>
                        <p>Hide your heads, the terrible curſe comes like a ſtone upon you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Rancor, ſpite, malice, hate, and all diſaſters,</l>
                           <l>Strengthen my faith againſt all poetaſtors.</l>
                           <l>May their intents though pure as chriſtall glaſſes,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="29"/>Be counted falte and capitall Treſpaſſes,</l>
                           <l>O may their lines and labour'd induſtrie,</l>
                           <l>Though worthy of <hi>Apollo's</hi> plaudite,</l>
                           <l>The cleereſt thought in loyalty excelling,</l>
                           <l>Be by ſome Dor preſented for libelling;</l>
                           <l>When they have writ a Scene, in which their braines</l>
                           <l>Have dropp'd their deereſt ſweets, and their ſwolne veines</l>
                           <l>Emptied the Conduit of their pureſt ſpirit,</l>
                           <l>As they ſtand gaping to receive their merit,</l>
                           <l>In ſtead of Plaudities, their chiefeſt bliſſes,</l>
                           <l>Let their deſerts be crown'd with mewes and hiſſes:</l>
                           <l>Behind each poſt, and at the Gallery corners,</l>
                           <l>Sit empty gulls, ſlight fooles, and falſe Informers;</l>
                           <l>Let ſome ſlye Foxe out of diſcretions embers,</l>
                           <l>Terme them the Lands unneceſſary members;</l>
                           <l>And like the Deere, when they have ſpent their breath</l>
                           <l>To make Kings ſport, let them be torne to death,</l>
                           <l>Even by their friends; 'twould ſet my thoughts a twanging,</l>
                           <l>Might I but ●e one of them goe to hanging.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>A paſſing ſtrange curſe, and no queſtion he has travelled farre for ſome of the times.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>He muſt travell further that findes any reaſon in't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>No matter for reaſon, there's rime enough if that be good.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Some of it is no better then it ſhould bee, or my judge|ment deceives me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Sure hee had ſome reaſon to make this rime, and a man could picke it out.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>Rather then Ile bee counted inquiſitive, mine eares ſhall content themſelves with the rimes only, and leave the reaſon to the ſcanning of Poets, whom it more neerely concernes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>But where's the wag that invited us to this banquet of mirth, ſhrunke in the wetting?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I were a rare jeſt now, if whil'ſt the Boy keeps us here in expectation of <hi>Dametas</hi> gullery, his Maſter has made an eſcape with the Dukes daughters.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>That, or ſome knavery elſe upon my life: I had the boy in ſhrewd ſuſpicion at the firſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>And this his ſudden and ſtoln departure confirms it currant.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Then we are ſped, for in ſuſpitions face</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="29"/>I ſee ſome ſubtle ſtratagem in chace.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Miſo</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> wife.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Will your Ladiſhip beleeve me now? nay and I ſay't your worſhip may ſwear't, though I have but a (poore as to ſay) hole of mine owne, I hope the ſpirits have more denomination over mee, then to make it a common Slaughter-houſe of carnallity, where eve|ry Iacke may command fleſh for his money.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>No more wordes ſweete woman, I confeſſe I was in the wrong, this is not the hole the Foxe hides his head in, and therfore for the love of woman-hood conceale mine errours; for howſoever I complain'd, tis thy forehead akes, thy temples have the terrible blow as they ſay, thy husband is a bad man.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>My husband?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I, I, good woman, thy husband; hee is, as I ſay, a fleſhly member, and I feare he has overcome the fooliſh thing my daughter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Your daughter? Ile ſlit her noſe by this light, and ſhe were ten Ladies, twas not for nothing my husband ſaid hee ſhould meete her this Evening at <hi>Adonis</hi> Chappell: but and I come to the God|ſpeed on't, Ile tell em on't ſoundly.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe good woman, tell em on't and ſpare not, but in any caſe doe not ſcold.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, may not a Gentlewoman ſcold in a good caſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not what a Gentlewoman may doe in a good caſe, but a Lady muſt not in any caſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>Though I may not ſcold, I may tell em roundly on't I hope.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>That you may doe law.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>And Ile not bee mealely mouth'd I warrant em: will you beare me company to the Chappell Madam?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>With all my heart Miſtris: What <hi>Dorus</hi> hath given me, Ile give my friend, No foole to company.</p>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="act">
                     <head>ACTVS V. SCENA I.</head>
                     <stage>Enter the King at <hi>Adonis</hi> Bower.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>FArewell bright Sunne, thou lightner of all eyes,</l>
                           <l>Thou fall'ſt to give a brighter beame to riſe.</l>
                           <l>Each tree and ſhrub weare trammells of thy haire,</l>
                           <l>But theſe are wiers for none but Kings to weare,</l>
                           <l>And my rude tongue, ſtriving to blaze her forth,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="30"/>Like a bad Arts-man, does diſgrace her worth:</l>
                           <l>But here's the place, upon this Chriſtall ſtreame,</l>
                           <l>Where <hi>Citharea</hi> did unyoake her teame</l>
                           <l>Of ſiluer Doves to interchange a kiſſe</l>
                           <l>With young <hi>Adonis,</hi> ſhall I meet my bliſſe?</l>
                           <l>The gentle minutes crown'd with chryſtall flowers,</l>
                           <l>Loſing their youths, are growne up perfect houres,</l>
                           <l>To haſten my delight: The baſhfull Moone,</l>
                           <l>That ſince her dalliance with <hi>Endymion</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Durſt never walke by day, is under ſaile,</l>
                           <l>In ſtead of ſheetes has ſpread her ſilver vaile,</l>
                           <l>Each gliding Brooke and every buſhy tree,</l>
                           <l>Being tipt with ſilver, weare her livery;</l>
                           <l>And the dimme night, to grace our amorous warres,</l>
                           <l>Hath ſtucke nine Spheares full of immortall ſtarres,</l>
                           <l>In ſtead of pearles; the way on which ſhe treads</l>
                           <l>Is ſtrew'd with chryſtall deaw and ſilver beades:
<stage>Enter Dutcheſſe.</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>She comes, her feet make muſicke with the ground,</l>
                           <l>And the chaſt aire is raviſht with the ſound,</l>
                           <l>My ſoule flies forth to meet her: hell, my wife,</l>
                           <l>Her preſence like a murtherer drives the life</l>
                           <l>Out of my pleaſures breſt, her jealous eye</l>
                           <l>Envies the heaven of my felicity.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Zelmane,</hi> or my husband? life, or hate?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>What makes old Autumne out a bed ſo late?</l>
                           <l>That ſnow ſhould goe a wooing to the Sunne,</l>
                           <l>When one warme kiſſe workes her confuſion!</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>I have the jeſt, ſuſpition that keepes</l>
                           <l>Court in my husbands thoughts, ſeeing my Love</l>
                           <l>Elect this walke, hath brought him after him.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>King.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>She dogs her ſure, and ſhe to ſhake her off</l>
                           <l>Hath tane ſome other walk, Ile place mine care</l>
                           <l>In diſtance of her will.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Could I but heare the innocent delivery of his breath,</l>
                           <l>'Twould be a ſecond Iubile of mirth.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Here comes my Love.</p>
                        <stage>Enter <hi>Manaſſes</hi> like <hi>Liſander.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Your Love? Alas poore Duke,</l>
                           <l>Your forward hopes will meet a barren ſpring,</l>
                           <l>My Sunne appeares.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="30"/>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Fie, your love ſpeakes too loud,</l>
                           <l>Your Sunne's eclips'd, you doate upon a cloud.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>See how his armes, like precious Phoenix wings, Spread to imbrace me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Now the Cuckow ſings;</l>
                           <l>Thoſe amorous armes doe make a golden ſpace</l>
                           <l>To hug a Duke.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>But Ile fill up the place.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Thoſe fingers tipt with curious Porphery,</l>
                           <l>Staining <hi>Pigmalions</hi> matchleſſe imag'ry,</l>
                           <l>Like amorcus twins all of one mother ●urſt,</l>
                           <l>Contend in courteſy who ſhould touch me firſt.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Should touch me firſt; their ſtrife is undertooke,</l>
                           <l>To twine a young Bay, not a ſtooping Oake.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Young Bay? ſtale jeſt, that a dry ſapleſſe rinde</l>
                           <l>Should hold young thoughts, and a licentious mind:</l>
                           <l>Were ſhe but gone now.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Were the Duke away,</l>
                           <l>My hopes had got the better of the day.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>This is <hi>Adonis</hi> Chappell, I wonder they come not; though I beare but a litle learning about me, and a few good clothes, I would not wiſh em to make <hi>Balams</hi> Aſſe of me: for though many fooles take no felicity but in wearing good clothes (though they bee none of their owne) I have a further reach in me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>I could ban my ſtarres.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>〈…〉 my fate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>That croſſe me thus.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Makes me unfortunate.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Alas good Lady, how her pretty feet</l>
                           <l>Labour to find me.</l>
                           <l>Such blacke events.</l>
                           <l>Darken her ſelfe.</l>
                           <l>That in the boſome of ſome foggy cloud</l>
                           <l>I might imbrace my love.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>That my hopes ſhould meet</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>O would the friendly night</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Would the Moone loſe her light,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>But night is purblind,</l>
                           <l>To make a Duke a ſlave.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>To make e Dutcheſſe</l>
                           <l>Wreſtle with amorous paſſions.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Life a ſpleene,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="31"/>Could my rough breath like a temptſtuous wind,</l>
                           <l>Blow out heavens candles, leaue the world ſtarke blind,</l>
                           <l>That it might either haue no eyes to ſee,</l>
                           <l>Or uſe thoſe eyes it hath to pleaſure me.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Or uſe thoſe eyes it hath to pleaſure me?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Who would haue thought the cold had beene ſo good a muſician? how it playes upon my chaps? and maketh my teeth skip up and downe my mouth like a company of virginall Iacks, but I find ſmall muſicke in it, and <hi>Mopſa</hi> ſhould come now I could doe her little good, yet and ſhe were here, ſhe and I would haue about at cob-nut or at chery-pit, or ſome what to keepe our ſelues from idle|neſſe, though ſhe be but a foole, the bable's good enough to make ſport withall in the darke, and that very word hath ſtarted her.</p>
                        <stage>Enter Mopſa.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Whoſe there <hi>Manaſſes?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes <hi>Mopſa.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Plaine <hi>Mopſa,</hi> I might bee Madam <hi>Mopſa</hi> in your mouth, goodman—where's <hi>Dorus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Why? becauſe he will not be ſaid to make too much haſte to a bad bargaine, he is not come yet.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Not come? a peaſcod on him, but al's one, I thought at firſt he would make but a foole on mee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Would you haue him mend Gods workemanſhip?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>But chuſe him, ſince he hath buld me with an vrchin, ile goe fetch <hi>Raph</hi> our Horſe-keeper; let him that got the calfe keepe the cow in a knaues name and he will, haue you your booke here?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>No matter wench, I can do't well enough without booke.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay and yee can do't well enough your ſelfe, I care for neither of them both, but indeed I loue to haue a thing well done, for ſayes my mother, a thing once well done, is twice done, and I am in her mind for that up and downe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Whoſe with my Lord the Duke? it cannot be,</l>
                           <l>Mine eye would not conceale ſuch treachery.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Tis not the Dutcheſſe ſure, no it is amarous <hi>Ioue,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>That ſeeing <hi>Zelmane</hi> paſſionate for loue,</l>
                           <l>Deſcends to comfort her; <hi>Ioue</hi> if there be</l>
                           <l>A powerfull <hi>Phoebus</hi> God of poetry,</l>
                           <l>In deare remembrance of faire <hi>Daphnes</hi> rape,</l>
                           <l>To winne my loue, lend me ſome ſtranger ſhape,</l>
                           <l>Such as your ſelues haue worne, that when your ſame</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb facs="31"/>Is ſung by Poets, they may quote my name.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure tis my daughter.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Daughter? how her eye</l>
                           <l>Cut out new formes, new ſhapes of jealouſie?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>As ſure as death tis ſhe, for ſee they ſtand</l>
                           <l>Like amarous twins, in twiſted hand in hand,</l>
                           <l>Breaſt againſt breaſt, and that no joy be miſſing,</l>
                           <l>To heare diſcourſe, their lips keepe time with kiſſing,</l>
                           <l>Ile not endure't, impatience grow ſtrong,</l>
                           <l>And though a Prince, tell him he doth thee wrong.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Doe, prethee doe, this ſweetens all the reſt,</l>
                           <l>But here would be the elixar of the jeſt,</l>
                           <l>If whilſt we keepe each other at a bay,</l>
                           <l>A third ſhould come, and beare the hare away.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Dametas.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Villanous poetry, unchriſtian-like poetry, I am cozend of my gold by poetry, rob'd of my charge by poetry, made an apparant foole by poetry, villanous Oke, accurſt <hi>Dorus,</hi> unfortunate <hi>Dametas:</hi> whoſe there my daughter and with <hi>Zelmane?</hi> a wel-willer to <hi>Do|rus,</hi> a favorite to poetry, and therefore enemy to <hi>Dametas,</hi> come hi|ther <hi>Mopſa,</hi> a thy fathers bleſſing come not neare her: what <hi>Mopſa.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, whoſe there? <hi>Dorus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Confuſion a <hi>Dorus,</hi> I am thy miſerable father, didſt not ſee <hi>Hippolita?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>No by my troth not. Did yee not ſee <hi>Dorus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Poxe of <hi>Dorus,</hi> I am undone Madam and thou telft me not of <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Poxe a <hi>Hippolita,</hi> I am a dumbe woman and you can tell me newes of <hi>Dorus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>I had rather ſee ten <hi>Doruſſes</hi> hanged, then looſe <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>I had rather ſee ten fathers damn'd, then looſe my ſweet <hi>Dorus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſhall run mad and I find not <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſhall run franticke and I find not <hi>Dorus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Whats here? I ſhall run mad for <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>And I ſhall run franticke and I find not <hi>Doras,</hi> I hold my life we haue ſome Comoedy in hand, wee ſhall haue a full Scene, for here comes more Actors.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Miſo</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes Wife.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                        <p>As ſure as I am a ſinner to God Madam, that ſames he.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="32"/>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>What with a brace of wenches, ifaith old brocke, have I ●●ne you in the manner, is this the fruits of your lying alone, is this your Court cuſtome with a wannion? lend me thy knife, though I had neither houſe nor land to give em, Ile beſtow a whores marke betwixt you, and yet I will not ſcold neither.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>What a goodyer aile you mother, are you frampall, know you not your owne daughter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Mopſa?</hi> O inſufferable wrong, make thine owne natu|rall child thy Bawd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Here's an excellent patterne for wives to learne to ſcold by.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>What Miſtreſſe <hi>Amazon?</hi> ha you ſuch a cocking ſpirit, honeſt women cannot keep their husbands at home for you? tis not for nothing now I ſee, that the Dutcheſſe lookes yellow on you, but Ile teare that painted whores face of yours, (by this light) and yet I will not ſcold neither.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>Ile mad you with a vengeance.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>The Duke and Dutcheſſe ſt. p both forth and reſtraine her.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Touch not the Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>On your allegeance forbeare, what means this outrage, can|not our private walkes be priviledg'd from your wild contentions?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>How fares the Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>How cheeres my good <hi>Zelmane?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Zelmane?</hi> No Gods my judge my ●iege ● am <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> miſerable <hi>Manaſſes▪</hi> your husbands Scribe-major Madam.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Manaſſes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>A foole.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>My m●n.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                        <p>And my deare h●●d●a● ſweet love, what makeſt th●● here?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>M●y worke for the Hang-man, and the Duke bee not the more mercifull.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>There's ſome deceipt in this: <hi>Dametas,</hi> where's <hi>Hippolita?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>I, I, there's ſome knavery in this: <hi>Mopſa,</hi> where's <hi>Hippolita?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi</speaker>
                        <p>Doubtles ther● ſome villany in this: <hi>Mopſa,</hi> wher's <hi>Hipolita?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>There's no plaine dealing in this, <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> where's <hi>Dorus?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Anſwer directly, where's <hi>Hippolita?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dam.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas Madam I know not, whil'ſt I almoſt mel●ed my ſelfe with digging of gold in <hi>Diana's</hi> Oke, I left her in my wives charge.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                        <p>And whil'ſt I ran to <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> thinking to take my husband and his wife in the manner, I left <hi>Hippolita</hi> in my daughters chamber.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>And whil'ſt ● came to <hi>Adonis</hi> chappel, to be toſt in my mari|age blankets with <hi>Dorus,</hi> I left my litle dog <hi>Pearle</hi> picking dazies.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="32"/>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Who ſent you to <hi>Diana's</hi> Oake to dig gold?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Who ſent you to take your husband in <hi>Manaſſes</hi> houſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Miſo.</speaker>
                        <p>Dorus.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Who ſent you to <hi>Adonis</hi> Chappell?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mop.</speaker>
                        <p>Dorus.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>And who turn'd you into this ſhape?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>They that I feare have made Gulls of us all, <hi>Zelmane</hi> and <hi>Dorus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>We are all ſimply gulld, and ſee where the S●n ſcarce halfe ready, skips from his Eaſterne bed, ſmiling at our gullery.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Liſander</hi> and <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Come where's this luſty wit-maſter?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſa.</speaker>
                        <p>The Keeper of this Love-lotterie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>This gallant <hi>Iuventus</hi> of foureſcore, that like my Ladie of the Lake, diſplayes againſt all commers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>May a couple of plaine-witted Princes have a ſight of your prizes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Where be theſe Ladies, ha? ha your wits had ſuch a skir miſhing, that the two Maids have loſt their heads in the conflict?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Heads? I and bodies too my Lord, and all at one ſhot, and which is worſe, our wits are ſo ſcattered with the terrible blow, that, to be plaine, we are ſcarce our owne men againe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Then you had ſome knocking.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>So it appeares by the ſtorie my Lord.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Li.</speaker>
                        <p>How ſay you my Lady, what Oule ſings out of that Ivy-buſh?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>VVas your wit Knighted in this laſt action?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <p>I am not ſuch a foole, I love my Lord, I am no Knight, I am <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> they made a plaine foole.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>The onely weare, for the guarded foole is out of requeſt: but faith my Liege, how did your oppoſites behave themſelves, did they winne the wenches faire at the point?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>At the very puſh of invention, and went off cleere untoucht.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>And could you draw no blood of their wits?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Not a drop.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Nor <hi>Dametas</hi> neither, nor <hi>Manaſſes?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>Neither, to our diſgrace be it ſpoken, the carriage of this ſtratagem deſerves applauſe, and I hold it a credite to reſt captive to ſuch valiant conquerours.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>VVhy ſo be, I like a man that will confeſſe his errour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="33"/>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>It merits commiſeration Madam and my Liege, not to de|tract from our worth: your eare, we two are the parties you wot on.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Were you the man?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>No he was the man, marry I was the woman in the Moone, that made you walke all this laſt night like the man in the miſt, I could ſay ſomewhat to you Madam, as for <hi>Dametas</hi> and his man, let them ſtand like fooles as they are.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>Can it be poſſible?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no, we are Guls, innocent ſots, but <hi>lante tanta,</hi> the girles are ours we haue won them away to Dargiſon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>Come we haue won the conqueſt, and that's ſufficient.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>You are a <hi>Manaſſes</hi> tis not ſufficient: aha not <hi>Hercules</hi> for <hi>Iole, Ioue</hi> for <hi>Danae, Apollo</hi> for <hi>Daphne, Pan</hi> for <hi>Sirne;</hi> nay the whole packe of their piperly godheads could a diſcharg'd a ſtrata|gem with more ſpirit of all merit; an ambling nag and a downe a downe we haue borne her away to Dargiſon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Iulio</hi> and <hi>Amintas.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>'Twas the moſt rareſt, divineſt, Metaphyſicalſt piece of in|vention, that—what ſay you my liege?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>I giue your deſerts their full merit, you haue gotten equality.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>All the wenches gaue you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas ●hat ſpirits under the Moone could haue detaind her, but know that her cherry red lip, a downe, a downe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Truſt me but you haue deſerved high commendation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio</speaker>
                        <p>Your merit ſtood of the upper ſtaire of admiration.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Why thou haſt a pretty reliſh of wit now, that canſt ſee the broad eye of my deſert at a little hole of demonſtration.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>Your deſert ſaue mee free, you haue done a moſt (to uſe your owne phraſe) Metaphyſicall peece of ſervice, but you had ſome helpe in't queſtionleſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>I doe not thinke but the Ladies had ſome handin't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>A finger, I confeſſe a finger by the hope of perſeverance, a very little finger.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>I thought as much by making of the jeſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>I cannot detract from the Ladies worth, for I know them for excellent worke-women.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Worke-women fit to make Taylors men.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>I by my faith doe I, nay your beſt taylors are arrant bot|chers to them, you ſhall haue a Lady make an end of a ſute, a Court
<pb facs="33"/>
ſute, eſpecially when all the Taylors in a countrey know not how to ſet a ſtitch in't.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
                        <p>Some ordinary ſute perhaps.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Your beſt Court ſuits that are, are finiſht by Ladies, I haue knowen a ſuite my ſelfe lien a making and m●ring ●, ●, and fiue yeare together, and then a Lady hath diſpatcht it in a moneth with a wet finger, ſuch a finger might the Ladies haue in your plot.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Never wet a finger by this Sunne.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Then ſhe helpt you with one dry jeſt or another, but and we may be ſo bold: faith whereare the Ladies?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Sure enough I warrant you, ſome fooles now would haue kept them here, and haue bin guld on them againe, and laught at age, but to prevent all danger, we haue ſhipt them home for <hi>Lacedemon.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>To <hi>Lacedemon?</hi> your ſunne of wit ſhines but dimly in that me thinkes, to whoſe charge haue you truſted them?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>To them we durſt, nay you muſt thinke we are no fooles,</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Fooles? nay deepe wit, and pollicy forbid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>We had no ſooner their ſurpriſall, but we had diſguiſe rea|dy, a ſhip ready, a couple of luſty friends ready, the <hi>Lacedemon</hi> In|telligencers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>Durſt you truſt ſuch pretious jewels in ſuch ruſty caskets?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Durſt? our health, our liues, why they were my tenants; nay you muſt thinke we ſifted them, we are no fooles in that neither.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>If in any thing your wits deſerue the bable tis in that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>None but fooles would haue committed ſuch ineſtimable peeres to a couple of ſtrangers.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>And in a ſhip too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                        <p>And under ſaile too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                        <p>And unfurniſht of friends too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                        <p>And without ſhipping to follow them too.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                        <p>You were no fooles in any thing but that, and in that not to flatter, you expreſſe the true ſhape of folly, and meerely merit the name of fooles.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>What will you ſay now when theſe fellowes ſurrender us our loues?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Weele diſcharge you and ſet their names downe for Guls in your ſteed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>You knovv the Proverbe, vvhen the skie ſals vve ſhall haue Larkes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſan.</speaker>
                        <p>And vvhen you can bring proofe that vve are conſend of our Wenches vveele be the Woodcocks.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="34"/>
                        <speaker>Iulio.</speaker>
                        <p>VVhy then we have once ſpring'd a couple of woodcocks.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Violetta</hi> and <hi>Hippolita.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                        <p>Doe you know theſe? who are the fooles now?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Hippolita?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>My <hi>Violetta?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>VVhat a ſtrange change is here▪</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes ſaith Gallants, you have very ſtrange carding and you knew all, but I hope you'l offer up your cards, and yield the ſet loſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Gulls?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Liſ.</speaker>
                        <p>And abus'd? Ile loſe my life before Ile loſe my honour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
                        <p>Honour and life before Ile loſe my love.</p>
                        <stage>draw.</stage>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay Gentlemen, wee barre all violence; the liberty of our challenge was to all alike equally free, and ſince theſe by faire play have won em, it ſtands with our honour to ſee them peaceably poſ|ſeſt of em, then ſurely take em, for though you weare the breeches, give us leave to ſtand a little.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>VVhy father, is't not time that we were ſped?</l>
                           <l>Tis a great charge to keep a Mayd●●●-head,</l>
                           <l>Loſe it we muſt, and to prevent ill courſe,</l>
                           <l>Better to giv't, then haue it tane perforce,</l>
                           <l>If you be pleas'd let envy doe her worſt,</l>
                           <l>Spit out her poyſon, or contain't and burſt.</l>
                           <l>VVelcome to all, to all a kind good-night,</l>
                           <l>They truely live, that live in ſcorne of ſpight.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         </TEI>

