<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Three excellent tragœdies.:  Viz. The raging Turk, or, Bajazet the Second. The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the First. And The tragoedie of Orestes· / Written, by Tho. Goff, Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford; and acted by the students of the same house.</title>
            <author> Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>137 400dpi TIFF images (displayed as GIF) and XML-encoded text (displayed as HTML).</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 December (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85334</idno>
            <idno type="vid">114751</idno>
            <idno type="Aleph">5358848</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing (2nd ed.) G1006.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1066.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Thomason E.1591[2].</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Madan III 2290.</idno>
            <idno type="bibno">(UnM)99862588e</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Where applicable, subject to copyright.  Other restrictions on distribution may apply.  Please  go to http://www.umdl.umich.edu/ for more information.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Three excellent tragœdies.:  Viz. The raging Turk, or, Bajazet the Second. The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the First. And The tragoedie of Orestes· / Written, by Tho. Goff, Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford; and acted by the students of the same house.</title>
                  <author> Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
                  <author>Meighen, Richard, fl. 1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, carefully corrected by a friend of the authors.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 263, [7] p.    </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Bedell and T. Collins, at the middle Temple gate Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Rich. Meighen.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>"The raging Turk", "The courageous Turk", and "The tragedy of Orestes" each have separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>With three final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2007-07-06.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term>English drama (Tragedy)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="60"/>
                  <pb facs="60"/>
                  <p>THE COURAGEOUS TURK, OR, AMURATH THE FIRST.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Tragedie, Written by</hi> THOMAS GOFF <hi>Maſter of Arts,</hi> and ſtudent of Chriſt-Church in OXFORD, and Acted by the Studens of the ſame houſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Edition</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for G. BEDELL and T. COLLINS, at the middle Temple Gate <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1656.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="61"/>
                  <pb facs="61"/>
                  <head>TO THE No leſſe honored, then deſerving, Sir WALTER TICHBORNE, Knight.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>_THis with another Tragedy, intitu|led, <hi>The raging Turk,</hi> the iſſue of one mans braine; are now come forth together from the Preſſe, neerer allyed, even as Twins in this their ſecond birth; They are full of Glory, Strength, and indeed full of what not, that beautifies? The more apt to be ſoyled, oppoſed, and diſgra|ced; the rather, becauſe the Auther ha's made his <hi>Exit</hi> hence. The intent, and uſe of Dedication (as I have obſerved) is to no o|ther end, then that ignorance and ſpite, (ſworne Enemies to ingenuity) ſhould know
<pb facs="62"/>
upon their dull or envious diſlikes, whether to repayre and recieve reformation. The Fa|therleſſe fellow-Orphan to this work reſteth ſafe under the protection of your moſt noble Brother, my much honoured Friend, <hi>Sir Ri|chard Tichborne,</hi> Knight and Baronet; Now for theſe reaſons, and that I might not make them ſtrangers by remote foſterings, but eſpecially ſtanding to you (moſt worthy SIR) equally engaged, I this to you Preſent and Dedicate: Together tendring the Love and unfained acknowledgements, of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt embounden Servant, RICHARD MEIGHEN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="printer_to_author">
                  <pb facs="62"/>
                  <head>TO THE AUTHOR, <hi>In that, Tranſcribing his Book, without his knowledge, I was bound by promiſe to ſtand to his pleaſure to keepe it or burne it.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>I Will not praiſe this Worke, 'twere loſt,</l>
                  <l>Rich Pearles beſt praiſe themſelves; nor will I boaſt</l>
                  <l>To be poſſeſt of more than <hi>India's</hi> wealth,</l>
                  <l>That were the way to loſe't, ſince I my ſelfe</l>
                  <l>Diſtruſt my ſelfe in keeping it, and ſtand</l>
                  <l>In feare of robbing by ſome envious hand:</l>
                  <l>Rob'd of it, ſaid I? Alas, that fate were juſt,</l>
                  <l>Since I am found firſt thiefe to you, who durſt</l>
                  <l>Unbidden thus, ranſacke your pretious ſtore;</l>
                  <l>This magazine of wit, ſo choyce; nay more,</l>
                  <l>Steale from the chariot of the glorious Sunne,</l>
                  <l>This heavenly fire. What ſhall I ſay, 'tis done;</l>
                  <l>I doe confeſſe the enditement, pity then</l>
                  <l>Muſt be my ſureſt Advocate 'mongſt men.</l>
                  <l>None can abate the rigor of the Law,</l>
                  <l>But the Law-giver; but me thoughts I ſaw,</l>
                  <l>(Or hop'd I ſaw) ſome watry beames of Mercy</l>
                  <l>Breake, glimpſing forth of your imperious eye.</l>
                  <l>O let me beg reprive, your pardon may</l>
                  <l>By due obſervance come another day.</l>
                  <l>Here loe, I tender't backe to bide the doom,</l>
                  <l>By promiſe bound to him, to him with whom</l>
                  <l>I would not breake for all rich <hi>Tagus</hi> ſands;</l>
                  <l>Now he the Priſoner at your mercy ſtands.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>— Ergo ibit in ignes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoc opus aeternum ruet, &amp; tot bella, tot Enſes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Cineres dabit hora nocens. —</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="prologue">
                  <pb facs="63"/>
                  <head>THE PROLOGUE.</head>
                  <l>VVEre not our preſent ſubject mixt with feare,</l>
                  <l>'Twould much affright us to ſee all you here.</l>
                  <l>One would ſuffice us, or no Auditor.</l>
                  <l>Each to himſelfe an ample Theater,</l>
                  <l>Let rude Plebeians thinke ſo, but we know</l>
                  <l>All judgements here from the ſame Spring doe flow;</l>
                  <l>All here have but one cenſure, all one breſt,</l>
                  <l>All ſonnes of the ſame Mother; but the reſt</l>
                  <l>We preoccupate their Cenſure, and fore-tell,</l>
                  <l>What after may be ſaid not to be well.</l>
                  <l>As in moſt decent Garments you may ſee.</l>
                  <l>Some gracious Ornaments inweaved bee;</l>
                  <l>Which ſerve for little uſe; but on ſome day</l>
                  <l>Deſtin'd to pleaſe himſelfe, the wearer may</l>
                  <l>Without a bluſh put on, when his beſt friends</l>
                  <l>Intend to viſit him. So our hope intends</l>
                  <l>The ſacred Muſes Progeny to greet,</l>
                  <l>Which under our Roofe, now the third time meet.</l>
                  <l>We will not ope the booke to you, and ſhow</l>
                  <l>A ſtory word by word, as it doth goe;</l>
                  <l>But give invention leave to undertake,</l>
                  <l>Of it's owne ſtraines, ſome benefit to make:</l>
                  <l>For though a Tragicke Pen may be confin'd</l>
                  <l>W thin a ſtudies private Walles, the mind</l>
                  <l>Muſt be unbounded, and with inventions ſteele,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="121" facs="63"/>Strike fire from the alient Flints —</l>
                  <l>So free we are from ſetting any price</l>
                  <l>On theſe our ſtudied Vanities, that advice</l>
                  <l>Almoſt diſdain'd the whispers of thoſe tongues</l>
                  <l>Which, private firſt, though vented, publike wrongs</l>
                  <l>To the Patient, Patient oft. We'il here begin</l>
                  <l>To be a litle peremptory. Oh that ſinne</l>
                  <l>Of willfull indiſcretion; 'tis no bayes</l>
                  <l>To make us Garlands of our owne mouthes praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Which who affect, may they ſo Lawrell lacke,</l>
                  <l>That ſlanders Thunders may behind their backe</l>
                  <l>Blaſt them with Calumny; for we vow, they deare</l>
                  <l>Pay for their paines, that give attention here.</l>
                  <l>And ſince it's ſuffered with kind indulgence,</l>
                  <l>We hope that Kingly Parent's our defence;</l>
                  <l>Who would not have his dandling love be knowne,</l>
                  <l>But unto thoſe had off-ſpring of their owne.</l>
                  <l>And (for we are aſſured that here be</l>
                  <l>No braines ſo curſt with blacke ſterilitie,</l>
                  <l>But of ſome nature they can frely call</l>
                  <l>Births more mature, and Caeleſtiall;</l>
                  <l>Their ſtudies iſſue) they, like kindeſt Mothers,</l>
                  <l>With tender hands will ſwath the limbes of others.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="64"/>
                  <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                  <l>A Suppo'd Victory by AMURETH</l>
                  <l>Obtain'd in <hi>Greece,</hi> where many captives tane,</l>
                  <l>One among the reſt, IRENE, conquers him,</l>
                  <l>For, taken with her love, he ſounds retreat</l>
                  <l>Eternally from Warre: but after, mov'd</l>
                  <l>With murmur of his Nobles, in her bed,</l>
                  <l>Before his Councils face, ſtrikes off her head.</l>
                  <l>Then ruminating former bloudy broyles,</l>
                  <l>He ſtraight o'recomes all Chriſtian Provinces,</l>
                  <l>Invades the Confines of his Sonne in Law,</l>
                  <l>Fires <hi>Caramania,</hi> and makes <hi>Aladin</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With's Wife and Children ſuppliant for their lives:</l>
                  <l>At length appointed his great'ſt Field to fight</l>
                  <l>Upon <hi>Caſſanae's</hi> Plaines; where having got</l>
                  <l>A wondrous Conqueſt 'gainſt the Chriſtians,</l>
                  <l>Comes the next morne to overview the dead;</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt whom a Chriſtian Captaine, <hi>Cobelitz,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lying wounded there, at ſight of <hi>Amurath,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Riſing and ſtaggering towards him, deſperately</l>
                  <l>With a ſhort dagger wounds him to the heart,</l>
                  <l>And then immediately the Chriſtian dyes.</l>
                  <l>The Turke expiring, <hi>Bajazet</hi> his Heyre</l>
                  <l>Strangles his younger brother: Thus ſtill ſprings</l>
                  <l>The Tragick ſport which Fortune makes with Kings.</l>
                  <pb facs="64"/>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <pb facs="65"/>
                  <head>THE ACTORS.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Amurath.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lala Schahin.</hi> — Tutor to Amurath.</item>
                     <item>two Turkiſh Captaines.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eurenoſes,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Chaſe Illibegge.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cobelitz</hi> a Chriſtian Captaine.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lazarus</hi> the Deſpot or Governour of Servia.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saſmenos</hi> Governour of Bulgaria.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aladin</hi> Sonne in Law to Amurath: and King of Caramania.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Two Lords with Aladin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Two Embaſſadors.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bajazet,</hi> Eldeſt Sonne to Amurath.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jacyl,</hi> Youngeſt Sonne to Amurath.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carradin Baſſa</hi> A Governour under the Turke.</item>
                     <item>For the Maske.
<list>
                           <item>Jupiter</item>
                           <item>Juno</item>
                           <item>Mars</item>
                           <item>Ve●us</item>
                           <item>Hector</item>
                           <item>Achil</item>
                           <item>Apollo</item>
                           <item>Pallas</item>
                           <item>Alexander</item>
                           <item>Philoxenus</item>
                           <item>Neptune</item>
                           <item>Cupid</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Women Actors.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eumorphe,</hi> Concubine to Amurath.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Menthe,</hi> An attendant on Eumorphe.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hatun,</hi> Daughter to the Lord of Phrygia, married to Bajazet.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Aldines Wife,</hi> Two little Boyes with her.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mutes.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Men</hi> Christians <hi>taken, given to</hi> Amurath <hi>for</hi> Janizaries.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sixe</hi> Chriſtian Maidens <hi>preſented to</hi> Hatun <hi>ſuppoſed to be Kings Daughters.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="play">
                  <pb facs="65"/>
                  <head>THE COURAGEOUS TURK, OR, AMURATH THE FIRST.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 1.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter as from Warre,</hi> Lala-Schahin <hi>at one doore, with warlike Muſicke, Souldiers, a March. Enter to him at the other doore,</hi> Amu|rath <hi>in State, with</hi> Eumorphe <hi>his Con|cubine, attendants, Lords and Ladies.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>AMURATH.</speaker>
                           <l>BE dumb thoſe now harſh notes, our ſofter cares</l>
                           <l>ſhall never be acquainted with ſuch ſounds.</l>
                           <l>Peace (our grand Captain) ſee here <hi>Amurath,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>that would have once confronted <hi>Mars</hi> himſelfe,</l>
                           <l>(Acknowledg'd for a better Deity)</l>
                           <l>Puts off ambitious burdens; and doth hate</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="126" facs="66"/>through bloudy Rivers to make paſſages,</l>
                           <l>whereby his Soule might flote to <hi>Acheron.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Wrinckle your browes no more (ſterne fates) for we</l>
                           <l>ſcorne to be made the ſervile Miniſters</l>
                           <l>to cut thoſe threads, at which your ſelves have trembled,</l>
                           <l>eſteeming us the fiercer Deſtiny.</l>
                           <l>Yet muſt great <hi>Amurath</hi> thanke thoſe ſacred powers,</l>
                           <l>they have enricht our ſoules with ſuch a price,</l>
                           <l>as had thoſe <hi>Heroes,</hi> whoſe revengefull Armes</l>
                           <l>ſerv'd <hi>Mars</hi> a ten yeares Prentiſhip at <hi>Troy,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>ere dream'd ſucceeding times ſhould be poſſeſt</l>
                           <l>with ſuch an unparallell'd, unprized beauty as my Saint,</l>
                           <l>they would not have prevented ſo their bliſſe,</l>
                           <l>but beene moſt humble Sutors to the Gods</l>
                           <l>to have protracted their then fond ſpent life</l>
                           <l>but to behold this object; which out-ſhines</l>
                           <l>their <hi>Helena,</hi> as much as doth the eye</l>
                           <l>of all the World dazle the leſſer fires.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Jove,</hi> Ile outbrave thee; melt thy ſelfe in Luſt,</l>
                           <l>embrace at once all ſtarre-made Concubines,</l>
                           <l>Ile not envie thee, know I have to ſpare</l>
                           <l>beauty enough, to make another <hi>Venus;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>And for fond Gods, that have no reward in ſtore</l>
                           <l>to make me happier, here Ile place my Heaven.</l>
                           <l>And for thy ſake, this ſhall my Motto be,</l>
                           <l>I conquered <hi>Greece,</hi> one <hi>Grecian</hi> conquered me.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
                           <l>But (gracious Lord) thoſe ſtreames (we ſee) ſoon ebb,</l>
                           <l>which with outragious ſwelling flow too faſt;</l>
                           <l>forbid <hi>(Lucina)</hi> this ſoone kindled fire,</l>
                           <l>ſhould ere burne out it ſelf. Tis a true Theame,</l>
                           <l>That nere laſts long, that ſeemeth moſt extreame.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Can this rich price of nature, precious jem,</l>
                           <l>give entertainment to ſuſpecting gueſts?</l>
                           <l>Come, come, theſe armes are curious chaines of love,</l>
                           <l>with which thou link'ſt my heart aeternally,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="127" facs="66"/>thy cheeks the royall Paper interlined,</l>
                           <l>with Natures Rhetorique, and loves perſwaſion</l>
                           <l>ſtands there attracting ſtill my gazing eye:</l>
                           <l>This then Ile read, and here I now will faine,</l>
                           <l>that thoſe all antique fables of the Gods</l>
                           <l>are writ in flowing numbers; firſt thy lip,</l>
                           <l>was faire <hi>Europaes,</hi> which they ſay, made <hi>Jove</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>turne a wild Heyfer: next, this ſparkling eye</l>
                           <l>was the <hi>Aemonian Io's:</hi> then, this hand</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Laedaes,</hi> faire Mother to thoſe Star-made Twins;</l>
                           <l>Thus, thus Ile Comment on this golden Booke:</l>
                           <l>Nature nor Art, have taught me how to faine;</l>
                           <l>Faireſt, 'twas you firſt brought me to this vaine:</l>
                           <l>In loving Combats, now I valiant prove,</l>
                           <l>let othets warre, great <hi>Amurath</hi> ſhall love.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scha.</speaker>
                           <l>Brave reſolution! O the fond thoughts of man!</l>
                           <l>awake <hi>Euno!</hi> Ile find ſtratagems:</l>
                           <l>There ſhall be Phyſick, to purge this diſeaſe:</l>
                           <l>light ſores are gently us'd; but ſuch a part</l>
                           <l>muſt be cut off, left it infect the heart.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amar.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Schahin,</hi> Our Tutor, we command this night</l>
                           <l>be ſolemniz'd with all delightfull ſports</l>
                           <l>thy learn'd invention beſt can thinke upon.</l>
                           <l>Prepare a Maske, which lively repreſents,</l>
                           <l>how once the Gods did love: that ſhall not teach</l>
                           <l>us by examples; but we'll ſmile to thinke,</l>
                           <l>how poore and weake their idle faining was</l>
                           <l>to our affection. <hi>Schahin,</hi> be free in wit,</l>
                           <l>and ſuddaine: now come my Kingdomes Bride:</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hymen</hi> would wed himſelfe to ſuch a Bride.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt all but Schahin.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Actus 1. Scena 2.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Nature, and all thoſe univerſall powers,</l>
                           <l>which ſhew'd ſuch admirable Godlike skill,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="130" facs="67"/>in framing this true modell of our ſelves,</l>
                           <l>this Man, this thing cal'd man, why doe you thus,</l>
                           <l>make him a ſpectacle of ſuch laughter for you,</l>
                           <l>when in each man we ſee a Monarchy?</l>
                           <l>For, as in ſtates, all fortunes ſtill attend:</l>
                           <l>So with a Kingdome, with a compleat ſtate</l>
                           <l>will govern'd, and well manag'd in him ſelfe:</l>
                           <l>both each man beares, when that beſt part of man,</l>
                           <l>(Reaſon) doth ſway and rule each Paſſion.</l>
                           <l>Affections are good Servants: but if Will</l>
                           <l>makes them once Maſter, they'l prove Tyrants ſtill.</l>
                           <l>No more King now, poore Subject AMURATH;</l>
                           <l>whom I have ſeen, breake through a Troope of Men,</l>
                           <l>like lightning from a Cloud: and done thoſe Acts,</l>
                           <l>which 'ene the Furies would have trembled at:</l>
                           <l>Treading downe Armies, as if by them he meant</l>
                           <l>of dead mens backes to build up ſtaires to Heaven:</l>
                           <l>And now ly'th lurking in a womans armes,</l>
                           <l>drencht in the <hi>Lethe</hi> of Ignoble luſt,</l>
                           <l>appoints me for the wanton Engineer</l>
                           <l>to keepe his ſo looſe thoughts in ſmoothing tune.</l>
                           <l>Woman, enticing woman, golden hooke</l>
                           <l>to catch our thoughts, and when we once are caught</l>
                           <l>to drag's into the publike view of ſhame;</l>
                           <l>And there we lye bath'd in inceſtuous pleaſure</l>
                           <l>for all good men to laugh and ſcorne at once.</l>
                           <l>Bane to my ſenſes! I could eyther wiſh</l>
                           <l>our birth were like thoſe Creatures, which we ſay</l>
                           <l>Are bred from putrid and corrupted matter;</l>
                           <l>Then that we ſhould acknowledge our deare being</l>
                           <l>with graſſe and flowers: for what elſe is our ſtate</l>
                           <l>up to the top? But then the waight ſhall fall</l>
                           <l>upon their head that caus'd it. Worke (my braine)</l>
                           <l>tuſh, bloud, no● water muſt waſh off this ſtaine.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <pb n="129" facs="67"/>
                        <head>Scena 3. Actus 1.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Amurath <hi>in ſtate with Nobles:</hi> Eumorphe <hi>with attendant Ladies: while</hi> Amurath <hi>aſcends his Throne, and placeth</hi> Eumorphe <hi>by him.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Shine here (my beauty) and expell the night</l>
                           <l>more than a thouſand ſtarres that grace the Heavens:</l>
                           <l>Me thinkes, I ſee the Gods inventing ſhapes</l>
                           <l>in which they meane to court thee. <hi>Jove</hi> he frownes,</l>
                           <l>and is more jealous, more ſuſpitious</l>
                           <l>of thee, then all the painted Truls, whoſe eyes</l>
                           <l>bedeck the all ennamel'd Firmament.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
                           <l>Beauty (my Lord) 'tis the worſt part of woman,</l>
                           <l>a weake poore thing, aſſaulted every hour</l>
                           <l>by creeping minutes of defacing time;</l>
                           <l>A ſuperficies which each breath of care</l>
                           <l>blaſts off: and every humerous ſtreame of griefe,</l>
                           <l>which flowes from forth theſe Fountaines of our eyes,</l>
                           <l>waſheth away, as raine doth Winters ſnow.</l>
                           <l>But thoſe bleſt guiders of all Nuptiall rites,</l>
                           <l>have wrought a better cement to make faſt,</l>
                           <l>the hearts of Lovers; the true name of Wife</l>
                           <l>guilds o're our thrones, with a more conſtant ſhape</l>
                           <l>than can be ſubject or to time, or care:</l>
                           <l>And in our ſelves; yea in our owne true breſts</l>
                           <l>we have obedience, duty, carefull Love;</l>
                           <l>And laſt and beſt of all, we may have Children,</l>
                           <l>Children are <hi>Hymens</hi> pledges, theſe ſhall be</l>
                           <l>perpetuall chaines, to linke my Lord and me.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Art thou a Woman? Goddeſſe, we adore,</l>
                           <l>and Idolize what we but loved before.</l>
                           <l>What Divels have men beene, whoſe furious braines</l>
                           <l>have oft abus'd that Deity cald Woman:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="130" facs="68"/>dipping their Ravens quil in <hi>Stygian</hi> Inke,</l>
                           <l>to blaſt ſuch heavenly paper as your faces!</l>
                           <l>Were all the enticing luſts, damn'd policies,</l>
                           <l>prodigious faſcinations, unſearcht thoughts,</l>
                           <l>diſſembled teares, broke vowes, loath'd appetites,</l>
                           <l>luxurious and unſatiate deſires;</l>
                           <l>Were all theſe of women equally weighed,</l>
                           <l>that vertue in thy breſt 'twill out-balance all,</l>
                           <l>and recompence the ruine of all thy Sexe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Enter a Servant and ſpeakes.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                           <l>So pleaſe your Majeſty, L. <hi>Schahin's</hi> ready</l>
                           <l>for entrance with his Maſque.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Tell him, we're wholly bent for expectation.</l>
                           <stage>Exit Serv.</stage>
                           <l>Sit, ſit (my Queene) Muſicke exceed your Spheares,</l>
                           <l>thinke I am <hi>Jove,</hi> and Godlike pleaſe our eares.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 4. Actus 1.</head>
                        <stage>A Maſque.</stage>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter from aloft two Torch-bearers, then</hi> Jupiter <hi>and</hi> Ju|no, <hi>and two Torch-bearers more, then</hi> Mars <hi>and</hi> Ve|nus, <hi>and two Torch-bearers more, then</hi> Apollo <hi>and</hi> Pallas▪ <hi>and two more Torch-bearers, then</hi> Neptune <hi>and</hi> Diana. <hi>Whilſt they are deſcending,</hi> Cupid <hi>hanging in the Ayre, ſings to ſoft Muſicke this Song following.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cupid</speaker>
                           <stage>ſings.</stage>
                           <l>Gaze you mortals, gaze you ſtill,</l>
                           <l>On the Gods now looke your fill.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Jove</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi> are deſcending,</l>
                           <l>Yet her Jealouſie's not ending,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Mars,</hi> ſterne <hi>Mars,</hi> he will not fight,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="131" facs="68"/>But with <hi>Venus</hi> when 'tis Night.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Daphne</hi> crownes Apollos head,</l>
                           <l>Whom ſhe would embrace in Bed;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Neptune</hi> ſwels his frothy cheeke,</l>
                           <l>Cauſe <hi>Diana</hi> is not meeke.</l>
                           <l>Gaze you mortals, &amp;c.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jup.</speaker>
                           <l>Come now my (Siſter and Wife) wee'l begin</l>
                           <l>to court afreſh! Nay, loure not (Heavens Queene)</l>
                           <l>here on this greene we'll a Lavalto dance;</l>
                           <l>What if our haires grow ſilver, yet our ſtrength</l>
                           <l>Is young, and vigorous. Say (fellow Gods)</l>
                           <l>(Since we are full of Nectar, and our cares</l>
                           <l>Lye drencht in our <hi>Nepenthe</hi>) take your Queenes, and be</l>
                           <l>All joviall; <hi>Mars</hi> for our Daughter <hi>Venus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Apollo</hi> joyne with <hi>Pallas,</hi> Brother of Flouds</l>
                           <l>embrace <hi>Diana;</hi> Gods ſometimes merry be;</l>
                           <l>but in the night, when mortals may not ſee.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Each God as appointed by Jove, takes his Goddeſſe, they dance a Maſque dance, and in the dance Juno obſerves Joves glances to</hi> Eumorphe, <hi>and at the end of the dance, ſpeaketh thus.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jup.</speaker>
                           <l>How now (wanton?) Can I no where goe,</l>
                           <l>for recreation, but you follow me?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jun.</speaker>
                           <l>Is this your recreation? Fye! My Lord,</l>
                           <l>will you be wanton ſtill! For here you came</l>
                           <stage>Points at Eumorphe.</stage>
                           <l>For ſome new Harlot, ſome new Queene for you.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jup.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Juno,</hi> Wife.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
                           <l>Your Siſter, (thunderer,) and not your Wife!</l>
                           <l>Baniſht from Heaven I am; and your Bed:</l>
                           <l>reſigne them both to Strumpets, Concubines.</l>
                           <stage>Points at Eumorphe.</stage>
                           <l>And now you come to ſee a freſh new laſſe,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="132" facs="69"/>in which Pole now, or in what part of heaven</l>
                           <l>ſhall ſhe be ſtellified?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jupit.</speaker>
                           <l>Shall ſtill ſiniſter thoughts wrong our intent?</l>
                           <l>wel <hi>(Juno)</hi> wel, you'le ever be a woman,</l>
                           <l>a very, very woman! But ſince ſhe ſcolds,</l>
                           <l>Let's hence (yee Gods) leſt her infectious breath</l>
                           <l>blaſt the ſucceeding day; and mortals curſe</l>
                           <l>her hel-bred jealouſie: Calumnious woman,</l>
                           <l>Come, ſcold in heaven; For if Gods liv'd on Earth,</l>
                           <l>ſuſpicious tongues would blame moſt innocent mirth.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Here all the Gods and Goddeſſes aſcend; at the top of the aſcent, Juno ſtops and ſpeakes.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jun.</speaker>
                           <l>Wel, <hi>Jove</hi> lookt pale, I toucht him to the quick;</l>
                           <l>'tis ſome new Minion he came downe to ſee:</l>
                           <l>Harke (jealouſie) know <hi>Juno</hi> is a woman!</l>
                           <l>Am I not mad yet? Miſtris Bride, adieu,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Jove</hi> ſhall not ſteale a kiſſe; My curſe is paſt,</l>
                           <l>when thou ſleep'ſt firſt a Bride, mayſt ſleepe thy laſt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                           <l>Faire Bride, I ſang thy <hi>Epithalamy,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>and left <hi>Elyſium</hi> for thy Nuptials:</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Juno</hi> here thundered 'againſt the Thunderer;</l>
                           <l>knowing how thy beauty dazles hers,</l>
                           <l>ſhe durſt not let heavens King once glance a looke,</l>
                           <l>but threatned with her helbred incantations,</l>
                           <l>to metamorphiſe thine unparall'ell'd</l>
                           <l>and moſt caeleſtial ſhape into worſe formes;</l>
                           <l>And more prodigious than ever poyſoned charmes</l>
                           <l>wrought on the fabled Concubines of <hi>Jove:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>but know great Queene, my Mother <hi>Venus</hi> vowes</l>
                           <l>her everlaſting guard to ſave ſuch beauty;</l>
                           <l>Leſt if thou periſh, Nature her ſelfe</l>
                           <l>loſe her onely parterne of ſerenity.</l>
                           <l>But I muſt haſt, Love, which the Gods protect,</l>
                           <l>can never be indangered by neglect.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Aſcend't.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="133" facs="69"/>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Schahin,</hi> thine Art is excellent but ſay,</l>
                           <l>doe Gods fall out for love amongſt themſelves?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, theſe are but fables: yet to make</l>
                           <l>the ſhew more pertinent, and to grace your Queene,</l>
                           <l>conceipt tooke leave to put the frowne on <hi>Iuno.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lords and friends, we ſhall be ever thankfull</l>
                           <l>and reſt a Debtor to your curteſie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Not ſo, faire Queen, but durſt I now entreat</l>
                           <l>the Kings detaining from the ſweets of Bed,</l>
                           <l>there yet remaines one thought upon conceipt,</l>
                           <l>which you would doubly grace me to behold.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Our worthy Tutor ſhall obtaine a night,</l>
                           <l>a night of us, in any caſe we can!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>But then let me informe your Majeſty,</l>
                           <l>that 'tis a warriors ſhew, which once you loved,</l>
                           <l>but now are free from.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>'tis beſt of all, with greedineſſe we'l ſee it,</l>
                           <l>O how the ſoule doth gratulate it ſelfe</l>
                           <l>when ſafely it beholds the dangerous ſtate</l>
                           <l>of others, and it ſelfe ſecurity free!</l>
                           <l>Glad are we ſtill to ſtand upon the ſhore,</l>
                           <l>and ſee afarre off others toſt i'th' Sea:</l>
                           <l>or in a Gallery at a Fencers ſtage,</l>
                           <l>we laugh when mutually each one takes wounds;</l>
                           <l>Sit ſtill <hi>(Eumorphe:) Schahin,</hi> thy ſhew in haſt;</l>
                           <l>'Tis beſt delight, to thinke on troubles paſt.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 5. Actus 1.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter in Maſque the Ghoſt of</hi> Hector <hi>and</hi> Achilles, <hi>to them</hi> Alexander <hi>the great ſtands gazing on t em, whilſt</hi> Fame <hi>ſpeakes from aloft.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
                           <l>Stay you moſt worthy ſhades▪ brave <hi>Hector,</hi> ſtay;</l>
                           <l>And proud <hi>Achilles,</hi> know your maſſie Tombes,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="134" facs="70"/>which have ſo long orewhelm'd your valiant bones,</l>
                           <l>yawnes wide to let the impriſoned coarſes forth.</l>
                           <l>I muſt afreſh imbalme your ſacred Trunkes,</l>
                           <l>and ſweet your memory with moſt happy oyle</l>
                           <l>of juſt report; the Gods awakt me Fame</l>
                           <l>from out the oblivious Sepulcher of ſleepe,</l>
                           <l>to drop that Inke into old <hi>Homers</hi> pen,</l>
                           <l>wherewith he curiouſly hath lin'd your names,</l>
                           <l>enfolding them in Everlaſting Cedar,</l>
                           <l>and make them live to all poſterity.</l>
                           <l>Vertue to valour hath his guift aſſign'd,</l>
                           <l>great men may dye, yet deeds ſtill reſt in mind.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt umbrae Hectoris &amp; Achilis, Manet</hi> Alex|ander <hi>looking after them, reading in</hi> Homer.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alexand.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <seg xml:lang="unk">〈◊〉 〈◊〉〈◊〉</seg>
                           </l>
                           <l>moſt fortunate young man, whoſe worth is crown'd</l>
                           <l>with everlaſting Trophies of renowne,</l>
                           <l>how hath he ſet thee on the wings of fame</l>
                           <l>which ſoare i'th middle region of high glory,</l>
                           <l>propos'd to all, a never dying ſtory!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter to</hi> Alexander, <hi>Philoxenus a Captaine.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                           <l>May it pleaſe thee (Sonne of <hi>Jupiter</hi>) to accept</l>
                           <l>a Preſent, which our fight enricht us with?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                           <l>Is it a Band of ſtubborn Souldiers, Captaine?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Philox.</speaker>
                           <l>O no (my Liege) of exquiſite form'd Ladies,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Darius</hi> his wife, the wonder of her Sexe;</l>
                           <l>Beſides a Troope of ſuch ſhap't <hi>Ganimedes,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>that <hi>Love</hi> not equals.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Philoxenus,</hi> We thanke thee. Yet harke,</l>
                           <l>there is a ſecret we would know of thee,</l>
                           <l>and you muſt tell Us: on your faith you muſt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                           <l>My Leige —</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, no Court oyle (by your leave) no flattery,</l>
                           <l>we are but man, this very trunke of ours,</l>
                           <l>Is but a Veſſell fild with humane blood,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="135" facs="70"/>and we truſt not that Paraſite like pen,</l>
                           <l>
                              <seg xml:lang="unk">〈◊〉 〈◊〉〈◊〉</seg>.</l>
                           <l>All the deſtroying vices of fraile man,</l>
                           <l>I may be ſubject to; but what baſe looſeneſſe,</l>
                           <l>or ſupple Luxury, didſt thou ere obſerve</l>
                           <l>ſo to benumne our ſenſe, that thou ſhouldſt thinke</l>
                           <l>we could be pleas'd with ſuch effeminate Preſents?</l>
                           <l>Know ſir, our eyes ſhall have that abſtinence</l>
                           <l>that will not looke on them, on boyes, or women.</l>
                           <l>Hence then, and preſent ſome coward with them.</l>
                           <stage>Exit Philoxenus</stage>
                           <l>Give me a ſpectacle would pleaſe the Gods,</l>
                           <l>and make them bend their Ivorie browes to the Earth;</l>
                           <l>a man, a Souldier, ſtrong with his wounds;</l>
                           <l>'mongſt fate and ruine, upright and unſhap't,</l>
                           <l>his minde being all his guard, his wall, and armour▪</l>
                           <l>and if he fall, ſtill noble wrath remaines</l>
                           <l>in his amaſed Trunke: not all the darts</l>
                           <l>ſtucke in his ſides, making him all one wound,</l>
                           <l>affright his courage; but wrath lending weapons,</l>
                           <l>himſelfe doth ſeeme a new and horrid Warre.</l>
                           <l>Nor are thoſe Milke-ſops which beguile the time,</l>
                           <l>with ſtealing minutes from their Ladies lips,</l>
                           <l>ſuch as the Gods doe love; for as the Winde</l>
                           <l>loſeth it's force, if it be not oppos'd</l>
                           <l>with woods of ſtrong and ſtubborne planted trees;</l>
                           <l>So Virtue, if it walke in troden paths.</l>
                           <l>That breakes up honours gap, and makes the way</l>
                           <l>through pathes of death: that flame burnes ſtrong</l>
                           <l>which is reſiſted: valor ſhines in wrong:</l>
                           <l>Of <hi>Alexanders</hi> Souldiers be this ſaid,</l>
                           <l>warre was as peace, when he the army led.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
                           <l>Brave <hi>Macedon,</hi> how truly haſt thou weighed</l>
                           <l>the reaſon of mans birth! who is equall borne,</l>
                           <l>for all the world, as well as for himſelfe.</l>
                           <l>the world's a field too narrow for thy worth,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="136" facs="71"/>and allthough Nature hath her enacted bounds</l>
                           <l>for Sea and earth, nay for the heavens themſelves,</l>
                           <l>nor Sea nor earth ſhall coope thy valour up:</l>
                           <l>Valour of Nature ever this attaines,</l>
                           <l>that it breakes forth, farre, and beyond her chaines,</l>
                           <l>and this Ile trumpet out; The whole worlds Ball,</l>
                           <l>in which thou art ſo great, to thee is ſmall.</l>
                           <l>When men want worlds to ſhew their vertue in,</l>
                           <l>that is the crime o'th Gods, and not their ſinne:</l>
                           <l>'Tis a decree of a true Souldiers mind,</l>
                           <l>to thinke nought done, when ought is leſt behind.</l>
                           <l>On (valiant youth) for, know I will appoint</l>
                           <l>a <hi>Grecian</hi> Prince, who ſo ſhall ſteepe his quill</l>
                           <l>to paint thy name in Wels of eloquence,</l>
                           <l>that this thy ſcorne of Luſt ſhall be propos'd</l>
                           <l>for Kings example to poſterity.</l>
                           <l>Know mortals, that the men the Gods moſt love,</l>
                           <l>in hard and dangerous Arts they alwayes prove</l>
                           <l>When men live brave at firſt, then fall to crimes,</l>
                           <l>their bad is Chronicle to future times:</l>
                           <l>For, who begins good Arts, and not proceeds</l>
                           <l>he but goeth backward in all noble deeds.</l>
                           <l>Death conſecrates thoſe men whoſe awfull end,</l>
                           <l>though moſt men feare, yet all men muſt commend.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>aſcends.</stage>
                        <stage>Amurath <hi>ſeemes troubled, yet collecting himſelfe, diſſembles his Paſſion, ſpeakes.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Scahin,</hi> the <hi>Macedon's</hi> heholding to thee,</l>
                           <l>and hiſtory ſhall pay you thankes for this,</l>
                           <l>which we reſt Debtors for.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>Great Prince, ſuch kindneſſe of acceptance payes</l>
                           <l>For things which are but for a Kings delight:</l>
                           <l>in ſeeing them, he amply doth requite.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Eumorphe,</hi> Love, Queene, Wife, le'ts haſt to Bed,</l>
                           <l>and may we wiſh this night eternall time.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="137" facs="71"/>
                              <hi>Scahin,</hi> good night: good night, kind gentelmen.</l>
                           <l>Thus when we are dead ſhall we revive o'th' ſtage:</l>
                           <l>one houre can preſent a kings whole age.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 2.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Schahin, <hi>Eurenoſes.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Obſerv'd you not the Kings looks? Grew they not pale?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>O yes (Lord <hi>Schahin</hi>) you muſt be his Parent,</l>
                           <l>and ſnatch him out o'th' Gulph he's falling in.</l>
                           <l>That fayned ſpeech of <hi>Alexanders</hi> wrought</l>
                           <l>like to moſt purging Phyſicke; nights then blacke,</l>
                           <l>when 'tis compar'd with day: Boldneſſe is cleare,</l>
                           <l>when 'tis preſented before baſtard feare.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Ile tell thee, <hi>Eurenoſes,</hi> thou art a Souldier,</l>
                           <l>and I am both a Souldier, and a Scholar;</l>
                           <l>And for theſe two Profeſſions am both moſt glorious,</l>
                           <l>and moſt meritorious; <hi>Pallas</hi> is for both:</l>
                           <l>O what <hi>Tyſiphon,</hi> what ſnaked ſcourge</l>
                           <l>can make a Scholar, that ſhould never ſleepe,</l>
                           <l>but 'twixt the Pillowes of <hi>Pernaeſſus</hi> Hils,</l>
                           <l>and dip his lips in ſprings of <hi>Helicon,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>make him by ſnoaring on a wanton breſt,</l>
                           <l>and ſuck the adulterate and ſpiced breath</l>
                           <l>of a lewd famed woman?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>And for a Souldier <hi>(Schahin,)</hi> let me ſpeake:</l>
                           <l>We that doe know, the uſe of ſwords and fire,</l>
                           <l>we that doe know, halters can throatle us,</l>
                           <l>ſhall we ere venture on a Womans cruelty?</l>
                           <l>We that endure no Lords, ſhall we endure</l>
                           <l>a woman to overcome us? Moſt true <hi>Demophoon,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>I reverence thy memory: no pewling phraſe</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="138" facs="72"/>could ſo enchaine thee to thy <hi>Thracian</hi> Dame,</l>
                           <l>but thou wouldſt rather periſh than ſhe ſave thee.</l>
                           <l>Ile not declaime long on that common theame,</l>
                           <l>but they have luſt lye in their fingers ends,</l>
                           <l>and whilſt their ſweet-hearts breath ſtickes in their ſheets,</l>
                           <l>they will admit another <hi>Lucrece</hi> in the day,</l>
                           <l>to be a <hi>Thais,</hi> if the night will not gain-ſay.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>Why <hi>(Eurenoſes)</hi> why ſhould we endure</l>
                           <l>a new Queen now? this Kingdom wants not heires:</l>
                           <l>we know (ſhould we have more) 'twere dangerous.</l>
                           <l>But harke! The Queens for Bed-inticing ſleepe</l>
                           <stage>ſoft Muſicke.</stage>
                           <l>with charmes of Muſicke: wel, even ſuch a Night</l>
                           <l>may yet prove diſmall ere the following Light!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eurenoſ.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Scahin,</hi> let's in:</l>
                           <l>the firſt degree to purge ſuch ils as theſe,</l>
                           <l>is to inſtruct the patient his diſeaſe:</l>
                           <l>that you have done.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>Yea, and wil yet once more</l>
                           <l>adventure a new ſtratagem. Juſt when the King</l>
                           <l>h'as rid his Chamber, and with covetous haſt</l>
                           <l>thinks for to clip <hi>Eliſium,</hi> and drinke deepe</l>
                           <l>of his long wiſh'd delight, I having skil</l>
                           <l>and uncontroul'd acceſſe, will in diſguiſe</l>
                           <l>ſeem his deceaſed Fathers apparition:</l>
                           <l>and by all tyes of children to their Parents,</l>
                           <l>bid him forſake that vile bewitching woman.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>An eaſie Medicine doth and ſure wil work,</l>
                           <l>to rub ſhrewd wounds, make them but feſter more,</l>
                           <l>Foule Med'cines we worſe brook, than a foule ſore.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 2. Actus 2.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Eumorphe <hi>as to Bed in her Night-robes, attended with Tapers and Ladies.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Menth.</speaker>
                           <l>Madam make haſt, The King will be impatient</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="139" facs="72"/>if he be from you long. O Happineſſe!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Emorph.</speaker>
                           <l>Why <hi>Menthe!</hi> then thou deem'ſt us happy</l>
                           <l>thus to command a world of ſervices,</l>
                           <l>to have a King my ſubject; and attended</l>
                           <l>with theſe harmonious ſounds t'affect our eares?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Menthe.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes (truely Madam) 'tis a happineſſe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eumorph.</speaker>
                           <l>'Tis, were 't Eternal: but I feare a power,</l>
                           <l>a womans power, doth but make ſport with us.</l>
                           <l>Why, were we not once <hi>(Menthe)</hi> a Captive Wretch?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Menthe</speaker>
                           <l>Yes Lady! now your happineſſe's the more:</l>
                           <l>Riches pleaſe beſt, when there went want before.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
                           <l>That power which rais'd us from ſo baſe, ſo high,</l>
                           <l>can throw us downe againe as ſuddenly:</l>
                           <l>Me thinks my life is but a Players Scaene</l>
                           <l>in the laſt Act: my part was then to play</l>
                           <l>a captive creature, and a Queene to day.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Menthe.</speaker>
                           <l>Your Morals (Madam) are too ſerious;</l>
                           <l>Me thinks theſe Ornaments ſhould elevate</l>
                           <l>your dumpiſh ſpirits. Thinke this Bed a place,</l>
                           <l>in which no Icie ſlipping chance hath power;</l>
                           <l>A Kings ſafe Bed is like a guarded Tower.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
                           <l>No <hi>(Menthe)</hi> no, 'tis not the Bed of ſtate,</l>
                           <l>nor the free ſmile of a well pleaſed King:</l>
                           <l>'tis not the embracing Armes of Emperors,</l>
                           <l>nor all the Gemmes that ſo inwreath the browes</l>
                           <l>can ſo allure Fortune unto their gaze,</l>
                           <l>as ſhe ſhould ſtill be conſtant; O ſhe's blind,</l>
                           <l>nor doth ſhe know her ſelfe where ſhe is kind;</l>
                           <l>Thoſe, thoſe are Kings, and Queenes, whoſe breſt's ſecure,</l>
                           <l>like brazen walles, Luſt's entrance not endure;</l>
                           <l>Where impotent ambition not intrudes,</l>
                           <l>nor the unſtable talke of multitudes;</l>
                           <l>Fortune ſerves ſuch, they happineſs command</l>
                           <l>more than all <hi>Lybia's</hi> gold, all <hi>Tagus</hi> ſand;</l>
                           <l>as heaven hath given us no more conſpicuous things,</l>
                           <l>than forme or beaury: ſo like a forward ſpring,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="140" facs="73"/>Nothing more ſhort.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Menthe.</speaker>
                           <l>Madam, divine not of a change; Beliefe</l>
                           <l>is too too prone, in entertaining griefe!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
                           <l>Our Lord attends, to enter in,</l>
                           <l>and ſurely ſleepe envyeth his delight,</l>
                           <l>for he ſits heavy on my drowſie lids,</l>
                           <l>draw all our Curtaines; ſleepe be guiles our eares.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Men.</speaker>
                           <l>Madam, good night, time helpes ſuſpicious fears!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit Menthe.</stage>
                        <stage>This Song is to be ſung in the Muſick roome to ſoft Muſicke, now when ſhe lookes, ſhe's dreaming ſent to Eliſium.</stage>
                        <quote>
                           <l>Drop golden ſhowers, gentle ſleepe,</l>
                           <l>And all the Angels of the Night,</l>
                           <l>Which doe us in protection keepe,</l>
                           <l>Make this Queene dreame of delight</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Morpheus</hi> be kind a little, and be</l>
                           <l>Deaths now true Image, for 't will prove</l>
                           <l>To this poore Queene, that then thou art hee;</l>
                           <l>Her grave is made i'th Bed of love.</l>
                           <l>Thus with ſweet ſweets can Heaven mix gall,</l>
                           <l>And marriage turne to Funerall.</l>
                        </quote>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <head>Scaena 3. Actus. 2.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Amurath <hi>in his Night robes, a Taper in his hand, ſeemes much diſturbed, speakes.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Turke, <hi>Amurath,</hi> ſlave, nay ſomething baſer,</l>
                           <l>King! For all airy titles which the Gods</l>
                           <l>have blaſted man withall, to make them ſwell</l>
                           <l>with puft up honour, and ambitious wind,</l>
                           <l>this name of King holds greateſt antipathy</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="141" facs="73"/>with manly government: for if we waigh,</l>
                           <l>'Tis ſubjects, and not Kings beare all the ſway.</l>
                           <l>Each whiſpered murmur from their idle breath</l>
                           <l>condemnes a King to infamy, to death;</l>
                           <l>Were there a Metempſeucoſis of ſoules,</l>
                           <l>and nature ſhould a free Election grant</l>
                           <l>what things they afterwards would reinforme,</l>
                           <l>the vaine and haughtieſt minds the Sun ere ſaw,</l>
                           <l>Would chuſe it's Cottage in ſome Shepherds fleſh,</l>
                           <l>nay, be confin'd within ſome Dog or Cat,</l>
                           <l>than (Antique-like) pranck in a Kings gay-clothes▪</l>
                           <l>Were I no King, and had no Majeſty,</l>
                           <l>I had more then all Kings, bleſt liberty;</l>
                           <l>And without rumor might enjoy my choyce,</l>
                           <l>not fearing Cenſure of each popular voyce.</l>
                           <l>Poore men may love, and none their wils correct:</l>
                           <l>but all turne Satyres of a Kings affect.</l>
                           <l>O my baſe greatneſſe! What diſaſterous ſtarre</l>
                           <l>profeſt it ſelfe a Midwife at my birth,</l>
                           <l>to ſhape me into ſuch prodigious States?</l>
                           <l>But hence regard of tongues! Were we a Saint,</l>
                           <l>ſome envious tongue would dare our names to taint:</l>
                           <l>and he from ſlander is at ſecureſt reſt,</l>
                           <l>not that hath none, but that regards it leaſt.</l>
                           <l>Open you envious Curtaines; here's a ſight,</l>
                           <stage>Drawes the Curtain.</stage>
                           <l>that might commend the act of Love ſo Chaſt.</l>
                           <l>Were now the chariot-guider of the Sunne</l>
                           <l>weary o's taske, and would intreat a day</l>
                           <l>of Heaven to reſt in, here's a radiant Looke,</l>
                           <l>that might be fixt ith' midſt oth' Axletree;</l>
                           <l>and in deſpight of darke conſpiring Clouds,</l>
                           <l>ſhe would out-ſhine Sunne, Moone and all the Stars.</l>
                           <l>O, I could court thee now (my ſweet) a freſh,</l>
                           <l>mixing a kiſſe with every period;</l>
                           <l>Telling the Lillies how they are but wanne,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="142" facs="74"/>earth in the vernant ſpring is dull, and darke,</l>
                           <l>compar'd with this aſpect! the Aeaſterne ayre,</l>
                           <l>fann'd with the wings of <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Jove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>infectious, but compar'd with this perfume.</l>
                           <l>Hence then th' ambition of that furious * youth, <hi>Alexis</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>who knew not what a crime his raſhneſſe was!</l>
                           <l>I might orecome more Kingdomes, have more dominion,</l>
                           <l>enthrone my ſelfe an Emperor oth' world;</l>
                           <l>I might, I might; <hi>Amurath</hi> thou mightſt.</l>
                           <l>The Chriſtians now will ſcoffe at <hi>Mahomet;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Perchance they ſent this wretch thus to inchant me!</l>
                           <l>O my perplexed thoughts! Tuſh, Ile to bed,</l>
                           <l>ſhould the commanding Thunder of the Gods</l>
                           <l>prohibite me, or ſtrike me in the act.</l>
                           <l>Talke on (vaine rumor) fame I dare thy worſt!</l>
                           <l>Call me a Luſty, Lazy, wanton, coward!</l>
                           <l>ſhould I win all the world, my breath once fled,</l>
                           <l>my bad would ſtill ſurvive all good be dead.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Eumorphe,</hi> ſweet, I come! you ſacred powers</l>
                           <l>who have beſtowed ſome happensſſe on man,</l>
                           <l>to helpe to paſſe away this ſinful life,</l>
                           <l>Grant me a youthfull vigor yet a while,</l>
                           <l>full veines, free ſtrength, compleat and manly ſenſe,</l>
                           <l>to know, and take a beauty moſt immenſe!</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 4. Actus 2.</head>
                        <stage>Amurath <hi>makes haſte to the Bed, on a ſuddaine enter</hi> Schahin <hi>diſguiſed like the Ghoſt of</hi> Orchanes, <hi>father to</hi> Amurath.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scabin.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Amurath, Amurath.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
                           <l>Divel, Divel; what?</l>
                           <l>Dar'ſt thou appeare before an <hi>Angell</hi> (Fiend?)</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>O <hi>Amurath,</hi> why doth intemperate Luſt,</l>
                           <l>raging within thy furious youthfull veines,</l>
                           <l>burſt through thy fathers Tombe? Diſturbe his ſoule?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="143" facs="74"/>Know, all the torments that the fabulous age</l>
                           <l>dream't, did afflict deceaſed impious Ghoſts,</l>
                           <l>heartbiting-hunger, and ſoule-ſearching thirſt,</l>
                           <l>the ne're conſumed, yet ever eaten prey</l>
                           <l>that the devouring Vulture feeds upon,</l>
                           <l>are not ſuch tortures as our off-ſprings crimes:</l>
                           <l>They, they ſit heavy on us, and no date</l>
                           <l>Makes our compaſſionate affection ceaſe.</l>
                           <l>O thou hereditary Ulcer, hearke,</l>
                           <l>by the name of Father, and by all thoſe cares</l>
                           <l>which brought me to my grave, to make thee great:</l>
                           <l>Thou that haſt nothing of me but my crowne:</l>
                           <l>My enterprize ſurpaſt the boundleſſe Sea,</l>
                           <l>cutting the churliſh Waves of <hi>Helleſpont,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>when the flood ſtood which wind for to obey!</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Euxinum</hi> groan'd beneath my burdenous ſhips:</l>
                           <l>I was the firſt of all the Turkiſh Kings</l>
                           <l>that <hi>Europe</hi> knew, and the fond Chriſtians plague.</l>
                           <l>What coward blood ran flowing in my veines,</l>
                           <l>when thou wert firſt begot, who marreſt all</l>
                           <l>thy Fathers acts by thy untam'd deſires?</l>
                           <l>Wherefore with Stygian curſes I will lade thee:</l>
                           <l>Firſt, may ſhe prove a Strumpet to thy Bed,</l>
                           <l>be her lips poyſon, and let her looſe embraces▪</l>
                           <l>be venemous as Scorpions: If ſhe conceive</l>
                           <l>a Generation from thee, let it be;</l>
                           <l>as ominous as thou haſt beene to me;</l>
                           <l>Rebellious to thy Praecepts, printing cares</l>
                           <l>upon thy aged browes. O may they prove,</l>
                           <l>as Faries for to laſh thee in thy reſt!</l>
                           <l>But <hi>Amurath,</hi> if thou canſt quench this flame,</l>
                           <l>if thou wilt cut this Gordian thred, and rend hence</l>
                           <l>that putrid Wenne which cleaves unto they fleſh,</l>
                           <l>be all thine actions proſperous. <hi>Mahomet</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>ſhall be auſpitious unto each deſigne;</l>
                           <l>Fortune to ſhew thee favour ſhall be proud,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="144" facs="75"/>Farewel. If what men doe ſpeake laſt before</l>
                           <l>they die take root, then dead mens ſhould take more.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit Schahin.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>What, art thou vaniſht? Know (thou carefull ſpright)</l>
                           <l>thou ſhalt no ſooner pierce the wandring clouds</l>
                           <l>with unperceived flight, than my reſolve</l>
                           <l>ſhall expiate my former Vanity.</l>
                           <l>Looke on thy ſonne, thou airy intellect,</l>
                           <l>and ſee him ſacrifice to thy command!</l>
                           <l>Now <hi>Titan</hi> turne thy breathing courſers backe,</l>
                           <l>ſtart hence bright day, a ſable Cloud invade</l>
                           <l>this univerſall Globe, breake every prop</l>
                           <l>and every hindge that doth ſuſtaine the Heavens:</l>
                           <l>For ſtraight muſt die a woman, I have nam'd</l>
                           <l>a crime, that may accuſe all Nature guilty.</l>
                           <l>The Sexe wiſely conſidered, deſerves a death;</l>
                           <l>For thinke this, <hi>Amurath,</hi> this woman may</l>
                           <l>proſtrate her delicate and Ivory limbes</l>
                           <l>to ſome baſe Page, or Scul, or ſhrunk up Dwarf,</l>
                           <l>Or let ſome Groome lye feeding on her lips,</l>
                           <l>ſhe may deviſe ſome miſhapen trick</l>
                           <l>to ſatiate her goatiſh <hi>Amurath;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>and from her bended knees at Meditation,</l>
                           <l>be taken by ſome ſlave toth' deepe of Hell!</l>
                           <l>Th'art a brave Creature, wert thou not a woman.</l>
                           <l>Tutor! Come! thou ſhalt ſee my well-kept vow,</l>
                           <l>and know my hate, which ſaw me dote but now:</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Schahin! Eurenoſes!</hi> Captaines, ho!</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <head>Scaenae. 5. Actus. 2.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Schahin, Eurenoſes, Chaſe-Illibegge.</stage>
                        <l>Our Tutor, <hi>Eurenoſes,</hi> Captaines, welcome.</l>
                        <l>Gallants, I call you to a ſpectacle:</l>
                        <l>My breſt's too narrow to hoard up my joy▪</l>
                        <l>Nay, gaze here Gentlemen! give Nature thanks,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="145" facs="75"/>for framing ſuch an excellent ſence as Sight,</l>
                        <l>whereby ſuch obiects are injoyn'd as this▪</l>
                        <l>Which of you now impriſon not your thoughts</l>
                        <l>in envious and ſilent policy.</l>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord to whatſoever you ſhall propoſe,</l>
                           <l>my ſentence ſhall be free.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Euren</hi> And mine.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chaſe-il.</speaker>
                           <l>And mine.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Which of you then dare challinge to himſelfe</l>
                           <l>ſuch a pathetical Praerogative,</l>
                           <l>ſo ſtoically ſevered from affection?</l>
                           <l>That, had he ſuch a Creature as lieth here,</l>
                           <l>one, at whom Nature her ſelf ſtood amazed,</l>
                           <l>one, whom thoſe lofty extaſies of poets,</l>
                           <l>ſhould they decay, here't muſt nor barely dump</l>
                           <l>their dull inventions with ſimilitudes,</l>
                           <l>taken from Sun, Moon, Violets, Roſes;</l>
                           <l>and, when their ruptures at a period ſtand,</l>
                           <l>a ſilent admiration muſt ſupply.</l>
                           <l>Onely name her, and ſhe is all diſcrib'd.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hyperbole</hi> of women, Coulour it ſelfe</l>
                           <l>is not more pure, and incontaminate!</l>
                           <l>ſleep doates on her and graſpes her eye-lids cloſe?</l>
                           <l>the skie it ſelfe hath onely ſo much blew</l>
                           <l>as the azure in her veines lends by refluxe.</l>
                           <l>Here's breath that would thoſe vapors purifie,</l>
                           <l>which from <hi>Avernus</hi> choakes the flying Birds:</l>
                           <l>here's heat would tempt the numb'd <hi>Athenian,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>though all his blood with age were conjeal'd yee!</l>
                           <l>Now, which of you all is ſo temperate,</l>
                           <l>that did he find this Jewel in his bed</l>
                           <l>(unleſſe an Eunuch) could refraine to grapple,</l>
                           <l>and dally with her? come! ſpeak freely all.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Sch.</speaker>
                           <l>Truly (my Lord) I came of mortal parents</l>
                           <l>and muſt confeſſe me ſubject to deſires;</l>
                           <l>freely injoy your Love!</l>
                           <l>that were ſhe mine, I ſurely would do no leſſe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="146" facs="76"/>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>What ſayth <hi>Eurenoſes?</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, I ſay,</l>
                           <l>that they may raile at light, that nere ſaw day;</l>
                           <l>but had I ſuch a Creature by my ſide,</l>
                           <l>were the world twice enlarged, and all that world</l>
                           <l>orecome by me, all volumes writ,</l>
                           <l>made clean and fild up by Rhetorique ſtraines</l>
                           <l>of my great deeds, Hiſtorians ſhould ſpend</l>
                           <l>their Inke and Paper in my ſole Chronicle;</l>
                           <l>A thouſand ſuch alluring idle charmes</l>
                           <l>could not conjure me from betwixt her armes.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Your ſentence <hi>Ch●ſ</hi>-Illebeg?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chaſ.</speaker>
                           <l>What need your grace depend upon our breath?</l>
                           <l>I vow (my Lord,) if all thoſe ſcrupulous things</l>
                           <l>which burden us with precepts ſo preciſe,</l>
                           <l>thoſe parents, which when they are married once</l>
                           <l>and paſt their ſtrength of years, think their ſons ſtraight</l>
                           <l>ſhould be as old in every thing as they;</l>
                           <l>I ſay my Lord, did my head weare a crowne,</l>
                           <l>that Queen ſhould be the chiefeſt jem t'adorne it,</l>
                           <l>ſpite of all hate. That's an unhappy ſtate,</l>
                           <l>when Kings muſt feare to love leaſt ſubjects hate.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>Wel ſpoke, three Milkſops, <hi>Schahin.</hi> your ſword,</l>
                           <stage>Scahin gives him a Sword.</stage>
                           <l>Now, now be valour in this manly arme</l>
                           <l>to cut off troupes of thoughts that would invade me!</l>
                           <l>Think you my minde is waxie to be wrought</l>
                           <l>int'any faſhion? <hi>Orchanes,</hi> thy ſtrength!</l>
                           <l>Here do I wiſh, as did that Emperour,</l>
                           <l>that all the heads of that inticing Sexe</l>
                           <l>were upon hers, thus then ſhould one full ſtroake</l>
                           <l>mow them all off.</l>
                           <stage>Amurath <hi>cuts off</hi> Eumorphes <hi>head, ſhewes it to the nobles.</hi>
                           </stage>
                           <l>there kiſſe now (Captaines) do, and clap her cheekes:</l>
                           <l>this is the face that did ſo captive me:</l>
                           <l>theſe were the lookes that ſo bewicht mine eyes:</l>
                           <l>here be the lips, that I but for to touch,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="147" facs="76"/>gave over fortune, victory, fame and all;</l>
                           <l>theſe were two lying mirrors where I lookt</l>
                           <l>and thought I ſaw a world of happineſſe.</l>
                           <l>Now tutor, ſhall our ſwords be excerciſed</l>
                           <l>in ripping up the breſts of Chriſtians?</l>
                           <l>Say Generals, Whither i'ſt firſt?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>A.</speaker>
                           <l>For <hi>Thracia.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
                           <l>On then for <hi>Thracia,</hi> for he ſurely ſhall,</l>
                           <l>that conquers firſt himſelfe, ſoon conquer all.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 3.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Cobelitz <hi>ſolus.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cobelitz.</speaker>
                           <l>Thou ſacred guider of the arched Heavens,</l>
                           <l>who canſt collect the ſcattering ſtarres, and fixe</l>
                           <l>the Erratique planets in the conſtant pole!</l>
                           <l>O why ſhouldſt thou take ſuch ſolicitous care</l>
                           <l>to keep the ayre, and Elements in courſe?</l>
                           <l>That Winter ſhould uncloth our Mother Earth,</l>
                           <l>and wrap her in a winding ſheet of ſnow;</l>
                           <l>that then the ſpring duly revives her ſtill,</l>
                           <l>unbinds her ſinews, fils her cling'd up veynes</l>
                           <l>with living dew, and makes her young again.</l>
                           <l>Next that, the <hi>Nemean</hi> terror breathes her flames,</l>
                           <l>to parch her flaxie haires with furious heat;</l>
                           <l>which to allay too, thou op'ſt the Chataracts,</l>
                           <l>and water'ſt the worlds gardens with bleſt drops;</l>
                           <l>canſt thou, which canſt ſuſtain the ponderous world,</l>
                           <l>and keep it in true poize, ſecurely ſleepe,</l>
                           <l>letting a Tyrant (which with a fillip, thus;</l>
                           <l>thou mighteſt ſink to earth) to baffle thee?</l>
                           <l>A warrior in thy fields, I long have been</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="148" facs="77"/>To ſee if in thy ſacred providence,</l>
                           <l>Thou meanſt to arm me with thy thunder-bolt,</l>
                           <l>Yet, yet, it ſtrikes not; now he Giant-wiſe,</l>
                           <l>Dares thee again; pardon our earneſt zeal</l>
                           <l>What ere's decreed for man, by thy beheſt,</l>
                           <l>He muſt perform, and in obedience reſt.</l>
                           <l>Thou, like Spectators when they do behold</l>
                           <l>an hardy youth encountring with a Bear,</l>
                           <l>or ſomthing terrible▪ then they give a ſhout;</l>
                           <l>ſo doſt thou even applaud they ſelf to ſee</l>
                           <l>Religion ſtriving with Calamity.</l>
                           <l>Which while it often bears, and ſtill reſts true,</l>
                           <l>it's fence 'gainſt all that after ſhall enſue.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Turk,</hi> ile oppoſe thee ſtill; Heaven has decreed,</l>
                           <l>That this weak hand, ſhall make that tyrant bleed▪</l>
                           <l>a man religious, firm, and ſtrongly good</l>
                           <l>cannot oth● ſuddain be, nor underſtood.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Actus 3. Scena 2.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Amurath <hi>in Arms,</hi> Schahin, <hi>Captains, Souldiers.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
                           <l>Riſe (Soul!) injoy the prize of thy brave worth:</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Schahin,</hi> the Preſent that thou ſo profeſt,</l>
                           <l>ſhould from the City of <hi>Oreſtias,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>make proud our eyes! then tell me, Haſt thou ſlain</l>
                           <l>a thouſand ſuperſtitious Chriſtian ſouls?</l>
                           <l>made them ſtoop to us: O, I would bath my hands</l>
                           <l>in their warm blood to make them ſupple <hi>(Schahin)</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>that they may weild more Spears: our hands are dull,</l>
                           <l>our furie's patient! Now will I be a <hi>Turk.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>and to our Prophet's Altars do I vow,</l>
                           <l>that to his yoke I will all necks ſubdue,</l>
                           <l>or in their throats my bloody Sword imbrew.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <pb n="149" facs="77"/>Schahin <hi>calls in his Souldiers, and each of them pre|ſents to</hi> Amurath <hi>the head of a dead Chriſtian.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scha.</speaker>
                           <l>Then King, to adde freſh oyl unto thy hate,</l>
                           <l>and make it raiſe it ſelf a greater flame,</l>
                           <l>ſee here theſe Chriſtians heads; thus ſtill ſhall fall</l>
                           <l>before thy fatal hand, theſe impious ſlaves:</l>
                           <l>ſo long as numbers 's wanting to the ſand,</l>
                           <l>ſo long as day ſhall come with Sun, and night</l>
                           <l>be ſpangled with the twilight dawning ſtars,</l>
                           <l>whilſt floods ſhall fall into the Ocean,</l>
                           <l>ſhall Chriſtians tremble at <hi>Turks</hi> thundring ſtroaks.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amurat.</speaker>
                           <l>So am I <hi>Amurath,</hi> the great King of <hi>Turks,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>O how it glads me thus to paſh their brains,</l>
                           <l>to rend their locks, to tear theſe Infidels!</l>
                           <l>Who thundered when theſe heads were ſmitten off?</l>
                           <l>Stars I could reach you with my lofty hand,</l>
                           <l>'tis well, enough, enough, (great <hi>Amurath</hi>)</l>
                           <l>for now I ſit in <hi>Orchanes</hi> great Throne,</l>
                           <l>and ſacrifice due Rites to <hi>Mahomet;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>yet why enough? Ile on, and dung the Earth,</l>
                           <l>with Chriſtians rotted trunks, that from that ſoyl,</l>
                           <l>may ſpring more <hi>Cadmean</hi> Monſters to orecome them.</l>
                           <l>Captains, what Countries next ſhall we make flow,</l>
                           <l>with Channels of their blood?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>To <hi>Servia</hi> (my Lord) there are troups of arms,</l>
                           <l>gathered to reſiſt <hi>Mahometan.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Chaſe.</speaker>
                           <l>At <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> there they ſet on fire,</l>
                           <l>the Countries as they paſs, 'twere good we haſte.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>VVhy they do well! we like of their deſire</l>
                           <l>to make the flame in which themſelves muſt fry!</l>
                           <l>Ruine, deſtruction, famine, and the ſword,</l>
                           <l>ſhall all invade them: Sun ſtay thou thy flight,</l>
                           <l>and ſee the ſneaks in their own River drencht,</l>
                           <l>whilſt with their blood our furious thirſt is quencht!</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <pb n="150" facs="78"/>
                        <head>Scena. 3. Actus 3.</head>
                        <stage>Enter in armes, Lazarus Deſpot of Servia, Seſmenos Governor of Bulgaria.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>La.</speaker>
                           <l>Whither <hi>(Bulgaria)</hi> whither muſt we flye?</l>
                           <l>the Butcherous Turk's at hand. Bleſt Sanctity!</l>
                           <l>if thou didſt ere guard goodneſſe, wall our towers,</l>
                           <l>bring ſtrength into our Nerves. For in thy cauſe</l>
                           <l>our Breſts upon their Rapiers we will run;</l>
                           <l>we'll with juſt hope confront the tyrants rage,</l>
                           <l>meet him i'the face, fury will find us armes,</l>
                           <l>there is a power can guard us from all harmes.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Seſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Let us be ſuddain: for we'l not find ſcope,</l>
                           <l>to ſee our haps. Who moſt doth fear, may hope.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Enter to them Cobelitz.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Governor, Captains, haſt unto your arms:</l>
                           <l>the dangers imminent, and the Turk's at hand.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>-<hi>(Cobelitz)</hi> muſt we ſtill wade thus deep</l>
                           <l>in blood and terror?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes <hi>(Servia)</hi> we muſt, we ſhould, we ought,</l>
                           <l>Eaſe and lucreſſe keeps baſeneſs company.</l>
                           <l>Shall we not bluſh to ſee the regiſter</l>
                           <l>of thoſe great Romans, and Heroick Greeks,</l>
                           <l>which did thoſe acts, at which our hearts are ſtruck</l>
                           <l>beneath all credence, only to win fame?</l>
                           <l>and ſhall not we for that Eternal name?</l>
                           <l>To live without all credence, even to win fame,</l>
                           <l>is not to know life's chief, and better parts:</l>
                           <l>To us of future hopes: calamity</l>
                           <l>muſt help to purchaſe immortality.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Seſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Well ſpoke (trueChriſtian) they who ſtil live high,</l>
                           <l>and ſnoare in prais'd applauſe nere know to bear,</l>
                           <l>a contumely, or check, or fate.</l>
                           <l>Wiſely to ſteare a Ship, or guide an Army,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="151" facs="78"/>undaunted hardineſſe is requiſite;</l>
                           <l>O then lets to our weapons! make him yeild;</l>
                           <l>they which deny all right, oft give't ith'Field.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Enter Chriſtian Souldiers falling out among them-fighting confuſedly.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Why (Gentlemen) we want no foes to fight,</l>
                           <l>nor need we turn our weapons on our ſelves.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>One Souldier ſpeaks as drunk.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1.</speaker>
                           <l>You lazy rogue, what come in my Cabinet?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>anſwer the other.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>2.</speaker>
                           <l>Conſpiring ſlave, you murmur'd gan'ſt th'allowance,</l>
                           <l>and wouldſt perſwade upon a larger pay,</l>
                           <l>to betray all Garriſons, and turn Turk.</l>
                           <l>Thou half Can-carouſing raſcal, Ile teare thee,</l>
                           <l>and thoſe treacherous veines of thine. Will you ſee,</l>
                           <stage>They all fall by the eares.</stage>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Blew-Jackets,</hi> will you ſee your Corporal wrong'd?</l>
                           <l>well, ſince I fight for victuals, for company.</l>
                           <l>Uſe now your ſwords and Bucklers.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>La.</speaker>
                           <l>Treaſon, the next man that ſpeaks or ſtrikes a blow.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                           <l>Then ſhall our Laundreſſes fight for us?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>2.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, Amazons! Baudicans, come help to ſcratch.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Enter ſome Truls on both ſides, they fight and ſcratch.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Seſm.</speaker>
                           <l>O <hi>Cobelitz,</hi> what way ſhall we appeaſe them?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Truls ſcold confuſedly: Thus</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1. <hi>Trul.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>Out, thy Corporal (huſwife) hath the itch,</l>
                           <l>you now will have foul waſhing. Drab, Ile tear your mouth:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>2.</speaker>
                           <l>An inch or two yet wider.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>What, ſouldiers! think you each diſtaſteful word,</l>
                           <l>given 'mongſt your ſelves ſo ſtrong an obloquie,</l>
                           <l>that revenge ſpurs you to each others death?</l>
                           <stage>The General parts them with his ſword.</stage>
                           <l>And will not ſeek to waſh thoſe blaſphemies,</l>
                           <l>in Seas of their foul blood, which are belcht out</l>
                           <l>by our approaching foes, againſt the Eſſence</l>
                           <l>of the Eternal!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="152" facs="79"/>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Leave, leave, theſe factions; ceaſe theſe mutinies</hi>
                           </l>
                           <stage>A Drum from the Turk's Camp.</stage>
                           <l>Hark, their Drums take advantage of theſe ſtirs:</l>
                           <l>let us oppoſe our ſtrength againſt our foe;</l>
                           <l>and in our Camp let not one Souldier be,</l>
                           <l>who will not finde, and ſtrike his Enemie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Now (bleſt guider and great ſtrength of arms)</l>
                           <l>if in thy ſecret and hidden decree,</l>
                           <l>thou haſt not yet appointed the full time</l>
                           <l>wherein thou meaneſt to tame this Tyger,</l>
                           <l>who dare murmur againſt thine hidden will?</l>
                           <l>Be we ſlain now, there's victory in ſtore,</l>
                           <l>which when thou pleaſeſt thou 't give, and not before.</l>
                           <l>Give us ſtill ſtrength of patience, not to wiſh,</l>
                           <l>a funeral honour unto all the world,</l>
                           <l>when we are periſhing, we'l ſtill believe,</l>
                           <l>thoſe dangers worth our death we undergo,</l>
                           <l>whilſt he, who's ours, is alike thy foe.</l>
                           <l>Should Fortune loſe this day, when we are ſlain,</l>
                           <l>thou canſt give hands, and ſtrength, and men again;</l>
                           <l>on thee we truſt then, and on thee bear,</l>
                           <l>ſcorning for Heaven's ſake to ſhed a tear.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <head>Actus 3. Scena 4.</head>
                        <stage>A March within, excurſions, alarums. Enter as Conquerors, Cairadin Baſſa, Schahin, leading young men Chriſtians, Priſoners.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Baſſa,</hi> we thank thy valour and diſcretion,</l>
                           <l>in finding fit occaſion to invade</l>
                           <l>the mutinous Chriſtians! theſe Captives here</l>
                           <l>ſhall be good Preſents to our worthy Maſter.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Baſſa.</speaker>
                           <l>General, now truſt me theſe young ſlaves,</l>
                           <l>be full of Valor, they have metal in them.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schuh.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes: and to his Highneſs ſhall perform</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="153" facs="79"/>a Service which I long have thought upon,</l>
                           <l>and when his <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Majeſty requires;</l>
                           <l>they'l fit to be a near attendant Guard,</l>
                           <l>on all occaſions to the Emperour;</l>
                           <l>therefore they ſhall be called <hi>Janizaries,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>by me firſt inſtituted, for our Princes ſafeties ſake.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Baſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Their vigor &amp; ſtrong hearts becomes ſuch ſervice,</l>
                           <l>for to orecome them made our Souldiers ſweat</l>
                           <l>much <hi>Turkiſh</hi> blood: the <hi>Servians</hi> kept the Fight</l>
                           <l>with ſtubborn hard reſiſtance, The <hi>Bulgarians</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>left the right wing; there ſet I forward firſt,</l>
                           <l>and like a torrent roll'd deſtruction on,</l>
                           <l>raiſing huge ſtorms of blood, as doth the Whale</l>
                           <l>puffe up the waves againſt a mighty Ship;</l>
                           <l>me thinks, I ſee the Rivers of their gore:</l>
                           <l>their Leaders trampled on by <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe,</l>
                           <l>the Body of their Army quite diſperſt,</l>
                           <l>themſelves all floating in Vermillian pools,</l>
                           <l>with their own weapons haſting to their death,</l>
                           <l>and ſuch a ſlaughter did we make of them,</l>
                           <l>as Nature ſcarce can ere repair again.</l>
                           <l>One haſtning t'others death, pulling to ground</l>
                           <l>him that held up, ſo they each other drown'd.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Still are they confident upon a power,</l>
                           <l>they know not what, who (as they think) can ſnatch</l>
                           <l>their preciſe ſouls from out the jaws of death.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Baſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, ſuch a ſuperſtition doth poſſeſs them;</l>
                           <l>for when they lookt for nothing but their fate,</l>
                           <l>and danger ſtood in ſweat upon their brows:</l>
                           <l>they yet ſcorn'd <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and prophan'd his Rites,</l>
                           <l>and nought but horror made them to believe</l>
                           <l>ſo many men were fighting on his ſide,</l>
                           <l>as might have chang'd my ſeat, and part ith' world,</l>
                           <l>(though Nature ſtood againſt) to a new place:</l>
                           <l>or carry <hi>Seſtos</hi> whereby <hi>Abydos</hi> ſtands,</l>
                           <l>or pull down <hi>Atlas</hi> with ſo many hands.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <pb n="154" facs="80"/>
                        <head>Actus 3. Scena 5.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Amurath <hi>with Embaſſadors from German</hi> Ogly, <hi>concerning</hi> Bajazet, Amurath's <hi>Eldeſt ſon, and the Mahometans Daughter.</hi> Cairadin Baſſa <hi>pre|ſents</hi> Amurath <hi>with his Captives for Ianizaries. &amp;c.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
                           <l>How like our Captaines the laſt Victory?</l>
                           <l>(if any can propheſie of future things)</l>
                           <l>me thought I did dream of this bleſſed hap.</l>
                           <l>How fortune did involve them in their ruin!</l>
                           <l>and flight from danger, brought them in their ruine.</l>
                           <l>each one aſtonied with a ſuddaine feare,</l>
                           <l>knew not the danger that was then moſt neare.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Baſſa &amp; Schahin preſents Amurath with Captives for Ianizaries</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Baſſa.</speaker>
                           <l>To adde more tryumph, I preſent my Liege,</l>
                           <l>with theſe young Rebels, which you may bring up</l>
                           <l>in all the praecepts of our Mahomet.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>And, (for great Emperor, your perſon wants</l>
                           <l>a thing which much ore-Clouds your light of ſtate,</l>
                           <l>attendant <hi>Ianizaries</hi> to a Prince:)</l>
                           <l>theſe may be ſo trained up, as to ſupply</l>
                           <l>the duty fit for ſuch a Majeſty.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Baſſa,</hi> we thank thy ſtrength, <hi>Schahin</hi> your counſaile</l>
                           <l>and to that end, let them have ſafe protection.</l>
                           <l>But we muſt treat now of a marriage (Lords)</l>
                           <l>the German <hi>Ogly,</hi> he whoſe Scepter ſwaies</l>
                           <l>the <hi>Phrygian</hi> confines in ſtrong <hi>Aſia,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>by Embaſſie intreats that he may joyne</l>
                           <l>his Daughter <hi>Hatum</hi> to our <hi>Bajazet.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Embaſſador, here to our Counſell ſpeak</l>
                           <l>your Maſters Meſſage.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="155" facs="80"/>
                           <speaker>Emb.</speaker>
                           <l>Pleaſe then your Maj. and theſe reverend heads</l>
                           <l>to be inform'd my maſters will by me?</l>
                           <l>In wedlock if your prince may be combin'd</l>
                           <l>to the faire princeſſe his ſole daughter,</l>
                           <l>he freely gives the <hi>Phrygian</hi> territories,</l>
                           <l>and <hi>Bythinia</hi> to you for your dowry;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cutas, Simon, Egregios, Sanſale,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Abbettingon,</hi> the <hi>Ottomans</hi> eſtate;</l>
                           <l>which <hi>Ottomans,</hi> becauſe he not endures,</l>
                           <l>the Noble <hi>Zelzucciom</hi> family proteſts,</l>
                           <l>to joyn with you in quelling their ambition</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Sca.</speaker>
                           <l>May't pleaſe your majeſty to like mine advice,</l>
                           <l>it's good to have alliance with ſuch friends;</l>
                           <l>Kings that combine themſelvs are like to ſhafts,</l>
                           <l>the ancient Sage propos'd unto his ſonnes;</l>
                           <l>which whilſt together they were cloſe compact,</l>
                           <l>armes, knees, and his whole ſtrength, could never break;</l>
                           <l>take one by one, they with a touch were crack'd:</l>
                           <l>ſo Kings may be orecome that ſtand alone;</l>
                           <l>but two ſuch princes, knit thus hand in hand,</l>
                           <l>ſhould Nations totter they would firmely ſtand.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes <hi>Schahin,</hi> we'll approve what thou ſaieſt,</l>
                           <l>then from us carry the great Aſiaes Monarch</l>
                           <l>this our kindeſt greeting:</l>
                           <l>tell him, the gates of <hi>Pruſa</hi> ſhall ſtand ope,</l>
                           <l>and the glad ayre ſhall Eccho notes of joy▪</l>
                           <l>to entertaine her who ſhall bleſſe our Land</l>
                           <l>with hopefull iſſue; greedy thoughts expect</l>
                           <l>her ſoon arrivall; and ſo (Embaſſador)</l>
                           <l>enforme thy princeſſe, when ſhe ſhall appear,</l>
                           <l>A laſting Starr ſhall ſhine within our ſpheare.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="scene">
                        <pb n="156" facs="81"/>
                        <head>Scen 6. Actus 3.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Saſmenos, Lazarus, Cobelitz.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Saſ.</speaker>
                           <l>O <hi>Servia,</hi> our Cities are turn'd flames;</l>
                           <l>each ſtrives to haſt his own and others death:</l>
                           <l>And as though heaven conſpir'd deſtruction too,</l>
                           <l>that rains down ſcalding Sulphure on our heads,</l>
                           <l>here one that lyes thick gaſping for his breath</l>
                           <l>is choakt with blood that runs from's fellows wounds;</l>
                           <l>whilſt others for the dead are making graves,</l>
                           <l>themſelves are made the corps that do fill them.</l>
                           <l>Nobles, and baſe, together periſh all,</l>
                           <l>and a drawn ſword ſticks faſt in every rib;</l>
                           <l>our ſtones are dy'd Vermillion with our blood:</l>
                           <l>old creatures that are creeping to the grave,</l>
                           <l>are thruſt on faſter.</l>
                           <l>Infants, but in the threſhold of their lives,</l>
                           <l>are thus kickt off: Oh moſt diſaſtrous times,</l>
                           <l>to love our deaths, and make our life our crimes!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>See, ſee, the ruins of our goodly Walls,</l>
                           <l>our Cities ſmoak hinder the ſight of heaven:</l>
                           <l>The conqueror yet amaz'd meaſures out our Towns,</l>
                           <l>with eyes of terror, and doth ſcarce believe</l>
                           <l>he hath overcome us, yet among theſe fires,</l>
                           <l>our dead men are denyed their funeral flames:</l>
                           <l>And thoſe infectious carkaſſes do perform,</l>
                           <l>a ſecond murder on the reſt that live;</l>
                           <l>and all the hope of ſafety that we have,</l>
                           <l>is now to fix our flattering lips at's feet:</l>
                           <l>mercy (perhaps) may wearied ſlaughter meet.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Saſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Will you do ſo? ſpeak, for I am determin'd—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <lg>
                              <l>No (worthy General) heaven avert</l>
                              <l>and arm you with the proof of better thoughts!</l>
                              <l>What though a Tyrant ſtrives to terrifie</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb n="157" facs="81"/>all Chriſtendome, and would not be beloved;</l>
                              <l>let not your feares give impious rage ſuch ſcope,</l>
                              <l>as for to bring Religion to prophaneneſſe:</l>
                              <l>fortune and heaven will ſcorn to try a man,</l>
                              <l>that hurles his weapons hence and runs away:</l>
                              <l>How is he worthy of heavens victory,</l>
                              <l>that, when it frownes, dares not look up and ſee?</l>
                              <l>Me thinks we three are now inviron'd round,</l>
                              <l>with hoſts of Angels, and our powerful <hi>Mars</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>is putting bows of ſteel into our hands:</l>
                              <l>he doth ſuggeſt our wrath, and bids us on.</l>
                              <l>O what an army 'tis to have a cauſe</l>
                              <l>holy and juſt; there, there's our ſtrength indeed!</l>
                           </lg>
                           <quote>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>—Tu mente Labantes,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Direge nos, dubios, et certo Robore firma.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                           </quote>
                           <lg>
                              <l>If we muſt dye, the narrow way to bliſſe</l>
                              <l>ſhall be made wide for us: the gate's wide ope,</l>
                              <l>and the ſpread Palace entertaines with joy.</l>
                              <l>Mean time, let's look like men upon our grief,</l>
                              <l>our frown fate Deſpot, <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> come.</l>
                              <l>Turk, once more at thee (Tyrant) mortals muſt</l>
                              <l>command heavens favour in a caſe ſo juſt. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 4.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aladin King of Caramania, ſon in Law to A|murath, with Nobles, Embaſſadors from Amurath.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>Sends our proud father-in-law this greeting to us?</l>
                           <l>was our ſword ſheath'd ſo ſoon to heare this anſwer?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Emb.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, he bad me tell you that 'twas you</l>
                           <l>have made him leave off this great Prophets wars,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="158" facs="82"/>when he was hewing down the Chriſtians;</l>
                           <l>therefore ſubmiſſion ſhould not now appeaſe him,</l>
                           <l>no, though your wife, his daughter, ſhould her ſelf,</l>
                           <l>upon her penitent knees be ſupplyant.</l>
                           <l>No ſooner ſhall the <hi>Tycian</hi> ſplendid Sol</l>
                           <l>open heavens Caſements, and inlarge the day,</l>
                           <l>but his horſe hoofs ſhall beat your treacherous earth;</l>
                           <l>and that you may be warn'd of his approach,</l>
                           <l>murder and flames ſhall be his Prodromo's!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>Confederate Princes, and my kind allyes,</l>
                           <l>ſhall his proud noſtrils breath thoſe threats on us?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Emb.</speaker>
                           <l>Moreover, my Lord will, or win, or raze,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Iconium</hi> and <hi>Larenda.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Iconium</hi> and <hi>Larenda?</hi> I? No more?</l>
                           <l>had beſt look firſt, how ſafe his <hi>Pruſa</hi> ſtands.</l>
                           <l>Lords, I am mov'd, and will forget my Queen</l>
                           <l>was ere the iſſue of his hated blood:</l>
                           <l>My ſplene is toſt within, mine entrailes pant,</l>
                           <l>as, when the Sea is rais'd with Southern guſts,</l>
                           <l>the wind allay'd, yet ſtill the waves will tremble,</l>
                           <l>Princes, now binde your ſelves with ſuch ſtrong chaines,</l>
                           <l>your faith and breaths can make; ſwear to me all,</l>
                           <l>to be as firm to me 'gainſt <hi>Amurath,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>as is the skin and fleſh unto the Nerves; <stage>They all kneel, and ſwear upon his ſword.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Nobles.</speaker>
                           <l>We all ſweare we will.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>Then all here kiſſe my ſword,</l>
                           <l>which ſhall be ſteept within the head-mans throat:</l>
                           <l>We'l make him know thoſe will not flie in war,</l>
                           <l>which may in policie intreat a peace!</l>
                           <l>Haſt thy courſe (time) and ſoon reduce the year!</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Lucan: — Infeſtique obvia Signis</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Signa, pares aquilas, &amp; pila minantia pilis.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Enſignes may Enſignes meet, <hi>Carmania's</hi> King,</l>
                           <l>great <hi>Aladin,</hi> ſcorns to avoyd a <hi>Turk.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Princes, and Neighbours, muſter up your ſtrength,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="159" facs="82"/>that we may meet him on his full Cariere;</l>
                           <l>and let it be <hi>Carmanian's</hi> pride to ſay,</l>
                           <l>to o'recome him we ask no ſecond day.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 2. Actus 4.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Amurath <hi>at one door with Nobles,</hi> Bajazet; <hi>En|ter at th'other,</hi> Hatum, <hi>richly attended, they meet, ſa|lute in dumb ſhews;</hi> Amurath <hi>joynes the hands of the Prince and Princeſſe; whilſt this is ſolemnizing, is ſung to ſoft Muſick, this Song following.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="song">
                                 <head>SONG.</head>
                                 <lg>
                                    <l>Thine O <hi>Hymen,</hi> thine is ſhe,</l>
                                    <l>Whoſe Beauties verſe <hi>Calliope,</hi>
                                    </l>
                                    <l>Sing to Marriage ties an <hi>Io;</hi>
                                    </l>
                                    <l>
                                       <hi>Io</hi> to <hi>Hymen.</hi>
                                    </l>
                                 </lg>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>To thee <hi>Apollo</hi> is my ſute,</l>
                                       <l>Lend me a while thy ſilver Lute,</l>
                                       <l>O what a woe it is to bring,</l>
                                       <l>A Bride to Bed and never ſing,</l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Io</hi> to <hi>Hymen.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                    </lg>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>When ſhe's old, ſtill ſeemes ſhe yong,</l>
                                       <l>When ſhe's weake, to her be ſtrong!</l>
                                       <l>Be <hi>Cyprus,</hi> both, and <hi>Paphos</hi> here,</l>
                                       <l>Love, ſing with merry cheere,</l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Io</hi> to <hi>Hymen.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                    </lg>
                                 </sp>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>You Gods of Marriage, ſacred Protectoreſs</l>
                           <l>of lawful propagations, and bleſt Love,</l>
                           <l>be moſt propitious to theſe grafted ſtemmes;</l>
                           <l>drop dewing ſhowers of generation on them.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="160" facs="83"/>Think (Son) this day ſo prodigal of bleſſing,</l>
                           <l>as, that had <hi>Juno</hi> taskt thee (like <hi>Alcides</hi>)</l>
                           <l>to grapple with <hi>Stymphallides,</hi> or cleanſe</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Augean</hi> ſtables: or like the Trojan Boy,</l>
                           <l>ſit like a Shepheard on <hi>Dardanias</hi> hills,</l>
                           <l>ſuch a reward as this fair Queen repayes.</l>
                           <l>O thou hop'd future off-ſpring, ſpare thy Parent!</l>
                           <l>Hurt not this tender womb, theſe Ivory worlds,</l>
                           <l>in which a pritty people yet ſhall live</l>
                           <l>when you are born; O be within your limbs</l>
                           <l>the Granſire, <hi>Amurath,</hi> and fathers ſtrength;</l>
                           <l>line their faces (Nature) with their mothers dye:</l>
                           <l>And let the deſtinies make the enſuing night</l>
                           <l>in their Eternal Books, with notes moſt white.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>All.</speaker>
                           <l>Grant it great <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                           <l>Moſt awful father, and my honored Prince,</l>
                           <l>although it be enacted by the heavens,</l>
                           <l>that in theſe bonds of marriage, ſuch curſe</l>
                           <l>attends on Princes above private men,</l>
                           <l>that no affection, nor home-nouriſht Love</l>
                           <l>but ſtate and policy muſt elect their wives,</l>
                           <l>which muſt be fetcht from Countries far remot;</l>
                           <l>yet the protecting Powers have ſuch a care,</l>
                           <l>both of their off-ſprings and their Kingdoms ſtate.</l>
                           <l>That to what they ordain, they work in us</l>
                           <l>a ſuddain willingneſſe to make's obey;</l>
                           <l>for in this breſt, I do already feel</l>
                           <l>that there's a kindling a Diviner heat,</l>
                           <l>which diſobedience never ſhall extinguiſh.</l>
                           <l>And if there be any felicity</l>
                           <l>from theſe united Loves to be derived</l>
                           <l>from the weak ſex unto the husbands ſoul,</l>
                           <l>then may my Lord make his affection ſure,</l>
                           <l>to be repaid with an untainted Love.</l>
                           <l>With ſoft and yeilding courteſie in all</l>
                           <l>he ſhall command, my willing arms ſhall ſtill</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="161" facs="83"/>be ope t'enfold within a wives embrace,</l>
                           <l>if any comfort elſe there be in ſtore,</l>
                           <l>(which modeſty keeps ſilent to it ſelf</l>
                           <l>cauſe only husbands and the night muſt know't)</l>
                           <l>my Loyalty ſhall ever all perform:</l>
                           <l>and though my Lord ſhould frown, Ile be the ſame,</l>
                           <l>green wood will burn with a continued flame:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Baja.</speaker>
                           <l>Princeſſe, our ardour is already fired,</l>
                           <l>yet with no violent temerity;</l>
                           <l>ſuch as might feare it's ſhort and ſoon decaying:</l>
                           <l>thy vertue ſeems ſo to exceed thy Sex,</l>
                           <l>and wiſdome ſo far to out-pace thy yeares,</l>
                           <l>that, ſurely (Princeſs) ſoon maturity,</l>
                           <l>argues in them hidden Divinity.</l>
                           <l>Expected <hi>Hymen</hi> here hath bound our hands</l>
                           <l>and hearts, with everlaſting ligaments:</l>
                           <l>Fortunate both we are, and have one bliſſe,</l>
                           <l>the want of which for ever doth infect</l>
                           <l>with anxious cares the ſweets of marriage beds:</l>
                           <l>our parents benediction and conſent,</l>
                           <l>they are the trueſt <hi>Hymens,</hi> and ſhould be</l>
                           <l>to children the beſt marriage Deity.</l>
                           <l>Thus then attended with ſuch ſacred charmes</l>
                           <l>our laſt day of content ſhall never come;</l>
                           <l>till we muſt part by th'unreſiſted doome,</l>
                           <l>with a pleas'd error we will age beguile,</l>
                           <l>all ſtars on us, an equal yoke, muſt ſmile,</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>Now (Lords) who'le dance</l>
                           <l>a Turkiſh meaſure? Ladies our nerves are ſhrunk;</l>
                           <l>and you now fix the ſign of age on me,</l>
                           <l>you, who have blood ſtill flowing in your veines,</l>
                           <l>be nimble as an Hart: Caper t' the Sphaeres:</l>
                           <l>O you are light, that want the weight of years! <stage>Muſick</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Here Amurath aſcends his Throne, the reſt ſet down to dance,</hi> Bajazet <hi>with</hi> Hatum, &amp;c. <hi>the end of the dance, all kneel,</hi> Amur. <hi>begins an health, a flouriſh with Cornets.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="162" facs="84"/>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>And health to our Bride and her father:</l>
                           <l>O (Nobles) would this wine were Chriſtians blood,</l>
                           <l>but that it would Phrenetique humours breed,</l>
                           <l>and ſo infect our braines with Superſtition!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Enter Eurenoſes with ſix Chriſtian Maidens, richly attyred, their Haire hanging looſe, in their hands Cups of Gold with Jewels, &amp;c.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eure.</speaker>
                           <l>Auſpicious fortunes to great <hi>Amurath:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>to ope more ſprings to this full-tide of joy,</l>
                           <l>know (potent Emperor) I from Europe bring</l>
                           <l>ſix daughters of ſix ſeveral Kings,</l>
                           <l>whoſe Cities we have equall'd to the ground;</l>
                           <l>and of their Palaces did torches make,</l>
                           <l>to light their ſouls through the black cave of death.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Deſcribe (good Captain) how the dogs were wea|ried.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eure.</speaker>
                           <l>So weary were they to indure our ſwords,</l>
                           <l>that by impetuous mutiny themſelves</l>
                           <l>turn'd on each other, ſlew their Maſters;</l>
                           <l>Childrens own hands tore out their fathers throats,</l>
                           <l>and each one ſtrove who ſhould be ſlaughtered firſt;</l>
                           <l>Here did a brother paſh out a brothers braines,</l>
                           <l>ſome in ſtinking Quagmires, and deep Lakes</l>
                           <l>(which they had made t'avoide their excrements)</l>
                           <l>ran quick, and in the lake lay buryed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Good Executioner of our moſt juſt wrath!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Eur.</speaker>
                           <l>Nor did it leave till death it ſelf was wearie,</l>
                           <l>murder grew faint, and each ſucceeding day</l>
                           <l>ſhew'd us the ſlaughter of the day before.</l>
                           <l>'Mongſt carcaſſes and funerals we ſtood,</l>
                           <l>denying thoſe that liv'd ſuch Ceremonies</l>
                           <l>as in their Temples to the Indian gods,</l>
                           <l>with prayers and vowes they daily offred:</l>
                           <l>Nor deſtiny, nor cruelty ere left,</l>
                           <l>till they had nothing for to work upon;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="163" facs="84"/>for, of ſo many ſouls that breath'd of late,</l>
                           <l>theſe ſix are all remain: which as a Pledge</l>
                           <l>of my beſt ſervice to your Majeſty,</l>
                           <l>I here am bold to yeild an offer.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>Nor ſhall this preſent be unrecompenced;</l>
                           <l>for thy true ſervice, on thee Ile beſtow</l>
                           <l>all the rich gifts, which all theſe <hi>Aſian</hi> Lords</l>
                           <l>brought to adorn theſe happy Nuptials;</l>
                           <l>on you faire Bride, great Princeſſe, and our Daughter</l>
                           <l>do we beſtow theſe Virgins (daughters to Kings)</l>
                           <l>for your attendance.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                           <l>We are two much bound unto our Princely Fa|ther</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>No (Daughter) no, we hope thou art the ſpring</l>
                           <l>from whence ſhall flow to all the world a King.</l>
                           <l>Captaines and Lords, to morrow we muſt meet,</l>
                           <l>to think of our rebellious ſon in Law.</l>
                           <l>Be this time all for comfort and delight,</l>
                           <l>ſhort wedding dayes make it ſeem long to night. <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 3. Actus 4.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Lazartis and Cobelitz, bringing the dead body of Saſmenos.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>Here ſet we down our miſerable load,</l>
                           <l>O <hi>Cobelitz,</hi> with whom is't that we fight?</l>
                           <l>VVith <hi>Lybian</hi> Lyons? Or <hi>Hyrcanian</hi> Beares,</l>
                           <l>which grinde us daily in their ravenous teeth?</l>
                           <l>The Tyrant (as it were deſtructions Engineer)</l>
                           <l>helps Nature to deſtroy the worlds frame quickly.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Alas, my Lord, that needs not, every day</l>
                           <l>is a ſufficient helper to decay:</l>
                           <l>Great workman, who art ſparing in thy ſtrength</l>
                           <l>to bring things to perfection: and to oreturn</l>
                           <l>all thy beſt works, thou uſeſt ſuddaine force.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="164" facs="85"/>when mans an Embrio and firſt conceived,</l>
                           <l>how long 'tis ere he ſees his native light?</l>
                           <l>Then born, with expectation for his growth,</l>
                           <l>tenderly nouriſht, carefully brought up:</l>
                           <l>grown to perfection, what a little thing</l>
                           <l>ſerves to call on his ſuddain ruining?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>Come <hi>Cobelitz,</hi> 'mongſt thoſe demoliſht ſtones</l>
                           <l>we'll ſit as <hi>Hecuba,</hi> at thoſe <hi>Trojan</hi> walls:</l>
                           <l>our teares ſhall be falſe glaſſes to our eyes,</l>
                           <l>through theſe we'l look, and think we yet may ſee</l>
                           <l>our ſtately Pinacles, and ſtrong founded holds:</l>
                           <l>that which one hour can delapidate,</l>
                           <l>one age can ſcarce repaire.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                           <l>No ſir, for nothing's hard</l>
                           <l>to Nature, when ſhe meanes for to conſume:</l>
                           <l>A thouſand Oakes (which time hath fixt i'th earth,</l>
                           <l>as Monuments of laſting memory)</l>
                           <l>are in a moment turn'd to aſhes; all</l>
                           <l>things that riſe ſlowly, take a ſuddain fall.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>What courſe now, <hi>Cobelitz?</hi> muſt we ſtil be yoakt</l>
                           <l>to miſery, and murder? We ſcarce have room</l>
                           <l>upon our bodyes to receive more wounds,</l>
                           <l>and muſt we ſtill oppoſe our ſelves to more?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes! We are ready ſtill; a ſolid mind</l>
                           <l>muſt not be ſhak't with every blaſt of wind.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Pollux,</hi> nor <hi>Hercules,</hi> had none other art,</l>
                           <l>to get them Manſions in the Spangl'd heavens</l>
                           <l>then a true firm reſolve; th' <hi>Adriatike</hi> Sea,</l>
                           <l>ſhall from his currents with tempeſtuous blaſts</l>
                           <l>be ſooner mov'd, than vertue from its aime.</l>
                           <l>Let us but think (when we ſo many ſee</l>
                           <l>enjoying greater quiet than our themſelves)</l>
                           <l>how many have endur'd more miſery;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Ilion, Ilion,</hi> what a fate hadſt thou?</l>
                           <l>How fruitful wert thou in matter for thy foe?</l>
                           <l>Thus we'll delude our grief, make our ſelf glad,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="165" facs="85"/>to think of miſeries that others had.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>Ay, (Captain) ay; they that furniſh thee</l>
                           <l>with ſentences of comfort, never ſaw,</l>
                           <l>their Cities burnt, their Countries deſolate.</l>
                           <l>'Tis eaſie for Phyſicians for to tell</l>
                           <l>advice to others, when themſelves are well.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Tuſh, tuſh (my Lord) there's on our ſide we know,</l>
                           <l>one that both can, and will our weake hands guide,</l>
                           <l>one that will ſtrike and thunder; Gyant then,</l>
                           <l>look for a dart! we muſt not appoint when;</l>
                           <l>mean while help to convey this burden hence.</l>
                           <l>Turk, though thy tyranny deny us graves,</l>
                           <l>corruption will give them ſpite of thee:</l>
                           <l>Nor do our corps, ſuch Tombs and Cavernes need:</l>
                           <l>for our own fleſh, ſtill our own graves do breed:</l>
                           <l>And, whom the earth receives not when they die,</l>
                           <l>heavens vault overwhelms them, ſo their tomb's ith'skie. <stage>Exeunt with a dead Trunk.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <head>Actus 4. Scena 4.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aladin as flying, an arrow through his arm, wounded in his forehead, his ſhield ſtuck with darts: With him two Nobles.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>Beſieged on every ſide? <hi>Iconium</hi> taken?</l>
                           <l>Entrencht within my foes my ſelf muſt lie</l>
                           <l>wrapt in my Cities ruine. Turks come on.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1. <hi>Nob.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>Nay but my Lord, mean you to meet your death?</l>
                           <l>let's haſt our flight, and truſt more to our feet</l>
                           <l>then words, or hands—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>Why ſo much of our blood</l>
                           <l>is already ſpilt, as ſhould the glittering Sun</l>
                           <l>exhale it upward, 'twould obnubulate</l>
                           <l>It's luſter, elſe to fiery Metors turn.</l>
                           <l>ſome counſel (Lords) he that's amidſt the Sea,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="166" facs="86"/>when every curled wave doth threat his death,</l>
                           <l>yet truſts upon the oares of his own armes,</l>
                           <l>and ſometime the ſalt fome doth pity him.</l>
                           <l>A VVolf, or Lion, that hath fild his gorge</l>
                           <l>with bloody prey, at laſt will lie to ſleep,</l>
                           <l>and the unnaturalſt creatures not forget</l>
                           <l>their love to thoſe whom they do know their own:</l>
                           <l>My wife's his daughter; ſince we cannot ſtand</l>
                           <l>his fury longer, ſhe ſhall ſwage his wrath.</l>
                           <l>The boyſterous Ocean when no winds oppoſe,</l>
                           <l>grows calm: revenge is loſt, when't hath no foes.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>2. <hi>Nob.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>VVhy then (my Lord) array your ſelf in weeds</l>
                           <l>of a Petitioner: take the Queen along,</l>
                           <l>and your two children; they may move his eyes;</l>
                           <l>for, deſperate ſores aske deſperate remedies.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ala.</speaker>
                           <l>Go (Lords) go: fetch ſome ſtraight. O heavens!</l>
                           <l>O fortune, they that leane on thy crackt wheel,</l>
                           <l>and truſt a Kingdomes power, and domineer</l>
                           <l>in a wall'd Palace, let them look on me,</l>
                           <l>and thee <hi>(Carmania;)</hi> greater inſtances</l>
                           <l>the world affords not to demonſtrate</l>
                           <l>the frail eſtate of proudeſt Potentates,</l>
                           <l>of ſturdieſt Monarchies: high Pinacles</l>
                           <l>are ſtill invaded with the prouder winds;</l>
                           <l>they muſt endure the threats of every blaſt;</l>
                           <l>the tops of <hi>Caucaſus</hi> and <hi>Pindus</hi> ſhake</l>
                           <l>with evey crack of thunder; humble Vaults</l>
                           <l>are nere toucht with a bolt: ambiguous wings</l>
                           <l>hath all the ſtate, that hovers over Kings.</l>
                           <stage>
                              <hi>Enter the</hi> 2. <hi>Nobles with a winding ſheet, A|ladin puts it on.</hi>
                           </stage>
                           <l>I, I, this veſture ſits my miſery!</l>
                           <l>this badge of poverty muſt now prevaile,</l>
                           <l>where all my Kingdomes power and ſtrength doth fail.</l>
                           <l>Why ſhould not a prophetick ſoul attend</l>
                           <l>on great mens perſons, and forewarn their ills?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="167" facs="86"/>Raging <hi>Bootes</hi> doth doth not ſo turmoile</l>
                           <l>the <hi>Lybian</hi> ford, as Fortune doth great hearts.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Bellona</hi> and <hi>Erynnis</hi> ſcourge us on;</l>
                           <l>ſhould wars and treaſons ceaſe, why our own weight</l>
                           <l>would ſend us to the earth, as ſpreading armes</l>
                           <l>make the huge trees in tempeſt for to ſplit.</l>
                           <l>For as the ſlaughter-man to paſture goes,</l>
                           <l>and drags that Oxe home firſt, whoſe Bulk is greateſt,</l>
                           <l>the leane he ſtill lets feed: diſeaſe takes hold</l>
                           <l>on bodies that are pampered with beſt fare;</l>
                           <l>ſo doth all ruine chuſe the faireſt markes,</l>
                           <l>at which it bends, and ſtrikes it full of ſhafts;</l>
                           <l>ambition made me now that eminent Butt:</l>
                           <l>And I that fell by mine own ſtrength, muſt riſe</l>
                           <l>by profeſt weakneſſe; Buckets full ſink down,</l>
                           <l>whilſt th'empty dance i'th' ayre and cannot drown.</l>
                           <l>Come (Lords) he out of's way can never range,</l>
                           <l>who is at furtheſt; worſt nere finds ill change.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 5.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>Enter at one door Amurath, with attendants; at the o|ther door Aladin, his Wife, two Children, all in white ſheets, kneel down to Amurath.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Our hate muſt not part thus; I'le tell thee (Prince)</l>
                           <l>thou 'aſt kindled violent <hi>Aetna</hi> in our breſt,</l>
                           <l>and ſuch a flame is quencht with nought but blood:</l>
                           <l>His blood whoſe haſty and rebellious blaſt▪</l>
                           <l>gave life unto the fire; ſhould heaven threat us;</l>
                           <l>know, we dare menace it; are we not <hi>Amurath?</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>(whoſe awful name is even trembled at)</l>
                           <l>ſo often dar'd by Pigmy Chriſtians;</l>
                           <l>which we will cruſh to ayre? what haughty thought</l>
                           <l>buzz'd thy preſumtuous eares with ſuch vain blaſts,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="168" facs="87"/>to puffe thee into ſuch impetuous acts?</l>
                           <l>or what, durſt prompt thee with a thought ſo frail,</l>
                           <l>as made thee covetous of ſo brave a death,</l>
                           <l>as this known hand ſhould cauſe it? know, that throat</l>
                           <l>ſhall feel it ſtrangled with ſome ſlave brought up</l>
                           <l>to nought but for an Hangman: thy laſt breath,</l>
                           <l>torn from thee by a hand that's worſe than death.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>Why then, Ile (like the Roman <hi>Pompey</hi>) hide</l>
                           <l>my dying ſight, ſcorning imperious looks</l>
                           <l>ſhould grace ſo baſe a ſtroke with ſad aſpect;</l>
                           <l>thus will I muffle up and choke my grones,</l>
                           <l>leſt a griev'd teare ſhould quite put out the name</l>
                           <l>of laſting courage in <hi>Carmanias</hi> fame.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>What? ſtill ſtiffe necked? Is this the truce you beg?</l>
                           <l>Sprinkled before thy face thoſe Rebel Brats,</l>
                           <l>ſhall have their braines, and their diſſected limbes,</l>
                           <l>hurld for a prey to Kites; for (Lords) 'tis fit</l>
                           <l>no ſpark of ſuch a mountain threatning fire,</l>
                           <l>be left as unextinct, leaſt it devoure,</l>
                           <l>and prove more hot unto the Turkiſh Empier,</l>
                           <l>then the <hi>Promethean</hi> blaze did trouble <hi>Jove!</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>firſt ſacrifice thoſe Brats.—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>All. Wife.</speaker>
                           <l>(Deare father) let thy fury ruſh on me;</l>
                           <l>within theſe entrailes ſheath thine unſatiate ſword,</l>
                           <l>and let this ominous, and too fruitful womb</l>
                           <l>be torn inſunder, for from thence thoſe Babes,</l>
                           <l>took all their crimes; error made them guilty,</l>
                           <l>'twas Natures fault, not theirs: O if affection</l>
                           <l>can work, then now ſhew a true fathers love;</l>
                           <l>if not, appeaſe thoſe murdering thoughts with me:</l>
                           <l>For as <hi>Jocaſta</hi> pleaded with her ſons</l>
                           <l>for their deare Father, ſo to a Father I</l>
                           <l>for my dear babes and husband; husband, father,</l>
                           <l>Which ſhall I firſt embrace? Victoriors father,</l>
                           <l>be blunt thoſe now ſharp thoughts, lay down thoſe threats,</l>
                           <l>unclaſp that impious Helmet; fix to earth</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="169" facs="87"/>that monumental Speare, look on thy child</l>
                           <l>with pardoning looks, not with a warriers eye:</l>
                           <l>Elſe ſhall my breſt cover my husbands breſt,</l>
                           <l>and ſerve as buckler to receive thy wounds.</l>
                           <l>Why doſt thou doubt? Feareſt thou thy daughters faith?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>I feare, for after Daughters perjury,</l>
                           <l>all Lawes of Nature ſhall diſtaſteful be;</l>
                           <l>nor will I truſt thy children or thy ſelf.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                           <l>No Father, 'tis I: fear you him, he you,</l>
                           <l>I both, but for you both, for both you war;</l>
                           <l>ſo that 'tis beſt with him that's overcome.</l>
                           <l>O let me kiſſe (kind father) firſt the earth</l>
                           <l>on which you tread, then kiſſe mine husbands cheek.</l>
                           <l>Great King embrace theſe babes, you are the ſtock</l>
                           <l>on which theſe Grafts were planted—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>True, and when ſprouts do rob the tree of ſap,</l>
                           <l>they muſt be prun'd.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                           <l>Dear Father, leave ſuch harſh ſimilitudes:</l>
                           <l>By my deceaſed Mother, (to whoſe womb</l>
                           <l>I was a ten moneths burden:) By your ſelf,</l>
                           <l>(to whom I was a pleaſing Infant once)</l>
                           <l>pitty my husband, and theſe tender Infants.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, to have them collect a manly ſtrength,</l>
                           <l>and their firſt leſſon that their Dad ſhall teach them</l>
                           <l>ſhall be to read my miſery.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>All.</speaker>
                           <l>Stern Conqueror: but that thy daughter ſhews,</l>
                           <l>there once dwelt good in that obdurate breſt,</l>
                           <l>I would not ſpend a teare to ſoften thee.</l>
                           <l>Thou ſeeſt my Countries turn'd into a grave:</l>
                           <l>my Cities ſcare the Sun with fiercer flames,</l>
                           <l>which turn them into aſhes, and my ſelf</l>
                           <l>ſo flickt and carved, that my amazed blood</l>
                           <l>knows not through which wound firſt to take it's way;</l>
                           <l>if not on me, have mercy on my babes, —</l>
                           <l>which, with thy mercy thou mayſt turn to Love.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>No ſir, we muſt root out malicious ſeed:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="170" facs="88"/>nothing ſprouts faſter, than an envious weed!</l>
                           <l>We ſee a little Bullock, 'mongſt an Herd</l>
                           <l>(whoſe horns are yet ſcarce crept from out his front)</l>
                           <l>grows on a ſuddain tall, and in the Field,</l>
                           <l>frolicks ſo much, he makes his Father yield.</l>
                           <l>A little Twig left budding on an Elm,</l>
                           <l>ungratefully bars his Mother ſight from Heaven!</l>
                           <l>I love not future <hi>Aladins.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>Threat all a Conquerour can, canſt threat but death,</l>
                           <l>and I can die: but if thou wouldſt have mercy!—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                           <l>Let's ſee your feet, we're proud with this hands kiſs!</l>
                           <l>The higher thoſe great powers have rais'd you,</l>
                           <l>preſs that which lyes below with gentler weight:</l>
                           <l>to pardon miſeries is Fortunes height:</l>
                           <l>alas, theſe infants, theſe weak ſinewed hands</l>
                           <l>can be no terror to theſe <hi>Hectors</hi> arms!</l>
                           <l>Beg (Infants) beg, and teach theſe tender joynts</l>
                           <l>to ask for mercy; learn your liſping tongues</l>
                           <l>to give due accent to each ſyllable:</l>
                           <l>nothing that Fortune urgeth to, is baſe;</l>
                           <l>put from your thoughts all memory of deſcent:</l>
                           <l>forget the Princely Titles of your Fathers:</l>
                           <l>if your own miſery you cannot feel,</l>
                           <l>learn thus of me to weep, of me to kneel.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                           <l>Do (boys) and imitate your Parents tears,</l>
                           <l>which I (like <hi>Priam</hi>) ſhed, when he beheld,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hector</hi> thrice dragg'd about the <hi>Trojan</hi> Walls.</l>
                           <l>He that burſt ope the Gates of <hi>Erebus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>and rouz'd the yelling Monſter from his Den,</l>
                           <l>was conquer'd with a tear. Great Monarch learn,</l>
                           <l>To know how dear a King doth weeping earn.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1. <hi>Ch.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>Good Grandſire ſee, ſee how my Father cries!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>2. <hi>Ch.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>Good Mother take my napkin for your eyes!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                           <l>(Good father) hear, hear how thy daughter prays!</l>
                           <l>Thou that know'ſt how to uſe ſtern Warriers arms,</l>
                           <l>learn how to uſe mild VVarriers pity too.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="171" facs="88"/>Alas? Can ere theſe ungrown ſtrengths repair</l>
                           <l>their Fathers battered Cities? Or can theſe,</l>
                           <l>theſe orethrown Turrets? <hi>(Iconium)</hi> what ſmall hopes</l>
                           <l>haſt thou to lean upon? If theſe be all?</l>
                           <l>Not half ſo mild hath our misfortune been</l>
                           <l>that any can ere fear us: Be pleaſed —</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Riſe (my dear Child) as Marble againſt rain,</l>
                           <l>ſo I at theſe obedient ſhowers, melt;</l>
                           <l>thus I do raiſe thy Husband: thus thy Babes:</l>
                           <l>freely admitting you to former State.</l>
                           <l>But <hi>Aladin,</hi> wake not our wrath again;</l>
                           <l>"Patience grows fury that is often ſtirred;</l>
                           <l>when Conquerours wax calm, and ceaſe to hate,</l>
                           <l>the conquer'd ſhould not dare to reiterate.</l>
                           <l>Be thou our Son and Friend.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
                           <l>By all the Rites of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> I vow it.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Then, for to ſeal unto you this our love,</l>
                           <l>your ſelf ſhall lead a wing in <hi>Servia,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>in our immediate VVars; we are to meet</l>
                           <l>the Chriſtians in <hi>Caſſanoe</hi>'s Plains with ſpeed:</l>
                           <l>Great <hi>Amurath</hi> nere had time to breath himſelf,</l>
                           <l>ſo much as to have warring with new Foes;</l>
                           <l>no day ſecurely to his Scepter ſhone,</l>
                           <l>but one VVars end, ſtill brought another on. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Actus 5. Scena 2.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Lazarus, Cobelitz, Souldiers, all armed.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Let now victorious wreathes ingirt our brows,</l>
                           <l>let Angels 'ſtead of Souldiers wield our arms</l>
                           <l>'gainſt him, who that our Cities might be his,</l>
                           <l>ſtrives to depopulate, and make them none!</l>
                           <l>But look, look in the air (me thinks) I ſee</l>
                           <l>an Hoſt of Souldiers brandiſhing their Swords;</l>
                           <l>each corner of the Heaven ſhoots thunderbolts,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="172" facs="89"/>to nail theſe impious forces to the Earth.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
                           <l>Souldiers ſtand to't, though fortune bandy at's,</l>
                           <l>let's ſtand her ſhocks, like ſturdy Rocks ith' Sea,</l>
                           <l>on which the angry foaming Billows beat,</l>
                           <l>with frivolous ruſh, and break themſelves, not them;</l>
                           <l>ſtand like the undaunted countenance oth' sky,</l>
                           <l>or, like the Sun, which when the fooliſh King,</l>
                           <l>thought to obſcure with a cloud of darts,</l>
                           <l>out lookt them all, our lives are all inchanted,</l>
                           <l>and more invulnerate than <hi>Thetis</hi> Son.</l>
                           <l>We ſhall have hands and weapons: if the ſtone</l>
                           <l>of Fortune glide from under our weak feet,</l>
                           <l>and we muſt fall, yet, let all Chriſtians ſay,</l>
                           <l>'Tis She, and not the Cauſe, that wins the day.</l>
                           <l>We muſt believe Heaven hath a greater care</l>
                           <l>of them, whom Fortune doth ſo oft out dare!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Gentlemen, Brothers, Friends, Souldiers, Chri|ſtians,</l>
                           <l>we have no reaſon to command of Heaven</l>
                           <l>a thing denied to all mortality.</l>
                           <l>Nor ſhould we be ſo impudently proud,</l>
                           <l>as in this weak condition to repute</l>
                           <l>our ſelves above the ſtroak of Lady Chance,</l>
                           <l>a caution muſt divine it, ever fixt,</l>
                           <l>that whilſt her checks equally fall out,</l>
                           <l>community ſhould eaſe their bitterneſs.</l>
                           <l>I could afreſh now ſhed thoſe Princely tears,</l>
                           <l>to think ſuch ſuddain ruine ſhould attend</l>
                           <l>Heroick ſpirits glittering in bright arms!</l>
                           <l>But if the <hi>Graecian</hi> (when he heard the dreams</l>
                           <l>diſputed ſubtilly by Philoſophers,</l>
                           <l>to prove innumerable extant worlds)</l>
                           <l>was ſtruck with penſiveneſs, and wept to think</l>
                           <l>he had not yet obtain'd one for himſelf;</l>
                           <l>what terror can affright a Chriſtians thoughts</l>
                           <l>who knows there is a world, at liberty</l>
                           <l>to breath in, when this glaſs of life is broke?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="173" facs="89"/>our Foes with circling fury are intrencht;</l>
                           <l>Pelions of Earth and darkneſs ſhall orelade them,</l>
                           <l>whilſt we ſhall mount, and theſe our ſpirits light,</l>
                           <l>ſhall be yet ponderous to depreſs them lower.</l>
                           <l>Nay, my Enthuſiaſtick ſoul divines,</l>
                           <l>That ſome weak hand ſhall from the blazing Zone</l>
                           <l>ſnatch Lightning, which ſhall ſtrike the ſnarling Cur</l>
                           <l>with horror and amazement to the Earth,</l>
                           <l>which Hell cannot oppoſe! <hi>Turk,</hi> Tyrannize,</l>
                           <l>ſtand, yet at length to fall my ſacrifice.</l>
                           <l>Super Olympick vigor will (no doubt).</l>
                           <l>ſqueez all thy ſupercilious rancor out! <stage>Exeunt in a March.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 3. Actus 5.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>The Heavens ſeem on fire, Comets and blazing Stars appear,</hi> Amurath <hi>ſpeaks.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Who ſet the world on fire?</l>
                           <l>How now (ye Heavens) grow you</l>
                           <l>ſo proud, that you muſt needs put on curl'd locks,</l>
                           <l>and cloth your ſelves in Periwigs of fire?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Mahomet</hi> (ſay not but I invoke thee now!)</l>
                           <l>command the puny-Chriſtians demi-God</l>
                           <l>put out thoſe flaſhing ſparks, thoſe <hi>Ignes fatui,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>or i'le unſeat him, or with my Looks ſo ſhake</l>
                           <l>the ſtaggring props of his weak ſeated Throne,</l>
                           <l>that he ſhall finde he ſhall have more to do</l>
                           <l>to quell one <hi>Amurath,</hi> than the whole Gyant brood</l>
                           <l>of thoſe ſame Sons of Earth, than ten <hi>Lycaons.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Do the poor ſnaks ſo love their miſery</l>
                           <l>that they would ſee it by theſe threatning lights?</l>
                           <l>Dare ye blaze ſtill? I'le toſs up Buckets full</l>
                           <l>of Chriſtians blood to quench you: by thoſe hairs</l>
                           <l>drag you beneath the Center: there put out</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="174" facs="90"/>all your preſaging flames in <hi>Phlegeton.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Can you outbrave me with your pidling Lights?</l>
                           <l>Yawn earth with Caſements as wide as hell it ſelf. <stage>Vault opens.</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>Burn heaven as ardent as the <hi>Lemnian</hi> flames,</l>
                           <l>wake pale <hi>Tiſiphon,</hi> ſpend all thy ſnakes;</l>
                           <l>Be <hi>Eacus,</hi> and <hi>Minos,</hi> as ſevere</l>
                           <l>as if the Goale delivery of us all</l>
                           <l>were the next Seſſions. Ile pull <hi>Radamant</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>by his flaming furres from out his Iron Chaire.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Whilſt he is in his fury, ariſe four Fiends, framed like Turkiſh Kings, but black, his ſuppoſed Predeceſſors daunce about him; to a kind of hideous noyſe, ſing this Song following.</stage>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="song">
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>1. Fiend.</speaker>
                                    <l>Horror, diſmal cryes, and yells</l>
                                    <l>Of theſe thy Grandſires thee fore-tels,</l>
                                    <l>Furies ſent of thee to learn</l>
                                    <l>Crimes, which they could nere diſcern.</l>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                                    <l>Furies ſent, &amp;c.</l>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>2. Fiend.</speaker>
                                    <l>O <hi>Amurath</hi> thy Father's come,</l>
                                    <l>To warn thee of a ſuddain doome,</l>
                                    <l>Which in <hi>Caſſanoe's</hi> fields attends</l>
                                    <l>To bring thee to thy helliſh friends.</l>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                                    <l>Which in <hi>Caſſanoes,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>3. Fiend.</speaker>
                                    <l>
                                       <hi>Megaera</hi> and <hi>Ennio</hi> both do ſtand</l>
                                    <l>Trembling leſt when thou art damn'd,</l>
                                    <l>Chief of Furies thou ſhouldſt be,</l>
                                    <l>And they their ſnakes reſigne to thee.</l>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                                    <l>Chief of Furies, &amp;c.</l>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <pb n="175" facs="90"/>
                                    <speaker>4. Fiend.</speaker>
                                    <l>Terror, we a while will leave thee,</l>
                                    <l>Till <hi>Cocytus</hi> Lake receive thee.</l>
                                    <l>
                                       <hi>Cerberus</hi> will quake for feare</l>
                                    <l>Where he a new Turks fate ſhall heare.</l>
                                 </sp>
                                 <sp>
                                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                                    <l>
                                       <hi>Cerberus</hi> will, &amp;c.</l>
                                 </sp>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>Now who the divel ſent my Grandſires hither?</l>
                           <l>Had <hi>Pluto</hi> no task elſe to ſet them too?</l>
                           <l>He ſhould have bound them to <hi>Ixions</hi> wheel,</l>
                           <l>or bid them roule the ſtone of <hi>Syſiphus:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Beſhrew me, but their ſinging did not pleaſe me!</l>
                           <l>Have they not been ſo drunk with <hi>Lethe</hi> yet,</l>
                           <l>as to forget me? They can portend no ill;</l>
                           <l>for, ſhould the fates be twining my laſt thread,</l>
                           <l>yet none durſt come from hell to tell me ſo.</l>
                           <l>Shall I be ſcar'd with a Night-walking Ghoſt;</l>
                           <l>or what my working fancy ſhall preſent?</l>
                           <l>Why, I can look more terrible then night,</l>
                           <l>and command darkneſſe in the unwilling day:</l>
                           <l>Make <hi>Hecate</hi> ſtart, and draw back her head</l>
                           <l>to wrap it in a ſwarthy vaile of clouds.</l>
                           <l>Drop ſheets of Sulphure, you prodigious skyes,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cyclops,</hi> run all thy Bullets into <hi>Aetna,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>then vomit them at once; ſhould Chriſtians</l>
                           <l>couch to the bottomleſſe abyſſe of <hi>Styx,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>or hide themſelves under <hi>Avernaes</hi> ſhade,</l>
                           <l>this arm ſhould fetch them out. Day muſt perform</l>
                           <l>what I intend, wrath raines a bloody ſtorm:</l>
                           <l>And now, 'gins riſe the Sun, which yet not knows</l>
                           <l>the miſery it ſhall ſee on <hi>Amuraths</hi> Foes!</l>
                           <l>Lords, Leaders, Captaines— <stage>Enter Schahin and others.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scha.</speaker>
                           <l>Your Highneſſe up ſo ſoon?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
                           <l>He ſmall reſt takes,</l>
                           <l>that dreames on nought but bloody broyles and death.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="176" facs="91"/>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Your Grace ſeems much diſtempered: Beds of ſweat</l>
                           <l>bedew your brows with never-wonted paleneſs</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Why; ſee you not? The heavens are turn'd Court Ladies,</l>
                           <l>and put on other Hair beſides their own:</l>
                           <l>canſt gueſs (learn'd <hi>Schahin</hi>) what theſe flames portend?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, ſuch things as theſe, we men muſt ſee,</l>
                           <l>and wonder at, and yet not ſearch the reaſon;</l>
                           <l>perchance unwholſom fogs exhailed by th' Sun</l>
                           <l>are ſet a blazing by his too neer heat:</l>
                           <l>but 'tis not lawful that a mortal eye</l>
                           <l>ſhould dare to penetrate Heavens ſecrecy.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Doth it not bode a Conqueſt?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, 'gainſt the Chriſtians:</l>
                           <l>for, unto them it bends ſiniſter looks,</l>
                           <l>and frowns upon their Army more than ours.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>So, ſo: come on, ere <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> appear</l>
                           <l>let's too't, and ſo prevent that ſluggard <hi>Sol.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>If we want Light, we'll from our Whinyards</l>
                           <l>ſtrike fire enough to ſcorch the Univerſe;</l>
                           <l>Mine Armour there! <stage>Some go for his Armour.</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>Now <hi>(Mahomet)</hi> I implore</l>
                           <l>thy promiſt Aid for this auſpicious day:</l>
                           <l>toſs me aloft, and make me ride on Clouds:</l>
                           <l>If my Horſe fail me, thoſe fire breathing jades,</l>
                           <l>(which the boy <hi>Phaëthon</hi> knew not how to guide)</l>
                           <l>will I pluck out from out the flaming Team,</l>
                           <l>and hurle my ſelf againſt thoſe condenſe Spheares,</l>
                           <l>on which I'le ſit, and ſtay their turning Orbs;</l>
                           <l>the whole vertigious Circle ſhall ſtand ſtill,</l>
                           <l>but to behold me: <hi>Mine Armour, ho!</hi>
                              <stage>They bring his Armour.</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>So, help on here; now like <hi>Alcides</hi> do I girt my ſelf</l>
                           <l>with well knit ſinewes, able to ſtagger Earth,</l>
                           <l>and threaten Nature with a ſecond Chaos:</l>
                           <l>If one impetuous broyl remain to come</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="177" facs="91"/>in future ages, ſet on foote this houre.</l>
                           <l>How well this weight of ſteele bents my ſtrength!</l>
                           <l>Me thinks the Gods ſtand quivering, and doe feare</l>
                           <l>(when I am arm'd) another <hi>Phlege●'s</hi> neare.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Chiron</hi> ſhall ſee his <hi>Piadus</hi> at my feet;</l>
                           <l>And ile climbe up to heaven, and pull it downe</l>
                           <l>and kick the weighty burden of the world,</l>
                           <l>from off the Babies ſhoulders that ſupports it.</l>
                           <l>for I am ſafer Buckled 'gainſt my foe,</l>
                           <l>then ſturdy <hi>Jaſon,</hi> who by th' inchanted charmes</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Medea</hi> gave, encountred Unicornes,</l>
                           <l>Queld Lyons, ſtruggl'd with fire-belching Buls,</l>
                           <l>obtain'd a glorious prize, a Fleece. A Fleece</l>
                           <l>dipt deepe in tincture of the Chriſt'ans bloud</l>
                           <l>ſhall be my ſpoyle; nay ſhould they hide their heads</l>
                           <l>in their Gods boſome, here's a ſword ſhall reach them.</l>
                           <l>Come they ſhall know no place is free from wrath,</l>
                           <l>when boyling bloud is ſtirr'd in <hi>Amurath.</hi>
                              <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>An alarme, excurſions: fight within. Enter at one doore a Chriſtian, at another a Turke; fight, both kild, ſo a new charge, the Turkes kill moſt. Enter</hi> Lazarus, Schahin <hi>kils him. Enter</hi> Eureno|ſes, Cobelitz, <hi>they fight,</hi> Cobelitz <hi>faints, falls for dead. A ſhowt within, a token of Victory on the Turkes ſide, a Retrait ſounded.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 4. Actus 5.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter above</hi> Amurath, Bajazet, <hi>Nobles, to ſee the ſpoyle.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Here, mighty Prince, take view of Victory,</l>
                           <l>and ſee the field too narrow for thy ſpoyles.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Erynnus</hi> hides her head as if afraid,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="178" facs="92"/>to ſee a ſlaughter ſhe durſt never hope for.</l>
                           <l>Earth hath the Carkaſſes: and denies them Graves,</l>
                           <l>and lets them ly and rot, and fat her wombe,</l>
                           <l>ſcorning to be unto the ſlaves a Tombe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Where are become thoſe ominous Comets now?</l>
                           <l>What? are thoſe piſſing Candles quite extinct?</l>
                           <l>leave their diſacterous ſnuffes no ſtench behind them?</l>
                           <l>'tis ſomething yet, that their God ſeeth their ſlaughter,</l>
                           <l>lending ſulphurious Meteors to behold</l>
                           <l>the bleſt deſtruction of theſe Paraſites.</l>
                           <l>I knew the Elements would firſt untye</l>
                           <l>the Nerves of th' Univerſe, then let me dye.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Here</hi> Cobelitz <hi>riſeth as awakt, amazed, lea|ning on his Sword, ſtumbling ore the dead bo|dies, lookes towards</hi> Amurath.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>See (King) heres's one worme yet that dare confeſſe</l>
                           <l>he breaths and lives, which once this hand cruſht downe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Ha, ha, by <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and we are weary now:</l>
                           <l>Some Mercy ſhall lay Victory aſleepe.</l>
                           <l>It will a Lawreat prove to this great ſtrife,</l>
                           <l>'mongſt all theſe murdred to give one his life,</l>
                           <l>ſo we'll deſcend. <stage>He goeth from aloft.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>From what a diſmall grave am I awak'd,</l>
                           <l>entomb'd within a Golgatha of men!</l>
                           <l>Have all theſe Soules prevented me in bleſſe,</l>
                           <l>and left me in a dreame of happineſſe?</l>
                           <l>But ſoft! me thoughts he ſayd he would deſcend!</l>
                           <l>Then, Heavens, one minutes breath, that's all I aske,</l>
                           <l>and then I ſhall performe my lifes true taske.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Amurath deſcends on the Stage, Cobelitz ſtaggers towards him.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Poore ſlave, wouldſt live?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Here Cobelitz is come to him, ſeeming to kneele, ſtabs him with a pocket Dagger.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="179" facs="92"/>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes <hi>Turke</hi> to ſee thee dye.</l>
                           <l>Howle, howle, grim <hi>Tartar,</hi> yel (thou griſly Wolfe)</l>
                           <l>force forth the bloud from out thy gaping Wound!</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Dii tibi non mortem, quae cunctis poena paratur,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Sed ſenſum poſt fata, tuae dent (impie) morti.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>My ſpirit makes me not to feele thy weapon!</l>
                           <l>Hold, you crackt Organs, of my ſhattered life,</l>
                           <l>I 'm not toucht yet; can I not mocke my death,</l>
                           <l>and thinke 'tis but a dreame tells me I 'm hurt?</l>
                           <l>Dar'ſt thou then leave me (bloud?) Canſt be ſo bold</l>
                           <l>as to forſake theſe veynes to flow on Earth?</l>
                           <l>And muſt I, like th'unhappy <hi>Roman,</hi> dye</l>
                           <l>by a ſlaves hand?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Tyrant, 'tis knowne</l>
                           <l>He's Lord of others lives that ſcornes his owne.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>I that could ſcarce ere ſleepe, can I ere die?</l>
                           <l>And will none feare my life when I am dead;</l>
                           <l>Tortures and torments for the murderer.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Ha, ha, ha! <stage>Leaning on his ſword.</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>I thanke thee (great omnipotent) that I</l>
                           <l>ſhall here laugh out the lag end of my life!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Villaine, thy laugh wounds worſe then did thy Dagger.</l>
                           <l>Are you Lethargick (Lords) in cruelty?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, heare me <hi>(Turke)</hi> now will I prompt their rage:</l>
                           <l>Locke me up in the Bull of <hi>Phalaris,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>cut off theſe eye-lids, bid me then out-gaze</l>
                           <l>the parching Sunbeames; flea this tender skin,</l>
                           <l>ſet neſts of Hornets on my raweſt fleſh,</l>
                           <l>let the Siconian Clouds drop brimſtone on me,</l>
                           <l>powre boyling Lemnos on my greeneſt wounds,</l>
                           <l>put on my ſhoulder <hi>Neſſus</hi> poyſon'd ſhirt,</l>
                           <l>bind all theſe bloudy faces to my face,</l>
                           <l>Racke me, <hi>Procraſtes</hi> like — <stage>
                                 <hi>The Lord that holds up</hi> Amurath <hi>offers to touch his wounds.</hi>
                              </stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
                           <l>Hell, oh! I cannot brooke your ſmalleſt touch.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="180" facs="93"/>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Ha, Ha! each groane is Balſome to my wounds:</l>
                           <l>I am perfect well. <stage>Bajazet <hi>offers to kill</hi> Gobelitz; <hi>a Nobleman holds his hand.</hi>
                              </stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>Raſcall, dar'ſt deride us?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Yea? and while your witty furies ſhall invent</l>
                           <l>for me ſome never heard of puniſhment;</l>
                           <l>I ſee a guard of Saints ready to take me hence.</l>
                           <l>Take then free flight my new rewarded ſoule,</l>
                           <l>and ſeate thee on the winged Seraphims,</l>
                           <l>haſt to the Empyreum, where thy welcome</l>
                           <l>ſhall be an <hi>Haleluia,</hi> anthem'd forth</l>
                           <l>By the <hi>Chorus</hi> of the Angell-Hierarchy.</l>
                           <l>Pierce with ſwift plumes, the concave paths oth' Moone</l>
                           <l>Where the black aire enlightened is with ſtarres.</l>
                           <l>Stay not to wonder there at wandring Signes,</l>
                           <l>at bi-horn'd <hi>Gemini,</hi> or <hi>Amphions</hi> Harpe,</l>
                           <l>at <hi>Arctos,</hi> or <hi>Bootes,</hi> or the Beare,</l>
                           <l>(Which are to pleaſe wizard Aſtrologers:)</l>
                           <l>Soare higher with thy pitch, and then looke downe</l>
                           <l>to laugh at the hard trifles of the world;</l>
                           <l>Perchance ſome oft have knowne a better life,</l>
                           <l>Never did one ere leav' it more willingly.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>Feare your death (Gods!) for I have loſt my life,</l>
                           <l>and what, I moſt complaine, my tyranny.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
                           <l>Soule, to detaine thee from thy wiſhed reſt!</l>
                           <l>were but an envious part! ariſe, farewell:</l>
                           <l>To ſtay thee to accuſe or fate or man,</l>
                           <l>would ſhew I were unwilling yet to leave thee.</l>
                           <l>But deare companion hence: cut through the ayre</l>
                           <l>let not the groſeneſſe of my Earth ore-lime</l>
                           <l>thy ſpeedy wings, fly without weight of crime. <stage>He dyes.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                           <l>O, now have I and Fortune try'd it out.</l>
                           <l>With all her beſt of favours was I crown'd</l>
                           <l>and ſuffred her worſt threats, when moſt ſhe frown'd.</l>
                           <l>Stay (Soule! a King, a Turke, commands thee ſtay.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="181" facs="93"/>Sure I am but an actor, and muſt ſtrive</l>
                           <l>to perſonate the Tragicke ends of Kings.</l>
                           <l>And ſo (to winne applauſe unto the Scene)</l>
                           <l>with fained paſſion thus muſt graſpe at death.</l>
                           <l>O but I ſee pale <hi>Nemeſis</hi> at hand:</l>
                           <l>Art thou dull, fate, and doſt not overſpread</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cimmerian</hi> wings of death throughout the world;</l>
                           <l>What? Not one Earthquake? One blazing Comet</l>
                           <l>T'accompany my ſoule t' his Funerall?</l>
                           <l>Is not this hour the generall period</l>
                           <l>to nere returning time! Laſt breath command</l>
                           <l>a new <hi>Deacalions</hi> deluge, that with me</l>
                           <l>the world may ſwim to his Eternall Grave.</l>
                           <l>Cracke hindge that holds this globe, and welcome death.</l>
                           <l>Wilt thou not ſtay Soule? Friend, not ſtay with Kings?</l>
                           <l>Sinke then, and ſink beneath the Thracian Mount.</l>
                           <l>Sinke beneath <hi>Athos,</hi> be the <hi>Brackiſh</hi> Waves</l>
                           <l>Of <hi>Acheron</hi> thy Tombe; Ile want a Grave;</l>
                           <l>So all parts feare, which firſt my Corps ſhall have;</l>
                           <l>For in my Grave, Ile be the Chriſtians foe,</l>
                           <l>here like a maſſie <hi>pyramide</hi> ile fall,</l>
                           <l>Ile ſtrive to ſinke all the whole fabricke with me:</l>
                           <l>quake <hi>pluto,</hi> for 'tis I that come</l>
                           <l>a <hi>turke,</hi> tyrant, and a conquerour.</l>
                           <l>and with this groane, like thunder will I cleave,</l>
                           <l>the timerous earth, whilſt thus my laſt I breath. <stage>He dyes.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Bajaz.</speaker>
                           <l>O eaſie powers, to give us all at firſt,</l>
                           <l>but in their loſſe, they make us moſt accurſt. <stage>
                                 <hi>Here all the Nobles kneele to</hi> Bajazet.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
                           <l>The Taper of your Fathers life is ſpent;</l>
                           <l>We muſt have light ſtill and adore a Sunne.</l>
                           <l>that next is riſing; therefore mighty Prince,</l>
                           <l>upon your ſhoulders muſt the pondrous load</l>
                           <l>of Empire reſt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="182" facs="94"/>
                           <speaker>Bajaz.</speaker>
                           <l>Why (Lords) we have a Brother,</l>
                           <l>who, as in the ſame bloud he tooke a ſhare,</l>
                           <l>ſo let him beare his part in Government.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Sch.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, within the ſelfe-ſame Hemiſpheare</l>
                           <l>It's moſt prodigious when two Sunnes appeare.</l>
                           <l>One body by one ſoule muſt be inform'd.</l>
                           <l>Kingdomes like (marriage beds) muſt not indure</l>
                           <l>any corrivall. <hi>Rome</hi> was nere ſecure</l>
                           <l>whilſt ſhe contain'd a <hi>Pompey;</hi> and a <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Like as one Prophet we acknowledge now,</l>
                           <l>ſo of one King in ſtate we muſt allow.</l>
                           <l>You know the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Lawes, Prince be not nice</l>
                           <l>to purchaſe Kingdomes, whatſoe'er the price.</l>
                           <l>He muſt be lopt, ſend for him he muſt dye.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Bajazet.</speaker>
                           <l>O happy <hi>Bajazet,</hi> that he was borne</l>
                           <l>to be a King when thou waſt Counſeller.</l>
                           <l>Call in our Brother <hi>Jacup.</hi>
                              <stage>Some goe for him.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Here ſixe men take up Amuraths Trunke on their ſhoulders.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Baj.</speaker>
                           <l>Why (Lords!) is <hi>Amurath</hi> ſo light a weight?</l>
                           <l>Is this the Trunk oth' <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperor?</l>
                           <l>Oh what a heape of thoughts are come to naught?</l>
                           <l>What a light weight is he unto ſixe men,</l>
                           <l>who durſt ſtand under <hi>Oſſa,</hi> and ſuſtaine 't?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, theſe Meditations fit not you:</l>
                           <l>You are to take the honour he hath left,</l>
                           <l>and thinke you of his riſing, not his fall! <stage>Enter Jacup.</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>Let your decree be ſuddaine, here's your Brother.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Baj.</speaker>
                           <l>Brother, I could have wiſhed we might have met</l>
                           <l>at times of better greeting! Our father hath</l>
                           <l>bequeath'd to the Grave theſe aſhes, to us his State.</l>
                           <l>Nor have we leyſure (yet) to mourne for him.</l>
                           <l>Brother, you know our ſtate hath made a Law,</l>
                           <l>that, he that ſits in a Majeſtick Chayre,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="183" facs="94"/>muſt not endure the next ſucceeding heyre.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, we doe:</l>
                           <l>And, Brother, doe you thinke 'tis crime enough</l>
                           <l>to dye, becauſe I am ſonne to an Emperour?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, we know there breathes in him that ayre</l>
                           <l>of true affeſtion, that he doth much deſire</l>
                           <l>you ſhould be equall in his Kingdome with him:</l>
                           <l>But ſtill when two great evils are propos'd;</l>
                           <l>the leſſe is to be choſen.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, your life 's but one:</l>
                           <l>Kings are the threads whereto there are inweaved</l>
                           <l>millions of lives, and he that muſt rule all</l>
                           <l>muſt ſtill be one that is ſelect from all.</l>
                           <l>Although we ſpeake, yet thinke them not our words,</l>
                           <l>But what the Land ſpeakes in us! Kings are free;</l>
                           <l>And muſt be impatient of equality.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                           <l>And is't eene ſo?</l>
                           <l>How have theſe Dogs fawn'd on me, lickt my feet</l>
                           <l>when <hi>Amurath</hi> yet lived! Felt all my thoughts,</l>
                           <l>and ſoothed them to the ſight of Empyrie!</l>
                           <l>And now the firſt would ſet their politique hands</l>
                           <l>to ſtrangle up that breath, a blaſt of which</l>
                           <l>their noſtrils have ſuckt up like perfum'd ayre.</l>
                           <l>Well brother well, by all men this is ſpoke,</l>
                           <l>that heart that cannot bow, may yet be broke.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Bajazet.</speaker>
                           <l>Brother, you muſt not now ſtand to upbraid;</l>
                           <l>They which doe feare the vulgars murmuring tongue,</l>
                           <l>Muſt alſo feare th' authority of a King;</l>
                           <l>For rulers muſt eſteeme it happineſſe,</l>
                           <l>that with their gov'rnment they can hate ſuppreſſe:</l>
                           <l>they with too faint a hand the Scepters ſway,</l>
                           <l>Who regard love, or what the people ſay:</l>
                           <l>To Kindred we muſt quite put off reſpect,</l>
                           <l>when 't is ſo neare it may our Crowne affect.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                           <l>Then name of Brother doe I thus ſhake off,</l>
                           <l>for 't is in vaine their mercy to implore,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="184" facs="95"/>when impious Statiſts have decreed before.</l>
                           <l>Yet King, although thou take my life away</l>
                           <l>ſee how Ile dye in better ſtate then thou!</l>
                           <l>Who like (my Father) after his greateſt glory</l>
                           <l>May fall by ſome baſe hand: The Miniſter.</l>
                           <l>'To take my breath, ſhall be thy ſelfe a King.</l>
                           <stage>
                              <hi>Here Jacup takes a Scarfe from his Arme, and putting it about his neck gives one end to</hi> Bajazet.</stage>
                           <l>Yet give me leave a while to Propheſie.</l>
                           <l>You that ſo Puppet-like delude your hopes,</l>
                           <l>and Wyer-draw the anceſtry from Kings,</l>
                           <l>thinking, that fates dare not aproach your bloud</l>
                           <l>till they doe ſeize you, then you leave this Earth,</l>
                           <l>Not as you went, but by compulſion dragg'd;</l>
                           <l>Still begging for a morrow from your Grave,</l>
                           <l>and with ſuch ſhifts you doe deceive your ſelves,</l>
                           <l>as if you could deceive mortality,</l>
                           <l>No (Brother King) not all the Glow-worme ſtate,</l>
                           <l>which makes thee be a Horſe-leach to thy bloud,</l>
                           <l>Not all the Paraſiteſt' Minions thou maintainſt,</l>
                           <l>nor the reſtorative Diſhes that are found out.</l>
                           <l>Not all thy ſhifts and trickes can cheat mortality,</l>
                           <l>or keepe thee from a death that's worſe then mine.</l>
                           <l>Should all this faile, age would profeſſe it ſelfe</l>
                           <l>a ſlow, but a ſure Executioner.</l>
                           <l>O 'tis a hard thing well to temperate</l>
                           <l>decaying happineſſe in great eſtate.</l>
                           <l>But this example by me may you gaine,</l>
                           <l>that at my death! not of Heaven complaine.</l>
                           <l>Pull then, and with my fall pull on thy ſelfe</l>
                           <l>Mountaines of burdenous honor, which ſhall curſe thee.</l>
                           <l>Death leades the willing by the hand</l>
                           <l>But ſpurs them headlong on, that dare command.</l>
                           <stage>
                              <hi>Here himſelfe pulls one end,</hi> Bajazet <hi>the other,</hi> Jacup. <hi>dyes.</hi>
                           </stage>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="185" facs="95"/>
                           <speaker>Bajazet.</speaker>
                           <l>Take up this Trunke; and let us firſt appoint</l>
                           <l>our Fathers, and our Brothers Funerals.</l>
                           <l>the ſenſe leſſe body of that Caitiffe ſlave,</l>
                           <l>hurle to a Ditch. Poſterity ſhall heare</l>
                           <l>Our leſſe ill Chronicled, but time ſhall heare</l>
                           <l>theſe minutes rather, then repeate their woe.</l>
                           <l>Now Primacy, on thee Ile mediate,</l>
                           <l>Which who enjoy thee, are in bleſt eſtate.</l>
                           <l>Whoſe age in ſecure ſilence fleets away,</l>
                           <l>Without diſturbance to his funeral day;</l>
                           <l>Nor ponderous nor unquiet honours can</l>
                           <l>Vexe him, but dyes a primare ancient man.</l>
                           <l>What greater powers threaten inferiour men,</l>
                           <l>a greater power threatens him agen:</l>
                           <l>And like to waſted Tapers Kings muſt ſpend</l>
                           <l>their lives to light up others: So all end.</l>
                           <stage>
                              <hi>Exeunt bearing out ſolemnely the bodies of</hi> Amurath <hi>and</hi> Jacup.</stage>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         </TEI>

