<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
					<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
					 <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Three excellent tragœdies.:  Viz. The raging Turk, or, Bajazet the Second. The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the First. And The tragoedie of Orestes· / Written, by Tho. Goff, Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford; and acted by the students of the same house.</title>
            <author> Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>137 400dpi TIFF images (displayed as GIF) and XML-encoded text (displayed as HTML).</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 December (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85334</idno>
            <idno type="vid">114751</idno>
            <idno type="Aleph">5358848</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing (2nd ed.) G1006.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1066.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Thomason E.1591[2].</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Madan III 2290.</idno>
            <idno type="bibno">(UnM)99862588e</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Where applicable, subject to copyright.  Other restrictions on distribution may apply.  Please  go to http://www.umdl.umich.edu/ for more information.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="_245">Three excellent tragœdies.:  Viz. The raging Turk, or, Bajazet the Second. The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the First. And The tragoedie of Orestes· / Written, by Tho. Goff, Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford; and acted by the students of the same house.</title>
                  <author> Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
                  <author>Meighen, Richard, fl. 1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, carefully corrected by a friend of the authors.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 263, [7] p.    </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Bedell and T. Collins, at the middle Temple gate Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Rich. Meighen.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>"The raging Turk", "The courageous Turk", and "The tragedy of Orestes" each have separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>With three final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2007-07-06.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.  Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term>English drama (Tragedy)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="96"/>
                  <pb facs="96"/>
                  <p>THE TRAGEDY OF ORESTES, <hi>Written by</hi> THOMAS GOFF <hi>Maſter of Arts,</hi> and ſtudent of Chriſt-Church in OXFORD, <hi>AND</hi> Acted by the STUDENTS of the ſame houſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Edition</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for G. BEDELL and T. COLLINS, at the middle Temple Gate <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1656.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prologue">
                  <pb facs="97"/>
                  <pb facs="97"/>
                  <head>The Prologue.</head>
                  <l>THe huſh'd contentment of two ſilent howres,</l>
                  <l>Breath pleaſing ayres on theſe attentive eares;</l>
                  <l>And ſince wee ſee in this well furniſh'd roome,</l>
                  <l>All our beſt neighbours are ſo kindely met,</l>
                  <l>Wee would deviſe ſome pleaſing talke, to ſpend</l>
                  <l>The lazie houres of the tedious night:</l>
                  <l>But for our owne invention, 'twas too weake,</l>
                  <l>Whereon our young Muſe durſt not wholly leane.</l>
                  <l>We here preſent for the revive a tale,</l>
                  <l>Which once in <hi>Athens</hi> great Eurypedes</l>
                  <l>In better phraſe, at ſuch a meeting told</l>
                  <l>The learn'd <hi>Athenians</hi> with much applauſe:</l>
                  <l>The ſame we will retell unto your eares;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Atticke judgement is no leſſe then theirs,</l>
                  <l>We here as builders which doe oft take ſtones,</l>
                  <l>From out old buildings, then muſt hew and cut,</l>
                  <l>To make them ſquare, and fitting for a new;</l>
                  <l>So from an old foundation we have ta'n,</l>
                  <l>Stones ready ſquar'd for our aedifice,</l>
                  <l>Which if in pleaſing our weake skill offends</l>
                  <l>In making corners diſproportionate,</l>
                  <l>Some roome too narrow or ſome loft to a high;</l>
                  <l>Yet we well hope, if the whole ſtructure fall.</l>
                  <l>Your hands, like props, will ſerve to beare up all.</l>
                  <stage>Spoken by the Authour himſelfe:</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="dramatis_personae">
                  <pb facs="98"/>
                  <head>The Names of the Actors.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Agamemnon, <hi>King of Greece.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Clytemneſtra, <hi>The Queene.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tyndarus Clytemneſtra's <hi>father.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Strophius; <hi>Father to</hi> Pylades.</item>
                     <item>Two deare friends.
<list>
                           <item>Oreſtes, <hi>ſoon to</hi> Agam.</item>
                           <item>Pylades, <hi>ſoon to</hi> Stroph.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Electra <hi>Daughter to</hi> Agamemnon.</item>
                     <item>Aegyſtheus, <hi>Adulterer with</hi> Clytemneſtra.</item>
                     <item>Myſander, <hi>A Favorite; and Paraſite.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ajoung Childe of</hi> Aegyſtheus.</item>
                     <item>Nurſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Two Lords.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Chamberlaine.</item>
                     <item>A Boy.</item>
                     <item>Attendants.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="play">
                  <pb n="191" facs="98"/>
                  <head>THE TRAGEDIE. OF ORESTES.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 1.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>Enter as from warre, Agamemnon, Clytemneſtra, Oreſtes, Pylades, Aegyſteus, cum caeteris.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                           <l>NOw a faire bleſſing bleſſe my deareſt earth,</l>
                           <l>and like a Bride adorne thy royall brow,</l>
                           <l>with fruits rich Garland; a new married Bride</l>
                           <l>Unto thy King and Husband, who too long</l>
                           <l>Hath left thee widdowed: O, me thinks I ſee</l>
                           <stage>Turnes to the ſpectators:</stage>
                           <l>how all my Grecians with unſatiate lookes</l>
                           <l>and greedy eyes doe bid mee welcome home:</l>
                           <l>Each eare that heares the clamour ſeemes to grieve,</l>
                           <l>it cannot ſpeake, and give a (welcome King:</l>
                           <l>Come <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> let not anger make,</l>
                           <l>his wrinkled ſeat upon my loves faire brow;</l>
                           <l>I have too long beene abſent from thy bed,</l>
                           <l>Chide me for that anon, when arme in arme</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="192" facs="99"/>I ſhall relate thoſe projects in love termes,</l>
                           <l>which when they firſt were acted, made <hi>Mars</hi> feare</l>
                           <l>to ſee each man turn'd to a God of warre.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O my deare Lord, abſence of things wee love,</l>
                           <l>thus intermixt, makes them the ſweeter prove:</l>
                           <l>That your departure pierc'd my tender ſoule,</l>
                           <l>witneſſe thoſe Chriſtall floods which in my eyes</l>
                           <l>did make a ſea, when you ſhould goe to ſea,</l>
                           <l>thoſe ſtreames, which then flow'd from the veines of greife.</l>
                           <l>at your returne doe overflow the banks.</l>
                           <l>But 'tis with joy.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                           <l>Now theſe eares indeed</l>
                           <l>have chang'd their place: they which were wont to heare</l>
                           <l>no muſique but the ſummoning of warre</l>
                           <l>blowne thorow diſcords brazen inſtrument,</l>
                           <l>are bleſſed now with accents that doe fill</l>
                           <l>my age-dry'd veynes with youthfull blood againe.</l>
                           <l>Theſe eyes which had no other object once,</l>
                           <l>but <hi>Hector</hi> twixt the armes of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Troy,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>hewing downe men, and making every field</l>
                           <l>Flow with a ſea of blood, now ſee's blood flow.</l>
                           <l>In my <hi>Oreſtes</hi> cheekes: heaven bleſſe this plant</l>
                           <stage>Oreſtes kneeles.</stage>
                           <l>ſprung from the ſap of this juiceleſſe oake;</l>
                           <l>Now be thy branches greene, under whoſe ſhade</l>
                           <l>I may be ſhadowed from the heat of warre.</l>
                           <l>Riſe young <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> Oh how it glads my ſoule,</l>
                           <l>to ſee my <hi>Queene</hi> and <hi>Sonne,</hi> my <hi>Sonne</hi> and <hi>Queene.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>But come my Lord, true love ſtill hates delayes,</l>
                           <l>let no eares firſt be bleſſed with your breath,</l>
                           <l>till on my breſt reſting your wearied head,</l>
                           <l>You tell your warre, where that the field's your bed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                           <l>My <hi>Queen</hi> ſhal have her wil, ſee how times change.</l>
                           <l>I that laſt night thought all the world a ſea,</l>
                           <l>As if our common mother earth, had now</l>
                           <l>ſhot her ſelfe wholly into <hi>Neptunes</hi> armes,</l>
                           <l>and the ſtrong hindges of the world had crackt,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="193" facs="99"/>letting the moone fall into th' ſwelling waves,</l>
                           <l>ſuch watry mountaines oft did ſeeme to riſe,</l>
                           <l>and quite o'rwhelme us, all the winds at warre,</l>
                           <l>banded the ſea on to the others coaſts,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Jove</hi> thinking <hi>Neptune</hi> gan to ſtrive for heaven,</l>
                           <l>ſent a new ſea from thence, and with his thunder,</l>
                           <l>bad ſilence to the waves; they uncontrold,</l>
                           <l>kept on their noyſe, and let their fury ſwell,</l>
                           <l>turning heaven, earth, ſea, clouds, and all to hell.</l>
                           <l>Each Trojan that was ſaved then 'gan cry,</l>
                           <l>happy were they that did with <hi>Priam</hi> die.</l>
                           <l>It glads mee now to thinke, that that night was</l>
                           <l>no ſtarre, no, not <hi>Orion</hi> there appear'd;</l>
                           <l>But this night's turnd to day, and here doth ſhine,</l>
                           <l>for a good <hi>Omen,</hi> my embraced <hi>Queene.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>With whom her <hi>Agamemnon</hi> ſtill will ſtay,</l>
                           <l>till age and death ſhall beare him quite away.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt Agamemnon, Clytemneſtra, cum caeteris.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 2.</head>
                        <stage>Manet Egyſteus.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>And that ſhal be ere long. Tuſh, ſhall be'sſlow,</l>
                           <l>my vengefull thoughts tell mee thou now art dead.</l>
                           <l>Fie faint <hi>Apollo,</hi> weakling infant-God,</l>
                           <l>why wouldſt thou let lame <hi>Vulcan's</hi> hammers beat</l>
                           <l>downe thoſe brave Turrets which thou help'dſt to build?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Venus,</hi> I ſee thou art a woman now,</l>
                           <l>which here are like to take a double foyle;</l>
                           <l>for we, that whilome revel'd in thy campe</l>
                           <l>in the ſweet pleaſures of inceſtuous ſheets,</l>
                           <l>muſt leave our lov'd unſatiate deſires:</l>
                           <l>But now begin, thou blacke <hi>Eumenides,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>You hand-mayds of great <hi>Dis,</hi> let ſuch a flame</l>
                           <l>of anger burne mee, as doth <hi>Etnas</hi> forge,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="194" facs="100"/>on fury, on, our hate ſhall not die thus:</l>
                           <l>I'll draw my poyſonous arrow to the length,</l>
                           <l>that it may hit the mark and fly with ſtrength. <stage>Exit</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <head>SCEN. 3.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Oreſtes: Pylades.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Come now my deareſt friend, my other ſelf,</l>
                           <l>my empty ſoul is now fild to the top,</l>
                           <l>brimful with gladneſſe, and it muſt run o'r</l>
                           <l>into my deare friends heart: thoſe ſilver haires,</l>
                           <l>which time hath crown'd my Fathers brow withal,</l>
                           <l>do ſhine within mine eyes, and like the Sun,</l>
                           <l>extract all droſſie vapors from my ſoul.</l>
                           <l>Like as the earth, whom froſt haſt long benumb'd,</l>
                           <l>and brought an Icie drineſſe on her face,</l>
                           <l>her veines ſo open, at a ſudden thaw,</l>
                           <l>that all plants, fruits, flowers, and tender grafts,</l>
                           <l>kept as cloſe priſoners in their mothers womb,</l>
                           <l>ſtart out their heads, and on a ſudden doth</l>
                           <l>the ſad earth count'nance with a ſummer look.</l>
                           <l>So in this breſt, here in this breſt deare friend,</l>
                           <l>whiles <hi>Annus</hi> ten times circled in the world</l>
                           <l>ten clumzie winters, and ten lagging ſprings</l>
                           <l>hath (with my fathers abſence) frozen beene</l>
                           <l>all thoughts of joy, which now ſhall make a ſpring</l>
                           <l>in my refreſhed ſoul.</l>
                           <l>"Things that we daily ſee th'affections cloy,</l>
                           <l>"hopes long deſired bring the greateſt joy.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, but dear Couſin, give not the reines too much</l>
                           <l>to new received joyes, leſt that they run</l>
                           <l>with ſo much ſpeed, that they out-breath themſelves:</l>
                           <l>your Father is come home; but being come,</l>
                           <l>ſhould now ſome woful afterclap of fate</l>
                           <l>(which <hi>Omen Jove</hi> forbid ſhould come to paſſe)</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="195" facs="100"/>but take him hence again, and croſſe your joy;</l>
                           <l>each ſpark of gladneſs which you now conceive,</l>
                           <l>would turn a flame for grief: ſtill one extreame,</l>
                           <l>altering his courſe, turns to the diverſe theame.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Tuſh <hi>Pylades,</hi> talk not of what may be,</l>
                           <l>we may, indeed i'th' cleareſt afternoone</l>
                           <l>expect a ſtorm.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, and ſuch ſtormes oft come,</l>
                           <l>and wet ſhrewd too, before we get at home.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, but I'll be above all fatal power:</l>
                           <l>I that have ſuch a Father new come home,</l>
                           <l>I that have ſuch a friend, ſuch too rare gifts;</l>
                           <l>who gave me theſe gifts, thought, no ſcowling frown</l>
                           <l>of angry fortune e'r ſhould throw me down.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Call them not gifts <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> th'are but lent,</l>
                           <l>meere lendings friend, and lendings we muſt pay,</l>
                           <l>when e'r the owner ſhall appoint his day.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>True, <hi>Pylades,</hi> but owners uſe to warn</l>
                           <l>their debtors when they muſt bring in their ſumms:</l>
                           <l>but heavens tell me with favouring aſpects,</l>
                           <l>I ſtill muſt keep their lendings, and poſſeſs,</l>
                           <l>with frolick joy, all their lent happineſs.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Truſt not the heavens too much, although they ſmile,</l>
                           <l>good looks do mortal hearts too oft beguile:</l>
                           <l>the heavens are uſurers; and as oft 'tis ſeen</l>
                           <l>a full poucht churle give a moſt faire good e'en</l>
                           <l>to his poor Creditor: who, truſting that,</l>
                           <l>hath ſlackt this payment: on the morrow next</l>
                           <l>he hath been rooted out by th' tuskey boare,</l>
                           <l>which gave the faire good e'en the day before:</l>
                           <l>The heavens can do thus too—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Tuſh: mortals muſt</l>
                           <l>lean on the ſacred heaven with greater truſt;</l>
                           <l>but it grows far in night, come let us in</l>
                           <l>to morrow ſhall our joyes afreſh begin. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <pb n="196" facs="101"/>
                        <head>Scen. 4.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aegyſtheus, Clytemneſtra; with naked daggers: Agamemnon lying in his bed.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O Night, now only ſpread thy ſable wings</l>
                           <l>over this climate, gather all thy fogs</l>
                           <l>that they may meet, and make thy face more black:</l>
                           <l>let horrid murder take thee by the hand</l>
                           <l>and come along: I have a prodigie</l>
                           <l>equall to all the murders, all the blood</l>
                           <l>that hath been ſhed in all Troyes ten yeeres ſiege.</l>
                           <stage>He draws the curtain.</stage>
                           <l>So, ſnore returned King; good <hi>Morpheus</hi> hang</l>
                           <l>thy leaden weight upon his drowſie eyes,</l>
                           <l>let him not wake till he ſhall ſee himſelf</l>
                           <l>drencht in a ſea of his vermilion goare:</l>
                           <l>Thou do'ſt no Trojan, now, no <hi>Hector</hi> feare,</l>
                           <l>but yet I'll ſhew thee a new <hi>Hector</hi> here.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>See, I'll turn man too now, and to the hate</l>
                           <l>which women beare, I'll add a manly ſtrength:</l>
                           <l>my minde does tremble, what I meane to do.</l>
                           <l>Breath forth your vapor's, O ye Stygian powers!</l>
                           <l>and liſten to a hateful womans prayers.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Pluto</hi> ſtand by me for to aide my hand,</l>
                           <l>I may ſtrike home now, and perform an act</l>
                           <l>may make <hi>Medea</hi> bluſh ſhe thought not of:</l>
                           <l>Could the old dry bon'd dotard ever dreame,</l>
                           <l>now he had drawn forth all his ſtrength abroad,</l>
                           <l>he could be welcome to lie bed-rid here,</l>
                           <l>and ſupple his numb'd joynts in my freſh armes?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Spoke like a queene, ſpoke like <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> love!</l>
                           <l>Now great <hi>Thyeſtes Genius,</hi> which didſt prompt</l>
                           <l>me to this act; Come, be ſpectator now!</l>
                           <l>and ſee revenge for Athens bloody feaſt.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="197" facs="101"/>And thou wrong'd <hi>Clytemneſtra</hi> call to mind,</l>
                           <l>how his unſatiate, luſtful loath'd deſire,</l>
                           <l>doted on every female face he ſaw,</l>
                           <l>rap't the Prieſts daughter, and ſo brought a plague</l>
                           <l>on all the Grecian hoaſt:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clytem.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, yes,</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>yes.</l>
                           <l>And rap't young <hi>Briſeis</hi> from <hi>Achilles</hi> bed.</l>
                           <l>Crowd all revengful thoughts into this houre,</l>
                           <l>now let thy ſword let out that luſtful blood.</l>
                           <stage>Egiſtheus ſtabs him.</stage>
                           <l>Wound him <hi>Egyſtheus,</hi> kill him not at once,</l>
                           <l>wee'll be true Tyrants, let him feel he dies.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                           <l>Help <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> help me, my deare Queen.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes dotard, I will help thee, thus, yes thus:</l>
                           <stage>She ſtabs him.</stage>
                           <l>Remember the Prieſts daughter: this for her,</l>
                           <l>and this for <hi>Briſeis:</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                           <l>See, my Grecians, ſee,</l>
                           <l>your King which you ſo gladly entertain'd.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Sol,</hi> hide thy ſelf in everlaſting night,</l>
                           <l>or when thou riſeſt, let thy bluſhing face</l>
                           <l>make theſe to bluſh.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clytem.</speaker>
                           <l>Ay, ſo, curſe on, curſe on:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                           <l>O <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> O my once deare wife,</l>
                           <l>is this the entertainment that thou giv'ſt</l>
                           <l>thy new come husband? gratulates thou thus</l>
                           <l>my ten yeares abſence? See theſe froſty haires</l>
                           <l>would even move <hi>Hecuba</hi> to pity me;</l>
                           <l>Look on theſe aged armes which in this bed,</l>
                           <l>thought to have been bleſſ'd with thy kind imbrace.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clytem.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, mine or <hi>Caſſandra's,</hi> old adulterer.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                           <l>Kinſman <hi>Aegyſtheus;</hi> O my deareſt wife</l>
                           <l>whom ſhall I call? me thinks you both are mine.</l>
                           <l>What <hi>Titius,</hi> what <hi>Megaera</hi> hath put on</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> and my <hi>Clytemneſtra's</hi> ſhapes?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Calſt thou us friends?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Stabs him againe.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                           <l>O be not ſo, and I'll not call you ſo:</l>
                           <l>Let not your coward weapons wound this head,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="198" facs="102"/>that earſt did ſcorne to ſhrink at <hi>Priams</hi> blow.</l>
                           <l>O hew me not down thus for my ſons ſake,</l>
                           <l>deare <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> for <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſake.</l>
                           <l>Is this the Trojan tale! how I ſhould tell,</l>
                           <l>that here great <hi>Hector</hi> ſlew <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>and here that <hi>Meontiades</hi> was ſlaine,</l>
                           <l>and poor <hi>Protheſilaus</hi> deare to <hi>Lacdamie:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>I thought to tell how theſe men loſt their blood;</l>
                           <l>and ſee my blood is thus let forth at home.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegy.</speaker>
                           <l>Is your hot blood yet cold!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>breath dotard, do.</l>
                           <l>you ſhall have gaps enough to let your ſoul</l>
                           <l>finde a free paſſage to his deſerved flames.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Agam.</speaker>
                           <l>No pitty yet? O then, no pitty light</l>
                           <l>on you, nor yours; but let dire revenge</l>
                           <l>come learn how ſhe may after handle you:</l>
                           <l>O, I am drown'd in blood, and now muſt yeild</l>
                           <l>to murderers weapons; treaſon win's the field.</l>
                           <l>Alas this coming home hath had ſmall joy;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Argos</hi> hath worſer foes then ever Troy. <stage>Moritur,</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Now I am <hi>Clytemneſtra</hi> right, now I deſerve</l>
                           <l>to add one more to the three Furies, now</l>
                           <l>do I count this more then my nuptial night;</l>
                           <l>'Tis mine, tis thine, <hi>Egyſtheus,</hi> and none elſe</l>
                           <l>ſhall ſhare a minute of this right, but we.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Me thinks I now go equal with the ſtarrs,</l>
                           <l>and my proud head toucheth the higheſt pole;</l>
                           <l>Hark, hell applauds me, and me thinks I heare <stage>A noiſe</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> tell me, I have done enough:</l>
                           <l>And now I kiſſe my hands, whilſt yet they beare</l>
                           <l>this tincture on them, and embrace my Queen,</l>
                           <l>now made my love; lets in, this night the Fates</l>
                           <l>have amply fed us with revengeful cates.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <pb n="199" facs="102"/>
                        <head>Scen. 5.</head>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Oreſtes, <hi>as from his Bed, unbutton'd in ſlippers, a Torch in his hand.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <l>What horrid dreams affright me? I ſee nought</l>
                        <l>that I ſhould fear, and yet me thinks I fear.</l>
                        <l>Mine eyes ſcarce clos'd, my buſie Fancy ſaw</l>
                        <l>a ſight that daſht all comforts of the day:</l>
                        <l>me thought my Father lying in his Tent,</l>
                        <l>hateful <hi>Achylles,</hi> for his wronged love</l>
                        <l>comes in with <hi>Briſeis,</hi> and they two let forth</l>
                        <l>ſtreams of freſh blood from out his aged ſide,</l>
                        <l>with that his Eccho'd ſchrich did make me wake;</l>
                        <l>but I remembred then he was come home,</l>
                        <l>and yet I'll ſee him, ſtill me thinks I quake.</l>
                        <l>Do I ſtill dream? Are not mine eyes unclos'd?</l>
                        <stage>He draws the Curtain.</stage>
                        <l>Is this a Torch? yea, 'tis, it burns, I ſee</l>
                        <l>I am awake, do not delude me Night!</l>
                        <l>Now ſtand on tip-toes <hi>Atlas,</hi> lift heaven higher,</l>
                        <l>I may have air enough to breath my woes in,</l>
                        <l>O let me yet recal thy poſting Soul!</l>
                        <l>if <hi>Charon</hi> have not hurried thee too faſt,</l>
                        <l>if yet thou haſt not drunk on <hi>Lethes</hi> Pool,</l>
                        <l>come back, and tell me who it is this night,</l>
                        <l>hath done this deed far blacker than the night?</l>
                        <l>Ah! Art thou fled paſt call? Why, thou wert old,</l>
                        <l>me thinks thou ſhouldſt not haſte ſo faſt away!</l>
                        <l>VVas it for this thou ſwe'tſt ſo oft in Arms!</l>
                        <l>Was it for this that the froth ſwelling foam,</l>
                        <l>when thy Ships top toucht heaven, and deep plac'd hell;</l>
                        <l>that thou muſt yet eſcape curl'd <hi>Neptune's</hi> waves,</l>
                        <l>to be a <hi>Palinurus</hi> in thy ſhoar,</l>
                        <l>there drown thy aged locks in Crimſon gore?</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="200" facs="103"/>O, if one ſpark yet of thy Princely Soul</l>
                        <l>remaine within this trunk, now let it ſhine</l>
                        <l>and light mine ignorant eyes to reade the names</l>
                        <l>of theſe night vultures, whoſe devouring bills</l>
                        <l>have made a <hi>Titius</hi> of thy royall corps:</l>
                        <l>who did not feare great <hi>Agamemnons</hi> ſleep?</l>
                        <l>Arm, arm your ſelves all you all-potent Gods,</l>
                        <l>you which we term juſt Miniſters of heaven!</l>
                        <l>ſhoot forked lightning from the marble poale,</l>
                        <l>let the all-ſeeing eye of heaven ſhoot flames</l>
                        <l>which may parch up the marrow from their bones,</l>
                        <l>ſhould they lie coucht i'th breſt o'th' Thunderer,</l>
                        <l>or be entrencht with guards of furies fierce,</l>
                        <l>heaven, earth nor hell, ſhould keep them from my ſword.</l>
                        <l>Doſt thou ſleep <hi>Jove!</hi> O, couldſt thou ſnore ſo faſt,</l>
                        <l>and let thy great vicegerent thus be torn?</l>
                        <l>Some of th'immortal powers have had fathers,</l>
                        <l>and know what 'tis to have them murdered thus.</l>
                        <l>But I turn woman now: O, I rave out</l>
                        <l>my paſſions; do, grief, pour out thy ſelf,</l>
                        <l>that thou mayſt make room in my empty heart,</l>
                        <l>to fill it with revenge.</l>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 6.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Clytemneſtra, Aegyſtheus, in night-robes.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>How now? what ayles our ſon, how now <hi>Oreſtes!</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O ſome are come now to help me to grieve:</l>
                           <l>See, mother, ſee, your husband and my father,</l>
                           <l>the King of Greece, great Shephard of his Land,</l>
                           <l>ſee, ſee him here:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>She faines her ſelfe to ſwoun, Egy. catcheth her falling.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O help me now good heaven to keep my ſex,</l>
                           <l>let me diſſemble.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Help (my Lords) the Queen.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why hinder'd you my ſoul, that whilſt he liv'd,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="201" facs="103"/>was linkt to his, and would too now have fled</l>
                           <l>with wing'd deſire to have been with him!</l>
                           <l>What doe I live for! <hi>Agamemon</hi> ſlain!</l>
                           <l>My Lord, my King, husband, wake my Lord,</l>
                           <l>what bloody Trojan followed thee from thence</l>
                           <l>to kill thee here? could he not one night</l>
                           <l>have let me reſted in thy ſweet embraces?</l>
                           <l>Muſt he for ſureneſſe make ſo many holes,</l>
                           <l>for thy ſweet ſoul to fly to be a God?</l>
                           <l>O let my teares be balm to theſe thy wounds,</l>
                           <l>let my lips kiſſe, and warm thy gellid lips;</l>
                           <l>let my haire wipe theſe clots of blood away</l>
                           <l>from thy age-honor'd ſide: O dry your teares,</l>
                           <l>joyn knees and prayers with me, awake ye Gods,</l>
                           <stage>They both kneele.</stage>
                           <l>and ſend our vows, ſince we can ſend no wounds:</l>
                           <l>Come ſon, we women ſtill know how to curſe.</l>
                           <l>Let him that did it be an Adulterer.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Faith ſhe begins well, ſure ſhe knows the man.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>aſide.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Let him be conſcious, he hath don a deed</l>
                           <l>deſerves revenge, whether it fall or no:</l>
                           <l>Let him for ever beare in mind this night,</l>
                           <l>and who 'twas helpt him in this bloody act.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegiſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, hee'll remember how you curſe him now.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>aſide.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Orſt.</speaker>
                           <l>If ever he have children, let them be</l>
                           <l>murdered before his face, that they may know</l>
                           <l>how nature binds a father and a ſon.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Now hands I thank you, now my ſoul grows glad,</l>
                           <l>had not he griev'd thus, I had loſt revenge.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>But come my ſon, now let us talk of graves,</l>
                           <l>of Epitaphs, and tombs, and's ſoul being fled,</l>
                           <stage>Draw the curtaine and carry him away.</stage>
                           <l>let's lap his Trunk up in a ſheet of lead.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt Clytemnestra, and Aegyſtheus. Manent Oreſt.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="202" facs="104"/>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Methinks I ſee a Tragedy at hand,</l>
                           <l>to which this night hath as a Prologue bin;</l>
                           <l>I'll make a prayer now worthy <hi>Atreus</hi> grandchild,</l>
                           <l>let the foul Adder ſting me as I walk,</l>
                           <l>the poyſonous toad belch her black venom forth</l>
                           <l>in my deſpiſed face, let it be thought</l>
                           <l>I never had a father, but ſome monſter</l>
                           <l>bred by a ſlimy exhalation,</l>
                           <l>If my revenge fly not with ample wing:</l>
                           <l>till then reſt ſoul, hate told, may loſe his ſting.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 2.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Caſſandra ſola as a mad Propheteſſe.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>O ye dead Trojans leape within your graves!</l>
                           <l>O mother that thou hadſt lived this night!</l>
                           <l>Now thou'ldſt be glad t'have loſt ſo many ſons:</l>
                           <l>the Grecians are reveng'd upon themſelves,</l>
                           <l>I thank thee ſoul, that thou keeptſt here till now</l>
                           <l>to let me ſee Greece overcome it ſelf;</l>
                           <l>I live, I live, I'm here, I live to ſee't:</l>
                           <l>I do not dream on't, no, I ſaw the blood</l>
                           <l>run from his ſide, whole Cataracts, all Greece.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Apollo,</hi> how am I bound now for this</l>
                           <l>that I do only ſee this happineſſe?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hecuba, Priam,</hi> young <hi>Aſtianax.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Look <hi>Hecuba,</hi> Greece now doth act your woes,</l>
                           <l>laugh <hi>Hecuba,</hi> for now <hi>Electra</hi> weeps:</l>
                           <l>and <hi>Tyndarus</hi> he knows not what to do:</l>
                           <l>Come little Cuz, come my <hi>Aſtianax,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Oreſtes</hi> is in a worſe caſe then thou.</l>
                           <l>Still I had others for to weep with me,</l>
                           <l>but none are left to laugh now, but my ſelf:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="203" facs="104"/>What ſhould he feare at home? A conqueror feare!</l>
                           <l>Tis done, 'tis done, leave fighting <hi>Hector,</hi> leave,</l>
                           <l>the Grecians meane to fight againſt themſelves,</l>
                           <l>from <hi>Tyndarus</hi> the firſt brand took fire</l>
                           <l>which burnt down Troy: and now an other here</l>
                           <l>kindles from him, to ſet a fire Greece,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Graia juvenca venit, quae ſe, patremque virumque</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Perdidit, Io laetor, Graja juvenca venit.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hellen,</hi> thy ſiſter <hi>Hellen,</hi> nay ſhee's thine:</l>
                           <l>who could have thought that <hi>Hector</hi> being ſlaine,</l>
                           <l>old <hi>Priam</hi> made a ſacrifice to death,</l>
                           <l>Troy turn'd to cinders, poor <hi>Andromacha</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>dragg'd by her hair to death; <hi>Aſtianax</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>ſent out o'th world before he well came in,</l>
                           <l>Ha, ha, who could have thought after all this</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Caſſandra</hi> ſhould have ever laught againe?</l>
                           <l>One hour of laughter following many yeares</l>
                           <l>of diſcontent, doth help to ſweeten teares <stage>Exit.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Actus 2. Scena 2.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aegyſtheus, Clytemneſtra.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegy.</speaker>
                           <l>Fair morning to my Queen, nay more, my love,</l>
                           <l>how likes my ſweet her change of bed-fellow?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Look as an hallow leafeleſſe failing oake,</l>
                           <l>to whom, for that h'hath bin her weight too long,</l>
                           <l>the earth denies to lend him moyſture, ſo</l>
                           <l>his ſap failes, and he ſtands on a green</l>
                           <l>'mongſt ſprouting Elms, that they may ſeeme more freſh</l>
                           <l>whilſt hee's but held a monument of years.</l>
                           <l>Such one ſeem'd <hi>Agamemnon;</hi> a dry tree:</l>
                           <l>thou like a ſprouting Elme, whom I embrace</l>
                           <l>like twining Ivy, with theſe now bleſt armes,</l>
                           <l>bleſt whilſt this treaſure in them they hold lockt:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="204" facs="105"/>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O who'd not do a murder for a woman!</l>
                           <l>Heaven had but two things for the Gods reſerv'd,</l>
                           <l>fire, and women: when with Giant ſtrength</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Promotheus</hi> had tane one, <hi>Jove</hi> in his rage</l>
                           <l>threw him the to'ther, bad him keep 'em both.</l>
                           <l>O th'are rare creatures, they have ſuch <hi>Meanders,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Their teares will come and go with ſuch brave art!</l>
                           <l>Come now my Queen, one ſweet Ambroſian kiſſe;</l>
                           <l>O <hi>Nectar!</hi> prethee hadſt thou taught thy teares</l>
                           <l>how they ſhould flow before?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>No, truſt me love,</l>
                           <l>I knew my teares would ſoon be at command,</l>
                           <l>and faith the boy had almoſt made me weep</l>
                           <l>really once. Were not my curſes rare?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, all was woman-like: but yet that boy</l>
                           <l>he took it deeply; would he were with his father,</l>
                           <l>ſo gon, it skills not how; were he away,</l>
                           <l>we would act freely all our luſtful play.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O but my love! hee's mine: Nor can the raven</l>
                           <l>dig her ſharp beake into her own birds breſt:</l>
                           <l>He will forget his father: woe will breake;</l>
                           <l>'tis not the greateſt griefe that moſt doth ſpeake.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, but hee'll beare ſtill a ſuſpicious eye;</l>
                           <l>and who in bloody Scenes doth act a part,</l>
                           <l>thinks every eye doth penetrate his heart.</l>
                           <l>Nor can we ere be free, or I enjoy</l>
                           <l>true pleaſures; we muſt be but theeves at moſt,</l>
                           <l>cloſe in delights, and have a Pander ſtill</l>
                           <l>to be a Factor 'twixt thy bed and mine:</l>
                           <l>this we could have before, what now we do,</l>
                           <l>the world ſhould ſee done, and applaud us too.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why my deare Love, I that would ſet my hand</l>
                           <l>to ſtain my marriage ſheets with husbands blood,</l>
                           <l>would let theſe hands, inſtructed now in ill,</l>
                           <l>not leave one arm of that uprooted tree;</l>
                           <l>Could but <hi>Aegiſtheus</hi> give me any hope,</l>
                           <l>that from this top there ſhould one ſpreading branch</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="205" facs="105"/>grow up and flouriſh.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Now thou art thy ſelf;</l>
                           <l>yes, yes my love, there ſhall one ſpring from us</l>
                           <l>ſhall be a lofty Pine, let this be cropt;</l>
                           <l>murder muſt murder guard, guilt add to guilt,</l>
                           <l>after one drop, whole ſtreams of blood be ſpilt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>walks away.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <head>Scen. 3.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Pylades, Oreſtes, Electra, Strophius.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Dear friend, what mean you, to o'rwhelm your ſelf</l>
                           <l>in ſuch a ſea of grief?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Father! deare <hi>Agamemnon!</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay ceaſe this tempeſt, thou haſt loſt a father,</l>
                           <l>why, 'tis but change, my father ſhall be thine,</l>
                           <l>I'll be thy brother, nay, I'll be thy ſelfe,</l>
                           <l>weep when thou weep'ſt, and where thou go'ſt I'll goe,</l>
                           <l>and bring thee on thy pilgrimage of woe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Brother, look up; have not I loſt a father?</l>
                           <l>yes, yes, and would a river of freſh teares</l>
                           <l>turne <hi>Lethes</hi> ſtream, and bring him from the wharf,</l>
                           <l>with a North gale of windy blowing ſighs,</l>
                           <l>I would expire my ſoul, become all teares.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stro.</speaker>
                           <l>Come, you have loſt a father, I a brother,</l>
                           <l>the Queen a Husband, all the Land a King;</l>
                           <l>yet all this but a man; therefore muſt dye:</l>
                           <l>Our woes may all be in one balance poys'd.</l>
                           <l>His book of life the Fates had over-read,</l>
                           <l>and turn'd the leafe where his laſt period ſtood.</l>
                           <l>Now an immortal wreath circles his brow,</l>
                           <l>and makes him King in heaven, who was before</l>
                           <l>at moſt a God on earth: Hence difference ſprings,</l>
                           <l>Kings are earths Gods, and Gods are heavenly Kings.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Let us joyne words then now, and Swan-like ſing</l>
                           <l>the doleful dirge to a departed King:</l>
                           <l>Thou friend didſt of this miſery divine,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="206" facs="106"/>therefore the burthen of the ſong is mine:</l>
                           <l>words Orators for woe, which plead the cauſe,</l>
                           <l>when griefe's the judge, and ſighs are all the laws,</l>
                           <l>each one a ſob for <hi>Diapaſon</hi> beares,</l>
                           <l>our tunes ſhall drown the muſick of the ſpheares:</l>
                           <l>O what <hi>Hirudo</hi> with unſatiate thirſt,</l>
                           <l>could draw the blood from out thoſe Princely veines,</l>
                           <l>from whence flow'd comfort to ſo many ſouls!</l>
                           <stage>Spies his mother, goes to her.</stage>
                           <l>Mother, when wept you laſt? here take a ſcarf</l>
                           <l>dry your eyes: now by—you need none,</l>
                           <l>what ſhine of comfort hath dry'd up your teares?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Our ſon's too ſawcie with his mother Queen:</l>
                           <l>Why, Sir, ſhall you tell us a time to weep?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Us? good: Who is't makes the plurality?</l>
                           <l>'Twas wont to be my father: does he live?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Sir, curb this laviſh ſpeech, or I'll forget</l>
                           <l>you are my ſon, and make you but a ſubject.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Good Couſin add not diſobedience</l>
                           <l>unto your mothers griefs.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>My mother, no,</l>
                           <l>ſhe is not here, no, ſhe hath hid her ſelf</l>
                           <l>in ſome odd nooke, or angle unperceiv'd,</l>
                           <l>ſhe might not ſee this impious ſtygian world.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aegyſtus,</hi> canſt thou ſtill ſuffer thy dull ſword i'th ſheath?</l>
                           <l>Take the rank head from this o'r-growing weed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stro.</speaker>
                           <l>Remember <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> he's your ſon.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>He is ſo, and I'll learn him to be ſo:</l>
                           <l>Had I a brazen bull, it ſhould be heat</l>
                           <l>hotter then for the Tyrant: Diſobedient!</l>
                           <l>More harſh then Adders hiſſes is thy voyce,</l>
                           <l>Sir, you ſhall dye, but with a living death,</l>
                           <l>he ſtill ſhall live, but live to know he dies;</l>
                           <l>who ſtrait threats death, knows not to Tyranize.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt Aegyſtheus, Clytemneſtra.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stro.</speaker>
                           <l>What temper's grown on the diſtracted Queen?</l>
                           <l>Hath grief, conceiv'd for her late husbands death,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="207" facs="106"/>brought her ſo far, ſhe hath forgot her ſelf?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>No Uncle, no, by — I do ſuſpect.</l>
                           <l>O, my prophetick ſoul divines much ill!</l>
                           <l>Well, I will flie. But hear this ſtratagem,</l>
                           <l>it ſhall be rumor'd i'th eare of the Court</l>
                           <l>I was found dead, I'll put a new ſhape on,</l>
                           <l>and live alone, to heare how things go here.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, not alone <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> whilſt I live,</l>
                           <l>ſhouldſt make thy bed upon the rigid Alps,</l>
                           <l>or frozen <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> wrapt in ſheets of ſnow,</l>
                           <l>I'd freeze unto thy ſide; we will tell tales</l>
                           <l>of Trojan warriers, and depoſed Kings.</l>
                           <l>Tell of ſtrange ſhipwrack, of old <hi>Priams</hi> fall,</l>
                           <l>how mad <hi>Andromacha</hi> did teare her hayre,</l>
                           <l>when the wild horſes tore brave <hi>Hectors</hi> limbs:</l>
                           <l>Wee'l think they all do come, and weep with us;</l>
                           <l>grief loves companions, and it helpeth woe,</l>
                           <l>when it heares every one groane forth his, Oh!</l>
                           <l>it eaſeth much, and our plaints fall more ſweet,</l>
                           <l>when a whole conſort in one tune do meet.</l>
                           <l>The half-dead ſhip-man, which hath ſhipwrack borne,</l>
                           <l>ſeeing many drown'd, it makes him leſſe to mourn:</l>
                           <l>It made <hi>Deucalion</hi> care the leſſe to die,</l>
                           <l>when he had all the world in company.</l>
                           <l>Thus we will ſit, and our teares turnes ſhall keep,</l>
                           <l>thou for thy father, I for thee will weep:</l>
                           <l>If actors on the Stage having no cauſe,</l>
                           <l>but for to win an hearers hands applauſe,</l>
                           <l>can let fall teares, wee'l think we Actors be,</l>
                           <l>and only do but play griefs Tragedie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, but deare friend, ſhould we but act a part,</l>
                           <l>the play being ended, paſſion left the heart,</l>
                           <l>and we ſhould ſhare of joy: but my whole age</l>
                           <l>muſt never move from off this woful Stage:</l>
                           <l>But we muſt take our leave; Uncle, farwel,</l>
                           <l>remember what I ſpake; and Siſter, you</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="208" facs="107"/>muſt tarry here, my thoughts ſhall buſied be,</l>
                           <l>to finde the man that let my father blood.</l>
                           <l>Can I but finde <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> did conſent,</l>
                           <l>to ſpill one drop, O, I would pierce his heart</l>
                           <l>with venom'd daggers, and ſo butcher him,</l>
                           <l>that all <hi>Apollos</hi> skill in phyſicke hearbs,</l>
                           <l>nor <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> th' <hi>Epidaurian</hi> God,</l>
                           <l>ſhould keepe his ſoule out of <hi>Enio's</hi> hand;</l>
                           <l>Come my deare friend; to all the reſt farewell;</l>
                           <l>If heaven relate it not, I'll know't from hell.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt Pylades, Oreſtes.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 4.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aegyſteus, Clytemneſtra, Myſander, Strophius, Electra another way.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>What, is <hi>Oreſtes</hi> fled? ſure there's ſome plot,</l>
                           <l>if you deare Queen, but ſearch <hi>Electra</hi> well,</l>
                           <l>you'll finde ſhe knowes whither her brothers gone.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>If in her heart there be but lodg'd a thought</l>
                           <l>unknown to mee, this hand ſhall rip her breſt,</l>
                           <l>and ſearch her inparts, but I'll finde it out.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Myſander,</hi> call <hi>Electra.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegiſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, were that moat tane from our comforts beams,</l>
                           <l>no cloud e'r then could overſhade our joyes,</l>
                           <l>his life muſt be cut off without delay,</l>
                           <l>miſchiefe, by miſchiefe findes the ſafeſt way:</l>
                           <l>But here's <hi>Electra.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
                           <l>Why! how now Minion! what a blubbering ſtill!</l>
                           <l>Huſwife, pray where's your brother, wher's my ſonne?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Mother, pray where's my father, wher's your husband?</l>
                           <stage>Enter Stropheus, and ſpeaks.</stage>
                           <l>Haile to my my gracious Queene, here's one at doore.</l>
                           <l>brings you a meſſage, hee will not relate</l>
                           <l>to any, but your ſelfe, he ſaies tis ſad.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="209" facs="107"/>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, the more diſmal, the more welcome 'tis.</l>
                           <l>But as for you—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Good mother do your worſt,</l>
                           <l>no plague can ever make me more accurſt,</l>
                           <l>nothing is worſe then death, that I'll not flie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, life is worſe to thoſe that faine would die.</l>
                           <l>But where's the meſſenger?</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 5.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Nuncius.</stage>
                        <l>What whirlwinde riſing from the womb of earth</l>
                        <l>doth raiſe huge <hi>Pelion</hi> unto <hi>Oſſa's</hi> top,</l>
                        <l>that both being heapt, I ſtand upon them both</l>
                        <l>and with an hundred <hi>Stentor</hi>-drowning voice,</l>
                        <l>relate unto the world the ſaddeſt tale</l>
                        <l>that ever burdned the weak jaws of man?</l>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, what portentous newes? Amaze us not,</l>
                           <l>tell us what e'r it be.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                           <l>Were my mind ſettled, would the gellid feare,</l>
                           <l>that freeſeth up my ſenſe, ſet free my ſpeech,</l>
                           <l>I would unfold a tale which makes my heart</l>
                           <l>throb in my intrals, when I ſeem to ſee't.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt</speaker>
                           <l>Relate it quickly, hold's not in ſuſpence.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                           <l>Upon the mount of yonder riſing cliffe,</l>
                           <l>which th'earth hath made a bulwark for the ſea,</l>
                           <l>whoſe peareleſſe head is from the ſtreams ſo high,</l>
                           <l>that whoſoe'r looks down, his brain will ſwim</l>
                           <l>with a <hi>vertigo:</hi> The ſpace remov d ſo far</l>
                           <l>the object from the eye, that a tall ſhip</l>
                           <l>ſeem'd a ſwift flying bird: upon this top</l>
                           <l>ſaw I two men making complaints to heaven,</l>
                           <l>one's voyce diſtinctly ſtill cry'd, Father, King,</l>
                           <l>great <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> whoſe diviner ſoul</l>
                           <l>fled from thy corps, exil'd by butchers hands:</l>
                           <l>his friend ſtill ſought to keepe his dying life</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="210" facs="108"/>with words of comfort, that it ſhould not ruſh</l>
                           <l>too violently upon the hands of Fate.</l>
                           <l>He deafe as ſea, to which he made his plaints,</l>
                           <l>ſtill cryed out, <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> I will come,</l>
                           <l>and find thy bleſſed ſoul where e'r it walk;</l>
                           <l>in what faire Temple of <hi>Elyſium</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>ſo e'r it be, my ſoul ſhall find it out.</l>
                           <l>With that his friend knit him within his arms,</l>
                           <l>ſtriving to hold him, but when twas no boot,</l>
                           <l>they hand in hand, thus plung'd into the maine;</l>
                           <l>ſtrait they aroſe, and ſtriv'd (me thought) for life,</l>
                           <l>but ſwelling <hi>Neptune</hi> not regarding friends,</l>
                           <l>wrapt their embraced limbs in following waves:</l>
                           <l>Until at laſt their deare departing ſouls</l>
                           <l>haſtned to Styx, and I no more could ſee.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stro.</speaker>
                           <l>O 'twas <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> 'twas my <hi>Pylades,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>which arm in arm did follow him to death.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>O my <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> O my deareſt brother!</l>
                           <l>'Tis he, 'tis he, that thus hath drown'd himſelf.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, then if <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and his ſon</l>
                           <l>have brought their leaſe of life to the full end:</l>
                           <l>I am <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> ſon, and the next heire,</l>
                           <l>to ſit in <hi>Argos</hi> Throne of Majeſty.</l>
                           <l>Thanks to our <hi>Alpheus</hi> ſea, who as 't'ad ſtriv'd</l>
                           <l>to gratifie <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> rais'd his force,</l>
                           <l>and gathered all his waters to one place,</l>
                           <l>they might be deep enough to drown <hi>Oreſtes:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>But come my Queen, let us command a feaſt.</l>
                           <l>To get a kingdome, who'ld not think it good,</l>
                           <l>to ſwim unto it through a ſea of blood?</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="act">
                     <pb n="211" facs="108"/>
                     <head>Actus 3.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Tyndarus, Miſander.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Our daughter ſends for us? how fares ſhe? well?</l>
                           <l>ſhe mournes I'm ſure for her husbands death.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, ſhe took it ſadly at the firſt:</l>
                           <l>But time hath leſſen'd it.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tind.</speaker>
                           <l>I, grief ſoon ends</l>
                           <l>that flows in teares; they ſtill are womens friends:</l>
                           <l>But how is't rumord now in <hi>Argos,</hi> though,</l>
                           <l>that <hi>Agamemnon</hi> died?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, he was old,</l>
                           <l>and death thought beſt to ſeize on him at home.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>'Twas a long home, he got by coming home:</l>
                           <l>Well, well, <hi>Miſander,</hi> I like not the courſe,</l>
                           <l>the peoples murmure makes my cheeks to bluſh.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                           <l>My gracious Lord, who truſts their idle murmur,</l>
                           <l>muſt never let the bluſh go from his cheek;</l>
                           <l>They are like flags growing on muddy banks,</l>
                           <l>whoſe weak thin heads blown with one blaſt of winde,</l>
                           <l>they all will ſhake, and bend themſelves one way:</l>
                           <l>Great minds muſt not eſteem what ſmall tongues ſay.</l>
                           <l>All things in ſtate muſt ever have this end,</l>
                           <l>the vulgar ſhould both ſuffer, and commend,</l>
                           <l>if not for love, for feare; great Majeſty</l>
                           <l>ſhould do thoſe things which vulgars dare not fee.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>O, Sir, but thoſe that do commend for feare,</l>
                           <l>do in their hearts a ſecret hatred beare.</l>
                           <l>Ever learn this; the trueſt praiſe indeed,</l>
                           <l>muſt from the heart, and not from words proceed.</l>
                           <l>I feare ſome ſoul play: doth <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> meane,</l>
                           <l>then totally for to inveſt himſelf</l>
                           <l>in <hi>Agamemnons</hi> ſeate? Where's young <hi>Oreſtes?</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Miſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Why my Lord, he for the great grief conceiv'd</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="212" facs="109"/>being young, not knowing well to rule himſelfe</l>
                           <l>with ſway of reaſon, ranne upon his death</l>
                           <l>and threw himſelfe with my lord <hi>Strophius</hi> ſonne,</l>
                           <l>into the midſt of <hi>Alpheus,</hi> ſo was drown'd,</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ty.</speaker>
                           <l>How took my daughter that?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, wiſely too,</l>
                           <l>and like her ſelfe; not being in deſpaire:</l>
                           <l>her royal wombe will bring forth many more,</l>
                           <l>ſhall be as deare as e'r <hi>Oreſtes</hi> was.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>I feare heaven cannot look with equall eyes</l>
                           <l>upon ſo many deaths, but meanes to ſend</l>
                           <l>plague after plague; for in a wretched ſtate,</l>
                           <l>one ill begets another diſmal Fate:</l>
                           <l>But go and tell my daughter I will come,</l>
                           <l>and help to ſolemnize her nuptial night:</l>
                           <l>Her haſty wedding, and the old Kings neglect,</l>
                           <l>makes my conjectural ſoul ſome ill ſuſpect.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Scen. 2.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Oreſtes, and Pylades.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>If ever God lent any thing to earth,</l>
                           <l>whereby it ſeem'd to ſympathize with heaven,</l>
                           <l>it is this ſacred friendſhip: Gordian knot</l>
                           <l>which Kings, nor Gods, nor Fortune can undoe.</l>
                           <l>O what Horoſcopus, what conſtellation,</l>
                           <l>held in our birth ſo great an influence,</l>
                           <l>which one affection in two minds unites?</l>
                           <l>How hath my woe been thine, my fatal ill</l>
                           <l>hath ſtill been parted, and one ſhare been thine!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, deareſt friend, ſuppoſe my caſe were thine,</l>
                           <l>and I had loſt a father, wouldſt not thou</l>
                           <l>in the like ſort participate my grief?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, witneſſe heaven I would.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="213" facs="109"/>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>So, now thou haſt loſt a father.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>True, <hi>Pylades,</hi> thou putſt me well in mind,</l>
                           <l>I have loſt a father, a dear, dear father,</l>
                           <l>a King, a brave old King, a noble ſouldier,</l>
                           <l>and yet he was murdered! O my forgetful ſoul!</l>
                           <l>Why ſhould not I now draw my vengeful ſword,</l>
                           <l>and ſtrait-way ſheath it in the murderers heart?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Minos</hi> ſhould never have vacation,</l>
                           <l>whilſt any of our progeny remain'd.</l>
                           <l>Well, I will go, and ſo maſſacre him,</l>
                           <l>I'll teach him how to murder an old man,</l>
                           <l>a King, my father, and ſo daſtardly</l>
                           <l>to kill him in his bed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Alas, <hi>Oreſtes!</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Grief doth diſtract thee: who is't thou wilt kill?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, he, or ſhe, or they that kill'd my father.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>I, who are they?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, I know not yet,</l>
                           <l>but I will know.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Stay thy vengeful thoughts,</l>
                           <l>and ſince thus long we have eſtrang'd our ſelves</l>
                           <l>from friends and parents, let's think why it is,</l>
                           <l>and why we had it noiſed in the Court,</l>
                           <l>we both were dead; the cauſe was thy revenge,</l>
                           <l>that if by any ſecret private meanes,</l>
                           <l>we might but learn who 'twas that drench'd their ſwords</l>
                           <l>in thy deare fathers blood, we then would rouze</l>
                           <l>black <hi>Nemeſis</hi> in flames from out her cave,</l>
                           <l>and ſhe ſhould be the umpire in this cauſe.</l>
                           <l>Mans ſoul is like a boiſtrous working ſea,</l>
                           <l>ſwelling in billows for diſdain of wrongs,</l>
                           <l>and tumbling up and down from day to day,</l>
                           <l>grows greater ſtill in indignation,</l>
                           <l>turns male-content, in pleaſeleſſe melancholy,</l>
                           <l>ſpending her humours in dull paſſion, ſtill</l>
                           <l>locking her ſenſes in uncloſed gins,</l>
                           <l>till by revenge ſhe's ſet at liberty.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, now my thirſty ſoul expects full draughts</l>
                           <l>of <hi>Ate's</hi> boyling cup: O, how twoul'd eaſe</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="214" facs="110"/>my heart to ſee a channel of his blood</l>
                           <l>ſtreaming from hence to hell, that kill'd my father.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>I, but deare friend, thou muſt not let rage looſe,</l>
                           <l>and like a furious Lion, from whoſe den</l>
                           <l>the forreſter hath ſtole away his young,</l>
                           <l>he miſſing it, ſtraight runs with open jaws</l>
                           <l>on all he meets, and never hurting him</l>
                           <l>that did the wrong: Wiſe men muſt mix revenge</l>
                           <l>with reaſon, which by providence will prompt,</l>
                           <l>and tell us where's the mark, whereat we aym.</l>
                           <l>Till then, in Cinders wee'l rake up our grief:</l>
                           <l>fire thus kept, ſtill lives, but opened dies;</l>
                           <l>from ſmalleſt ſparks great flames may one day riſe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>True, friend, but, O, who ever will reveale</l>
                           <l>this hideous act! what power ſhall we invoke?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, harken friend, I have bethought a meanes;</l>
                           <l>not diſtant far from this place where we live,</l>
                           <l>there ſtands a cave hard by a hollow oake,</l>
                           <l>in a low valley, where no Sun appeares,</l>
                           <l>no muſick ever was there heard to ſound;</l>
                           <l>but the harſh voyce of croking ominous ravens,</l>
                           <l>and ſad Nyctimine the bird of night:</l>
                           <l>There's now a ſhed, under whoſe ancient roofe</l>
                           <l>there ſometimes ſtood an Altar for the Gods,</l>
                           <l>but now ſlow creeping time, with windy blaſts</l>
                           <l>hath beaten down that ſtately Temples walls,</l>
                           <l>defac't his rich built windows, and until'd</l>
                           <l>his battlemented roofe, and made it now</l>
                           <l>a habitation, not for God, nor men:</l>
                           <l>Yet an old woman, who doth ſeem to ſtrive</l>
                           <l>with the vaſt building for antiquity,</l>
                           <l>in whoſe rough face time now hath made ſuch holes,</l>
                           <l>as in thoſe uncouth ſtones ſhe there hath made</l>
                           <l>her ſelf a cell, wherein to ſpend her age.</l>
                           <l>Her name's <hi>Canidia;</hi> great in Magick ſpells,</l>
                           <l>at whoſe dire voice, the gods themſelves would quake</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="215" facs="110"/>to heare her charm the ſecond time pronounc't.</l>
                           <l>One that can know the ſecrets of the heavens,</l>
                           <l>and in the ayre hath flying miniſters,</l>
                           <l>to bring her news from earth, from ſea, from hell:</l>
                           <l>which, when thick night hath compaſs'd in the world,</l>
                           <l>then doth ſhe go to dead mens graves and tombs,</l>
                           <l>and ſucks the poyſonous marrow from their bones,</l>
                           <l>then makes her charm, which ſhe nere ſpent in vaine:</l>
                           <l>Nor doth ſhe come as ſupplyant to the gods,</l>
                           <l>but making <hi>Erebus,</hi> and heaven to quake,</l>
                           <l>ſhe ſends a ſpell drowning infernal thunder,</l>
                           <l>by which all ſecrets that were ever done,</l>
                           <l>in faire white parchment writ in lines of blood,</l>
                           <l>lockt in the inmoſt room of hell it ſelf</l>
                           <l>is brought unto her: and by her we may</l>
                           <l>have leave to look in <hi>Pluto's</hi> regiſter,</l>
                           <l>and reade the names of thoſe moſt loathed furies,</l>
                           <l>which rent thy Fathers ſoul from out his trunk:</l>
                           <l>But ſhe muſt ſee thy fathers dead bones firſt,</l>
                           <l>them we muſt bring her, for by them ſhe works:</l>
                           <l>This if thou dar'ſt aſſay, I'll go along.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>If I dare aſſay! yes, yes, deare friend,</l>
                           <l>were it to burſt my fathers ſepulcher,</l>
                           <l>and wake his <hi>Manes,</hi> ſhew them <hi>Radamanth;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>their iterated ſight will burn my ſoul</l>
                           <l>with ſuch a ſparkling flame of dire revenge,</l>
                           <l>as <hi>Neſſus</hi> ſhirt did burn great <hi>Hercules:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>If that the ſcrowle which did conteine their names,</l>
                           <l>were in a lake of flaming brimſtone drencht,</l>
                           <l>I'de take it out, or fech't from <hi>Pluto's</hi> arms:</l>
                           <l>But come; if earth hath ſuch a creature as can tell,</l>
                           <l>twill ſave a journey (for this once) from hell.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <pb n="216" facs="111"/>
                        <head>Scena. 3.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aegyſtheus, Clytemneſtra, Tyndarus, Myſan|der, Strophius, Electra, cum caet. with a crown. Ae|gyſtheus aſcends the throne, Myſander crowns him: Clytemneſtra great with child.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                           <l>All years of happy dayes, all hours of joy</l>
                           <l>ſo circle in thy ſtate, as doth this crown</l>
                           <l>wreath and combine thy princely temples in,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>All ſpeak, Jove</hi> ſtill protect <hi>Aegyſtheus.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Thanks to my fathers ſubjects:</l>
                           <l>Now <hi>Argos</hi> ſwell up to the brim with joy,</l>
                           <l>and ſtreams of gladneſſe flow on <hi>Tyndarus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Now made our father; ſee old King, ſee here's</l>
                           <l>my Queen doth mean to make thee a grandfather,</l>
                           <l>ſee how thy royal blood ſhall propagate,</l>
                           <l>whoſe Kingly drops like heaven diſtilling dew,</l>
                           <l>ſhall add freſh life unto thy withered root.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, but <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> there were armes before</l>
                           <l>grew on this tree; but the Fates envious axe</l>
                           <l>hath cut them off before th'ad time to ſprout.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O Sir, the Fates needs muſt have leave to make</l>
                           <l>wayes for themſelves to manage what they do:</l>
                           <l>Had <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes</hi> liv'd,</l>
                           <l>they could not then have bleſt me with theſe gifts:</l>
                           <l>Still when the heavens and Fates do work their will,</l>
                           <l>they intend good, though ſometimes there come ill.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>O but pray <hi>Jove</hi> the Fates now were not forc't,</l>
                           <l>but deeds like words no man can e'r recal,</l>
                           <l>be't good or ill; once done, we muſt bear all.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Come father ſit we down, and make a feaſt,</l>
                           <stage>They ſet to the feaſt.</stage>
                           <l>to glad our hearts; Heaven ſtill doth for the beſt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="217" facs="111"/>
                           <speaker>Stro.</speaker>
                           <l>O let my latter age not live to ſee</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> wear great <hi>Argos</hi> diadem.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Feare not good uncle, there will be a time,</l>
                           <l>to pull him down, although he yet doth climbe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Who ever truſted much on fortunes gifts,</l>
                           <l>on wife, on ſtate, on health, on friends, on lands,</l>
                           <l>may look on <hi>Agamemnons</hi> coming home:</l>
                           <l>Fortune me thinks ne're ſhew'd her power more;</l>
                           <l>how quickly could ſhe turne her Fatall ſword</l>
                           <l>upon his breſt, that thought himſelfe paſt harme?</l>
                           <l>ſhe that had us'd death like an angry dogge,</l>
                           <l>holding him up, when that he ſhould have bit,</l>
                           <l>when all the game was paſt, and's fury laid,</l>
                           <l>the king being paſt all danger, ſafe at home,</l>
                           <l>then he ſlip's coller, never untill then,</l>
                           <l>and fortune ſhe ſtood hiſsing of him on,</l>
                           <l>till he had torne the good kings ſoule away.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Clytemneſtra ſeemes to weep.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay but good father let paſſe elegies,</l>
                           <l>you draw freſh teares now from your daughters eyes,</l>
                           <l>who ſhed enough before at's funeral:</l>
                           <l>let's talk who are to live, not who are dead;</l>
                           <l>and think what progeny ſhall ſpring from us</l>
                           <l>may beare your Image ſtampt upon the face,</l>
                           <l>this we muſt talk of now, not what griefs paſt</l>
                           <l>but of the joy to come. My Queen not well!</l>
                           <stage>Clytemneſtra riſeth from the table.</stage>
                           <l>Now good <hi>Electra</hi> look unto your mother,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Lucina</hi> be propitious to the birth;</l>
                           <l>why, will not now a young <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> be,</l>
                           <l>as grateful as an old <hi>Oreſtes</hi> was?</l>
                           <l>Thou times good lengthener, age, poſterity,</l>
                           <l>ſpread thy ſelf ſtill upon <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> line,</l>
                           <l>help me to treaſure up antiquity,</l>
                           <l>and from <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> loynes let ſpring an heire,</l>
                           <l>ſhall ever ſit in great <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> chaire. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <pb n="218" facs="112"/>
                        <head>SCEN. 4.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Pylades and Oreſtes, with his arms full of a dead mans bones, and a ſcull.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Neare to this ſhady grove, where never light</l>
                           <l>appeares, but when 'tis forced with ſome charm,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Canidia</hi> dwells, in ſuch a dusky place,</l>
                           <l>that the night goblins feare to come too neare it.</l>
                           <l>Here let us knock.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, <hi>Pylades,</hi> ſee here,</l>
                           <l>O give me leave to diſcant on theſe bones:</l>
                           <l>This was my Fathers ſcull; but who can know</l>
                           <l>whether it were ſome ſubjects ſcull, or no?</l>
                           <l>Where be theſe Princely eyes, commanding face,</l>
                           <l>the brave majeſtick look, the Kingly grace?</l>
                           <l>Where's the imperious frown, the God-like ſmile,</l>
                           <l>the graceful tongue, that ſpoke a ſouldiers ſtile?</l>
                           <l>Ha, ha, worms eate them! could no Princely looke,</l>
                           <l>no line of eloquence writ in this booke,</l>
                           <l>command, nor yet perſwade the worms away?</l>
                           <l>Rebellious worms! could a King beare no ſway?</l>
                           <l>Injurious worms! what could no fleſh ſerve</l>
                           <l>but Kings for you? By—you all ſhould ſterve,</l>
                           <l>had I but known't: What muſt my father make</l>
                           <l>a feaſt for you? O ye devouring creatures!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Now ſome <hi>Archilocus</hi> to help him make</l>
                           <l>vengeful Iambicks, that would make theſe worms</l>
                           <l>to burſt themſelves: Paſſion muſt pleaſe</l>
                           <l>it ſelf by words, grief told, it ſelf doth eaſe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>You cowardly bones, would you be thus uncloth'd</l>
                           <l>by little crawling worms! by— I never thought</l>
                           <l>my fathers bones could e'r have been ſuch cowards:</l>
                           <l>O you ungrateful worms! how have you us'd him?</l>
                           <l>See their ingratitude! O ambitious creatures,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="219" facs="112"/>how they ſtill domineere o're a Kings carcaſſe!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Py.</speaker>
                           <l>How could they think when thou cam'ſt to'the crown</l>
                           <l>that thou ſhouldſt bear, that theſe ſhould eat thy father?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>True, <hi>Pylades,</hi> ſhould I not rend their maws,</l>
                           <l>deviſe new tortures? O moſt horrible treaſon,</l>
                           <l>that worms ſhould come unto a great Kings face,</l>
                           <l>and eate his eyes! why, I would undertake</l>
                           <l>but at one ſtamp to kill a thouſand of'em:</l>
                           <l>and I will kill theſe:</l>
                           <stage>Stamps upon them.</stage>
                           <l>Goe you King-eating creatures: I will mar</l>
                           <l>all your digeſtion.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Alas, where be his wits?</l>
                           <l>He ſtands declaming againſt ſenſeleſſe worms,</l>
                           <l>and turns more ſenſeleſſe then the worms themſelves:</l>
                           <l>where's now the oracle you ſhould conſult?</l>
                           <l>The great Magician? now the <hi>Centaurs</hi> thought</l>
                           <l>ſhall be example to all future years;</l>
                           <l>and now tranſcend <hi>Proſerpina's</hi> invention.</l>
                           <l>Ha, haſt thou found them out? ha, were they worms?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O prethee laugh not at me, call her, call her;</l>
                           <stage>Pylades knock</stage>
                           <l>whilſt I ſtand gathering up my fathers bones,</l>
                           <l>his deare diſſected bones; O, I remember, here</l>
                           <l>ran the ſtrong ſinews, 'twixt his knitting joynts,</l>
                           <l>here to this bone was joyn'd his princely arme,</l>
                           <l>here ſtood the hand that bare his warlike ſhield,</l>
                           <l>and on this little joynt was plac't the head,</l>
                           <l>that <hi>Atlas</hi>-like bare up the weight of Greece:</l>
                           <l>here, here betwixt theſe hollow yawning jaws</l>
                           <l>ſtood once a tongue, which with one little word</l>
                           <l>could have commanded thouſand ſouls to death:</l>
                           <l>Good hands indure this your weighty task,</l>
                           <l>and good eyes ſtrive not to make moiſt his bones</l>
                           <l>with weeping teares:</l>
                           <l>What <hi>Scinis</hi> or <hi>Procuſtes</hi> ever could</l>
                           <l>have hackt a King into ſuch things as theſe?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="220" facs="113"/>Alas here's every part now ſo deform'd,</l>
                           <l>I know not which was his, yet all was his.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Sound infernal Muſick.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 5.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Canidia, like an Enchauntreſſe.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Protect us O ye Miniſters of heaven,</l>
                           <l>ſtand neare me my good <hi>Genius,</hi> my ſoul hath loſt</l>
                           <l>his humane function, at this helliſh ſight.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Who is't diſturbs our cave? what meſſenger</l>
                           <l>hath <hi>Pluto</hi> ſent, that would know ought from us?</l>
                           <l>what are you? ſpeak, <hi>Canidia</hi> cannot ſtay.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Prompt us ſome Ghoſt.</l>
                           <l>Great feare of earth, and governeſſe of nature,</l>
                           <l>in whoſe deep cloſet of that ſacred heart</l>
                           <l>are writ the characters of future Fate;</l>
                           <l>and what is done, and what muſt be thou knowſt:</l>
                           <l>Whoſe words make burning <hi>Acheron</hi> grow cold,</l>
                           <l>and <hi>Jove</hi> leave thundring, when he hears thy name:</l>
                           <l>to thee we come: O turn thy ſecret book,</l>
                           <l>and look whoſe names thou there ſhalt ſee inſcrib'd</l>
                           <l>for murderers, reade o'r all the catalogue,</l>
                           <l>untill thou findeſt there engraven thoſe</l>
                           <l>which kill'd the King of Greece, great <hi>Agamemnon.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, he that did owe theſe bones which worms have eate;</l>
                           <l>it is not now one of the meaner ſort</l>
                           <l>that craves this boone, but 'tis the heire of Greece,</l>
                           <l>heire only now but to my fathers grave;</l>
                           <l>I not command, but my aſtoniſht ſoul</l>
                           <l>entreats to know.</l>
                           <l>If in thy book it be not yet put down,</l>
                           <l>command the gods t' unlock the gates of heaven,</l>
                           <l>and fetch forth death, command him to relate</l>
                           <l>who 'twas put <hi>Agamemnon</hi> in his hands,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="221" facs="113"/>this is our buſineſſe, this, great propheteſſe,</l>
                           <l>made us approach to thy moſt hallowed cell.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Ho, ho, ho, I tell thee fond young prince,</l>
                           <l>a leſſer power thou mightſt have implor'd,</l>
                           <l>which might have urg'd th'unwilling fiends to this;</l>
                           <l>our dire enchantments carry ſuch a force,</l>
                           <l>that when the ſtars, and influence of heaven,</l>
                           <l>have ſuckt the lively blood from out mens veines,</l>
                           <l>I at my pleaſure bring it back again;</l>
                           <l>I knew each hour in the Trojan fight,</l>
                           <l>what Grecian, or what Phrygian ſhould die,</l>
                           <l>and fierce <hi>Achilles</hi> had no ſooner pierc't</l>
                           <l>great <hi>Hectors</hi> ſide, but Fate did ſend me word:</l>
                           <l>Earth, Sea, deep <hi>Chaos,</hi> all the ſtony hills,</l>
                           <l>will ope themſelves to ſhew me prodigies;</l>
                           <l>Night will unmask her brow, to let me ſee</l>
                           <l>what black conceptions reem within her womb.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O then relate, great Miſtreſſe of thy Art,</l>
                           <l>the things we crave:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>What time of night is't?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Upon the ſtroke of twelve.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Strait when a cloudy even clappeth the Ayre,</l>
                           <l>and all light's drench't in miſty <hi>Acheron,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>when the black palpheries of the full cheekt moon,</l>
                           <l>have got behind this part o'th' Hemiſpheare,</l>
                           <l>and dark <hi>Aldebor,</hi> and is mounted high</l>
                           <l>into the ſable <hi>Caſſiopeias</hi> chaire,</l>
                           <l>and night full mounted in her ſeate of jet,</l>
                           <l>ſits wrapt within a cabinet of clouds,</l>
                           <l>when ſerpents leave to hiſſe, no dragons yell,</l>
                           <l>no birds do ſing, no harſh tun'd toads do croake,</l>
                           <l>the Armenian Tyger, and the ravenous woolf,</l>
                           <l>ſhall yeild up all their tyranny to ſleep,</l>
                           <l>and then none walk but hells diſturbed ſpirits,</l>
                           <l>children of night, ſuch as belong to me,</l>
                           <l>I'll ſhew thee thy deſire; give me theſe bones.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Here, take them Mother, uſe them gently,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="222" facs="114"/>they were a Kings bones once. O not ſo hard.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Why ſenſeleſſe boy, doſt think that I reſpect</l>
                           <l>a Kings dead bones, more then another mans?</l>
                           <l>O they ſmell rankly; I, this ſent doth pleaſe,</l>
                           <stage>Smells to them.</stage>
                           <l>but I muſt now to work: why <hi>Sagana.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Looke here thou King of Greece, fond <hi>Menelaus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>thou which didſt bring ſo many goodly ſhapes</l>
                           <l>into ſuch things as theſe, and all for <hi>Helen:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <stage>Takes up the ſcull.</stage>
                           <l>Which when the worms bred of her dainty fleſh,</l>
                           <l>ſhall have knaw'd off her tender rubie lips,</l>
                           <l>and left her gumleſſe, looke upon her then;</l>
                           <l>and thou wouldſt even diſgorge thy ſelf to ſee,</l>
                           <l>ſuch putrid vermine to lie kiſſing her.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>This head had once a royall diadem,</l>
                           <l>now knock it, beat it, and 'twill ne'r cry treaſon.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Why <hi>Sagana.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt</speaker>
                           <l>There was a player once upon a ſtage,</l>
                           <l>who ſtriving to preſent a drecry paſſion,</l>
                           <l>brought out the urn of his late buried ſon,</l>
                           <l>it might the more affect him, and draw tears:</l>
                           <l>But I, as if I had no paſſion left,</l>
                           <l>not acting of a part, but really</l>
                           <l>in a true cauſe having my fathers bones,</l>
                           <l>his hollow ſcull, yet crawling full of worms,</l>
                           <l>I cannot weep, no not a teare will come.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Why <hi>Sagana, Veia, Erictho,</hi> know you not your time?</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="scene">
                        <pb n="223" facs="114"/>
                        <head>Scen. 6.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Sagana, Veia, Erictho, three witches.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                           <l>What would you, Beldam?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Hath not triform'd <hi>Hecate</hi> put on</l>
                           <l>her Styx-dyed mantle, is't not now fit time</l>
                           <l>to work our charms in?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Veia.</speaker>
                           <l>We here are ready 'gainſt thy ſacred charm.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>You two, ſit by, and beare in minde this charge;</l>
                           <l>Who e'r you ſee, who ever I preſent,</l>
                           <l>let your tongues be perculiſs'd in your jaws;</l>
                           <l>ſtir not, nor ſpeak not, till the charm be done.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Fear not, it ſhall be chain'd with ſilence.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Night, and <hi>Diana</hi> ſacred Queen,</l>
                           <l>Which ever hath ſpectator been</l>
                           <l>Unto our baleful hideous rights,</l>
                           <l>Ne're acted but in darkeſt nights,</l>
                           <l>Now in this fatal hearſ-bred hour,</l>
                           <l>Shew to my rites the greateſt power.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Erictho</hi> when my torch ſhall twinkle,</l>
                           <l>A vernal water thou ſhalt ſprinkle</l>
                           <l>About the room, now let us kneele,</l>
                           <l>Our heavy burthen hell ſhall feele:</l>
                           <l>Lets all coyn words, now we may ſee</l>
                           <l>Who 'twas did work this prodigie.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Omnes. Pluto,</hi> great <hi>Pluto,</hi> we command,</l>
                           <l>Thou ſend unto us out of hand,</l>
                           <l>The ſhapes of them that kill'd the King,</l>
                           <l>Great <hi>Agamemnon.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Infernal Muſick. <hi>Enter in a dumb ſhew, Aegiſtheus and Clytemneſtra, with their bloody daggers, look upon the bed, go to it, and ſtab, and then make a ſhew of gladnes and depart.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Or.</speaker>
                           <l>O'tis above my bearing! were I linkt here with chains,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="224" facs="115"/>I would like <hi>Cerberus</hi> draw <hi>Alcides</hi> back:</l>
                           <l>Stay, ſtay, by — revenge ſhall take you here;</l>
                           <l>nay, I will follow you, ſhould they take their cave,</l>
                           <l>where <hi>Etna</hi> vomits fire, I would in:</l>
                           <l>my mother! <hi>Clytemneſtra! Aegyſtheus!</hi> was it they?</l>
                           <l>Nay, I will o'rtake them.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>O ſon, remember what I told you, ſon,</l>
                           <l>many a rockie hill and ſtoney mount,</l>
                           <l>many a ſea, and vaſt <hi>Charybdis</hi> gulf,</l>
                           <l>ſtands betwixt them and thee, though they ſeem near.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O piety! O moſt prodigious nature!</l>
                           <l>What creatures haſt thou made to live on earth?</l>
                           <l>How haſt thou cloath'd black darkneſſe with a ſcarf</l>
                           <l>of unſtain'd purity, and put a godly face</l>
                           <l>upon portentous devils? Oh, how my mother wept!</l>
                           <l>How <hi>Clytemneſtra!</hi> how that <hi>Hyena</hi> wept!</l>
                           <l>No more my mother, I abjure the name,</l>
                           <l>ſhe did not bring me forth, I know ſhe did not:</l>
                           <l>But I'll o'rtake 'em; ſhew me <hi>(Canidia)</hi> where,</l>
                           <l>which way they went, where have they hid themſelves.</l>
                           <l>Should they mount up to the chariot of the Sun,</l>
                           <l>and in his Car fly to the <hi>Antipodes,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>or in the fartheſt nook of yonder ſphear,</l>
                           <l>get up and place themſelves 'twixt <hi>Taurus</hi> horns,</l>
                           <l>the fire-breathing bull, or <hi>Lerna's Hydra,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>were there no entrance but ten Lions jaws,</l>
                           <l>I'd run through all, and make my way my ſelf:</l>
                           <l>I'd fix them to the Axel-tree of heaven,</l>
                           <l>where their infectious carcaſſes ſhould hang</l>
                           <l>a bait for flying ſpirits in the Ayre.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Canidia,</hi> I thank thee for thy pains,</l>
                           <l>ſtill may thy ſacred Art reveale ſuch deeds,</l>
                           <l>ſtill keep the gates of <hi>Orcus</hi> yawning ope,</l>
                           <l>make the dark powers ready at command.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>But let us haſt deare friend, this vaſt worlds roome</l>
                           <l>allows us none, but thy dead fathers Tombe:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="225" facs="115"/>here's nought but ayres of death, no bed but ſtones,</l>
                           <l>〈◊〉 pillow's a dead ſcull, companions bones,</l>
                           <l>●●●s's all our comfort, if we needs muſt die,</l>
                           <l>〈◊〉 have a Grave prepar'd wherein to lie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Now pale <hi>Tiſiphone,</hi> O for thy Snakes!</l>
                           <l>〈◊〉 that renowned ſpirit, that more than man,</l>
                           <l>●hom all the Trojan hoſt could not o'rwhelm,</l>
                           <l>murdred! But what brave warrier wore a crown,</l>
                           <l>by guilding a dire ſword in his dear blood?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hector,</hi> nor <hi>Priam,</hi> no, nor <hi>Mars</hi> himſelf,</l>
                           <l>onely his Wife was his <hi>Bellona</hi> now.</l>
                           <l>O miſerable valour, to ſcape foes,</l>
                           <l>and come for to be murdred of his friends!</l>
                           <l>O ſhameful conqueſt! O moſt coward Fate!</l>
                           <l>that a weak Woman was competitor</l>
                           <l>in <hi>Agamemnons</hi> death: had it been any, yet</l>
                           <l>it ſhould have been a Goddeſs at the leaſt;</l>
                           <l>and yet ſhe's but a Queen, a mortal Woman.</l>
                           <l>Were ſhe a Goddeſs, I would make her mortal.</l>
                           <l>Dull coward that I am, and worſe than all,</l>
                           <l>after ſo many wrongs, yet unreveng'd:</l>
                           <l>their Palace now ſhould fire o'r their heads,</l>
                           <l>and the huge beams daſh out their guilty brains:</l>
                           <l>The roof, ſhould fall on me, ſo't fell on them.</l>
                           <l>Begin revenge, and now perform an act,</l>
                           <l>may give a theam to all poſterity.</l>
                           <l>ever to talk of, fraught ſo full of horrour:</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> and my Mother, may wiſh their's,</l>
                           <l>yet none was ever greater: yes, my deed.</l>
                           <l>Revenge is loſt, unleſs we do exceed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>But a bad mother, friend, thou ſhouldſt not hurt,</l>
                           <l>the Law of Nature doth forbid ſuch thoughts.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt:</speaker>
                           <l>Nor Gods, nor Nature, ſhall keep me in awe:</l>
                           <l>why towards my mother, by heavens Parliament,</l>
                           <l>who is moſt guilty, is moſt innocent.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Shall I thus by ſome Magick Art, my ſon,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="226" facs="116"/>take both their pictures in pure virgin wax?</l>
                           <l>And wound the place where that the hurt ſhould ſtand,</l>
                           <l>and ſo wound them?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Tuſh, this is too little.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can.</speaker>
                           <l>Shall I breed them hate?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Too little too.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Can:</speaker>
                           <l>Shall I conſume their children?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>All this too little:</l>
                           <l>Hell and the Furies ſhall ſtand all amaz'd,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Alecto</hi> ſhall come there for to behold</l>
                           <l>new kinds of murthers, which ſhe knew not yet:</l>
                           <l>and Nature learn to violate her ſelf.</l>
                           <l>I'll inſtantly to th'Court, and what I do,</l>
                           <l>my ſelf will ſee done, yes, and act it too.</l>
                           <l>Thanks great <hi>Canidia,</hi> this black night being done,</l>
                           <l>Revenge now knows her game whereat to run.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="act">
                     <head>Actus 4.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>Enter in ſtate, Aegyſtheus, Clytemneſtra, Tyndarus, Strophius, Electra, Nutrix; cum novo partu.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>NEver but when a royal off-ſpring comes</l>
                           <l>from a Kings loyns, can he be truly King.</l>
                           <l>Then doth he ſit firm, rooted in his ſtate,</l>
                           <l>then is he truly man, and then the gods</l>
                           <l>he knows do love him, which when Kings do want,</l>
                           <l>the curſe of Nature doth deny them fruit,</l>
                           <l>and brands their bed with loath'd ſterility.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> ſince the gods have bleſs'd you ſo,</l>
                           <l>have care their bleſſings turn not to your wo.</l>
                           <l>Your joy, my daughters joy, and my joy too,</l>
                           <l>have care it be preſerv'd, and brought up well:</l>
                           <l>And take heed, ſon, of <hi>Agamemnon</hi>'s blood,</l>
                           <l>Pierce not with envie the Babes tender heart.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Tuſh Father, now, not without grief I ſpeak,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="227" facs="116"/>all brooks which from the Princely Ocean ran,</l>
                           <l>are quite dry'd up, only <hi>Electra</hi> here,</l>
                           <l>our dear <hi>Electra,</hi> whoſe great weight of love</l>
                           <l>is in our balance equally ſo poys'd,</l>
                           <l>that ſhe ſhall ever think her Father lives,</l>
                           <l>our heart ſhall be ſo parallel with hers.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>El.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, great <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> wer't but our mothers will,</l>
                           <l>what ſhe thinks good of, I muſt not think ill:</l>
                           <l>Beſides, your love e'r ſince my fathers death,</l>
                           <l>as if it came from his departing ſoul,</l>
                           <l>and forth-with had reviv'd again in you,</l>
                           <l>hath held a proſpective for me, to ſee</l>
                           <l>his care redoubled, though the objects chang'd:</l>
                           <l>And, for I loſt a brother, if you pleaſe,</l>
                           <l>that I may challenge in your royal blood,</l>
                           <l>here do I tie with all affections bands,</l>
                           <l>my ſelf unto this Babe, which is as dear</l>
                           <l>unto my ſoul, as were <hi>Oreſt●s</hi> here.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Daughter, your heart now with obedience ſtrung,</l>
                           <l>makes a ſweet muſick ſounding from your tongue.</l>
                           <l>Nurſe, Bring the Babe. Give it <hi>Electra;</hi> ſo,</l>
                           <l>you daughter ſhall have overſight of it.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Nutr.</speaker>
                           <l>O, ſhall I part from't then?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
                           <l>No good Nurſe, no,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Electra</hi> with her care, you with your pains.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Nutr.</speaker>
                           <l>Now by <hi>Lucina,</hi> had it gone away,</l>
                           <l>I ſhould have ſit, and ſob'd away my heart;</l>
                           <l>'Tis the ſweeteſt Babe that ever Nurſe did kiſs.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Look here good father, look my nobles here,</l>
                           <l>upon this Babe ſcarce crept yet out of earth,</l>
                           <l>for you ſhall grow an Autumn of ripe years,</l>
                           <l>when time hath brought it to maturity.</l>
                           <l>Look on thy grandchild, <hi>Tyndarus,</hi> ſee, 'tis thine,</l>
                           <l>this came from thee, old-man; ſee how it ſmiles</l>
                           <l>upon the Grandſire, as if wiſe Nature had</l>
                           <l>taught him his kindreds Names 'fore he came forth.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>I ſee't <hi>Aegyſt.</hi> &amp; my ag'd blood grows warm,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="228" facs="117"/>as if my ſelf were a new father made,</l>
                           <l>and all the bleſſings I can render it,</l>
                           <l>ſhall drop like golden ſhowers on the head:</l>
                           <l>Me thinks it doth recal my ſliding age,</l>
                           <l>and makes ſwift time retire back again:</l>
                           <l>It doth unfold thoſe wrincles in my face,</l>
                           <l>which grief and years had fixed as their ſignes</l>
                           <l>upon my brow, and now it ſhall be ſeen,</l>
                           <l>although my hairs are gray, my joyes are green.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Long may our Father his opinion hold,</l>
                           <l>and you, our daughter, let not ſiniſter thoughts</l>
                           <l>wrong your ſuſpicious minde, though this being young,</l>
                           <l>it makes our Lord, and me to ſpeak our joyes;</l>
                           <l>yet our affection, and our natural love,</l>
                           <l>is not a whit to you diminiſhed.</l>
                           <l>A Mother can be Mother unto many,</l>
                           <l>and as from one Root hid within the ground,</l>
                           <l>ſprings many flowers, that lends ſap to all;</l>
                           <l>So from a Parents heart run veins of love,</l>
                           <l>which, though to many they without do flow,</l>
                           <l>yet from one heart, one Root, they all do grow.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>I hope our gracious Mother cannot think</l>
                           <l>we do ſuſpect her love; witneſs this charge,</l>
                           <l>which you have bleſs'd my arms and ſoul withal:</l>
                           <l>and as your love committed it with care,</l>
                           <l>my care ſhall ſtill defend it with my love.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>We thank our daughter, come Lord <hi>Strophius,</hi> come,</l>
                           <l>grief ſtill ſits heavie on your ſighing heart.</l>
                           <l>Be frolike, learn of us; in all the grace,</l>
                           <l>and pleaſure our Court extends, you ſhall have place.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stroph.</speaker>
                           <l>I thank my gracious Lord, time hath by this,</l>
                           <l>almoſt eate out the memory of our ſon,</l>
                           <l>and ſince the heavens let fall their dew on you,</l>
                           <l>and watred <hi>Argos</hi> with ſuch ſpringing hopes;</l>
                           <l>I will not ſeem a ſtock uncapable</l>
                           <l>of ſuch a general comfort, but revive</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="229" facs="117"/>my buried thoughts, and for my Sovereign's ſake,</l>
                           <l>old <hi>Strophius</hi> will a young mans perſon take.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>We thank old <hi>Strophius,</hi> and if honour can</l>
                           <l>keep thee ſtill young, our Princely hand is wide,</l>
                           <l>and freely ſhall extend all Graces on thee,</l>
                           <l>and you all our Subjects, which bear part</l>
                           <l>thus in our joy. And here I do proclaim,</l>
                           <l>and perſonally from my own Mouth pronounce,</l>
                           <l>ſealing it with the Signet of my State,</l>
                           <l>A general immunity to all</l>
                           <l>Murders, Rapes, Treaſons, Thefts, Conveyances,</l>
                           <l>which have been from the birth of our dear Childe,</l>
                           <l>in all the Confines of our Empire done;</l>
                           <l>nor ſhall your licence date be quite expired,</l>
                           <l>till the ſlow year ſeven times runs out his courſe.</l>
                           <l>Our ſelf thus ſpeak it; until then all's free,</l>
                           <l>Kings win their Subjects by immunity.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                        <stage>Manent Strophius, &amp; Electra.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stroph.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Electra,</hi> you are happy in your charge.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Electr.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, Uncle, and you happy in your favour.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                           <l>Madam, Shall I ſtay here until you come?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Comes back.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Electr.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, Nurſe, ſit down and ſing, look to the Babe,</l>
                           <l>I'll only with my Uncle change a word.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Nurſe</speaker>
                           <stage>ſings.</stage>
                           <l> Lullaby, lullaby Baby,</l>
                           <l>Great <hi>Argos</hi> joy,</l>
                           <l>The King of Greece thou art born to be,</l>
                           <l>In deſpight of Troy.</l>
                           <l>Reſt ever wait upon thy head,</l>
                           <l>Sleep cloſe thine eyes,</l>
                           <l>The bleſſed gaurd, tend on thy bed,</l>
                           <l>Of Deities.</l>
                           <l>O, how this brow will beſeem a Crown!</l>
                           <l>How theſe locks will ſhine!</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="230" facs="118"/>Like the rayes of the Sun on the ground,</l>
                           <l>Theſe locks of thine.</l>
                           <l>The Nurſe of heaven ſtill ſend thee milk,</l>
                           <l>Maiſt thou ●uck a Queen.</l>
                           <l>Thy drink <hi>Joves Nectar,</hi> and cloaths of ſilke,</l>
                           <l>A God mayſt thou ſeem.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cupid</hi> ſit on this Roſean cheek,</l>
                           <l>On theſe rubie lips</l>
                           <l>May thy minde like a Lamb be meek,</l>
                           <l>In the vales which trips,</l>
                           <l>Lullaby, Lullaby Baby, &amp;c.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>You never heard from my brother, Uncle,</l>
                           <l>nor from your ſon! they have been long away!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stroph.</speaker>
                           <l>In troth, <hi>Electra,</hi> I am in deſpair,</l>
                           <l>almoſt of ever ſeeing them again;</l>
                           <l>Sure if <hi>Oreſtes</hi> live, and ever hear,</l>
                           <l>unto what paſs <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> brings his ſtate,</l>
                           <l>ſeated him in the throne, and's mothers bed,</l>
                           <l>and like to leave <hi>Argos</hi> hereditary</l>
                           <l>to his Poſterity, it cannot e'r be born,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſpirit will endure no ſcorn.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Uncle, his long delayes make me ſurmiſe,</l>
                           <l>or he will never come, or come with prize;</l>
                           <l>He, if now come, he muſt not ſhew himſelf,</l>
                           <l>but live unknown, unnam'd, or change his name.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                           <l>His name, <hi>Electra,</hi> yes, and's nature too,</l>
                           <l>which I do fear me he will hardly do.</l>
                           <l>But if we hear not from them now e're long,</l>
                           <l>I'll liſten by ſome means about the land,</l>
                           <l>to hear of them; mean time you to your charge,</l>
                           <l>officious duty muſt our lives enlarge.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Come Nurſe. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <pb n="231" facs="118"/>
                        <head>Scen. 2.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Oreſtes, and Pylades.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, here's the Palace under whoſe kind roof</l>
                           <l>My tender years were gently ſoftered:</l>
                           <l>But now the ſight on't ſeems to ſtrike my ſoul,</l>
                           <l>when I but think it holds within the walls,</l>
                           <l>the patrons of ſuch luſt, incarnate devils,</l>
                           <l>meer Pythoniſts, that facinate the world.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, but <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> think now of your ſelf,</l>
                           <l>complain not of your wrongs, but ſeek to right them.</l>
                           <l>We might have liv'd i'th woods ſtill to complain,</l>
                           <l>and to that purpoſe we may turn again.</l>
                           <l>Whet up your former thoughts, and ſpend not time,</l>
                           <l>to rave, but to revenge this odious act.</l>
                           <l>We know they were their ſhapes, and no Chymera's.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, <hi>Pylades,</hi> know I thou art my friend?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>I hope you think it.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>I do, I dare ſwear it,</l>
                           <l>ſo I dare ſwear it was <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> and</l>
                           <l>the dumbe Witch, the — O, what thing's enough</l>
                           <l>to be an attribute to term her by?</l>
                           <l>The <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> O, we ſaw her do't.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>'Twas a black deed indeed, and paſt all thought.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, Hell it ſelf has not the pattern to't:</l>
                           <l>Some ſtench, ſome fogs and vapours ſtop their breath,</l>
                           <l>exhald from out the dampiſh wombe of Styx.</l>
                           <l>Did ever foul, diſaſtrous, fiendlike hands,</l>
                           <l>caſt up ſo huge a heap of hell-bred miſchief?</l>
                           <l>Were I to dive to'th depth of <hi>Phelgeton.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>or fetch young <hi>Gaenimed</hi> from the arms of <hi>Jove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>to rend <hi>Proſerpina</hi> from <hi>Pluto</hi>'s bed,</l>
                           <l>or take the vulture from off <hi>Titius</hi> heart,</l>
                           <l>and ſet it on my Mothers, I would do't;</l>
                           <l>I'll break ope doors, and nail 'em to their bed;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="232" facs="119"/>heark, revenge calls me, I come, I come.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, ſtill outrageous friend, good now contain</l>
                           <l>your heady fury in wiſdoms reyn:</l>
                           <l>hearken to my advice.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>I will, dear friend,</l>
                           <l>thou haſt plaid muſick to my doleful ſoul;</l>
                           <l>and when my heart was tympaniz'd with grief,</l>
                           <l>thou lav'dſt out ſome into thy heart from mine,</l>
                           <l>and kepſt it ſo from burſting; thou haſt tide</l>
                           <l>with thy kind counſel, all theſe looſned ſtrings,</l>
                           <l>they ſhould not crack aſunder with their weight.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Then liſten now, the beſt plot I can think,</l>
                           <l>is this: We here will live a while unknown:</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> thy Profeſſion ſhall be Phyſick,</l>
                           <l>I as your friend t'company you at Court;</l>
                           <l>carry it neatly, learn a few ſtrange words,</l>
                           <l>palliate your woe a while, and coope up grief,</l>
                           <l>you may in time ſo miniſter to the King;</l>
                           <l>Phyſicks occaſion fit revenge may bring.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Rarely invented, I'll ſpeak Aphoriſms,</l>
                           <l>ſublim'd Purgations, Quinteſſence diſtill'd,</l>
                           <l>each Doſe I give ſhall make a heart to bleed,</l>
                           <l>and prove a true Phyſician ſo indeed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Enter Myſander, having o'r-heard their talk.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                           <l>'Twas my good Genius guided me here now,</l>
                           <l>to hear Conſpiracy; wherefore I'll attach them.</l>
                           <l>Save you Gentlemen.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>Save you too, if you pleaſe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Sir, 'twas ſmall manners to interrupt our talk,</l>
                           <l>and give no warning of your being neer.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Warning? you ſhall have warning, yes, I know</l>
                           <l>I heard you both, and underſtood your plot,</l>
                           <l>you'll turn Phyſician, Sir, and give rare Clyſters,</l>
                           <l>ſhall work like <hi>Stibium,</hi> to purge our hearts:</l>
                           <l>You thought to act well true Phyſicians parts.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Therefore on thee our Medicine firſt ſhall work.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Stabs him.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="233" facs="119"/>
                           <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Help, murder.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay Paraſite, I'll gag you,</l>
                           <l>you ſhall not fawn again, or wag your tayl,</l>
                           <l>when the King nods.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Myſ.</speaker>
                           <l>O help me, I am ſlain.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Stop his breath quickly, if but he be dead,</l>
                           <l>we may eſcape the danger of the treaſon.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay he is ſilent; O, but we are beſet.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 3.</head>
                        <stage>Enter a Lord and others at the out-cry.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                           <l>Look out, me thought I heard one cry out murder,</l>
                           <l>ſome voice I am ſure did diſturbe the Court,</l>
                           <l>it was <hi>Myſanders</hi> voice, me thought that cried,</l>
                           <stage>Spies him dead.</stage>
                           <l>and ſee, hee's ſlain; one whom the Kings eſteem</l>
                           <l>did rank among the beſt; there are the Murderers:</l>
                           <l>Fellows, how durſt you thus abuſe the Court?</l>
                           <l>Go, haſte to' th' King, tell him the men be here.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>Gentlemen, we as lovers to the Court,</l>
                           <l>came here as ſtrangers, for to ſee the King,</l>
                           <l>this man being coming out, too ſoon for us;</l>
                           <l>and for himſelf us'd us uncivilly;</l>
                           <l>we have been Gentlemen, though our Fortunes now</l>
                           <l>have put on Beggars weeds upon our backs:</l>
                           <l>who anſwering in the ſame ſort he propos'd,</l>
                           <l>he ſtruck us, and men cannot endure blows:</l>
                           <l>ſo thinking much to be ſtruck again,</l>
                           <l>he grew ſo hot, he drew and made a Stab;</l>
                           <l>at which encounter both incloſing him</l>
                           <l>'twixt us he took a wound worſe than we thought</l>
                           <l>to give, for we did think to have given none;</l>
                           <l>But ſince 'tis thus, we muſt appeal to th' King.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes; and here comes his Majeſty in perſon.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <pb n="234" facs="120"/>
                        <head>Scena 4.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aegyſtheus, with a Guard.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegy.</speaker>
                           <l>A Guard there on us, here is murder done.</l>
                           <l>What, is <hi>Myſander</hi> kil'd, our truſty ſervant?</l>
                           <l>Where are the vilians?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O hold good heart, hark, hark, he calls us villains.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegy.</speaker>
                           <l>What is the matter? ſpeak, how came he dead?</l>
                           <l>They ſhall die two deaths, that did cauſe him one.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>O eſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O I am now undone; he muſt ſit judge,</l>
                           <l>to condemne us, that ſhould maſſacre him.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, keep a temper, hold good friend a while.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
                           <l>My gracious ſovereign, theſe two be the men,</l>
                           <l>which have confeſs'd the deed:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Are you the men which thus abus'd our ſtate?</l>
                           <l>Was't one or both? if both, you both ſhall die;</l>
                           <l>if one, that one: w're juſt in our Decree.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <head>Scen. 5.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Clyt. Tynd. Strophius, Electra.</stage>
                        <l>What, is my Queen come here, to hear the Cauſe?</l>
                        <l>We'll then aſcend, and judge them inſtantly.</l>
                        <stage>Aſcends the Throne.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Or.</speaker>
                           <l>O crack my ey-ſtrings, let theſe balls drop out,</l>
                           <l>or the quick ſights like darts fly to their ſouls,</l>
                           <l>and pierce their entrails; he King, my mother Queen!</l>
                           <l>The <hi>Briſeis</hi> and <hi>Achilles,</hi> that in my dream.</l>
                           <l>We come to be condemn'd amongſt our friends.</l>
                           <l>I will ſpeak to them, <hi>Electra</hi>'s there,</l>
                           <l>And <hi>Storphius,</hi> your old Father, <hi>Pylades.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Shew thy ſelf valorous, o'recome thy ſelf:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="235" facs="120"/>If we be known, we ſurely are condemn'd.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Father, Lord <hi>Strophius,</hi> ſit and hear the cauſe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, my Lord, what is't makes the buſineſs thus?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>My Queen ſhall ſtraitway know; Bring them away.</l>
                           <l>Although it is not fallen out of our minde,</l>
                           <l>of a free act of pardon of all faults</l>
                           <l>commited in the date of ſuch a time,</l>
                           <l>our hand of mercy muſt not be ſo ſoft,</l>
                           <l>to cover o're with gentle lenity,</l>
                           <l>ſuch ulcerous ſores as theſe; there is no place</l>
                           <l>for mercy left; murder muſt not finde grace:</l>
                           <l>Therefore our doom is paſt, one needs muſt die,</l>
                           <l>blood ſtill for blood unto the gods will cry.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Then, if thy doom be ſpent, great King here ſtands;</l>
                           <l>the man that did it, ſhewing his guilty hands.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>O hold thy doom a while; it was not he,</l>
                           <l>His ſerious ſtudies in the learned Arts,</l>
                           <l>hearing acute Philoſophers diſpute</l>
                           <l>'twixt life and death, and of a future ſtate</l>
                           <l>would fain haſte to it; but the man was I:</l>
                           <l>beleeve not him, 'twas his deſire to die.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>No King, 'tis he which in his deſperate thoughts,</l>
                           <l>would looſe the bands betwixt his ſoul and him;</l>
                           <l>ones ſelf againſt ones ſelf is witneſs ſtore,</l>
                           <l>my ſelf confeſſes, what wouldſt thou have more?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Believe him not, upon my knees I vow,</l>
                           <stage>Kneels.</stage>
                           <l>theſe hands are only branded with the guilt,</l>
                           <l>and for ones blood, let not two lives be ſpilt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>And on my knees I the like Oath do take,</l>
                           <l>I gave the ſtab, my Dagger's bloody yet.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>That was my Dagger, King, he took't from me.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Or.</speaker>
                           <l>He do's me wrong, by—, 'twas ever mine.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>This doth amaze us, I ne're yet ſaw two</l>
                           <l>turn Rhetoricians ſo to plead for death.</l>
                           <l>Would not the pardon of this odious fact,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="236" facs="121"/>like a foul ſtench, or an unwholſom air,</l>
                           <l>ſend an infectious vapour through the Land,</l>
                           <l>and choak up Juſtice; this fidelity</l>
                           <l>ſhould for this one time ſet two murderers free.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
                           <l>Now good my love, methinks I pity them,</l>
                           <l>and prethee for my ſake (I know them not)</l>
                           <l>abate thy edge of Juſtice for this once.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O what ſhe ſpoke! to damne it had been better.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>My love, thou knowſt I never look too ſtern</l>
                           <l>upon a fault that could ask lenity.</l>
                           <l>But this is ſo tranſcendent, and ſo great,</l>
                           <l>it muſt not be ſlipt with impunity.</l>
                           <l>To do a heynous murder, and i'th'Court,</l>
                           <l>i'th place of Juſtice, where the King might hear,</l>
                           <l>upon a chief attendant of the Kings!</l>
                           <l>Murder it ſelf is paſt all expiation,</l>
                           <l>the greateſt crime that Nature doth abhor:</l>
                           <l>not being, is abominable to her;</l>
                           <l>and when we be make others not to be,</l>
                           <l>'tis worſe than beſtial: and we did not ſo,</l>
                           <l>when only we by natures ayd did live</l>
                           <l>a Heterogenious kind, as ſemibeaſts,</l>
                           <l>when reaſon challeng'd ſcarce a part in us;</l>
                           <l>but now doth manhood and civility</l>
                           <l>ſtand at the Bar of Juſtice, and there plead,</l>
                           <l>how much they'r wronged, and how much defac't</l>
                           <l>when man doth dye his hands in blood of man.</l>
                           <l>Judgement it ſelf would ſcarce a Law enact</l>
                           <l>againſt the murderer, thinking it a fact</l>
                           <l>that man 'gainſt man would never dare commit,</l>
                           <l>ſince the worſt things of nature do not it.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O how his words now rail againſt a ſin,</l>
                           <l>which beat upon his Conſcious thoughts within!</l>
                           <l>His tongue ſpeaks fair, his inparts, look on them,</l>
                           <l>and they like Jury-men himſelf condemne:
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>But O great King, if juſtice muſt have right,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="237" facs="121"/>let me ſtand only guilty in thy ſight.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>No, 'tis not, King, 'twas I that did the deed,</l>
                           <l>and for my action, let no other bleed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>In troth this makes my Doom it cannot fall:</l>
                           <l>Will none of you confeſs?
<stage>Strophius weeps.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, I confeſs.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>No King, 'tis I confeſs.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>How now Lord <hi>Strophius,</hi> what affects you ſo,</l>
                           <l>that makes your tears bewrayers of ſome paſſion?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stroph.</speaker>
                           <l>My gracious Sovereign, this ſtrange ſpectacle</l>
                           <l>renews the Memory of my once great loſs,</l>
                           <l>and my dear Queens, we once were bleſt with two,</l>
                           <l>which ſo had link'd themſelves in bands of love,</l>
                           <l>as theſe men now do ſeem to me they have.</l>
                           <l>One ſtream of love did in two hearts ſo glide,</l>
                           <l>one with the other liv'd, with th'other di'd.</l>
                           <l>And would my Queen be my competitor,</l>
                           <l>for our Sons ſake my ſuits ſhould joyn with her,</l>
                           <l>ſince Juſtice craves but one, and both will go,</l>
                           <l>even ſave them both, and right wrong'd Juſtice ſo.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>I, good my love, let Juſtice come and look,</l>
                           <l>if ſhe can finde in all her Statute Book,</l>
                           <l>two men for the ſame crime ſhould rightly die;</l>
                           <l>ſhe will not ſay ſo, Juſtice cannot lie.</l>
                           <l>And ſince they both will die, let ones love ſave</l>
                           <l>the others life, and ſo both life ſhall have.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>In troth my Queen, and my old Lord have mov'd.</l>
                           <l>Well, ſince your loves are both ſo ſtrongly tyed,</l>
                           <l>and friendſhip like an old acquaintance ſends</l>
                           <l>to her friend Juſtice that ſhe ſhould be milde,</l>
                           <l>and looks with eyes of Mercy on your fault,</l>
                           <l>conſidering our immunity proclaim'd,</l>
                           <l>and ſuch Petitioners as you both have got,</l>
                           <l>Death in our Sentence, now ſhall have no part;</l>
                           <l>whilſt who ſhould have done worſt, confeſſion ſtrives,</l>
                           <l>too much confeſſion thus ſaves two mens lives:</l>
                           <l>But now we muſt demand, what you made here?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="238" facs="122"/>What buſineſs or condition you profeſs?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>Great King, our duty owes to thee our lives,</l>
                           <l>and were we men that ſtriv'd to ſet a cloud</l>
                           <l>before theſe gifts, Art hath inſtructed us,</l>
                           <l>or we have purchac't at a moſt dear rate,</l>
                           <l>of coſt and labour; yet thy clemency</l>
                           <l>commands us to lay open all to thee:</l>
                           <l>yet for my ſelf I rather count my ſtate</l>
                           <l>bleſt that I lighted on this honeſt man;</l>
                           <l>whoſe accurate and watchful indagation,</l>
                           <l>hath taught him for to heal the wounds of Nature,</l>
                           <l>by his exceeding skill in wholſom herbs;</l>
                           <l>one, that when I did think my shred of life</l>
                           <l>had been quite cut, did tie it up again,</l>
                           <l>and make it laſt: recall'd my youthful dayes,</l>
                           <l>and made me <hi>Aeſon</hi>-like, become thus young;</l>
                           <l>for which great practiſe I did owe my life,</l>
                           <l>and thence proceeded our late pious ſtrife.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aeg.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay then I'm glad our mercy did extend</l>
                           <l>on men whom ſuch rare vertues do commend;</l>
                           <l>our love ſhall then grow greater, &amp; our Court</l>
                           <l>ſhall entertain you, and't may chance we will,</l>
                           <l>my Queen and I, make tryal of your skill.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>My gracious Sovereign, words muſt not have wings,</l>
                           <l>to paſs and to out-flye the bounds of truth,</l>
                           <l>only to win the <hi>Elixar</hi> of opinion;</l>
                           <l>but for my friend, I here profeſs ſo much,</l>
                           <l>and for my life do ſtand ſo deeply bound,</l>
                           <l>that all my Art can ne're make recompence.</l>
                           <l>Pleaſe but your Graces ſelf▪ and your dear Queen,</l>
                           <l>appoint the ſecrets of the ſafeſt room</l>
                           <l>to let me ſhew my ſelf to none but you;</l>
                           <l>though Nature dried up with too much time,</l>
                           <l>deny to ſpring in fruit from forth your loins,</l>
                           <l>or any other ſtrange impediment;</l>
                           <l>our Art preſerves from ſickneſs ruining.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="239" facs="122"/>And 'twill be bleſt to ſhew it to a King.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Ha, prethee let me ſpeak with thee apart.</l>
                           <l>Thou ſtrik'ſt on tunes now, make me glad to hear,</l>
                           <l>we will commit our ſecreſie to thee.</l>
                           <l>Can'ſt water barren Wombs with ſuch a dew,</l>
                           <l>ſhall make 'em flouriſh and wax green with fruit?</l>
                           <l>Although we cannot altogether blame,</l>
                           <l>that Nature hath been too unkind to us;</l>
                           <l>yet we would plant each corner of our Realm</l>
                           <l>with ſpringing Branches of our Royal ſelf,</l>
                           <l>to compaſs in our ſelves, and we ſtand in the midſt.</l>
                           <l>Kings in their Children do great bleſſing finde,</l>
                           <l>and great men love to Propagate their kinde.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Great Sovereign, boaſting words ſhall ne're out-weigh</l>
                           <l>the things I will perform, I ſpeak not fame,</l>
                           <l>but what I have ſaid, I will do the ſame.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>We like thy temper well, and we will truſt;</l>
                           <l>therefore this night we will appoint it ſo,</l>
                           <l>thou ſhalt be guided to our ſecretſt room,</l>
                           <l>and there ſhalt uſe thy skill; which if it take,</l>
                           <l>our love ſhall honour thee for Phyſicks ſake.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt Aegyſt. Clyt. Tynd.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Good heavens I thank you, your effectual power</l>
                           <l>hath ſhewed your juſtice in this bleſſed hour.</l>
                           <l>Now is occaſion put; thus murder layes</l>
                           <l>the trap wherein it ſelf, it ſelf betrayes.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Old Lord, a word with you.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>and with you Lady.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>They take Stroph. and Elect. back.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Had not you once a Son lov'd the young prince?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stop.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes Sir, but Fates envied my happineſs,</l>
                           <l>and holds both Prince and Son away too long.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>And had not you a brother (Lady) once?</l>
                           <l>When heard you of him laſt? He went to travel.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>In truth I had, but I can hear no news.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>They diſcover themſelves.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="240" facs="123"/>
                           <speaker>Stro.</speaker>
                           <l>O ſee! my ſon! welcome my deareſt boy.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Our Brother, our <hi>Oreſtes</hi> is come home.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stroph.</speaker>
                           <l>'Tis they indeed; O how my blood revives!</l>
                           <l>Let me embrace them; O ye'r welcome home,</l>
                           <l>now is the Autumne of our ſorrow done.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>What ſilent place hath ſmothered you ſo long?</l>
                           <l>Of what great Powers have you counſel ta'ne,</l>
                           <l>concerning the great Plot you had in hand?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Uncle, and Siſter, we muſt not ſtand now</l>
                           <l>embracing much, and bidding welcome home;</l>
                           <l>you ſee before I come, how things do ſtand:</l>
                           <l>My buſineſs haſtens; and my friend, and I,</l>
                           <l>have yet a greater Project to perform:</l>
                           <l>Only <hi>Electra,</hi> we muſt have your ayde,</l>
                           <l>to help us with their Child, for now's the time,</l>
                           <l>when bleſt occaſion ſtrives to help revenge.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Why Brother, is the Child in any fault?</l>
                           <l>that was unborn when that our Father died:</l>
                           <l>And 'tis a luſty boy: O hurt not that.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Tuſh, I muſt have it, it ſhall have no hurt,</l>
                           <l>worſe than my Father:</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Shal't not, indeed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Believe me, no worſe hurt; but let's be gone.</l>
                           <l>I'le be a tripode <hi>Paracelſian.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="scene">
                        <head>Scen. 6.</head>
                        <stage>Enter a Chamberlain, and a Boy to ſweep the Room.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
                           <l>Boy, ſweep the room, ſet each thing in his place,</l>
                           <l>the King and Queen take Phyſick here to night.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                           <l>Sir, and you'll help me, I am ready here,</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>They ſet a Table.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
                           <l>Fetch them two Chairs.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, Sir.</l>
                           <l>What Carpet mean you ſhall be ſpread a'th boord?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="241" facs="123"/>
                           <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
                           <l>That of red velvet, ſet the ſilver cups,</l>
                           <l>there may be uſe of them to take the potion:</l>
                           <stage>Sets two bowles.</stage>
                           <l>So, now all's well, the room is well prepar'd.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Enter Oreſtes, like a Doctor of Phyſick.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Is this the room, friend, where the King muſt be?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, this is the room Sir, 'tis the privat'ſt, this.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>You muſt avoyd it then, and tell his Grace,</l>
                           <l>that I ſtay here provided 'gainſt he come.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
                           <l>His Grace ſhall know it.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 7.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Pylades, with a little boy in's hand.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>I faith <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> prethee ſpare the child,</l>
                           <l>it hath no fault, but 'tis too like thy mother.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Like my mother, O moſt execrable!</l>
                           <l>hadſt rank'd the confus'd <hi>Chaos</hi> of all ſins,</l>
                           <l>thou couldſt not have found out a fault more black,</l>
                           <l>more ſtinking, more infectious to my heart.</l>
                           <l>Art like my mother, O tranſcendent crime!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                           <l>Some ſay I'm eyd like her, but in the face</l>
                           <l>I do reſemble moſt the King my father.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Poor babe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>The King thy father! yes, too like them both.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Electra</hi> ſays, I'm ſomewhat like <hi>Oreſtes,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>her brother that is dead.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>How, like <hi>Oreſtes!</hi> when didſt ſee him child?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                           <l>Indeed I never ſaw him, but I love him.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Alas, dear friend, ſee the pretty knave.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>Would thou wert not my mothers, I could weep,</l>
                           <l>but ſee, O ſee now my relenting heart,</l>
                           <l>muſt now grow flinty, ſee my father, ſee,</l>
                           <l>now to ſhew pity were impiety.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <pb n="242" facs="124"/>
                           <hi>Enter Agamemnons ghoſt, paſſing o're the ſtage all wounded.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ghoſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why flaggs revenge? ſee thy now yeelding ſoul,</l>
                           <l>made me burſt ope my ſtrong jaw'd ſepulcher,</l>
                           <l>and rip the ſeare-cloth from my wounded breaſt.</l>
                           <l>O can a child ſmile blanke the memory</l>
                           <l>of all theſe horrid wounds, that make me groan,</l>
                           <l>in the darke caverns of the uncoucht earth?</l>
                           <l>from whence I come for to infect thy ſoul</l>
                           <l>with ayre of vengeance, may make <hi>Acheron,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>yea, and our ſelves, at the performance quake.</l>
                           <l>Fruit of our loynes, firſt vigor of our youth,</l>
                           <l>look on theſe wounds, as on the <hi>Gorgons</hi> head,</l>
                           <l>and turn thy heart to ſtone: hovering revenge</l>
                           <l>is falne into thy hands, O graſp her cloſe</l>
                           <l>by her ſnake knotted front, and make her do</l>
                           <l>things may incite a horror to her ſelf.</l>
                           <l>Forget all mother, in that diſloyal witch,</l>
                           <l>whoſe damned heate raging in ſtrumpets blood,</l>
                           <l>ſo ſoon did condeſcend to murther me.</l>
                           <l>By all the rights of Father I conjure thee:</l>
                           <l>By <hi>Atreus, Atreus,</hi> he whoſe revengeful ſoul</l>
                           <l>is eccho'd through the world ſuperlative;</l>
                           <l>do thou make <hi>Nemeſis</hi> as great a feaſt,</l>
                           <l>and be enthroniz'd in her fiery chaire,</l>
                           <l>in her triumphant chariot ever ride,</l>
                           <l>in which, Beares hurry her from the womb of hell,</l>
                           <l>and bear this Title as thy deſerved hire,</l>
                           <l>the brave revenger of thy murdred ſire.</l>
                           <l>Think on me, and revenge.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Stay, ſtay, and ſee't,</l>
                           <l>ſtay Sprite, thou ſtrik'ſt no terror to my ſoul:</l>
                           <l>For unamaz'd I now would dare out-look</l>
                           <l>ranks of <hi>Meduſa's,</hi> and the grim aſpect</l>
                           <l>of the moſt frowning object hell affords.</l>
                           <l>Think on me and revenge! yes, thoſe two words</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="243" facs="124"/>ſhall ſerve as burthen unto all my acts,</l>
                           <l>I will revenge, and then I'll think on thee:</l>
                           <l>I'll think on thee, and then again revenge,</l>
                           <l>and ſtab, and wound, and ſtill I'll think on thee:</l>
                           <l>I have a dropſie now to ſuck up fumes,</l>
                           <l>and drink the reaking ſtreams of vengeance fome:</l>
                           <l>Great <hi>Agamemnons</hi> Ghoſt, I will bedew</l>
                           <l>thy hearſe with blood in ſtead of briniſh tears,</l>
                           <l>and build a pile up of their murdered trunks,</l>
                           <l>to burn thy marrow-leſſe conſumed bones.</l>
                           <l>Arrows of forked lightening never flew</l>
                           <l>more ſwiftly from the awful arms of <hi>Jove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>then <hi>Nemeſis</hi> black Scorpions from me.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>'Twas a ſtrange ſight.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>I, didſt thou ſee't friend?</l>
                           <l>all of thoſe wounds will I ſtick in his breſt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Alas, one will be enough for him?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>I, but ſhe ſhall have more. A while go by:</l>
                           <stage>Pylades takes the child aſide:</stage>
                           <l>Were all the world their lives, the world ſhould die.</l>
                           <l>Now Tragedy fetch out thy crimſon robes,</l>
                           <l>and buckle ſure thy purple buskins on,</l>
                           <l>ſteep't ten grains deeper in their ſcarlet die;</l>
                           <l>this night ſhall give me now a deep carouſe,</l>
                           <l>of <hi>Clytemneſtrae's</hi> and <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> blood,</l>
                           <l>and <hi>Cerberus</hi> himſelf ſtand by to pledge me,</l>
                           <l>whileſt to hells fire I ſhall ſacrifice</l>
                           <l>three Hecatombs; it doth the furies good,</l>
                           <l>when e'r we wet their Altars with ſuch blood.</l>
                           <l>And now ye fiends of hell, each take a place,</l>
                           <l>as 'twere ſpectators at a firſt dayes play;</l>
                           <l>raiſe all the helliſh winds to expel nature:</l>
                           <l>Great Goddeſſe give me leave now to forget</l>
                           <l>all ſtrains of duty; all obedient thoughts</l>
                           <l>die in me quite: a mothers memory,</l>
                           <l>pious affections take no hold on me.</l>
                           <l>Be all my ſenſes circled in with Fiends,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="244" facs="125"/>and let <hi>Erynnis</hi> hold her flaming brand</l>
                           <l>to guide my murderous ſword; for all lights elſe,</l>
                           <l>vaniſh from out this Center, be this room fraught</l>
                           <l>ſo full of miſchief, may make the Fabrick crack,</l>
                           <l>and let no time now come into my thoughts,</l>
                           <l>but that dire night wherein my father dy'd.</l>
                           <l>I'll only be a Doctor now in word,</l>
                           <l>each potion that I give ſhall be my ſword.</l>
                           <l>But I muſt change.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena. 8.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Aegyſtheus and Clytemneſtra, in their night-robes.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O Doctor, you are buſie for our coming.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>My gracious Lord, I had no cauſe to fail.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Oreſtes looking on the cups.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, but is this fit time for phyſick, Doctor?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Firſt, Madam, for the phyſick that I give,</l>
                           <l>now the diaſtal fabrick of your pulſe,</l>
                           <l>ſhews all your paſſions moſt hyſterical.</l>
                           <l>Pleaſeth your Grace ſit down? on at each end o'th table.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, muſt we ſit? ſit there my Queen.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, now is <hi>Saturn,</hi> governour of nature,</l>
                           <l>in free conjunction with the planet <hi>Venus:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>And juſt at this time <hi>Jupiter</hi> begat</l>
                           <l>great <hi>Hercules: Sol, Luna, Mercury.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>in that Diameter, now favour propagation,</l>
                           <l>and now will my <hi>Alexipharmacon</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>ſtir the <hi>Analeptick</hi> veines and arteries:</l>
                           <l>If you out-live this night, you'll live to ſee</l>
                           <l>a royal, ſtrange, and Princely progeny.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Think'ſt thou ſo, Doctor?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Think it, nay, I know't.</l>
                           <l>Hem.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Surely he means to work rare Art upon us.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="245" facs="125"/>
                           <speaker>Aegy.</speaker>
                           <l>Pray God thy phyſick take.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, it ſhall take.</l>
                           <l>Hem.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Pylades binds Clytemneſtra to the chair: O|reſtes Egystheus: Pylades brings in the child.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egy.</speaker>
                           <l>Treaſon, we are betraid.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Or.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, tis your privat'ſt room.</l>
                           <l>View me wel mother, ha, do you know me yet?</l>
                           <stage>Puts off his gown.</stage>
                           <l>Here, here's the drugs my Art hath thought upon:</l>
                           <l>be pitileſſe now <hi>Pylades,</hi> be my friend.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                           <l>O help me father, elſe theſe men will kill me.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O my boy, my boy.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O ye'r faſt bound.</l>
                           <l>Yes, he is thine, thy face, thy eyes, thy heart,</l>
                           <l>and would I knew where Nature had couchd moſt,</l>
                           <l>of thy damnd blood, I thus would let it out,</l>
                           <stage>Stabs the child.</stage>
                           <l>and thus't ſhould ſprit in thy moſt loathed face.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egy.</speaker>
                           <l>O now the heavens rain vengeance on our heads.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                           <l>O mother, mother, ſave me, ſave me father.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Hold <hi>Pylades,</hi> be ſteadfaſt, for by—</l>
                           <l>he wounds me, that perſwades me not to wound.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O turn thy bloody weapon on my breſt,</l>
                           <l>'twas this womb that brought forth this babe and thee,</l>
                           <l>If that be guilty, I have made it ſo.</l>
                           <l>Rip up this place which firſt did bring thee forth,</l>
                           <l>'tis I intreat thee, 'tis thy mother, ſhe</l>
                           <l>which gave thee houſ-room here within this breſt,</l>
                           <l>upon whoſe dugs thy infant lips did hang.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>It was my father, he intreated you,</l>
                           <l>who many a time had clipt you in his arms,</l>
                           <l>who made you Queen of Greece, yes, it was he,</l>
                           <l>good <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> he did plead for life.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Egyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Bath not thy hands in a poor infants blood,</l>
                           <l>nor in thy mothers, I deſerve to die:</l>
                           <l>and yet remember how my doom ſav'd thee,</l>
                           <l>how eaſily mercy did obtain her ſuit.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, but <hi>Egyſtheus,</hi> you can aggravate,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="246" facs="126"/>to doe a haynous murther, and i'th Court;</l>
                           <l>I'th place of Juſtice, where the King might hear,</l>
                           <l>upon a chief attendant of the Kings.</l>
                           <l>Murther it ſelf is paſt all expiation,</l>
                           <l>a crime that nature moſt of all abhors,</l>
                           <l>and look how manhood and civility,</l>
                           <l>ſtand at the bar of Juſtice, and there plead,</l>
                           <l>how much they'r wrong'd, and how much defac'd,</l>
                           <l>when man doth dye his hands in blood of man.</l>
                           <l>Now hearken King, I'll uſe thy Rhetorick,</l>
                           <l>thou didſt a haynous murther in the Court,</l>
                           <l>not which the King did hear, but which he felt;</l>
                           <l>when no petition could (good man) prevaile,</l>
                           <l>therefore this dies, this firſt ſhall have his due,</l>
                           <stage>Stabs it againe, that the blood ſpirts in his face.</stage>
                           <l>this miſchief done, revenge ſhall prompt anew.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aeg.</speaker>
                           <l>O, the gods bluſh, and heaven looks pale at this,</l>
                           <l>a fathers face beſmear'd with his childs blood!</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>My haſt deceives my will; tuſh, all this yet,</l>
                           <l>may be call'd piety; you ſhall taſt too, mother.</l>
                           <stage>Turns it to her.</stage>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, why dos't baniſh nature from his place?</l>
                           <l>Look on thy mothers tears, worſe then thoſe groans,</l>
                           <l>and pangs ſhe had, when ſhe firſt brought thee forth.</l>
                           <l>When of thy friends or parents thou haſt wrong,</l>
                           <l>patience, not fury doth to thee belong.</l>
                           <l>Is this the bleſſing that thy knee ſhould ask?</l>
                           <l>Repay'ſt thou thus my kiſſes and my tears,</l>
                           <l>which flow'd from me to thee in tender years?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O why did you ſo baniſh woman-hood,</l>
                           <l>when you and this damn'd villain, baſe adulterer,</l>
                           <l>made in my fathers ſide ſo many wounds,</l>
                           <l>and brought a brave old King into this ſtate?</l>
                           <l>See here's his bones, my pocket can contain.</l>
                           <stage>Pulls bones from his pocket.</stage>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="247" facs="126"/>great <hi>Agamemnon;</hi> and repayd you thus</l>
                           <l>his kind embraces? all his loving ſigns?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> you are thirſty, you ſhall drink,</l>
                           <stage>Fills two cups with the childs blood: gives it them</stage>
                           <l>yes, you ſhall clear your throat, by — you ſhall.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegy.</speaker>
                           <l>O miſchief above miſchief! what <hi>Heniochus</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>bred on a ſtony rock, could e'r endure</l>
                           <l>to ſee a fathers thirſt quench'd with ſuch blood?</l>
                           <l>Haſt thou no meaſure, hath revenge no end?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>Who firſt doth miſchief, may keep mean i'th deed,</l>
                           <l>but who revengeth, muſt all mean exceed.</l>
                           <l>Nay mother wee'l not bar you of your draught.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Gives one cup to her.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O Nature, ſee here all thy law infring'd,</l>
                           <l>a mothers prayers prevail not with her ſon.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Pray with <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> it ſhall never move me:</l>
                           <l>But firſt <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> Do thou haſte revenge.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Stabs him.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, I am wounded, O when doſt thou end?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, I have ſcarce begun. Now mother, you.</l>
                           <stage>Sabs her</stage>
                           <l>So now, I'll ſtand and look, and on hell call,</l>
                           <l>nay, my revenge muſt not be uſual:</l>
                           <l>One more for thee <hi>Aegyſtheus;</hi> only let out</l>
                           <l>the blood you drank before.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegyſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, my heart feels it.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Now mother you, and your love the ſame.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O kill me quickly, time prolongs my wo,</l>
                           <l>and ſince I muſt die, let me quickly goe.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>You know your ſentence; <hi>Let him feel he dies.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>who ſtrait threats death, knows not to tyrannize.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Aegy.</speaker>
                           <l>This brings ten deaths.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Or.</speaker>
                           <l>Would twould an 100 bring,</l>
                           <l>one death's too little to revenge a King.</l>
                           <l>Hence, hence, adulterous ſoul to <hi>Tantalus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>and let hell know who 'twas ſent thee thither:
<stage>he dies.</stage>
                           </l>
                           <l>Now, mother, you ſhall follow: but he firſt,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="248" facs="127"/>leſt that like Lovers you go hand in hand.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why ſon, whoſe death is it thou doſt revenge?</l>
                           <l>thy fathers? but on whom? upon thy mother!</l>
                           <l>On her which brought thee forth, which took moſt care,</l>
                           <l>to bring thee up, from whom thou tookſt thy ſelf?</l>
                           <l>thou'rt ſure thou art mine, but doſt not know,</l>
                           <l>who 'twas begate thee.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Wil't Baſtardize me?</l>
                           <l>Yes, mother, yes, I know I was his ſon:</l>
                           <l>Alas! why, what are you? a ſenſeleſſe peice</l>
                           <l>of rotten earth can do as much to corn,</l>
                           <l>as you to me, bear it, and bring it forth;</l>
                           <l>but <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> he that ſeed did ſow,</l>
                           <l>and only unto him my ſelf I ow:</l>
                           <l>and for him thou ſhalt die.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
                           <l>O, I confeſſe,</l>
                           <l>my conſcience tells me, I deſerve no leſſe:</l>
                           <l>and thus thy mother from thee doth depart,</l>
                           <l>leaving vexation to torment thy heart.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>She dies.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Now friend, I ſee my father live again,</l>
                           <l>and in his royal ſtate at <hi>Argos</hi> Court:</l>
                           <l>This is the night in which he firſt came home,</l>
                           <l>O bleſſed powers of hell, divine <hi>Canidia,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Now am I ſatisfied, now hath revenge perfection;</l>
                           <l>and nothing grieves me, but that <hi>Tyndarus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>my mothers father, did not ſee her die.</l>
                           <l>Ile in and tell him, my thoughts muſt reveale</l>
                           <l>thoſe acts I do: this night who would conceale?</l>
                           <l>Now ſoul triumph, whiſt that my deed ſhall ſhine,</l>
                           <l>I'th face o th Court, and all the world know't mine.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="act">
                     <pb n="249" facs="127"/>
                     <head>Actus 5.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 1.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Oreſtes in his gown: Tyndarus, Strophius, E|lectra, Pylades, two Lords.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, your daughters potion works moſt rarely;</l>
                           <l>the King's aſleep, God bleſſe his Majeſty.</l>
                           <l>O, do not wake him, faith 'tis pity, la.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>What do I ſee? ha, blood, the little child</l>
                           <l>dead! my daughter bleed? <hi>Aegyſtheus</hi> kill'd?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Your Lordſhips eyes do fail, 'tis but ſpilt wine.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Lay hands o'th villain, 'tis the Phyſicians deed.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay friends, hands off 'tis no Phyſician now:</l>
                           <stage>Diſcovers himſelf.</stage>
                           <l>See, ſee, old <hi>Tyndarus,</hi> doſt thou know me yet?</l>
                           <l>Fetch me my Crown and robes, nay, I'll aſcend:</l>
                           <l>Is not <hi>Atrides</hi> eldeſt ſon your King?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>What haſt thou done, foul Viper, to eat out</l>
                           <l>thy mothers bowels? what, was this thy deed?</l>
                           <l>Thy ſilence ſayes 'twas thine. What <hi>Tanais,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Tygris</hi> or <hi>Rhenus,</hi> or what flowing ſea,</l>
                           <l>ſhould waſh thee in the ſalt <hi>Meotis</hi> ſtreame?</l>
                           <l>Or <hi>Tethis</hi> at full tide o'rflow thy banks,</l>
                           <l>ſtill would the ſpots of murder ſtick on them.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why Grandſire, I go not about to waſh,</l>
                           <l>by—'twas all the fruit I thought to win,</l>
                           <l>to think all miſchief here could be no ſin.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>See, ſee, thy mother, look upon her now,</l>
                           <l>on her, whoſe eyes thou haſt for ever clos'd,</l>
                           <l>which eyes have often wakned at thy cry,</l>
                           <l>and huſh'd thee with a lullaby to ſleep:</l>
                           <l>See, ſee, theſe hands, which oft with ſo much care,</l>
                           <l>wrapt gently up thy unſet tender limbs.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="250" facs="128"/>See, ſee, this face, wont at thy ſignes to ſmile,</l>
                           <l>when nature gave not leave unto thy tongue</l>
                           <l>to utter thy childs meaning.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>See, ſee theſe bones, theſe naſty rotten bones,</l>
                           <l>which had ſo often lock'd his hands in hers;</l>
                           <l>here ſtood the tongue, which oft had call'd her ſweet,</l>
                           <l>dear <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> and then ſtopt his ſpeech,</l>
                           <l>and told his love in a more ſpeaking ſigne.</l>
                           <l>Here ſtood thoſe eyes, which fed upon her face,</l>
                           <l>and made her of thy daughter, a great Queen,</l>
                           <l>and ſhe made him a diſh for loathed worms.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Suppoſe ſhe did, there was but one yet dead,</l>
                           <l>and with ones death again ſhould be repaid.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>No, <hi>Tyndarus,</hi> had I deſir'd but one,</l>
                           <l>I ſhould have thought I had deſired none.</l>
                           <l>Why, methinks, I ſhould too have kill'd thee,</l>
                           <l>the number is too little yet of three.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Into what land, what country wilt thou fly?</l>
                           <l>all earths, all lands, all countries will fly thee:</l>
                           <l>the heavens will look with a more chearful brow</l>
                           <l>on <hi>Cerberus.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, let heaven look as 'twill, tis my crown,</l>
                           <l>that I have done an act ſhall make heave frown.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>O, what earth loves ſo much a guilty ſoul,</l>
                           <l>that it can bear thee?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, Sir, this is mine,</l>
                           <l>and this ſhall bear me. Am I not right heire?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Thou heir to kingdoms! thou a ſubject rather,</l>
                           <l>to help to make a Players Tragedy.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, that will make me ſwell with greater pride,</l>
                           <l>to think my name ſhall drop in lines of blood,</l>
                           <l>from ſome great Poets quill, who well ſhall paint</l>
                           <l>how bravely I reveng'd my fathers death;</l>
                           <l>that is the thing I wiſh'd, and 'tis my glory,</l>
                           <l>I ſhall be matter for ſo brave a ſtory.</l>
                           <l>But where's my Crown?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1. <hi>Lord.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>No murderer, wee'l rather joyn with him,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="251" facs="128"/>this old man here, to take away thy life,</l>
                           <l>then ſuch a homicide ſhall frame us laws,</l>
                           <l>who hath himſelf rac'd out the laws of Nature.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>2. <hi>Lord.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>Yes, and wee'l ſet here <hi>Argos</hi> crown on him,</l>
                           <l>who ſhall enact ſome pnniſhment for thee;</l>
                           <l>which although none can equalize this deed,</l>
                           <l>yet what our griefs can think, all ſhall be done,</l>
                           <l>and wee'l forget thou'rt <hi>Agamemnons</hi> ſonne.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>Why, think you on your worſt, I ſcorn to crave:</l>
                           <l>I had three lives, you but my one ſhall have.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tyn.</speaker>
                           <l>Then ſince vile wretch, thou haſt committed that,</l>
                           <l>which while there is a world, throughout the world</l>
                           <l>will be pronounc'd for the moſt horrid deed,</l>
                           <l>that ever came into the thought of man;</l>
                           <l>a thing which all will talk of, none allow:</l>
                           <l>I here diſclaim that name of Grand-father,</l>
                           <l>and I muſt quite forget that in thy veynes,</l>
                           <l>my blood doth flow, but think it then let out,</l>
                           <l>when thou letſt out my daughters. And ſince you,</l>
                           <l>kind Lords, commit the ſtate unto my years,</l>
                           <l>years too unfit, heavens know, to beare a ſtate:</l>
                           <l>My mind, methinks, contends for to decree</l>
                           <l>ſomewhat, which to my ſelf I dare not tell.</l>
                           <l>Juſt conceiv'd wrath, and my affection ſtrives,</l>
                           <l>hate forbids pity, pity forbids hate,</l>
                           <l>and exile is but barren puniſhtnent:</l>
                           <l>Yet let me baniſh thee from out theſe eyes,</l>
                           <l>O never let thy ſight offend me more,</l>
                           <l>all thy confederates, and all thy friends.</l>
                           <l>You, <hi>Pylades,</hi> which did ſo ſmoothly cloake,</l>
                           <l>the dam'nd profeſſion he did undertake:</l>
                           <l>You, <hi>Strophius.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Strop.</speaker>
                           <l>My Lord, I know not ought.</l>
                           <l>Yet ſince one foot is now in <hi>Charons</hi> boat,</l>
                           <l>if it pleaſe you, ſet tother too aflote.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Not ſo, but I will baniſh you the Court,</l>
                           <l>and you <hi>Electra;</hi> come, I muſt forget</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="252" facs="129"/>affection too towards you, you gave the child,</l>
                           <l>which you had charge of, to the murtherers ſword.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Why Grandſire, I herein no wrong do find,</l>
                           <l>ſince all theſe go, I would not ſtay behind.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay, but no one ſhall company the other,</l>
                           <l>hence thou <hi>Cocytus,</hi> ſtream of this offence,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Strophius</hi> and <hi>Pylades, Electra,</hi> hence.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt Strophius, Pylades, Electra.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why farwel Grandſire, ſince thou bidſt, I flie,</l>
                           <l>and ſcorn companions for my miſery.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit Oreſtes.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Unto this puniſhmeht this one more I add,</l>
                           <l>that none ſhall dare to give <hi>Oreſtes</hi> food,</l>
                           <l>and this decree ſhall ſtand; I ſpeak with grief,</l>
                           <l>and here pronounce <hi>Oreſtes</hi> no relief.</l>
                           <l>Hence with theſe corps; poor child, what hadſt thou don?</l>
                           <l>thy Nurſes prayers, that there might ſpring a roſe,</l>
                           <l>where e'r thou trod'ſt could not keep back thy foes.</l>
                           <l>Some plague he hath; but ſuch a matricide</l>
                           <l>ſhould never die, although he ever dy'd.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 2.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Electra and Strophius.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>Thus never leſſe alone, then when alone,</l>
                           <l>where to our ſelves we ſweetly tell our woes.</l>
                           <l>Thou Uncle, chief companion to our griefs,</l>
                           <l>and ſoul partaker of our miſeries,</l>
                           <l>why do we live, when now 'tis come to paſſe,</l>
                           <l>it is ſcarce known that <hi>Agamemnon</hi> was?</l>
                           <l>He dies far eaſier, who at firſt doth drown,</l>
                           <l>then he which long doth ſwim, and then ſinks down.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Stroph.</speaker>
                           <l>Nay Neece, me thinks I now do ſee the haven</l>
                           <l>where my ag'd ſoul muſt leave this toſſed bark,</l>
                           <l>made weak with years and woes: yet I commend</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="253" facs="129"/>unto my ſon the heart of a true friend,</l>
                           <l>that's all the will I leave, and let him know</l>
                           <l>friendſhip ſhould ever be, but moſt in woe.</l>
                           <l>And ſo I leave thee Neece, I firſt muſt die,</l>
                           <l>to haſt a period to this Tragedie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>He dies.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Elect.</speaker>
                           <l>O envious Fates could you not uſe me thus?</l>
                           <l>have I not grief enough to burſt my heart?</l>
                           <l>Was my life's thread twiſted and knit ſo ſtrong</l>
                           <l>that the keen edg of all theſe miſeries</l>
                           <l>can never cut it off? muſt I bear more?</l>
                           <l>'Tis all my ſafety now not to be ſafe.</l>
                           <l>Are there ſo many wayes to rid ones life,</l>
                           <l>and can I hit on none? They ſay that death</l>
                           <l>is every where, and yet I find him not:</l>
                           <l>Tuſh, but I ſeek him not: why my own hand</l>
                           <l>might graſp him to me, if I did but ſtrive.</l>
                           <l>Now hand help eaſe my heart, and make a way</l>
                           <l>to let out grief, that hath ſo long dwelt here;</l>
                           <stage>Stabs her ſelf.</stage>
                           <l>Now knife thou'ſt done good ſervice, there lie by,</l>
                           <l>heaven well decreed it, nothing life can give,</l>
                           <l>but every thing can make us not to live.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 3.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Caſſandra.</stage>
                        <l>Now <hi>Priams</hi> Ghoſt, haſte, haſte I ſay, to look,</l>
                        <l>with chearful eyes on the ſiniſter book,</l>
                        <l>and there to <hi>Hecuba</hi> my mother ſhew</l>
                        <l>the tragick ſtory of thy conquered foe.</l>
                        <l>And let <hi>Andromecha</hi> my ſiſter ſee,</l>
                        <l>what <hi>Agamemnons</hi> race is come to be.</l>
                        <l>Now Troy may gratifie that moſt ſad doom,</l>
                        <l>conquered by thoſe that thus themſelves or'ecome.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="254" facs="130"/>let Greece ſo flouriſh ſtill, let <hi>Argos</hi> be</l>
                        <l>puft with the pride of their great victory.</l>
                        <l>Let it bear Souldiers, ſo withal it bear</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Oreſtes</hi> too; now mother, never fear</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Argos</hi> makes me to laugh, which made thee weep;</l>
                        <l>the Trojans in the grave now ſweetly ſleep;</l>
                        <l>their ſorrow hath the end, now theſe begin</l>
                        <l>to overflow themſelves with mutual ſin:</l>
                        <l>And after all, <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> we may ſee,</l>
                        <l>hath loſt his reaſon, mans ſole propertie.</l>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 4.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Oreſtes furens.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>By—you ſhall not, nay, I am decreed:</l>
                           <l>do, tear, tear me; yes, I have deſerv'd it.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>O brave, O brave, he's mad as well as I;</l>
                           <l>I'm glad my madneſſe hath got company.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Mother, why mother, will you kill my father?</l>
                           <l>Then I'll kill you; tuſh, I have don't already.</l>
                           <l>Much patience will grow fury in time:</l>
                           <l>follow you me, you, beaſt, you damn'd <hi>Aegyſtheus.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>I'll hew thee piece by piece, look off my mother.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>I am ſhe, or one loves thee well.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ore.</speaker>
                           <l>Out you witch, you witch.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                           <l>Murderer, murderer.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Doſt. whiſper with the devils to torment me?</l>
                           <l>O how they laſh me with their ſnaky whips!</l>
                           <l>Why <hi>Megaera, Megaera,</hi> wilt not hold thy hand?</l>
                           <l>Are you there too, <hi>Erynnis?</hi> hey, all hell!</l>
                           <l>my Grandſier <hi>Atreus</hi> he ſtands fighting there,</l>
                           <l>but hee'll ha'th better on't; keep <hi>Cerberus,</hi> keep,</l>
                           <l>keep the gates faſt, or all hell breaks looſe.</l>
                           <l>Mother, I ſee you; O you are a whore.</l>
                           <l>Did I kill you, witch, doſt thou laugh, doſt: thou?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Why this is fine, my very looks do whip him.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Orest.</speaker>
                           <l>Could I but get the ſtone from <hi>Syſiphus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="255" facs="130"/>I'de daſh thy brains out; O, are you there I faith,</l>
                           <stage>Spies Strophius and Electra dead.</stage>
                           <l>a bed ſo cloſe with your adulterer?</l>
                           <l>I'll ſtab your luſtful ſouls with your own knives.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Stabs them with Electra's knife.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>O clap, clap, O rare beyond expectation:</l>
                           <l>hold good heart, do not burſt with laughter.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Will you not wake, ſleep, ſleep then your laſt.</l>
                           <l>Look how they fly i'th ayre.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Caſ</speaker>
                           <l>I ſee them, ſee them.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Why <hi>Jove,</hi> doſt mean to let them into heaven?</l>
                           <l>O th'art come down, and gone to hell;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Pluto,</hi> ſee <hi>Pluto,</hi> hee's afraid of them,</l>
                           <l>O ſpare my ſides, my ſides, my ſides, the blood!</l>
                           <l>O now you touch my ribs.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Caſſ.</speaker>
                           <l>Hey, how he skips! O excellent, whips himſelf!</l>
                           <l>O ſweet Cataſtrophe, do's non ſee't but I?</l>
                           <l>Clap, clap, again, would all <hi>Priams</hi> ſons</l>
                           <l>and daughters were here now to help me laugh.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Laſh on, laſh on. <hi>Canidia,</hi> art thou there?</l>
                           <l>why grandſire, would it were to do again:</l>
                           <l>nay <hi>Aeacus</hi> I feare no whipping poſts,</l>
                           <l>lavgh'ſt thou, thou witch? I'll follow thee to hell.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exeunt currentes.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="scene">
                        <head>Scen. 5.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Pylades alone.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Thus ſeeking others, I have loſt my ſelf,</l>
                           <l>my friend and father baniſht, and whilſt I</l>
                           <l>wander to ſeek them for to eaſe their woe,</l>
                           <l>I here more grief proclaim'd againſt my friend,</l>
                           <l>that none muſt ſuccor, none muſt give him food,</l>
                           <l>and yet I'll ſeek him; and ſhould all the laws,</l>
                           <l>that tyranny ſhould think upon, reſtrain,</l>
                           <l>I'de draw my blood forth for to let him drink.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="256" facs="131"/>But O what's here? O I have found too ſoon,</l>
                           <l>one which I ſought, my fathers wearied ſoul</l>
                           <stage>Spies Strophius dead.</stage>
                           <l>in ſighs hath now expired out it ſelf.</l>
                           <l>Now, O ye ſiſters, your great task is don,</l>
                           <l>you ne're untwine what you have once begun.</l>
                           <l>Thus obvious to our Fates, t'our ſelves unkind,</l>
                           <l>we haſte to ſeek, that which too ſoon we find.</l>
                           <l>Alas, why do our ſouls too greedy burn,</l>
                           <l>to haſten thither whence we nere return?</l>
                           <l>We run to't of our ſelves, 'sif death were ſlow;</l>
                           <l>ſhould he come tardy, we too ſoon ſhould go.</l>
                           <l>For the firſt day that gives us our firſt breath,</l>
                           <l>doth make us a day nearer unto death.</l>
                           <l>All this huge world, which now on earth ſo ſtrive,</l>
                           <l>to morrow this time may not be alive.</l>
                           <l>Great Troy is down, ſince <hi>Agamemnon</hi> fell,</l>
                           <l>ſince my dear father, which but now was well.</l>
                           <l>O art thou come dear friend, for thee I ſought,</l>
                           <stage>Enter Oreſtes.</stage>
                           <l>here's ſome food yet, in ſpight of all the laws.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Wilt bid me to dinner <hi>Pluto?</hi> ha, with what?</l>
                           <l>Give me no ſnakes, I, I go, I go,</l>
                           <l>up to <hi>Cythaerus</hi> top, I hate thy meat.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Heavens! he's diſtracted, now doth fury right,</l>
                           <l>when thus againſt her ſelf, her ſelf doth fight.</l>
                           <l>'Tis I (man) here, 'tis <hi>Pylades,</hi> not <hi>Pluto.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Ha, <hi>Pylades,</hi> I, they have baniſht him,</l>
                           <l>but grandſire look too't, I'll tear out your maw,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Pylades, Pylades</hi> I come.—</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>Why I am he, look friend, doſt not know me?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Or.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, yes thou wert with me when I kil'd my mother,</l>
                           <l>and ſee, the Furies now would whip thee too.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Alecto!</hi> look, look, here's <hi>Alecto</hi> too.</l>
                           <l>O <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> hay, how the Lion skips,</l>
                           <l>and <hi>Taurus</hi> he would toſſe me on his horns.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="257" facs="131"/>Look on the Ram, ſee the Beare roars at me,</l>
                           <l>and <hi>Charon</hi> he would fling me into <hi>Styx.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>He fears the heavenly ſigns, nay then now time</l>
                           <l>hath brought true puniſhment on every crime.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Daſh out the puppets brains, the little boy,</l>
                           <l>the baſtard, my mothers baſtard: ſo blood ſpin,</l>
                           <l>my mother kild my father, kild the King,</l>
                           <l>but ſhe got little by't, look on her breſt,</l>
                           <l>it bleeds, it bleeds; ſo, ſo <hi>Aegyſtheus,</hi> ſo.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>O what a ſtrange diſtemper ſtirs his brain!</l>
                           <l>Thou gentle <hi>Somnus,</hi> in whom care doth reſt,</l>
                           <l>kind father of cold death, and ſon of peace,</l>
                           <l>which comes to Kings and poor men all alike,</l>
                           <l>bind his diſturbed brain, tie up his ſenſe;</l>
                           <l>let him but live to die, now tis not long</l>
                           <l>before we both ſhall ſing our funeral ſong.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Ha! muſt I ſink? can I not keep aloft?</l>
                           <l>What is the ſtream ſo ſtrong? why then I'll dive,</l>
                           <stage>Falls a ſleep.</stage>
                           <l>and come to hell the ſooner.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pylad.</speaker>
                           <l>So gentle ſleep,</l>
                           <l>thou gather'ſt up his wandring brains again,</l>
                           <l>this is but half dead, yet half dead he lies,</l>
                           <l>but tis not long, before he wholly dyes. <hi>Muſick within.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Heark they play Muſick; O theſe ſounds do harm,</l>
                           <l>enticing wo with their melodious charm.</l>
                           <l>Theſe pleaſe not men in woe, theſe time do keep,</l>
                           <l>but miſeries beſt falling is to weep.</l>
                           <l>Our ſtops are nought but ſobs, our hearts we bring,</l>
                           <l>whereon we prick the ſol-fa which we ſing.</l>
                           <stage>A ſong within, together with the Muſick.</stage>
                           <quote>
                              <l>Weep, weep you Argonauts,</l>
                              <l>Bewail the day</l>
                              <l>That firſt to fatal Troy</l>
                              <l>You took your way.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb n="258" facs="132"/>Weep Greece, weep Greece,</l>
                              <l>Two Kings are dead,</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Argos,</hi> thou <hi>Argos,</hi> now a grave</l>
                              <l>Where Kings are buried.</l>
                              <l>No heire, no heire is left,</l>
                              <l>But one that's mad,</l>
                              <l>See <hi>Argos,</hi> haſt not thou</l>
                              <l>Cauſe to be ſad?</l>
                              <l>Sleep, ſleep wild brain,</l>
                              <l>Reſt rock thy ſence,</l>
                              <l>Live if thou canſt</l>
                              <l>To grieve for thy offence.</l>
                              <l>Weep, weep, you Argonauts, &amp;c.</l>
                           </quote>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Peace Muſick, peace, our plaints have louder cries,</l>
                           <l>a heart that's ſad can never harmonize.</l>
                           <l>Grief cannot keep his time, all time's too long,</l>
                           <l>ſighs are beſt ſem-briefs to his doleful ſong.</l>
                           <l>My ditties mournful, though thou ſweetly play,</l>
                           <l>thus do we all even blow our lives away.</l>
                           <stage>Oreſtes wakes.</stage>
                           <l>But doſt thou wake, <hi>Oreſtes?</hi> is reſt fled?</l>
                           <l>ſleep ne'r dwels long in a moleſted head.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Hark, hark, the Furies entertain my mother,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Orpheus</hi> would fetch <hi>Euridice</hi> from hell,</l>
                           <l>ſee, he looks back, wouldſt venture ſo, thou fool?</l>
                           <l>I'de ſee my mother burnt before Ide goe,</l>
                           <l>why ſhouldſt thou bring her? ſhe would ſtifle thee,</l>
                           <l>ſtifle thee in thy bed as my mother did.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Still harping on thy mother?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Harping, no,</l>
                           <l>let <hi>Orpheus</hi> harp: O, I, ſhe was, ſhe was,</l>
                           <l>a very, very Harpie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Thus madneſs playes,</l>
                           <l>and keeps a certain meaſure in his words.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O I ſuckt out my mothers deareſt blood,</l>
                           <l>I did indeed, O ſhe plagues me for't now,</l>
                           <l>O I muſt goe lie down in <hi>Tytius</hi> place,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="259" facs="132"/>
                              <hi>Ixion</hi> too, he Sir would fain reſign.</l>
                           <l>I ſcorn your petty plagues, I'll have a worſe,</l>
                           <l>O the vulture, the wheel, the vulture.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>See how his conſcious thoughts, like fiends of hell,</l>
                           <l>do arm themſelves, and laſh his guilty ſoul!</l>
                           <l>He ſee's no vulture, nor no Scorpion ſtrikes,</l>
                           <l>yet doth his conſcience whip his bloody heart;</l>
                           <l>he needs no witneſſes, he hath within</l>
                           <l>a thouſand thoughts which teſtifie his ſin.</l>
                           <l>No puniſhment ſo ſtrict, no deadly ſmart,</l>
                           <l>as private guilt, that ſmiteth on the heart.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>I did, I do confeſſe I did, I killd them all,</l>
                           <l>ript up the womb that bear me; nay I did.</l>
                           <l>O <hi>Tantalus</hi> thy plague; ſome meat, ſome meat;</l>
                           <l>who pulls thoſe apples hence? let them alone,</l>
                           <l>nay ſink to the bottom, I will follow thee,</l>
                           <stage>Lies down to drink.</stage>
                           <l>the rivers dry, my mother hath drunk all.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Alas, come, go with me, we will find drink.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Is <hi>Pluto's</hi> buttry ope; his drink's too hot,</l>
                           <l>I doubt 'twill ſcald me, but I'll taſt on't yet.</l>
                           <l>Th' <hi>Eumenides</hi> ſtand to whip me as I go:</l>
                           <l>Nay I will paſſe you, I will out-ſlip them all.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit currens.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>See in his conſcience lies hells puniſhment,</l>
                           <l>our own thoughts judges, none are innocent.
<hi>Exit.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="chapter">
                        <head>Scen. 6.</head>
                        <stage>Enter two Lords.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1. <hi>Lor.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>We that have here been born to ſee this change,</l>
                           <l>may leave the Court, and tell our children tales,</l>
                           <l>of the dier fall of <hi>Inachus</hi> great houſe.</l>
                           <l>the young Prince mad, the Princeſs kill'd her ſelf,</l>
                           <l>old <hi>Strophius</hi> dead for grief; and murder heapt,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="206" facs="133"/>corps upon corps, as if they ment t'invite,</l>
                           <l>all hell to ſupper, on ſome jovial night.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>2. <hi>Lord.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>Nay but my Lord, this is moſt pityful,</l>
                           <l>that the young Prince ſhould thus from door to door,</l>
                           <l>beg for his food, and yet none dare to give.</l>
                           <l>I ſaw him wandring yeſterday alone,</l>
                           <l>flying from every Crow, or pratling Pie,</l>
                           <l>crying out mother, and as if there had</l>
                           <l>tormenting furies followed him with fraud;</l>
                           <l>and truth, I thought to tell old <hi>Tyndarus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>to move his ruthful years to pity him:</l>
                           <l>and will you joyn petitioner with me,</l>
                           <l>we'll tell the caſe, 'tis good t' eaſe miſery.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1. <hi>Lord.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>My Lord I like your motion, and will joyn,</l>
                           <l>for <hi>Agamemnons</hi> ſake my honour'd Maſter.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 7.</head>
                        <stage>Enter Oreſtes, Pylades, with naked rapiers.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>My fury leaves me, now I'm at my laſt,</l>
                           <l>and now me thinks thou truly art a friend:</l>
                           <l>now with undaunted ſpirit prevent my grief,</l>
                           <l>and let thy rapier drink blood greedily,</l>
                           <l>as if it lov'd it 'cauſe it is thy friends,</l>
                           <l>now rid me of my woe, thy friendly vow</l>
                           <l>never did truly ſhew it ſelf till now.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Why then dear friend, I thus erect this arm,</l>
                           <l>and will be ſtrong to thee, as thou to me,</l>
                           <l>we'll look upon our deaths with better face</l>
                           <l>then others do on life; come <hi>Tyndarus,</hi> ſee,</l>
                           <l>we ſcorn to live when all our friends are dead,</l>
                           <l>nor ſhall thy fury make baſe famine be</l>
                           <l>the executioner to my deareſt friend,</l>
                           <l>whilſt I can kill him, therefore ſpight of thee,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="261" facs="133"/>wee'll free our ſelves paſt all calamity.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes <hi>Pylades,</hi> we will beguile our time,</l>
                           <l>and make him ſearch through every nook o'th world,</l>
                           <l>if he in all his race can ever ſpie,</l>
                           <l>two that like us did live, like us did die:</l>
                           <l>But we delay our death, now bravely come,</l>
                           <l>and the laſt parting word ſhall be, ſtrike home.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>They run at one another.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>O bravely ſtrook dear friend, yet once again.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Run again.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Yes, at one thruſt two friends muſt not be ſlain.</l>
                           <l>O, how I love theſe wounds! heaven dropping ſhowers,</l>
                           <l>when the outrageous dog makes clouds of duſt</l>
                           <l>upon the thirſty earth, come not more ſweet,</l>
                           <l>then the bleſt ſtreams of blood thy rapier raines.</l>
                           <l>Hence weapon; for my loyns now ſcorn all props,</l>
                           <l>but my friends arms, O, bear good legs a while;</l>
                           <l>the weight of murder ſits upon my ſoul,</l>
                           <l>and bends my ſtaggering joynts unto the earth.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Haſte, haſte, I faint, but O, yet let my ſtrength be <hi>Atlas</hi> to ſuſtain the falling world;</l>
                           <l>Breathe, breathe ſweet vapors of two truſty hearts,</l>
                           <l>and let our breaths aſcend to heaven before,</l>
                           <l>to make a room hard by the frozen pole,</l>
                           <l>where that our winged ſouls ſhall mount and ſit,</l>
                           <l>more glorious then the Concubines of <hi>Jove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>wreath'd with a Crown of rich enamel'd ſtars,</l>
                           <l>leaving all ages to deplore our death,</l>
                           <l>that friendſhips abſtract periſht with our breath.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>Fly thou beſt part of man, where <hi>Hecate</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>born on the ſwarthy ſhoulders of the Even,</l>
                           <l>ſits in a grove of oakes, till gray ey'd morn</l>
                           <l>bids her to throw off nights black Canopie.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>Wil't die before me? Stay, ſtay, I come.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
                           <l>O graſp me then, our names like <hi>Gemini,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>ſhall make new ſtars for to adorn the sky.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="262" facs="134"/>Is thy breath gone?</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Pyl.</speaker>
                           <l>O, yes, 'tis almoſt paſt,</l>
                           <l>then both together, thus wee'l breath our laſt.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>They fall down dead, embracing each other.</stage>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="scene">
                        <head>Scena 8.</head>
                        <stage>Enter in haſt Tyndarus, Lords, with others.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tyn.</speaker>
                           <l>Went they this way? my Lords, you move me much,</l>
                           <l>could I find him now, I would ſeat him new,</l>
                           <l>in his right Kingdom, which doth weigh down me.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>1. <hi>Lord.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <l>I ſee my Lord, <hi>Oreſtes</hi> and his friend,</l>
                           <l>without your leave, have made themſelves an end.</l>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Tynd.</speaker>
                           <l>Then now is <hi>Argos</hi> Court like to ſome ſtage,</l>
                           <l>when the ſad plot fills it with murdered Trunks</l>
                           <l>and none are left alive but only one,</l>
                           <l>to ask the kind ſpectators <hi>plaudite,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>all elſe have bid <hi>valete</hi> to the world,</l>
                           <l>the man reſerv'd for that, is <hi>Tyndarus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>who thus hath ſeen his childrens childrens end,</l>
                           <l>his Grandchild, a bad ſon, a moſt deare friend;</l>
                           <l>the Scene muſt now be overflow'd with grones,</l>
                           <l>each man ſits downe to waile his private mones.</l>
                           <l>one for the Queen doth weep, one for the King,</l>
                           <l>all taſte the bitter waters of this Spring:</l>
                           <l>the Nurſe bewails the child, that part ſhe beares,</l>
                           <l>all have their ſubiects to bedew with teares;</l>
                           <l>each one yet have but one; but all of me,</l>
                           <l>challenge a part in griefes ſad ſympathy.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Oreſtes, Clytemneſtrae</hi> I muſt call,</l>
                           <l>theſe all for mine, thus muſt I weep for all:</l>
                           <l>let none believe this deed, or if they doe,</l>
                           <l>let them believe this puniſhment then too.</l>
                           <l>'Tis vile to hate a Father, but ſuch love,</l>
                           <l>as breeds a hate to'th Mother, worſe doth prove.</l>
                           <l>Our life conſiſts of ayre, our ſtate of wind,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="263" facs="134"/>all things we leave behind us which we find;</l>
                           <l>ſaving our faults; witneſſe <hi>Oreſtes</hi> here,</l>
                           <l>who was his own tormentor, his own fear;</l>
                           <l>Who flying all, yet could not fly himſelf,</l>
                           <l>but needs muſt ſhipwrack upon murders ſhelf:</l>
                           <l>and ſo his breſt made hard with miſery,</l>
                           <l>he grew himſelf to be his enemy.</l>
                           <l>Thus griefe and gladneſſe ſtill by turnes do come,</l>
                           <l>but pleaſure leaſt while doth poſſeſſe the roome.</l>
                           <l>Long nights of grief may laſt, but lo, one day</l>
                           <l>of ſhining comfort ſlideth ſoon away.</l>
                           <l>He, whom all fear on earth, muſt fear a fate,</l>
                           <l>for all our powers are ſubordinate.</l>
                           <l>Three hours ſpace thus well can repreſent,</l>
                           <l>vices contriv'd and murders puniſhment.</l>
                           <l>A Monarchs life can in this little ſpace,</l>
                           <l>ſhew all the pomp that all the time doth grace.</l>
                           <l>His riſings and his falls, and in one ſpan</l>
                           <l>of time can ſhew the vanity of man.</l>
                           <l>For none of us can ſo command the powers,</l>
                           <l>that we may ſay, to morrow ſhall be ours.</l>
                           <l>Now fortunes wheele is turn'd, and time doth call,</l>
                           <l>to ſolemnize this friendly funerall.</l>
                           <l>No force ſo great, no ſo diſaſter wrong,</l>
                           <l>as can unknit the band which holdeth ſtrong</l>
                           <l>united hearts: who ſince they thus are dead,</l>
                           <l>one room, one tomb ſhall hold them buried.</l>
                           <l>And as theſe friends joyn'd hands to beare their Fate;</l>
                           <l>ſo we deſire you them to imitate.</l>
                           <l>Who ſince they all are dead, we needs muſt crave,</l>
                           <l>your gentle hands to bring them to their grave.</l>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </TEI>

